We waited from California we left California at 1 a.m. and made it I mean
we made incredible time we made it through California Oregon and most of
Washington in one day. Wow do you guys trade off? Yeah you're totally smashing this
like internal opinion I have of you of a very sweet smelling man now. Well you
know all things said all things said I actually think I came out smelling like
roses really no real smell the hair got a little out of control but yeah so
that's why we didn't see much of you. If when if I do manage to get all these out
in Rover logs as the Rover log goes my hair goes from like combed to
progressively just a disaster because literally at one point I'm not joking
you on our way home we got stuck in a tornado in an RV and it was one of the
scariest things that's ever happened to me and so it just goes off the rails it
goes off the rails it's ridiculous it was a hell of a drive home. Where on the
west coast did you encounter a tornado? Yeah yeah Northern California Northern
California and it was no frickin joke it was I I literally thought I was going to
destroy my brand new home. Oh man. Hail the size of marbles at unbelievable
speeds it was. How did Rover to make it out? Well pretty good I think I mean
good I wouldn't I documented all of it so I'll put it all out in the Rover log
but it you know it's funny because we're driving down the road and we're
listening to a podcast and the stereo system switches over and there's this
piercing emergency sound that comes from the stereo it resets the volume it
resets it to the FM radio and they override your stereo system and you
start getting the if you are on the road take cover immediately this is an
emergency. I'm like holy crap! That's crazy. Yeah oh and Hadeah is sitting there driving
she was driving at that step at that point cuz we were trading off and she's
like should I keep going I kind of want to see it I'm like yeah let's keep going
let's see it. Think of the network Chris. And then as we start to see the big
semi-trucks bailing off the road and like taking refuge under overpasses I
start to realize this and then I start to I look ahead I'm like I I can't see
beyond a certain distance that's all just gray and and then I'm like pull
over pull over we gotta get off the road it was something I did not expect to run
into a tornado and and and they're like if you are in a high-profile vehicle or
a motorhome you may want to consider abandoning the vehicle like this what
they tell you on the radio broadcast because you're extra susceptible to the
wind right but the problem is the hail was so powerful and so fast and so
strong that you would have been seriously injured if you actually tried
to evacuate the vehicle so we couldn't evacuate your choice we had to stay in
this huge wind catcher there's a long tall wall that catches wind that's what
we had to stay in during the turn oh because we would have been I mean we
would have been seriously injured it was really something can I can I give you
some advice if you ever encounter tornado again yeah if you were watching
it and it doesn't appear moving get out of the way it's coming towards you hmm
yeah it was moving five five miles per hour across die five and one of the
things we thought about cuz where we had to park the whole vehicle was on level
right and so you're going through you're trying to just do everything you can but
the vehicle is really really off-kilter because we're hot we're half off the
road and like that makes us even more susceptible to wind to getting knocked
over right because we're sitting there leaning and so we're trying to decide
should we put the jacks down but of course the jacks are metal and there's
tons of lightning because it's a tornado and so I was like we can't put the jacks
down because then that would ground us because right now we're sitting on rubber
but the vehicles at a slant but so if we put the jacks down it would correct the
slant of the vehicle and make us more stable but the vehicle and if we got
struck by lightning we'd be really screwed so we stayed on the rubber it
was it was really something it was intense that sounds like quite the
moment yeah I'm glad I'm very thankful that we have you back on camera not all
of it but a lot so I was talking about the tornado just a second ago but the
other thing that worked out really really well is I pulled off at this
place called battle rock beach and it was in the middle of the night so I had
no idea what it was like I kind of I could tell because I couldn't see I
couldn't see off into the distance I thought this might be a great view so I
parked the rig down this is in Oregon on our way down to scale I parked it woke
up in the morning to this on that's beautiful look at this I went up I had
to go up and crawl up look at that that's not from the roof of the rover
there and I went out and I got some footage with the GoPro I got like some
super awesome that's that's I'm holding the GoPro there so that I have it on a
stable look at how happy you are so I took it up I took it up to the water now
I did I got this shot from far away so yeah I'm sitting to get a shot of the ocean so
I got my boots a little wet for for good footage well it's worth it yeah yeah
that's all all in on the line of duty but that was turned out to be a great
spot on the way down yeah I mean you you know I don't even know if you can get a
hotel that nice yeah right that was waterfront pretty pretty just wandered
right down to the water made up for the tornado on the way back from scale oh so
this is on the way down yeah this is on the way down and really the the the
whole payoff was giving you see poppy who turns out to be a well-smelling
gentleman oh yeah I can confirm he does smell well in real life he caught me on
a good day I know I mean no no a conference when you're traveling not your
typical good day I because I'll tell you what happened to me total devastating
disaster we were moving from the old rover to the new rover lady Jupiter as
we call her and we moved everything except for the absolutely most
important things for a trip like this my mixer my microphone oh Chris and and
all of the toiletries all of it toothbrushes combs hair anything so
anything left it all so we got down and on the road and realized we didn't have
any of our stuff it was awful so poppy I congratulate you for making it over to
the west coast of the US of a and smelling like a gentleman with your
basic hygiene intact while at a conference that's a that is a true feat
I'll tell you what the the hotel we stayed in was okay and and as with all
many canonical events when there's more than a certain number of people we share
room so I shared a room with one of the other community guys Michael Hall and
you know we didn't the shower wasn't huge so squeezing us both in there
together was a little bit of a squash but you know we managed this is Linux
unplugged episode 129 for January 26 2016
well I'm gonna let it unplug your weekly Linux talk show that's recovered from
the scale hangover by drinking beer my name is Chris my name is what hey there
wasn't a good beer it is it sure is the sour one now coming up on this week's
episode of the unplugged show we don't have a sour show no no never have a
great show we're gonna have some updates from our friends on some of the projects
they've been working on in the Linux community then did you hear the big drama
around the Linux Foundation kicking out the individual contributor it's a big
hoopla we'll tell you what's going on who's spreading rumors and what the
reality likely is with the Linux Foundation then later on have you
wondered where the hell is Wayland wait what wait it's almost become a joke
Wayland hasn't shipped yet what I actually went back in the Linux
action to archives I went back as far as 2011 we were still making jokes that
Wayland wouldn't ship this year that means we probably predicted in 2009 it
would ship I mean that's it's a mess I'll explain why Wayland hasn't shipped
and it's not the reason you're thinking in fact if you're asking that question
you're asking the wrong question mm-hmm that's right that's right that's right
and then towards the end of the show this week West is best friends over at
AMD good buds at AMD I love those guys they have launched today GPU open GPU
open actually I don't know if it was launched today but they have launched
recently GPU open and we will talk about that as well as catch up on shenanigans
baby chat a little about scale and all of those goodies right here on the
unplugged show you know before we get rolling let's bring in that mumble room
our virtual log time appropriate greetings mumble room
greeting hello guys hello so I don't know if anybody out there in the
mumble land is drinking along with the show today but West brought in a real
sour beer this is a sour beer it's called wild sour and it's the Flanders red
product of the USA it's got a BA score of 82 has an APV an ABV of 6% this is a
really like it almost tastes like like the sour stuff that's in some sour foods
it's so sour but it's also got a really nice clean finish I like it a lot so
that's what we're drinking this week on the upload we've been doing the beer
thing to sort of encourage the community hangout aspect it's been fun so West we
have a big story to talk about that I I meant to cover in Linux action show last
week but the scale shenanigans totally got away with things and didn't get it
didn't get a chance to cover this and so I wanted to give a mention out to
Jonathan Thomas who shipped OpenShot 2.0 beta this has been the Kickstarter
project we've all been waiting for OpenShot 2.0 is a whole bunch of new
stuff whole bunch of it's the new UI look it's it's a whole bunch of fixes
he's been working on and Kickstarter backers are getting the update first
it's pretty exciting because you guys know I follow Linux editing pretty
closely and I still think it's a pretty bad state of affairs
together a little video let's check it out it's pretty cool look at that that's
him putting that out now I'll jump ahead a little bit here so you can get a basic
idea of what the UI looks like here it's it's nice and it's available it works on
Windows it's gonna work on the Mac and Linux of course he's showing it here
under Ubuntu
I I am hopeful I am hopeful I am I am not exactly I'm not exactly sure what to
expect yet still there's no binaries that I have found even though I'm a
Kickstarter backer I maybe I missed an email that's very possible I've been
traveling but the source code is on github right now in fact I think like
even 205 beta is up or something like that is up on github so you could go
get it right now it just doesn't include a lot of a lot of things you need to
make it all run but there is hope out there we have a couple of good video
editors they're in the works right now so I don't think open shots ready yet
but hey you know what it's great to finally see some code shipping after
quite a while after I can't even remember but I think it's I think it's
been a few years now yeah yeah so Poby welcome back from from the US of a how
was your visit do we treat you okay while you were over here oh yeah I had
an amazing time loved it absolutely that's great I asked pop I said so what
was one of the first things you did when you got here and he's like well I got
chicken wings of course yeah did you get beer with the chicken wings or just the
chicken of course found a nice little place called Barney's and had some
Belgian beer and chicken wings and that sorted me out real really good you know
is this is this your is this isn't your first visit to California is it no it's
first one to LA I've been to Palo Alto and Oakland and San Francisco so what
did you think what strikes you when you visit here I'm curious just from
somebody who doesn't really have that outsiders perspective when you get here
what even if it's been like even if you've had the revelation before what is
it that strikes you when you visit so customer service is the first thing like
it's night and day compared to the UK so over there in the US it feels like
people genuinely want to serve you well and for you to have a good time whereas
over here you'll get a surly person who doesn't give a shit whether you have a
good time and whether you enjoy your food or drink or whatever whereas over
there when we're in the bar all the waitresses are very friendly and the
waiters as well it was just I just had a really nice time and I feel like the
people are nice and genuine and Pasadena is a lovely lovely place yeah I was
really surprised by how great of a venue that was you know how convenient it was
to like really great food oh but Khan had an after-party at the Brazilian
barbecue which is what happened to be where we went for lunch that day it's
just an incredible venue really nice classy accessible but big enough to
host a large group and that was one of many places around the convention center
you could have gone to a different place every night and you know we and we
randomly chose most of them we didn't have to you know go looking for Yelp
reviews or anything we stumbled on this little Korean place which was a little
bit weird it was it was super cheap and the few food was part Korean part
Japanese so it's like sushi and Korean sake and stuff but all the while there
was a TV which was constantly streaming Korean pop music which was really weird
you know that so it's funny you say that there are a lot of Korean channels in
Pasadena because the the Lady Jupiter has a HD antenna that goes up oh one of
the first things I do now that I got this is I raised the it's like it's
awesome it's literally called the batwing antenna and you you sit there
and you crank it up and it goes up and it kind of looks like a batwing and I
tuned in about 30 non-english channels and about half of them were Korean it's
funny try that I couldn't take I couldn't take my eyes off the TV
I'm like holy crap look at this this is unbelievable yeah my cat had great time
Michael was there he he helped us out with the reservations at the meetup
Popey it was able to come and say hi to the meetup he made an appearance because
you know he was a working girl while while at convention well we all were in
a sense but I mean he had to go back and and do his business so how did that all
go for you was it a decent success would you do it again yeah totally I like the
so the you become was good because there were a few talks that I didn't know
about yeah stuff that I was I was interested in seeing so actually you
know as someone who's one of the old well partially one of the organizers and
I was giving a talk myself it was really nice for me to hear like what other
people in the community had to say and see a different perspective than you
know just the one from canonical tell me a little about your talk so I talked
about a service that I created so immediately before my talk Stuart
language talked about building services right on top of Ubuntu phone so rather
than just you know nagging us about when the next phone is going to be available
when you're moaning that there's no game center or something like that rather
than you moan about it why don't you build out there and build something
right so his talk was all about building something and that kind of dovetailed
nicely with my mine and his joint talk which was we built something so yeah it
was quite cool it was nice and I did a demo and it worked and that's always
nice yeah I had a webcam pointed at a phone in my house a few thousand miles
away just to prove that it was doing what it wanted to do so cool I've had
the foresight to set up a webcam before I left the house flying around the world
well I had a I had like five minutes to talk to Mark Shuttleworth and I asked
him if this is gonna be something that we're probably gonna keep doing he kind
of gave me a can't answer which I kind of gave him a hard time about but
essentially he said that that the the unconference format feels pretty good to
him and that this in-person thing and go and and and sort of riding along with
another conference seems like a no-brainer for them so I don't know
probably if you guys are gonna do something like ubi-con again but I
thought yeah I thought it was a big draw I saw I talked to a lot of people there
were there specifically to go to ubi-con so I think it's something you guys should
keep up with yeah the next one's gonna be in Europe I think Germany is the next
one towards the end of the year I think it might even be booked in for November
okay we'll probably alternate you know and have one in Europe one in the US and
then but the thing is it's not us as in canonical that organize them it's up to
the community if you want to have one you create one in your region and so
it will help you where we can how did that work exactly so the ubi-con that
happened at scale was set up by a virtual who is that who's who's talking
back to us all right Wes has got it Wes watching there it was the it was the
virtual user the virtual it was the real actual users group the physical users
group this sort of organized it how did that work exactly so the Southern
California Linux user groups and the and the local teams the Ubuntu community
teams are all really active and there many of them are involved in scale
anyway so it was very easy for them to you know organize things with scale and
get the venue and get the rooms booked and all that kind of stuff so they did
all the logistics and you know we have a stand in the expo area and all that at
scale as well and for the whole of life for ubi-con as well so it was very easy
for them to do that organization because they were already linked to an
existing event and I think that's where it probably pays off is if if you're in
a local area and there's already an event nearby you can tack one day or two
years old it's like a good relationship yeah yeah I mean it means you don't you
as a as a community person don't have to fork out for a you know huge venue
that's very expensive and that Pasadena Center is massively expensive it's
really really yeah well it's a nice venue so I would imagine it is yeah we
had a chance to chat with one of the organizers about the incredible ham
radio setup they have there just so that way the different organizers can
communicate really wow that's how they punch through some of the interferences
they use ham radio and it was so cool to hear them geek out about that and you
and then he pointed out where some of the antennas were if you look you can see
like they have and and the Pasadena Convention Center of course is
pre-wired they'd have antennas installed because this is like this is a common
thing I guess pretty neat pretty cool I mean it's a pretty big event I mean you
have to keep this in perspective it's being put on by the community right it's
not it's not O'Reilly media coming in and and organizing all of this it's not
the Linux Foundation that is organizing all of this it's the community and it's
still a huge event I think they said they had something like three thousand
six hundred people that was the number I heard two was 3600 that's just what I
was gonna add so it was a really cool thing I mean we're gonna go more in
detail than Linux action show but it was really neat to see there poppy and I
wouldn't even know to you and you know what we had a hell of a meetup hell of a
meetup it was it was pretty funny because we had 40 people RSVP or plus 40
plus people RSVP and so Micah 68 there in the chat room or was it no not Micah
he was Micah not Micah 60 a different Micah in the chat room realized well we
should probably give these people a heads up well at the time he gave them a
heads up it was only 20 on the meetup oh or something like that and then they
lost the reservation all together they lost it all together and so I get there
and I'm like it was a reservation for 20 but it's probably gonna be more than
that and then I'm like I should and then like five minutes go by and I'm like I
should probably let her know by more than that I mean double so let me
clarify but they never they never heard me after the number 20 they just went
with the number so and like party of 20 yeah we have 20 people coming yeah they
got 20 we need to set up a table for 20 like I heard them talking all the time
about 20 people I'm like and I kept like ma'am it's probably me more than like
40 eventually we just completely overtook their entire outer seating
area I mean I think it was like maybe 55 60 people I don't know how many people
Wow that's huge it was huge as well we went there a few times and yes the beer
the beer is good in there and the food was good yeah the yard house yeah they
had a great selection of beer great selection which was the rarity including
Ian from system 76 had me try this peanut butter beer that he got peanut
butter beer peanut butter beer oh and it was smooth it was real smooth I got a
little one chunky peanut butter beer I got some I got some yeah you don't I got
some strong Belgium ale I can't remember the name of it was now but it was really
good it was it was excellent hey you know something we've been talking about here
on this show I don't know I'm just I'm fascinated I key or Josh aren't here
today to talk about it with us but a lot going on with solace I don't know maybe
it's the way they communicate maybe it's the the brash goals that they have
something about this project I I'm just very visible right yeah and so they're
going out and making waves again and the folks over at softpedia have been really
I want to couch this conversation just saying they've been really making some
changes over at softpedia and I want to talk about that with you guys too
wimpy you're in here right I want to talk to you about this too but solo s is
going to be supported for the next couple of years this next version and so
there I guess they say they're gonna cry to squash I quote all bugs and I don't
know how the hell that's possible but alongside with their crutch and focus
for 1.1 we're also continuing our campaign of bug crushing we have crushed
22 bugs over the last week ranging from long string bugs that have been resolved
since budgie rewrite to recent ones that related to inclusions of git based
patches for new software in the repo so they're going through making supposedly
this next really super super solid West what would it take this is this is my
question to you what would it take for you to honestly and legitimately install
solace and run it on like this laptop or a work machine that you are gonna use
every single day what would it take I think it really probably comes down to
package availability I'm doing I'm gonna do a little bit of bit of work to get
the packages if I need to nothing crazy but if I can use the tools I expect day
to day you know you know even if it's like a compiling or something akin yeah
so it sounds like the barrier is not high yeah no I mean everything looks
nice I'd have to play around with budgie a little more to see if it met you know
like my workflow but I assume I could change that if I is anybody in the
mumble room using this as their daily driver right now yeah that's a good
question it doesn't sound like it I don't think it's reached that level yet
all right maybe when this 1.1 comes out I'll step up and put it on this laptop I
don't want to I don't I don't really know I don't know how to I don't want to
use that there's a lot of softpedia shame online a lot of people don't like
softpedia yep and as somebody who just takes on a lot of news sources I just
sort of weigh each article on its own merits and I sort of build sort of a you
know following with an author those kinds of things and so for me it's not
so much about where you publish it's more about what you publish but
regardless softpedia has a hell of a name and not necessarily a good one at
that and I've been watching their coverage recently and I don't actually
know of another outlet out there say maybe for Onyx that is actually as
closely following less headline-grabbing projects that do deserve attention and
and they're also following projects to do deserve attention but I find I find
that they're actually in some cases contacting the distro makers and getting
quotes and actually verifying things which why that sounds like real
reporting yeah and I'm wondering wimpy I know I've seen a lot of articles from
them about Mate edition I'm wondering what your experience has been on the end
of the person getting reported on and what your experience because that's
that's a pretty valuable perspective yes softpedia certainly strike me as an
outlet that are far more grassroots community focused so they are paying
attention to a broader range of Linux news that appeals to probably more the
enthusiast you don't see so much of sort of where the enterprise stuff it's sort
of you know more that's a good desktop and mobile and yes in the past they have
contacted me directly to clarify things prior to putting stuff out but in the
main they like to be first to report on things so you know there yes it depends
whether it's a big story and they want to be first or if it's something new and
they want to be you know accurate it varies but also I forget his surname
swap nil from used to be mucked where and Linux Vader he writes for various
places he's very good as well if he wants to cover a story he's very thorough
he sets up a a Google Doc and gets all of the involved parties together and has
a whole question and answer and has various people come in and actually sort
of write their responses and then he brings that all together so he's the
most journalistic of the people that I've encountered that really goes to
people and gets gets not just copy off the website but actually wow you know
what was his name again would be oh I'm sorry I missed it yeah of course I know
that scale actually yeah a whole bunch of us from a bunch of those like eight
of us sat around a table yeah I love the picture you got of you guys crossing the
street he posted that to Google Plus that I hate that photo you look like
you're contemplating and looking ahead to the future thinking about converge
devices is a great shot of you I think I was just trying not to get run over yeah
but yeah okay yeah I told him you know the problem with swap me is is when I'm
now I'm already doing it right now is I want to say swap when I say his name so
that's that's really the big problem is I just want to call him swap but yeah
yeah you don't need swap nail if you have two gigs around but I'm bummed
anyway so yeah I agree that that is it's a see softpedia take a step up is nice
hopefully here's that here's the photo I was talking about hopefully look at it
that's poppy there in the in the jacket with the third over from the left
beautiful that's a great shot it really is look at look at that that's the that's
what needs a boon to crew crossing the street sort of in an echo of the good
the famous Beatles shot I think that's pretty good that's pretty good shot so
there's only one thing I would say about swap nil is that when he made that that
mucked where version of the onion was really annoying because he had it was
mugged where was both news and fake news oh it was kind of like it's difficult
why is like why are you purposefully creating noise there is a much
discussion to be had there but that said I would I would encourage people you
know just just sort of reconsider from time to time and can take each article
in its own perspective and of course Linux action show that reddit.com is a
great place to discuss the merits of an article because I do read those comments
and weigh them when I'm thinking about covering a story so yeah I have found
them their coverage to be interesting it's it's been something I've been
starting to visit on a reoccurring basis oh it's good to see better you know more
and better Linux news coverage yeah sure you're sure very much so you know what
else is new better and always getting better that's our friends over Digital
Ocean man they've been making UI improvements that I love there's some
really nice stuff to make you do things that make it possible to do things at
scale use our promo code right now won't you deal unplugged to support this show
and get a $10 credit over at Digital Ocean which is a simple cloud hosting
provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you get a
Linux rig super fast in the cloud that you control root access HTML 5 console
when you need to really screw around with that thing and you can start in
less than 55 seconds 55 seconds whoa man I said it is really something that is
whoa 512 megabytes of RAM boom 20 gigabyte SSD boom one CPU and a
terabyte a terabyte of acts absolute domination transfer for five dollars a
month use that promo code deal unplugged one word lowercase you get $10 credit
and the really nice thing about the Digital Ocean is they got data centers
out the wazoo yep they got them all over the place wherever you want to look like
a boss you can have a data center if it's in New York yeah you got a data
center in New York if it's in San Fran yeah now you got one in San Fran oh
Singapore sure Amsterdam you know how they work there yeah but let me tell you
about Toronto that's where you go to be in the north right right there on the
Americas but guess what's not in Toronto the NSA oh also by the way Germany this
is a sweet spot for all the Germany's neighbors or if you want to stream
something to Merkel herself you got to have a date you got to have a droplet in
country it's the only way she's gonna watch it but really what's great about
Digital Ocean is their awesome support of Linux working upstream all SSD drives
and this incredible interface mmm I love this interface which the only thing
better about this interface the only thing better is the API oh man that API
holy cow the API is straightforward but the nice thing about it and I'm gonna
tell you where sometimes I hit the lazy button see what I do here as I go over
to this community page and just go to community and then you go to projects
and you're like I want to have a project right no no this is where you go to find
a whole bunch of really good open source code already written around that Digital
Ocean API and there is tons of stuff you can take advantage of right now I'd be
scrolling if you're watching the video version oh did you see that I was just using the
vagrant integration the other day really yeah how so why spend up a VM on my local
machine when I can get one in the cloud for so cheap right totally totally they
in fact they even have hourly pricing and on top of all of that with one-click
applications deployments that are super easy they also have great guides like
here's when they just post on how to set up let's encrypt certificates nice for
multiple Apache virtual hosts on a boom to 1404 that's seriously helpful digital
ocean.com use the promo code deal unplugged go get your own super fast
rig up in the cloud that you have root access to you can do whatever you want
either either deploy applications with a single click or set up the entire
infrastructure yourself be a boost at digital ocean.com use the promo code
deal unplugged in a big thank you to digital ocean not only for rockin so
hard and make it Linux super cool and for a first-class citizen on your
service and using the Linux to power the entire infrastructure yeah but also for
supporting the show with deal unplugged digital ocean.com thanks guys all right
it is almost it's almost a joke now where in the world is Wayland and it's
always like is it ever gonna ship and I I will admit have having fully
participated in the joke I was gonna play a clip for you guys where where we
predicted Wayland would ship to show you just a bit of context how long we have
been expecting Wayland to be the default display server and this is sort of we
go off the rails but bear with me for a second best I could estimate I think in
2009 about our 2010 actually I think was 2010 2010 I said it would be default in
2011 in 2012 in 2013 I made a joke prediction as well as did Brian and Matt
at those times that Wayland would still not be shipping and no one would care
and it has sort of been the joke prediction in our show for so many years
that we stopped making the joke it's still a joke I heard the joke at scale
and the problem is it's actually completely and totally the wrong
question the question really isn't is Wayland ready yet that's not really what
you should be asking the better question is is gnome ready yet or is Kaywin ready
yet because I mean yes it's been it's there has been work that needs to happen
on Wayland but Wayland itself is a protocol I'm gonna get more than a
second but the blog post here from the gnome blog and I'm forgetting the
person's name right now because you know he says it's been our goal now for a
while to get to a point where Wayland could be declared complete and ready to
be enabled by default we've come a long way since starting the porting effort in
2013 in fact we feel we're close enough that we can aim for Wayland by default
in fedora 24 so this is you know something that's been everybody's been
talking about for quite a while now for you know getting Wayland by default
there's been a lot of work fixing things like dialog boxes and pop-ups and
applications GTK plus has had a lot of work that's gone into it kinetic
scrolling now works better under Wayland drag-and-drop now works under Wayland
copy and paste is getting close in a lot of cases but this isn't the problem see
what we what what this is what you have to understand the question isn't really
is Wayland ready yet that doesn't make a lot of sense Wayland is a communication
protocol and says very little about the implementation of the two sides you want
to communicate say your web browser a compositor the protocol is stable and
has been for a while but not every compositor and or toolkit or
application speak Wayland yet so it may not be sufficient for your use case so
rather than asking is Wayland ready yet you should be asking can I run gnome or
KDE or enlightenment under Wayland are they talking Wayland yet because they
have to be their own compositor now they have to do that on work they have to be
their own servers talking Wayland to the client application like all this stuff
now has to be implemented the burdens on them it's just not done yet it's not
ready yet but we still talk about it like if Wayland isn't shipping Wayland
shipped everybody news alert right here today breaking news on the unplug
program this is CNN breaking news Wayland shipped it shipped a while ago
one it's it's done the problem is graphics drivers aren't ready the
desktop environments aren't ready all of our little esoteric applications aren't
ready yet we're not ready Wayland is here it's good yeah I mean so I I wanted
to just sort of talk about this for a second because it's sort of I heard it
come up at scale I've seen it online a million times I there's a blog post
about it right now why aren't we shipping Wayland yet I've even I've even
participated in it and we're in the reality it's just that it showed up and
we weren't ready for it it's kind of what it feels like I don't know I think
I think what the author says here at the bottom that there are exceptions you
know that the protocol does still need a few things to be worked out in a way
that's not into implementation defined you know so we want to make sure that
KDE and GNOME don't do disparate things where the protocol is maybe lacking
clarification or lacking definition right right so and I wonder too in a
world where the Linux desktop is already not you know like a primary citizen how
much capability we can sacrifice the transition and still make it work so you
mean like you mean like if we don't get it right right like if copy and paste
almost works well how many people who use Mac or Windows can deal with not
having copy and paste right so I don't know I think we're getting really close
I think that this is a good a very good point and that you know we are already
seen like knowing I love when we see the updates from the GNOME team in the KDE
team about how far they're compositing their window managers are coming
especially the KDE updates but no kids and you think that's indicative of maybe
a systemic problem in the desktop projects themselves or the communities
what do you mean possibly it just seems like at least one of the desktops would
have it fully working by now since you know it's already shipped it's been
shipping for what six months about a year now I'm just kind of surprised that
like the X standards where they got together and all agreed on certain
standards or for like the icons etc drag and drop copy paste all that stuff there
was actually a huge foundation that was created just for that why don't they do
the same thing for Wayland I thought it was kind of being put on by the same
people I thought was my understanding heavens I want to give you a chance to
jump in just before we go too much further go ahead
yeah I mean those are really easy or simple reason why people who seem to
think of Wayland as a thing because our old X server was a server and I think
which had to run which Wayland doesn't need to run it's just a protocol for the
window manager it doesn't yeah window manager to actually manage and uses use
its compositor through so based on the x386 migrating to the X or server if
people just confuse it that way also we're going to secure by default which
is why something is weird as copy and paste or moving things between one
composited window to another secure positive like composited right no right
it's a little bit tricky well the X server is insecure and root horror right
that's actually so we were talking about the copy pasting the problem is is these
are all isolated protected applications now and so we've grown used to not
having the security yeah yeah so sharing data between them is tricky William go
ahead I want you to get a chance to jump in yeah so I don't think it's so much the
desktops holding it back because no actually has pretty decent Wayland
support if you use say the latest fedora image so it's mostly graphics drivers at
this point right yeah it works fine on Intel for the most part but yeah yeah
still missing complete open GL ES support which I need for Wayland to run
yes nobody's buying a thousand dollar plus computer and saying I don't need my
GPU let's I mean right maybe some of the most hardcore open source advocates are
but the majority of consumers are not going to buy a computer with a $300 part
in it and be like I don't need that right you could get iris pro graphics
that work though yeah some people are totally happy with the Intel graphics my
issue with Intel graphics remains once you put them in a high DPI environment
that you again feel the immediate crippling of integrated graphics if you
use in a 1080p environment or even a 2k environment iris would probably work for
people who don't play games a lot yep but yeah in the high DPI it's just it's
awful this is really this is really something that I I find to be fascinating
now wimpy what is the Maui project I know I've heard the name for is that
like Rebecca of black Linux what is this no no it's Maui is the operating system
and I think it's the Hawaii desktop or something yeah yeah they they took the
Western reference compositor and that and then built up our sort of a lightweight
desktop environment around it and it's the only aside from gnome 3 which is
sort of adapted from X to Wayland this is the only desktop environment that was
focused on Wayland from the outset now I don't know who actually had a chance
to install it but I think we actually talked about this about a year ago so
has this been around for a while because I think we yeah I've been aware of it
for a few years because okay now I think you brought up an important point when
describing it is so you've guys and you guys out there have heard of Wayland
obviously the only thing you often hear about is Weston Weston is a reference
compositor Weston is not really something it's not like it's not
something the K wing developers are going to use it's not something the
gnome people are going to use it's it was a reference point that's what
Western is and that's been done for a while too right now what are you gonna
make I was gonna say here's another Wayland focus environment that is
supposed to be a drop-in replacement for the i3 window is that what is this
called here yes way window manager sway WM yeah point look at this so I mean I
think is these things come along power users maybe right you know if there's a
nice styling window manager maybe I can do with Wayland right now yeah and
we're watching a little demo they have a little demo video up under our dinner
website dear that doesn't look pretty good so this is this and then maybe MP
MP plays with zero look at that it's kind of smooth too it actually has some
this is kind of nice yeah right I might give this a try this could be a
legitimate way to get into Wayland a little sooner and not expect all of the
features of such a rich desktop environment like no and you could
probably have this as one of your logins right you know from your display manager
and then go back to X if you needed you know he's playing video there in that
one in that one window there's no tearing there no it looks beautiful yeah
the dream let's put a link to this in the dock I'll put a in this we can have
that in the show notes that's pretty cool if you guys want to check that out
so it's a tiling window I do you call it a window manager now yeah that's what
it's their window manager so okay it's actually a successor to i3 because I
three team said they weren't gonna make a sofa Wayland version so that's one
and and it says that they bring in I your i3 configuration file so it has i3
configuration and I three IPC compatibility which would probably mean
like some of those plugins and stuff which is super cool and also multi head
support so and gap support which I know you had to compile in step or is that
for like in the monitor no like between your tiles if you don't want them right
next to each other you can have a little window gap between oh that's gonna look
pretty if you want to see you know you guys have wanted me to take a tiled
window manager challenge for a while this is the way for it to give me in now
now I'm like this is yeah this is really cool so yeah drop in replacement for i3
window manager but for Wayland instead it will work with your existing i3
configuration files and adds a few extra features on top of that and the other
thing I don't know what the state of multi monitor support is for like kwin
and no I'm sure it's like probably depends on the driver
hmm North Ranger yeah go ahead yeah I think you know we're finally getting to
a point of critical mass with Wayland where the whole ecosystem around it and
that's really what we've been waiting for for a long time as everybody's
alluded to it's drivers desktop environments it's the apps and we've
been through this kind of thing before I mean there was a long time ago and
Linux kernel was at 2.2 and you know people didn't trust you know kernel 2.4
for a long time you know so early adopters were hitting it first you know
things like that same thing with file systems and you know so I think there's
a lot of similarities there and you know overall I'm hopeful and I think we're
are reaching that tipping point where people want the security that comes with
Wayland you know the performance is pretty much a wash and you know we're
finally getting that decent support from the drivers and the ecosystem side yeah
I really hope that does pan out I'm still waiting but for mine but yeah I
definitely am ready to not see when I full screen video to see tearing right
so I was done with that video first class under Linux yeah I would love that
and and you know just the just it just this the sense of knowing that I'm using
something that's not so archaic like there's no material impact other than I
guess my my security is probably not as good as it should be right but I would
I'm ready to move on you know all right anybody else in the member of have any
closing thoughts on on the Wayland stuff before we move on do you really think
Wayland's about to be heralded in I still feel like it's a long way away hmm
I mean for example in the last few years whilst Wayland's being brewing we've all
been spoiled with steam yeah and while we don't have proprietary driver support
for Wayland I can't see people who have embraced steam on their Linux work
stations wanting to switch anytime soon no I you know the X the X shim the X
Wayland thing is not what that's for anyway but see this is the thing though
games you're gonna want the best performance possible I I know that the
next series that brings up that whole debate about you know how should Linux
do games should we have a way in the protocols right to give games there is
that when it comes to Wayland and KDE and GNOME it's up to KDE and GNOME to
actually get this implemented and deployed it's not Wayland themselves
which can actually deploy something and get everyone on it it's built in to the
best I guess the question there would be is there protocol implementations that
can make to make gaming better it's not about making gaming better and I don't
think that GNOME and KDE can be faulted because they've both been working very
hard on bringing them to desktop environments they've been too busy what
is it making their desktops actually usable and getting all the ironing all
the bugs out from their new three dot what ten releases KD 50 releases once
they get all these bugs and things wrinkles smoothed out from their new
desktop environment implementations you can finally focus on something that is
on a back burner which is Wayland support I would say no I disagree I
disagree because what's actually been happening is that the toolkits have been
evolving and therefore the desktop environments that built on top of those
toolkits have been evolving alongside those and that work has been moving on
at quite a pace if you actually look at the amount of effort that's gone into
supporting Wayland on KDE and GNOME 3 there's been a lot of effort and they're
both very close and they've both got implementations where you can run both
their desktops on top of Wayland but that's not the issue and the issue is
also not whether games will run better on Wayland or if there's protocol
support for in optimizing Wayland support for running games it's the
drivers we've got Intel support which is fairly decent but without the
proprietary driver support to give that performance that's required for gaming
and 3d and what-have-you people won't make the switch well here's here I see
two things that sort of our hedges in our favor the first being obviously
SteamOS I mean valve has the final say on what
ships on SteamOS and they can continue to use x11 for as long as they want or
they can build that some sort of shim something like that but I am I am
encouraged by the news I saw today that the next serious Sam game is going to
ship supporting Vulkan out of the box and really what the question is is what
we need the way we need things to line up is we need game developers to support
Vulkan and then we just need the Linux drivers to have good Vulkan support and
Wayland support not and if we can sort of all if everybody's interest and
priorities can align this way we're in pretty good shape and the thing is a lot
of priorities and interests are beginning to align this way already the
slow pivot yeah so Vulkan could be an answer to that and I think SteamOS is
our short-term hedge while this stuff is sort of sorted out because that's not
going to ship what valve doesn't want ship yeah but but the thing is is that
Vulkan has come along while Wayland has been and I'm not sure there's any
provision in Wayland for Vulkan at the moment I could wrong about that cuz I
haven't looked into it to care and I'm not entirely sure if it matters it
doesn't matter there's no reason why you would want at a display server level to
be concerned with something that would be interpreted by the driver and then
rendered out that way hmm boy you know what surely surely you need for example
for Wayland to let's just go back to GL open GL surely you need Wayland to
understand the open GL extensions for it to be able to render those things and in
the same way surely it needs to be able to do that for Vulkan as well that that
would be done by the drivers and stacks on top of them that's usually done by
Mesa now as to what protocol it uses to go into to use this with that's not so
sure I think Wayland needs to be able to interpret some of those extensions no it
really doesn't because all it's going to do the client of Wayland is it's going
to ask for an open GL buffer and I think you can still speak Vulkan over that I
think you can still upgrade that to be Vulkan compatible and it will just
render it within that frame that it was dictated by the Western compositor well
one of us is wrong I would be I would actually bet I would actually bet that
the answer lies somewhere in the in the middle because it seems it seems too
clean one way and it seems too ambiguous the other but I I will link to the
thread that you just put in the chat room West there is a Linux gaming thread
about how Vulkan will impact open-source drivers and I think they
get into Wayland in here we are about to go through a massive transition and the
closer we get to this the more and more obvious it is why why valve was very
very smart and thinking ahead when they decided to release steam OS because
they're like this is a great platform for us to target but and you know they
had to know about this stuff coming up I mean you don't choose Linux as a
platform without following what's happening and maybe that because they
now have so much skin in this game maybe they will be incentivized to work with
whoever they need to work with to make this an easier transition for us put
pressure on game developers to support these newer we could be so lucky right
isn't that the positive side of commercial interest using Linux we could
be so lucky yeah I wonder I will find out I wish we had a crystal ball right
now but I people in the chat room are saying that you know fedora 24 is is
with with Wayland is apart is real and is possible right now kits and I'll give
you the last word on performance and reliability then we'll wrap it up go
ahead yeah I've actually been using Wayland quite a lot as a driver on the
most recent fedora release really I think fedora should have just jumped in
release their current release with Wayland and said hey you know we were
all about promoting you know future technologies this is what we do this is
what this distro is about and I think did you go away gets him oh he went away
I thought he was making a good point essentially I think what his point is is
that because fedora is a cutting-edge distro it's the place to try it well
that's probably we are gonna see it first the outlook is good for the
eight-ball this is the j-bot eight-ball in the chat room there you go there you
go hey that is the decider that's the final word on them but that's it kids
and got a good point and I think when it comes time to do our fedora review and
my ex PS has an Intel Iris grounds car that was mm-hmm Chris's new Wayland
machine hey yo tell you what else is new my friends over at ting got some new
sales I'll tell you about here in just a second but first why you should switch
to ting I love it I use ting all the way down to scale and back and let me tell
you it is nice to know that ting is mobile that is finally different no
contract no real termination fee and you only pay for what you use six dollars
for your line pay for what you use so you go down to a trip to California
maybe use a little more a little more data on your way down on your way up no
bigs cuz you know what now I'm back here at the JB one headquarters I'm on the
Wi-Fi is Wes I'm on the Wi-Fi so it all is no bigs though my bill is cray-cray
with three smartphones is cray-cray cray-cray low whoa hey oh yeah like like
the like December was like 27 bucks oh that's like one meal out yeah the
average ting bill I guess per line is like $23 so think about a way now you
can go get a smartphone that's completely under your control you can
get the quote-unquote Google experience if you likes get that real pure
experience get something that's unlocked something you own outright and you're
paying like 23 bucks a month whoa man that's great so ting also has an ETF
relief program if you're stuck in a duopoly contract they have super great
customer service a fantastic dashboard to manage your ting account I mean it is
really the best in the industry and like I mentioned they got great sales going
right now so go to linux.ting.com to support the show and get $25 in credit
or $25 off a device if you want an internet phone they got the iPhone 5s
unlocked you own it outright 338 bucks right now nice really nice deal the s5
refurb edition 298 bucks that's a great Android phone for 298 bucks unlocked
yours yep you own that you own that s yeah with all the money you're gonna
save on ting I mean that's true buy one of these phones and not worry about it
the galaxy galaxy galaxy s6 this is a really nice phone with the octa core
processor few gigs of RAM the PCIe storage the fantastic camera you can own
it outright completely unlocked no contract 597 bucks boom that's a really
good deal I think I think what I got mine is like 700 bucks so don't tell
people that's embarrassing but now where you guys got a great phone oh yeah that's
true that's a true story that's all that's another that's another tings
history right there there you go yeah it pays to be the editor doesn't it so go
to ting go get yourself a great bone go get yourself a plan because really
they've got you know they got stuff as low you can get a decent phone for as
low as a hundred bucks or actually if you want to get a feature phone much
lower than that and if you got a phone and you probably do because I got GSM
and CDMA networks so if you got a phone I encourage you to just go get a SIM card
because the SIM cards are really cheap nine bucks you pop a SIM card in this
one SIM card here if it's all your different devices it like yeah it's
really cool to do it and you just pop it out to the size you need they were
really were pretty clever when they designed this thing I'm thinking about
having ting be my backup network you know and totally certain other large
networks aren't working so well this is a great way to go like if you if you
have six dollars a month we kind of unofficially do it here at the studio
already so of course we don't use it as our primary internet here at the studio
but when the studio goes out well the first thing we do is we start tethering
from our team devices because it's just data like it doesn't affect the
contract I don't have to call up and get a shared program you know it's just turn
it on and I don't know for what yeah it is really really nice check it out
linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged
program linux.com is where you go to support this show okay let's talk about
the linux foundation this happened while I was on the road I didn't even know
this was going down but apparently this is another disgusting example of what
happens in the Linux community I'll start you off at the top so there's been
a controversy that's erupted around the Linux foundation it's it's it's whether
the Linux foundation essentially is serving open source community or
corporate sponsors that's essentially the takeaway headline but the Linux
foundation the nonprofit organization that supports Linux and increasingly
other open-source projects like I'm a big fan of the fact that they have the
the core infrastructure initiative which funds a lot of really important
open-source they tend to not really have any controversies but I really hate
this Michael Garrett a security developer at
CoreOS former Red Hat employee etc etc you probably for the name before
recently spotted that the Linux foundation has changed its bylaws to no
longer permit individual foundation members to elect members of the group's
board of directors Garrett wrote the majority of its board is chosen by
member companies ten by platinum members platinum membership costs five hundred
thousand a year three by gold members gold membership cost a hundred thousand
dollars a year and by one silver member a silver membership is five thousand
dollars and a twenty thousand dollar a year depending on your company size up
until recently individual members which I am loved one for $99 a year could also
elect two board members allowing a community perspective to be represented
at the board level which is one of the reasons I became a Linux Foundation
member get your voice hurt mm-hmm so this is an article at ZDNet written up
by Steven and he says why would the Linux Foundation do this carrot
speculates it's because of Karen Sandler the executive directory director of the
software freedom conservancy a woman who we have interviewed many times on our
shows an organization that does vitally important work of the enforcement of the
GPL I recently shared with you the story about their fight to enforce GPL
violations of VMware VMware who is a Linux Foundation member so Garrett
speculates that the individual membership program was quietly renamed
to the individual supporter program and the promised benefit of being allowed to
stand for and participate in board elections was dropped he compares the
old page and gives you a link to the new page he asked why would the Linux
Foundation do this well he states that historically it's been less than
enthusiastic about GPL enforcement and the software freedom conservancy is
funding a lawsuit against one of the foundation's members for violating terms
of the GPL he speculates they have made this move to prevent Karen Sandler from
joining the board then because of this speculation Karen Sandler has found
herself under attack by people who have assumed that her mission is to bring
some sort of agenda to the Linux Foundation a one that they would define
as a social justice warriors agenda and so she has now come under attack because
of Garrett's speculation here the Linux Foundation didn't help the situation
it's not really their fault but Jim Zimmerman or Zimmerman Zemlin Zemlin
yeah who I've met and talked to before he's a nice guy was apparently busy
while all this shit was happening and everybody was declaring that the Linux
Foundation had betrayed the community and that this was an effort to switch
to corporate backing and that this was also an effort to block Karen Sandler
some even speculated a move by Linus Torvalds himself orchestrated by Linus
himself some of the crap that's out there is unbelievable and it turns out
of course that the guy that runs Linux Foundation was busy in China they
couldn't they couldn't get out because they were in China with limited access
to email as a result they only became aware of the problem 48 hours after it
blew up on social media and then they tried to make an immediate response on
their blog which completely sucked and was insufficient sorry Jim but it's true
the conversations relating to the Linux Foundation governance changes have
developed into personal inappropriate and offensive remarks he writes directed at
some members of the community in particular against Karen Sandler the
executive director of the software Freedom Conservancy but if you if you
extract yourself from all of that crap I think the real question behind the
debate is who actually is controlling the Linux Foundation is it the users or
is the companies now the current developers themselves are able to
direct some members to elect some members of the board like the technical
steering committee but Michael Garrett or Matthew Garrett sorry sees it as a
move as the Linux Foundation is taking one more step away from the community
and towards the corporate world it's not exactly addressed either that point is
not addressed in the Linux Foundation's post that's why I say it's in I say it's
insufficient but he does tell me say that the process for recruiting
community director should be changed to be in line with other leading
organizations in our community and our industry in other words nobody else does
it this way so in addition Garrett pointed out individuals are no longer
have the ability to run for and vote for the Linux Foundation board seat and
influence the direction of the foundation which I think is a bit of a
loss mm-hmm that said a lot of times what happens is these board positions
are clown shows they're people who are sort of positioned there by a corporate
interest they're people who are want to be pushed in position there because it's
better for their career to have it on their resume they are not always always
fully representative of who you actually want and a lot of times it's really the
companies that have different people in those positions line them up so that way
they can influence things and even when it's not the case like in the case of HP
it's often accused to be the case it's claimed to be the case so it often looks
bad anyways it is it to me I coming back from my trip I look at this and I go
this looks like a hot mess and I find myself to be sort of like taken aback by
all that wimpy I'm curious what your reaction is I see you had some thoughts
you know I'm wimpy hmm what do we are we in the wrong oh sorry with the go-ahead
so we're in the wrong room wimpy are you there do we lose you I think he's so
upset he left West well we should take a moment and have a beer we should take a
moment and have I do think he makes a good point though that you know we have
to consider the nature of Linux you know it's an open source thing it exists on
its own the Linux Foundation has always been you know like he's has a trade
association it's kind of a nice mechanism to extract money from people
who use Linux for their profits and then gear that you know they use it for open
you know the infrastructure but it has not it is not and as as Greg cage talks
in the our Linux link yeah you know if the community members haven't
necessarily besides be Dale then good representations of the community yes
they haven't really functioned this way so maybe a name oh I really like so
Greg cage took to the Linux subreddit and responded to some comments and I
really we're gonna link to that in the show notes because I really liked his
his take on it I don't can we not hear anybody in the number of somebody said
North Ranger say something for me can you do you say yeah do you see him
lighting up yep well I don't know what's going on computers are hard West I don't
know what's going on we're not experts here no no hi I don't I don't understand
the computers work and as far as I'm concerned we should all go back to
calculators I don't maybe close that thing and reopen it for me Wes I have no
idea I have no idea I I look at this and I I I'm trying I'm trying to suss out if
there is bad blood between the Linux Foundation and the software freedom
conservancy that's really my question right is there something going on there
is the Linux Foundation affected by its members I might oh I would tell you I
would like to sit here and tell you because I have a lot of respect for the
Linux Foundation I've worked with them on some projects in the past several
projects I do a lot of good things for the ecosystem yeah yeah like they pay
Greg and Linus that's a great right and the core infrastructure all kinds of
stuff they I also I also have seen sort of a side of the Linux Foundation that
gives me pause because it doesn't seem genuine it doesn't seem honest and that
is there are news outlets online they purport to be just straight news outlets
that are actually PR fronts press releases for the members of the Linux
Foundation primarily Sousa and Red Hat but others as well that hire people that
are their PR people to write articles for them and then they publish them on
these quote-unquote news sites as like as an article that essentially implies
this is why you should use distro you know insert Red Hat or Sousa or whatever
instead of something else and it's they are essentially native advertising
pieces that the Linux Foundation is allowing their members they're
contributing members to publish through their publishing platforms and I find
that to be disingenuous and I also over the years have found it to actually be
shaping the tone of the conversation in the community and I find that to also be
discussing and disingenuous so I would like to say that I have absolute
respect for the Linux Foundation but if I'm being completely honest with you I
have seen some practices that seem disingenuous to me I it basically it
seems that if you write a big enough check the Linux Foundation you get
access to their publishing platform and do what they want you want and that
bothers me because as somebody who publishes like that that really bothers
me now maybe I have it wrong maybe I don't but I do wonder if this is a shift
more towards corporate funding corporate sponsoring corporate interest which is
honestly where Linux makes its bones right now and maybe this is a moment for
us as community members to consider you know just how we think of the Linux
Foundation in terms of the larger ecosystem and other organizations that
maybe can do similar roles the other thing the other thing I question and I
wish I knew more about it and I absolutely welcome Matthew Garrett to
come on the show if you want to tell us about it himself the Mumba room is open
when it's working what I don't understand exactly is why Matthew made
these speculations about the known found the Linux Foundation making these
changes specifically to to try to screw Karen I know that there was some timing
of some talks canceled all that kind of stuff but when you talk to Karen there
doesn't seem to be any malice on her part I'm just wondering where that
speculation came from because it led to some weird stuff that happened and I'm
kind of curious why he did that and maybe if he knows something that we
don't know but it seems like he went to his blog and made some speculations that
ended up causing a shit ton of issues for the Linux Foundation who are
honestly doing something that any foundation would normally do I don't
know if it necessarily agree with it but and there is merit to him bringing up
that they did away with the seeds just kind of the other stuff that got glommed
on there that maybe took away from that exactly exactly like I think it's a good
thing to mention as a contributing member I wouldn't have known this
otherwise exactly that part totally valid we should have a conversation
about that the speculation where why they did it it feels off base because
it's nothing unusual for a foundation to do like this it by their own bylaws
they're allowed to make these changes like it's all internal yeah so I don't
know exactly it leaves me it leaves me taking a bit of a pause but the the full
write-up Stephen J Vaughn Hoff Nicholas did a great I just added the Hoff who
wasn't he wasn't at scale that's too bad yeah he's like pretty much one of the
only Linux quote-unquote celebrities that wasn't at scale I don't know I mean
that's all right Noah was there showing him up so it doesn't matter he would
have to compete with Noah how can you right he doesn't bring the Google Glass
though really you know why you know why no here's something you'd never know
unless you're a glass hole if you change radical climates Google Glass gets
destroyed only because so the way that works is the projector that projects the
thing in your eyeball it projects against a foil reflection reflection
reflective material okay that's on the end of the prism that then bounces it
back into your eyeball when you travel and see where Noah's at it's like below
it's like negative 16 Fahrenheit right now so it's like crazy cold it's in
human cold it literally is no one should I live there no he should move and he
should come to join us and be end up but he's you know like the boiling frog he
doesn't know life any other way but what he has learned is when he travels to
places that have human climates like the West Coast yep I'm not boy people are
snowed in right now I'm we don't get any snow so I don't mean to make fun of you
but anyways he travels but if he makes large climate changes the foil that is
that the prism uses for projection reflection bubbles up and it destroys the
ability to project anything in Google Glass permanently yeah and so as he has
to get it replaced every time he does this and Google's been pretty good about
it but now they don't make glass anymore he feels like this might be his last
glass so now he can be now he's afraid to travel with it in the winter it's a
home glass it's home glass yep cuz it's too cold where he lives yeah he needs
like a humidor for it yeah yeah maybe maybe yeah now hold on now see a gates
earthquakes ain't got nothing to do with climate that's the two separate issues
yeah we're gonna have an earthquake that's why I drove highway 101 so I
could see the coast before it falls off into the ocean though I thought it'd be
beautiful I don't know what to do about a mobile room yeah I don't know what to
do about that Rekai what's going on what's going on I'm not sure what's
going on with that you closed and opened it right I sure did yeah I don't know
we're in the on air channel yeah we are we are you know what I'm gonna do I'll
reset the channel over on the mixer here we go you're ready for that let's see
here with you I think that we should all make those yeah okay yeah I just gotta
purge this buffer over here get it out of here okay there we go
okay wimpy can you can you say something now are you there hello yeah dearest
friends the mumble room that's all you got to do you guys can you just got a
reset the channel and flash a little bit so it was if there's anything you want
to mention on the foundation thing go ahead no I think where's covered it my
point was very brief and that's that the Linux Foundation is a trade is a trade
Association you pay to be a member of that trade Association and the Linux
Foundation represent the interests of its members and for the most part the
interests of its members are going to be conflicted with grassroots community
stuff hmm there's going to be some overlap you know you've mentioned core
infrastructure projects and all the rest of it that's terrific but being no doubt
that we're a we benefit as a byproduct of them surfing look we made you a nice
platform that works oh you guys can have it yeah yeah yeah I mean you know but
you know there yeah that's it trade Association there are lots of them in
different industries and that's how they work I would understand that they wanted
to remove you know instead of having two seats they wanted to limit it so they
could have they could open another seat to another you know another corporate
interest or something like that that makes sense but to completely remove the
community from the situation is just really weird it feels like it would made
them special to me it feels like what made them special is gone right I don't
think we'd question it if they'd never had one if that has nothing grown up but
the fact that they have had it and then just remove it even if it wasn't
necessarily doing its job it yeah it's hard to ignore to see the internet go
batshit crazy though and say that Linus is orchestrating some sort of campaign
against social justice warriors is sort of like I can't imagine he would care
for more than his colonel to even worry about that yeah it's a total misread of
what live in the priorities are yeah it shows what total lack of understanding
people have of how they have the how the community actually works it's sort of
ridiculous yeah we've got a community calling for our destruction here Chris
is that no what happened in this earthquake oh I know dude dude they're
gonna they're gonna totally they're gonna totally call call that cause it to
happen thanks guys thanks guys that's alright
then I'll just have to move over to to yeah man my I got I got I live on
springs and shocks I won't even notice but no actually that's not true you know
what I do notice Linux Academy because I noticed that they have made some major
improvements over at Linux Academy I'd like you to go there it's a learning
platform for Linux and all the technologies around it everything that
really kicks ass in the Linux ecosystem they've got stuff to help you learn and
manage it including like AWS platforms of course the Red Hat certified courses
step-by-step video courses so many of them downloadable comprehensive study
guides instructor help is available 7 plus distress for you to choose from
that's the highlights Linux Academy has really been rocking they just had a big
announcement recently they've rolled out a ton of new features but one I want to
talk about today which I think is super cool is the new Linux Academy mobile app
for iOS and Android this is a really really great idea if you get a couple of
minutes on your device I think this is gonna be the way to go you're gonna see
the Android version coming at the end of q1 2016 it's gonna be free for all the
users of course you're gonna need to be a member to take advantage of it but
look at that right there it gives you an idea of what it's like to become a
Linux Academy member you go in there you can create you can choose a topic they
go you go into Linux certification training you can go into OpenStack AWS
DevOps then once you go into those realms there is so much content to learn
there is scenario based labs there are great great exercises for you to take
there are nuggets to go deep dive into a single topic when you're ready in-depth
resources virtual machines that spin up with the courseware on demand that you
can SSH into brand new CDN to distribute all of that content and live streams of
a bunch of really really great sessions where you can ask the educators
questions directly it's amazing how helpful this is just if you want to be a
Linux professional in any way right like yeah maybe you've been doing it forever
and you want to catch up with what's this DevOps jazz you keep hearing about
one of the things there's two things in the Linux Academy we're really kind of
like game changers for me personally the first one was taking courseware and
breaking it down into hours you know learn Python in six hours no longer this
nebulous thing oh I need to spend six hours that I can actually understand
Python but the other thing is is I suck at taking tests like not my thing I hate
it like because I always feel like tests are like of these scenarios that never
actually happen in the real world and so then I really just Google right so now
one of the things they have to help with test anxiety that I have is practice
exams nice yeah you can use Linux Academy practice exams to help prepare
your way through the like like maybe AWS or one of the red hats courses or
anything like that you can also take Linux Academy quizzes to help ensure
you're learning the core concepts required to be successful so not just
passing the test not just passing the test really understanding them yeah
that's really use it you know you've already deployed it once you've finished
with Linux Academy and as a listener of our program you go to Linux Academy on
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged you get a great discount that's cool thing
number one Linux Academy comm slash unplugged but because we've been talking
about Linux Academy for a while now lots of JB members in their community lots of
Jupiter colony members up in that community so you're hanging out with a
great group of friends that help give you that sort of confidence boost when
you need it or celebrate when you've got some breakthrough it's really cool
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for
sponsoring the unplug program and congrats on the new app and all of the
new updates you guys are kicking and Anthony was down at scale I didn't get
chance to say hi to him but he was down at scale so you might have got a chance
it really our community members I loves it yeah they're huge enthusiasts it's
really cool so AMD has got something hot for us GPU open GP open is composed of
two areas games and CGI for games graphics and content creation holy yeah
they're the first to provide code they say and documentation allowing PC
developers to exert more control over the GPU but that's the first part of it
the second part of it is a commitment to open source software the game and
graphics development community is an active hub of enthusiasts individuals
who believe in the value of sharing knowledge full and flexible access to
the source of tools libraries and effects is a key pillar of the GPU open
philosophy so it's not just talking to the driver it's art assets it's all
kinds of stuff documentation library is you need to take advantage of their
sweet sweet hardware so this is being put on by AMD I understand is that your
understanding as well yeah what every single year here's where I'm at with
this I'm getting real sick and tired of this crap getting real bitter and I'm
becoming a little skeptical every year I sit here and I'm reading you stories
about how AMD is gonna revolutionize their open source graphics driver how
they're gonna decouple this how they're gonna have user space that kernel space
that how they're gonna have initiative this protocol that and every single year
I feel like I'm just reading a different version of this story and this is the
coolest version yet that gets me just as excited as ever at the end of the day
what the hell is actually going on with what's going on here unfortunately I
think we're still in the wait and see you know I'm glad they've launched this
website they've had code up on github for a little while but so you know we're
still waiting for Vulcan we're still waiting for the I'm just all of the AMD
GPU stuff I am Colonel and be deployed by distributions I know I piss off all
the AMD fans when I say this but I'm just not impressed I I love all of the
things they're saying and every time they say them I love them every single
time and then I just I don't I guess what it feels like to me right now is
before the last idea ever even sees code they got a whole new idea that's even
better than the last idea that this right we had mantle and now well now
it's there for supporting Vulcan which is good but it's still like and I feel
like for three years I've been hearing about how they're gonna split the
graphics drivers up and it's gonna be super awesome and you can just use the
open source driver and if you want a few more features you go get this binary
blob in user space and you're good to go to be fair they never actually claimed
that mantle is coming to the Linux they even were asked specifically and they
just basically dismissed it saying that if people wanted it then maybe they'd
consider it but now they're actually saying that the since they're doing open
source is actually gonna be coming and I think it's great you know that like
what they're saying is great and I'm optimistic but you know it's been ten
years since they were reasonably usable in Linux so at this point I was still
not gonna buy their stuff yeah it's hard to come back from underperforming to
such a level here's why it's a double burn for me and this is really obsessed
me so not only are they saying crap that I like and want and they're not
delivering as far as I can estimate and these any material way that actually
matters at all but at the same time it's like hey everybody and this is something
the Windows users that's like the savvy ones are starting to give Linux users a
hard time about hey come to the Linux desktop the land of free and open source
choice where you have all the great choices in the world oh except for your
graphics card if you want any performance at all use Nvidia replace
most of your weird X stack with so like we have one video card manufacturer that
makes I mean like really where where's the choice you can use Intel and have a
subpar experience you can use Nvidia or you can use AMD and in my testing the
Nvidia is by far and and and and really the only easy one-click solution by most
distros for end-users to implement and get great graphics performance yeah we
have one choice if you're a regular end-user in Linux land and it's Nvidia
there's there's no come to the land of multiple choice except for why here you
only have one choice and and and AMD is done nothing in all this time nothing to
change the situation a lot of good talk I get all hot and bothered they kind of
just have followed Nvidia's track but not done it as well
wimpy what do you think you think the iris graphics is is finally there you
think we're finally finally there with the 6100 I'm not the biggest gamer but I
have embraced steam in the last few months and my nut with iris 6100 plays
all the games I have and I've got I think I don't know if I have a 6100
machine I don't know if I have one and I haven't tried that one but I'm not just
running the games but running the games at quad HD so just to be clear this is
not 4k quad HD is 1440p that's nice it's not William I'm curious to see what you
think about this so I think AMD has been in the state where they just have to
announce paper launches for things yeah like we have this great idea here it is
but they're not gonna have that thing materialized for years like oh we've
made an initial commit and we have a plan here's this thing we're launching
but it's not gonna launch for a couple of years and see until we get down the
road until we have hardware support until we have all these things until
we've actually written the software like don't don't abandon us don't abandon us
right they don't want you to abandon them because they're kind of falling
behind and they're trying to show all these paper releases that just aren't
there yet so we're in I hope we get there and I think we will get there
eventually so is the way to take time so do you think the way to look at GPU open
is more about it's a piece to the overall strategy so an open source
driver is a piece to that but also piece of that is giving developers open
resources to take advantage of to make great games like it's it's part of the
overall strategy but it's just part of it and we're just waiting around that
really that's really what's going on here isn't it I mean it's even like the
splitting of the GPU driver it's part of the strategy they're gonna try and make
all the kernel space stuff open and integrated into the mainline kernel and
then have a bunch of user space components that they can change out
depending on whether you want proprietary features or not right I'm
so nice and they're just we're slowly getting there like they just started
committing this I want to say like five kernel versions back you know we're
finally getting to somewhere where it's usable yeah they have at least dumped
some code into the kernel which is but they announced it way back when yeah
that's where that's where I'm kind of like oh come on already but I like the
idea of open source resources graphic assets all that kind of stuff for
developers that's really cool we'll see if they can get their foot in the door
with like scientific stuff if open CL can really compete with yeah you know
yeah video stuff there yeah and they're also distracted with all their side
projects like they're building the a1100 arm chips and they got to get sent out
the door and they got to get the new GPU architecture done like they've got all
these things yeah that was a huge paper release like they talked about this
three years ago as being ready in a year and it still isn't even shipping like
we're just getting there now hopefully so we'll see you know I've talked about
this before but you look at the next three years for Linux mm-hmm we have
never had more change coming ever so you have you have obviously we've talked
about today Wayland coming you have Vulcan coming right you have the
continuation of evolution of system D and bus one or KD bus whatever it's
gonna be that's coming and all of these transitions are gonna be some of the
biggest transitions we have ever seen in the desktop ever like a lot of times we
see things that are really huge on the cloud and server but this this is gonna
be huge and wimpy there's another big one I didn't even mention coming isn't
there yeah I was said if s is I think it's gonna really gain traction in in
the Linux mm-hmm over the next yeah 12 months yeah 18 months well I'll be
running ZFS on root machines with Wayland open-source AMD graphics it'll
be a glorious future in system D container yeah right exactly and spawn
man oh whatever you're drinking where's I want to find you know I'm gonna just
end it right there that's a good way to wrap it up on the unplugged show it is
gonna be a couple of crazy years and guess what we're gonna be talking about
it they do every single annoying minutia along the way we'll be discussing right
here on your talk show Linux unplugged we'd love to have you joins don't forget
we do this show on Tuesdays go over to Jupiter broadcasting comms less calendar
to get the live time jblive.tv is where you watch it Linux actually showed out
reddit comms where you go to submit content and stories and you heard our
virtual log you could participate in that you just need the mumble software
open-source software go to our IRC room you can get the info on how to join us
we'd love to have you here on the unplugged program if you can't make it
the subreddit it's just great all right thanks for being here see you right back
here next Tuesday
so I kind of feel like I'm gonna get some crap for calling out the Linux
Foundation on that on that news outlet thing but that is something that they do
that really bothers me yeah because it feels really dishonest and it's
basically you know you got to be of a certain you got to be of a certain
contribution level it seems I can't go I can't exactly tell what it is and you
have to have writing staff and if you meet those qualifications you get to
publish through some fairly well well-established news outlets and then on
top of that because they're because they're established enough all of this
all of the new syndication sites pick up those stories and then it just becomes
part of the discussion and it feels like they get background cred in the
community because of the Linux Foundation name on the front right even
if the company play maybe uses it for their end but doesn't isn't a good
community player it's not something I've brought up before a lot because I feel
like I'm good there's gonna be a certain amount of backlash because I value my
relationship with the Linux Foundation because I think in other words they in
other you know other realms they do a lot of good and I've worked with them in
several projects before and they've been fruitful and I enjoyed that and and also
you know I like to be able to speak to the people that they pay they write the
paychecks to but at the end of the day like that is a concern of mine that I
have so it's a real tight line for me to walk there but I kind of feel like I
have to say it's something that bothers me and it doesn't mean that they're bad
as a whole it just means this is an aspect that happens that I don't quite
understand maybe I'm wrong about but to me I would like to know more information
about it and it doesn't it doesn't preclude the fact that they also
contribute to open source projects when they can that they contribute to people
that are making incredible changes in the Linux kernel that doesn't doesn't
it doesn't take away from any of that so I hope I don't get too much crap for it
but I'm probably gonna get some crap well you always get crap that's just
have you been to the internet before I don't know but yeah yeah that's all it's
true that's true I do that it's good boy I'm trying to think of like what's the
worst-case slack scenario because it because I'm starting to slide West I'm
sliding into slack and it's I mean I've had a great I love that they have it
even if it's just chromium they have the Linux dev files that I've enjoyed that
yeah I think it's sub clutter I can't remember what the name of it is that I'm
using on the Linux desktop for a dedicated slide okay and you know their
iOS client is great Android no complaints yeah really either but I mean
even we have a couple channels just for like individual projects and on some of
them we've gone past 10,000 messages yeah and then the archive starts to go
away and it's like you start depending especially on things like where you're
sharing information you're like oh well just just pass there I know the some
information I wanted did I put it in this channel for use and so we are hey
we've asked if like you know we're trying to see if not yet so we haven't
been we're seeing about pain and so serious so that I saw like there was a
recent thread did you get on reddit about matter most yeah yeah I have not
actually tried it I know I should huh the thing is I guess the thing that
matter most isn't gonna deliver for me right now at least is it takes 30
seconds almost to set up a new slack like yeah it's super easy great and if
I'm hosting it myself I just I don't really have time for this right now I
just need problems solved I don't want to create more problems down the road
but here's what I'm truly truly worried about and I don't know exactly where you
go to find it I'm trying to figure out yeah like if so here's an example like
if I want to upgrade to standard edition $880 per year is what it would cost
Jupiter broadcasting right now and that's just because we only we only have
11 users in our slack I think for us it was somewhere in the couple grand rate
yeah or eight per user per month that's a little more swallow me sending
invoices out to crew members so then it goes back to well okay it's kind of
worth looking at matter most but it is it has become a critical tool and the
thing the other does it well and the other problem is a lot of people now
have slack accounts yep so you can it's already have the client on their phone
yeah yeah they already know how to use it too and some people are already kind
of like slack clever and they like yeah so I like that one of them I don't
remember it was better most or rocket chat I think had better markdown support
slack has like partial but yeah markdown support would be kill Lark cuz then we
could actually cut and paste stuff right into show notes yeah yeah somebody should
set up a matter most for us and let us try it out maybe we need like a matter
most slack bridge well I would I would be I would also like to know people know
of a hosted matter most solution yeah yeah because I just don't I just am not
in a position to manage more stuff I like if I have free time right now I
want to spend it on other projects right now I don't want to spend my time on
that so I would really like to get a recommendation I wonder if there's also
just for me like maybe I can just set up the IRC bridge and then have a IRC
program that saves all my history archives it that way keep up the keep
the free moon yeah I assume that so when I think of hosting matter most right my
my mind immediately goes to well I'm gonna spin up a digital ocean droplet
right and I'm gonna register a domain and I'm gonna create user accounts and
then I'm gonna convince all of the JB people to switch over from slack to this
new system and we're gonna have to do a cream a clean break of our history and
then when we fill up space or we want more users or whatever it's always gonna
be on me to do it and just right I'm not digging that idea that's a big workload
and you're not gonna want to troubleshoot it when you're right before
show then again I don't feel like spending a grand a year for essentially
fancy IRC right when you have the technical capability yeah not maybe the
time is a real son-of-a-bitch problem yeah I almost wish I was ignorant and
just had to pay and it's like you smart for your own good Chris yeah I guess
that is kind of a thing I don't know