Now that we're through the holidays, it's the season of events.
And there's one that I was just looking through our list that we don't have in here.
And maybe it's because it's like outside the US.
But we got to include everybody, right?
Of course we do. That just wouldn't be fair.
No, exactly.
Oddcamp 2019. That didn't make our list for this week's episode.
It's going to be in Manchester October 19th.
Jeez, that's like forever from now. That's like forever from now.
It is. So you have plenty of time to plan your trip.
Oddcamp is an unconference celebrating free culture,
free and open source software, hardware hacking, digital rights,
and all manner of collaborative cultural activities.
It'd be pretty fun to go, Wes.
I mean, I'm just saying.
I know.
Chris and Wes, mess up Manchester.
I can hear it now.
Yeah, you said it first.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 285, for January 22nd, 2019.
Oh, hey there, and welcome into Linux Unplugged,
your weekly Linux talk show that's all over the world recording live
and mostly has its crap together.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes. And speak for yourself, Chris.
Hello, Mr. Payne.
You know, I should, I should.
It's just, when I look at today's episode,
I think we must be going at an unbelievable,
unstoppable pace, if you will.
We have a bunch of really interesting community news,
some that's getting a lot of attention.
I don't know why it's getting so much attention,
but we'll have Wes break it all down for us.
Then we have a bunch of great updates,
so many things to announce and to cover today.
A lot of stuff going on in the community.
Then we'll chat with someone, an individual,
one crazy person out there,
who hopes to make the next design tool for Linux
to build applications, not just for Linux,
but for other operating systems as well.
And it's one of those tools that when you talk to developers,
Linux desperately needs.
And the plan to fund this thing is rather unique
and seems like they could actually pull it off.
So we'll bring on Alex, the main developer and originator
behind this project,
and see what he has planned.
Then, in the second half of the show,
it's undeniable that open source is facing a new,
quote-unquote, headwind.
Yeah, there's your business speak for you.
And it's obvious when you look at things like
the recent MongoDB relicensing,
AWS's announcement of DocumentDB,
which is a MongoDB rip-off,
and so many other things that open source projects
that are server-side projects
that we're hoping for some significant funding
once they grew to a certain size
are being replaced by commercial products
that offer all of the wonderful benefits
of these commercial products
and none of the openness.
And it's a massive problem
that's actually impacting the way
these open source projects get funded.
So we'll talk about that,
and I'll give you my first impressions
of Ubuntu 19.04 Disco Dingo,
which I've been running here for a few days.
And it's fast.
I'll tell you a little bit about that.
But before we go any stinking further into the show,
we must bring in that virtual lug.
Time-appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Good morning, everyone.
Greetings.
Hello.
Hello, Bruce and Cubicle Nate
and Mini Mac and Sean and Brent.
It's good to see you back as well.
How has your travels gone?
I'm still traveling.
It's kind of a crazy, crazy time.
Wow, of course you are.
I know.
I know it's nuts.
But good to be a little bit closer
to you guys in the world.
Where are you?
That's a great question.
I'm currently in...
That doesn't sound like you know, Brent, honestly.
I'm starting to piece it together.
I'm currently in B.C.,
sort of like southeastern B.C.
Next week I'm in Quebec City,
and we'll see after that.
Okay, I'm in Texas,
and Wes is in Seattle,
so it's a good spread.
We've got a good spread going here today.
So let's start with the story
that you may see shared the most right now.
If you're listening around the time
this episode is released,
which is around the last
or second week of January-ish,
depending on when you're listening to this,
there is a lot of discussion right now
about vulnerabilities in apt,
including remote code execution,
which is also leading to other discussions
about using HTTP versus HTTPS.
So Wes, I was hoping maybe you could break down
like what is the big hoopla about right now
in regards to remote code execution
and the man-in-the-middle attacks with apt.
Oh yeah, it's been making the rounds today.
And a security researcher by the name of Max
found a remote code execution vulnerability
in apt and apt-get.
And really the first thing you should acknowledge,
and we've talked about this before,
is when you install packages,
well, at least in the apt system,
they have root access to your file system
so bad things can happen.
It's important to trust where your packages come from
and go through the hoops to verify
that that package actually came from the source you expect.
Now combine that with the fact that,
by default, at least in Ubuntu and Debian,
your system is generally not set up
to use an HTTPS mirror.
So just plain text over HTTP.
Now, most of the time that's just fine, right?
As we said, there's usually at least checksums
and almost always a GPG signature involved.
So you can go check and verify
that the package is valid.
Yeah, so the actual packages,
even if it's coming down over HTTP,
the actual packages have signatures.
Yes, okay, so here's where it gets a little bit trickier.
Now, internally, when apt runs,
it has an internal helper for HTTP.
So the main process sort of spawns it off
and says, here's all the packages I'm working on.
Go do all the HTTP stuff.
And then that process responds back over a socket
to the main process with, like,
oh, here's the URL or, you know,
there was a redirect or 404,
whatever the particulars of the transaction might be.
What you didn't expect, though,
is that, of course, it's an older utility
and it's not a nice protocol
and no, no, it's just line delimited plain text.
Yeah, exactly.
And the HTTP helper doesn't really handle the redirects.
It reports the redirect
and then the main process decides what to do,
usually then issues a new request,
you know, for wherever the new resource
can actually be found after the redirect.
There's like a multi-process architecture here
where there's one part of apt
that becomes aware of a redirect.
It captures that and then it delivers it
to another part of apt which then makes the decision.
Yes, and also the helper is responsible
for handling, like, unencoding,
unescaping all the URL parameters,
but it just blindly includes that in its output.
It doesn't sanitize it.
It doesn't make sure that it's carefully delimited.
It just hands that right back to the main process.
And so someone could sneak something in there, basically.
Exactly.
So if you construct a malicious URL in your redirect,
you can basically tell the main process
to go download any arbitrary package you want,
which includes any arbitrary signature
and because as we talked about,
packages have root access,
that's a remote code vulnerability.
Okay, okay, okay.
So really, it's a couple of things here.
I mean, essentially, at the core of it,
it's a man-in-the-middle attack
which perhaps something like using HTTPS
would potentially help with.
So even though the packages have signatures,
doing everything over HTTP means
that the things aren't getting verified as they would
if they was using HTTPS, correct?
Right, so yeah, basically, there's two possible attacks
and one is a compromised mirror itself, right?
Somebody takes over the mirror that you're using
and HTTPS doesn't help you there.
You're kind of just screwed and your trust is broken.
But the bigger thing and the thing that HTTPS
can protect against is network attacks,
things like BGP hijacks or anytime someone
is able to be a man-in-the-middle,
change your connection so that you are presented
with someone who's not real.
If you've got an HTTPS connection,
then you have a root certificate somewhere
that presumably your man-in-the-middle attacker
can't attack or at least it's a lot harder to do that
than just to, say, put a man-in-the-middle
between you and your corporate firewall.
Okay, so what's going on here?
Because I did a little looking around.
OpenSUSE's zipper uses HTTPS, DNF uses HTTPS.
Why is Ubuntu and Debian not using HTTPS?
Seems like they should be.
You know, that's a good question
and it's kind of been quite the debate
for a number of years.
Now, of course, you can use HTTPS.
It makes some things like setting up,
easily setting up caches in between,
it makes those things harder.
So there are some downsides.
And you might have less mirror selection, of course.
But security really comes down to defense in depth.
And so while most of the time signatures are enough,
HTTPS can really be helpful.
So it seems like why not make that the default?
You can still have HTTPS available as a fallback.
That's fine.
Just let users have the most security right out of the gate.
I think it's worth mentioning
that this isn't just a theoretical threat.
On March 9th, 2018,
there was a report that a Turkish ISP
had swapped the downloads of popular software
with their own hosted spyware infected versions.
Now, this was mostly targeted at Windows users
so us Linux users don't really need to worry about it that much.
But the concept is the same.
And a lot of tools that you would download
to just make your Windows box run decent
were replaced with their own infected versions of the applications
where the download links were just using HTTP.
And it does kind of make you think
like this could be done on a larger scale.
Say, this could be an attack against all Ubuntu users potentially.
It might not be a common threat, but it is a very real threat.
Well, you still, remember, have the package signatures here.
You still have to have a valid package
that passes the signature check.
But that assumes that everything from the get-go
was set up without a man in the middle.
Right. And with this vulnerability,
it was possible to add additional...
Because you can have these same problems,
let's say, if you started off with something
that was affected from the ISO,
which is often also not served over HTTPS.
Oh, no. Oh, no.
Now we're going down a rabbit hole of paranoia.
But it is something I think that is worth thinking about.
And it's gotten a lot of attention.
We should note, too, that this is already patched
in recent versions of apt.
And you can mitigate it just by enabling HTTPS
and using an HTTPS repo.
So go do those things if you need to.
In both Debian and Ubuntu, this has been patched,
but you have to be on a supported version, obviously,
to get those fixes.
Do you think this is something that they'll address?
Do you think in a period of time we'll see HTTPS apt mirrors?
Or is this something that will just kick down for a while?
This is a can that will continue to get kicked.
What do you think?
Oh, that's hard to say.
You know, I could see it certainly in Ubuntu.
The times, the landscape, it's changing.
HTTPS is just about everywhere.
There's been a lot of pushers browser side.
I think everyone's just a little more comfortable with it.
So the time's ripe.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, let's shift gears and talk about something
that I think is the Linux user's version of defragging your disk.
At least it is for me.
You know, when you talk to Windows users,
they'll talk about how they love watching disk defrag
because it's sort of peaceful,
like just to sit there and watch the data reassemble.
And then they used to debate, like, when should you defrag the disk
and all these kinds of things.
Well, I do this myself with the Linux scheduler.
I'm constantly wondering, like, am I using the best IO scheduler?
Am I using an IO scheduler for a server when I'm in a desktop environment?
I've also heard that Manjaro will ship a desktop optimized IO scheduler.
And I guess, Wes, while we're still having you break things down for us,
I wanted to have you break down this story.
To the best of your ability, what the hell is an IO scheduler?
And then kind of related to that,
could you talk about this article that we found
where they attempted to use eBPF,
which is a new feature in the Linux kernel,
which is super cool that we should talk about too.
They attempted to use eBPF to determine which IO scheduler is the best.
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay, so there you are, Mr. Chris Fisher,
and you're doing a recording, you're making Linux unplugged,
and you got to save those bytes to disk.
So you tell your operating system.
I mean, really, you request your operating system,
go save these files to the disk, please.
But of course, you know, there's multiple blocks involved there.
Your disk is probably already doing other things from other processes
and maybe users running on that system.
So you got to have a schedule, in this case, an IO schedule.
And that's basically the kernel takes the input blocks
and the requests coming in and orders those
and then actually ships them out physically to the disk
to go get written to disk through whatever firmware is involved with your fancy SSD.
eBPF is a handy new feature that you see in modern kernels that does bytecode.
So you get to write cool little programs that get loaded into the kernel
and the whole idea is to be able to instrument and get statistics
on all the things happening in the kernel.
Basically, think of it as the building block we needed
to have D-Trace-like functionality on Linux.
This case, Fred over at Circonus, which is a monitoring company,
well, he's always been curious, right?
What is the best IO scheduler?
Because you've got a couple options here.
You've got the completely fair scheduler.
There's deadline. There's no op.
There can be more options in general,
but those are the ones he's looking at here today.
There's got to be differences on your workloads, right?
So eBPF is something that you can use.
Circonus has their own monitoring agent,
so he installs that on some Ubuntu systems.
You wouldn't have to do that.
They just happen to have a fancy eBPF plug-in for it
because eBPF is the new hotness, right?
And that lets him make easy graphs.
He sends it up to their service, and he can make charts and stuff.
What's funny is that ends up biting him in the butt,
as you'll see later on.
But it is still a pretty handy feature,
and I think it shows that those sorts of functionalities
are now becoming common even in commercial products.
Yeah, so the real story here isn't really the results
that they got from the test
because it doesn't really tell us much, unfortunately.
But perhaps the real story is,
holy shit, eBPF is awesome,
and now we have this functionality built in
to the fricking Linux kernel.
People probably will be familiar with the Berkeley packet filter.
Super quick version.
How is this different than what the BSDs have
with the Berkeley packet filter?
What is eBPF, and why is it way better
and so cool that we have it in Linux?
Well, eBPF is extended BPF.
And really why it's neat is it's always been super helpful,
and it's something you can use to write little programs
to go catch network traffic.
So it's what you're using under the hoods
when you're using TCP dump.
You write your little TCP dump command line,
which is basically just a DSL for writing this stuff.
TCP dump under the hood compiles it into BPF,
into bytecode, and then runs it against the network traffic,
and then you can set up these really tight little routines
to match, like, oh, I don't know,
only UDP traffic on port 53, for example.
Yeah, and that bytecode is running inside the kernel
in a safe way.
It's incredible.
You can do a lot of fancy analysis to sort of prove,
you know, this won't loop forever
and other sort of escape analysis.
And what's neat about it is that it's extended
because it's not just for network stuff.
You can load it all over the kernel.
So you finally get access to a bunch of information
that you couldn't do without manually instrumenting
and recompiling your kernel before.
I think that's a really important point to make there.
It's not just about networking.
In fact, we did a deep dive in TechSnap.
Go to TechSnap.systems slash 388.
It's the one about eBPF.
It's like a super competitive game-changing feature
that's coming, well, it's arrived.
And it's so nice that there's really high-end hardware
being built around this functionality now.
And so it's not something that's probably on your radar,
but it's such a cool thing that Linux can do now,
and I really recommend you go check out that episode
of TechSnap.
But in the meantime, it appears it's getting easier
than ever for Linux workloads on Windows 10.
Now, the Windows subsystem for Linux
has been around for quite a while,
but it has one huge limitation.
And that is it's actually lacking a functional Linux kernel.
Now, of course, you could fire up an Ubuntu VM or a Debian VM
or what have you in Hyper-V.
But it's not quite as functional and as easy
to script and control as you would, say,
be able to fire up a VM on Linux.
That's where Canonical's multipass comes in,
which today is coming out of private beta.
And it looks pretty nice.
Oh, yes.
Multipass, at its core, is a service to manage Linux
and really, in this case, Ubuntu.
Linux, Ubuntu, they're virtual machines running on Windows 10
but without the overhead of having to deal with Hyper-V yourself.
Maybe, especially, I think, in our case,
if you are a Linux user who might just have to use Windows 10
for some reason, for whatever job or particular workflow,
but you still want your Linux.
I'm not an experienced Hyper-V administrator.
I respect it, but I don't know it very well.
So multipass is awesome.
Right.
It's sort of using Hyper-V as an implementation detail
to just get really fast VMs fired up on a Windows box
that you can now access and control from the command line.
And once they're launched,
a PowerShell user could fire off commands and scripts
at multipass and the VM itself,
including things that run inside the VM,
applications that should be loaded
and features that can allow you to scale up multiples of these
or reproduce VMs for development purposes.
Yeah, I mean, really, that's it right there.
David Chalmers, a product manager over at Canonical,
told The Register that that's exactly what multipass is aimed at,
developers in a corporate environment.
There's a lot of challenges to do.
It's not a good workflow normally, right?
You might have either a horrible command line experience
that doesn't have like a full kernel and it's sort of confusing
or you've got this full virtualized GUI,
which again is not what you want.
It's nice to see Linux everywhere, isn't it?
Like this is becoming the runtime.
This is becoming the runtime of the enterprise environment
and that's why this is important.
This isn't really at desktop Windows 10 users
that want to play Steam games.
This is designed for people in the corporate environment
that want to use Linux as sort of a runtime
that they can get everywhere.
And you have all kinds of options now on Windows.
It's sort of amazing.
You have the subsystem for Linux,
which gets you a pretty usable Linux environment.
Now you've got these easy optimized Hyper-V VMs
that are the graphical way to do this
where Microsoft has worked with upstream distribution creators
like Canonical to make an optimized environment for Hyper-V,
which gives you nice things like keyboard and mouse
and copy and paste integration and alt-tabbing in and out
amongst other things.
And if that's not your flavor,
you prefer to work on the command line and script
and shell script things, you've got multi-pass now.
And it really is a sort of what works best for you
kind of option on Windows.
In this weird way, Windows 10 gives you ubiquitous Linux.
You can have a window that has Ubuntu up,
that has OpenSUSE up, that has Fedora up
and is running multiple types of different virtual environments
all on Windows 10.
There's no excuse, right?
As a Windows user, you can have Linux
in all or some of the ways that you like.
We're looking at a kind of modularity here.
It's Linux modularity on Windows.
But what if this went even deeper?
What if this went to the core of Windows itself?
And that might just be what's happening
thanks to what may go down as one of history's
most ridiculous technology story leaks ever.
Think about this in context.
A massive story about Microsoft open sourcing
core components of Windows itself.
Windows itself.
What are you talking about?
That cannot be true.
I know.
And then, get ready for this part,
it gets leaked by some mid-level employee
who's just updating his LinkedIn profile
because that is apparently what has happened this week.
We've never talked about Windows core before.
It has been a rumor for a couple of years.
I have heard it kicked around for a couple of years now.
But we've never seen anything about it.
And LinkedIn is advertised as a place
where people can share their work experience,
find jobs, and mingle with their peers.
And it's also over and over again
a roundabout way to leak information
about what massive corporations are working on
because one Microsoft employee profile mentions
the quote, open source components in Windows core OS.
Yeah, the profile in question
is a security program manager tasked with managing quote unquote
the security of Windows core OS
from malicious actors and code.
Hmm, now that's a little confusing
since Windows core OS hasn't been announced yet.
And that is the exact name of rumors
that I have personally heard
from people that would be familiar with the matter.
So I'm a little confused
because they were just rumors that I was dismissing until now.
And that same security program manager then said quote
that he improved the security posture
of Windows open source components
through initiatives that investigate vulnerabilities
found and establish a process for redemption.
So if you connect the dots between the two
you have reason to suspect that the Windows core OS
is going to rely on some mysterious open source components
which essentially brings us to the story now.
Yeah, I mean there's been rumors about core OS
I think since 2017
essentially people are suspect anyway
that it's kind of the core of a modular version of Windows
customized for all kinds of devices.
Microsoft already tried something like that with Windows 10.
Remember Windows 10 mobile, Chris?
Yes, I do.
But Windows core OS seems to be purpose built
for more cross-platform, if anything.
What do you think of this, Wes?
I mean Windows core, could you imagine Windows core OS being free
and the next version of the
and even they speculate in this article over at Tom's Hardware
they speculate about the next version of Windows desktop
being based on this Windows core OS.
This lines up, right?
It does and it doesn't.
I think it lines up because we've seen huge moves by Microsoft
in the world of open source, right?
They clearly understand, at least in their modern tooling
that open source is useful
and they take advantage of it and contribute to it.
But we haven't really, excluding some of the.NET stuff
.NET Core and PowerShell
we haven't really seen any inroads into the world of Windows
and that's where the Windows branding on this makes it kind of stand out.
Yeah, I think it's also worth mentioning Visual Studio Code
has been pretty well received.
In fact, when you look at their open source project
remember they just recently released Azure Sphere
which is based on Linux.
They open sourced the old MS-DOS recently
TypeScript, WinForms,.NET Core
They keep writing all those little handy command line utilities for Linux?
There's a lot of little things that over the years
have been sort of adding up
and this Core nomenclature has been the direction they've been going
PowerShell Core,.NET Core, Core, Core, Core
I could possibly see it.
The reason why I don't get extremely excited about it
is simply because you know it wouldn't be GPL
and I don't mean to be that guy
but, you know, it's not going to change the world if it's not GPL
The GPL is that special kind of license that really made Linux grow
because when Samsung was contributing to the GPL
or was contributing code that was GPL
they had to also work with competitors at the same exact time
whereas if Linux wasn't GPL licensed
they could have just kept all those innovations for themselves
not necessarily shared them upstream if they didn't want to
and I don't know if we would have had the same success story
with say the Linux kernel on Android or etc.
Right, I think it's less of a really big philosophical moment
and probably just Microsoft being practical
Yeah, exactly, and it's still good
I don't mean to like diminish
Oh yeah
Yeah, but it's not like change humanity good
It's more like it's a practical kind of good
That all said
I kind of want to ask Brent this question
This is really out there
But let's just say we're 10 years down the road after this thing happened
If you could sit there and say
I can switch to Windows
and say it's Windows 15 or Windows 25 at this point
and it's got an open core
I can run an operating system with an open core
and I can use Adobe Photoshop
I can use Adobe Lightroom
I can use Adobe Premiere
But when I open up my file manager
when I browse the internals in my operating system
when I open up my web browser
that's all open source software
when I open up my text editor
that's open source software
It's just Windows open source software
Do you think that would be a compelling proposition to you?
I'm throwing in my mind
how is that different than the Linux I'm using currently
You can run proprietary software on the top
and all the base is mostly open
The only difference here might be that it's going to be Win32 compliant
It can run Windows traditional software
I suppose would be the major difference
That and the fact that it's a different type of license
Your Linux desktop is GPL software
where this might be BSD, Apache or some Microsoft license
Yeah, interesting
I think it would hit some of my
partly some of my ideals
I know the difference in GPL is huge
But for some people
simply the idea that they can have open source
and see it and modify it is enough
But I wonder
So maybe I'll throw a question back at you guys
What would be the advantage for some Linux users like us
to have simply an open source Windows
and how would that be any different
from a usability standpoint from what we have today
I don't think it is a net win
I don't know
I'm not fully convinced of this
LinuxUnplugged.com slash contact changed my mind
I feel like if it's not GPL
then it doesn't really stand the chance
of the long term infinite time scale
humanity scale kind of contribution
When we talk about Richard Stallman
and when he's talking about free software
I've never installed GNU slash Linux
He's talking about
He's talking about keeping something from humanity
He's talking about making software code
that is sustainable long term by humanity
versus something that is closed and proprietary
and that doesn't advance humanity
And when you think about it
in those larger long term contexts
I don't see the net positive of it
A GPL desktop with a full GPL software stack
could be around for a thousand years
But a commercial operating system
even if components of it are open source
much like Mac OS
is inherently tied to the commercial whims
and the ebbs and flows of
the United States stock market
It's not at the same scale
What do you think Wes?
I see what you mean
It's not going to take over the world in that way
It's sort of just incremental change
and it's nice to see
but probably we can all just stick to
our wonderful world of Linux
and our free and open source desktops
I find that interesting
It's nice to see
but doesn't really change that much does it?
It's kind of like something to talk about
but it doesn't really affect too much
Okay, well we should probably
we should probably stop at this point
because this is all just rumor
related to some LinkedIn stuff
but it just got us thinking about this kind of thing
You can never tell with modern Microsoft
It just makes you wonder
Right?
Where is it going to go next?
Like that is legitimately
what is at the core of the story
is at this point
I think we're ready for anything
in Windows core
and that even in itself really tells you something
Now, I think also
we could continue this conversation
into our next couple of major topics
including an application designer for Linux
as well as this whole S-storm
around MongoDB
which we've been covering pretty diligently
in Linux Action News
but I'll recap for you
in a wider context
that I think I'm a little concerned
could affect the fundamental funding
of future large scale open source projects
because it just seems like we'd come to a new normal
and now all of that's out the window
but I want to do a little housekeeping
because there's so many community events coming up
that I want to make sure we have one episode right here
where we really kind of bust through this stuff
All of what I'm about to tell you
will be linked up
at linuxunplug.com
slash 285
So let's bust through some of the things
that are coming down the road
First up, extremely proud
happy, thrilled, excited
to say that our
live audio stream
is now once again in working order
and sounding better than ever
jblive.fm
You can plug that into your mobile web browser
and it'll just start streaming
You can go into VLC, like open network
and plug in http://jblive.fm
Boom, enter
and you're now streaming our audio stream
And Wes has been working on some cool stuff on the droplet
to kind of like make it so that way
even when we're like at Linux Fest
or when Alan's streaming BSC Now
it's all up in there
Is there any open source in any of that
that you're doing?
Yeah, I mean, whatever we decide on
There's multiple interesting tools
They're all open source that we're using
It's kind of a hot race right now
between a couple to see
which will actually end up in production
The good news is they all work
They all sound great
And it means that if it's on jblive.tv
it'll be on jblive.fm
Yeah, and we
I'm just super happy with the way it sounds
We were very picky with where we went
and I think it sounds great
It took us a little bit to get there
But if you're on the road
and you know we're doing like Linux Unplugged
or something like that
just plug in jblive.fm and listen live
It's really nice
And also, just a little other bit of
network related housekeeping
I'm really very, very happy to announce
that Jim Salter has joined Mr. Wes Payne
as the full-time co-host for TechSnap
Oh, yeah
Yeah, you guys did
You just put out your first episode
Episode 395, TechSnap.Systems
Slash 395
All about Let's Encrypt
You guys do a deep dive
I love it
I love it, it was great
You know, yeah, Jim is great
I'm really excited for where this is going to go
because he has a lot of experience
a lot of knowledge
and some great stories
So expect a lot more from the TechSnap program
coming right up
Yeah, Jim's coming to Linux Fest too
so I'm excited to get to meet him in person
He's an author
He's a writer over at Ars Technica
He's been running Apache himself
on his own hosted systems
since FreeBSD 3.1
and he's been a fierce advocate
of free and open source software since then
and he's published some books
he's published some work
and, of course, you can read him on Ars Technica
and he covers everything from Wi-Fi
to NAS distributions
and next generation file systems
And our favorite, WireGuard
Yes, he's just like you and me
he's a big WireGuard fan
so I don't think we could have found a better co-host for you
and that first episode is out
and go check it out
TechSnap.Systems slash 395
go subscribe
because they're going to a new fortnightly schedule
so it's not too much
but when they do an episode
it's information dense
and I loved it
Alright, so I mentioned Linux Fest
You know, we're going to Linux Fest Northwest
LinuxFestNorthwest.org
It's April 26th through the 28th
although I don't really know what's going on on the 26th
26th is a Friday, right Wes?
Am I wrong on that?
But 26th is a Friday
No, you're absolutely
Normally it's like two days
this time it's three
so I'm not sure either
but I guess that means there's no reason
not to be in Bellingham on Friday
Does that mean we're supposed to be set up Thursday?
That fundamentally changes everything
You know, I suspect it's going to be just slightly more official
because in times past
they've had things like game nights on Friday
or other get-togethers
so it's probably just a little formalization of that
Yeah, it's going to be the 20th anniversary
of Linux Fest Northwest
and we have a huge Jupiter broadcasting crew
We have team members that you haven't even met yet
that we're still trying to get them on air
so you can meet them
We have, everybody really is coming
with pretty much the exception of Michael Dominic
from Koda Radio
Alan is going to make it
Jim Salter is going to make it
Popey and Wimpy are hoping
I think they're making it
I think they're like 95% locked in
Joe's going to be out here
Noah's going to be out here
Wes will be there
Angela will be there
It's going to be a huge
There's people I'm not even
because I could just sit here and go on and on
There's a huge crew coming
and we're going to have our Saturday evening
parking lot barbecue outside of Lady Jubes
Huge hit
I mean, how many people do you think were there last year, Wes?
Oh, I don't know
It was probably right around 50
and it was a great time
People were coming and going and hanging out
and there was always someone new to meet
someone friendly to hang out with
I suspect there'll be a Levi friend again this year too
You bet
Yeah, I've already talked to Emma at System 76
when you and I went out there to do the Thaleos coverage
We made sure we were on the same page
and we're going to do an even bigger cookout
We'll have multiple grills going
Lady Jubes will be there
Bring your drones
and bring a friend
and come hang out with us
I have the Meetup page up right now
You can find that at meetup.com
It'll also be linked in the show notes
Let us know if you're going to make it
We also have a Telegram group
that is now linked in the show notes for Linux Fest
So we have an official Linux Fest 2019
community Telegram group
linked in the show notes
as well as the Meetup
This stuff is getting official
We're getting excited
There's probably going to be several of your
broadcasting friends hosting talks
at Linux Fest this year
Definitely going to be a big show
Really encourage that you go to it
All the details are linked up in the show notes
Now, moving right along
Like I said, we've got a lot of community events
A couple of more to go over
At the Pasadena Convention Center
March 7th through the 10th, 2019
is Scale 17x
Again, we're going to be there
We won't have a booth necessarily
but we'll be at the event
One of our team members at least
Maybe more will be giving talks
I think both Wes and myself
I think, Wes, you want to go, Wes?
Yeah, why not?
Let's do it
Wes and I will be there
as well as another one of our team members
that you have yet to meet will be there
And it's going to be a great show
The convention center is beautiful
The location next to it has great places to eat
Always a great community at scale
So Jupiter Broadcasting is going again
March 7th through the 10th, 2019
at the Pasadena Convention Center
ScaleExpo.org
We have a link in the show notes
And we also have a telegram group
already set up for that
which is also linked in the show notes
I encourage you to participate
in these telegram groups
because this is really where you get
all of the information as it's developing
A lot of times we're at these events
and things change quick
And that telegram group is the most up-to-date spot
And now, last but not least
May 31st through June 1st
at the Irving Convention Center
right there by Dallas
Texas Linux Fest 2019
We will be there
And I'm very excited to say that again
Talks will be had
Meetups will be had
We will have a telegram group
All of that as it gets closer
We actually have a telegram group
JupiterBroadcasting.com slash Texas
for that one
And we'll do a meetup as it gets closer
And yeah, I don't know how many of us
are going to go there because it's in May
And we have Linux Fest in scale ahead of us
But a couple of us at least
will also be at Texas Linux Fest this year
So that's a lot of cool events, eh Wes?
Like, boom!
Oh my god, there's so much going on
So many great opportunities
to just meet people, hang out
and chat about our love for Linux
You know, we give time to these kinds of things
in the show because these events
build stronger connections in the community
And in a community where people are
dedicating their passion and their time
and they're scratching their own itch
to create software for other people
It is so fundamentally important to do that
It matters way more than it does
in other contexts
Like in the business world
there's this profit motive that forces
everybody to be fake nice to each other
and get along because
everybody wants to earn a buck
and nobody wants to take any big risk
or loss
But in the open source community
we don't have that fake pretext
that forces us to get along
People can be jerks to each other
and it's very counterproductive
But these events
and not just chatting with other people
even if you're anti-social
just going there and being around other people
that like the same things you like
or are giving you information
about things you need to know about
like through the talks and whatnot
It changes the game
And if you've never participated
in an event like this
it will take your passion for Linux
and open source up to an entirely new level
And if you haven't been in a year or so
it will re-energize you
That's why we talk about this
It does move the needle
And one last thing in the show notes
If you've ever considered
maybe giving a talk
but didn't know how to start
didn't really have any resources
for public speaking
Go check the show notes again this week
Linux Unplugged dot com slash 285
Link in there to a Github
that has so many great resources
about getting started
how to find a place to give a talk
just figuring out the best idea
how to write a CFP which is a call for papers
how to handle that and submit it
and write it in a way that's going to get accepted
and then tools to use for your presentation
I'm pretty sure you found this link, Wes
and it's just a killer resource
Yes, and that's because our little
local homegrown conference, Seagull
provides that link
and I came across it when I did a talk
for that last year
and it really is helpful
There's a ton of great things about
how to understand who are you presenting for
what should your talk be about
and how do you get started?
There you go
I know it was a lot to go through
in the housekeeping section
and I know that some of these regional events
aren't applicable to most of the people listening
but I hope our enthusiasm for them
at least encourages you to participate
in the ones in your area
or maybe go do a talk even
I think we could use a lot more of that out there
One last bit of housekeeping
I was just doing
I'm down here in Texas right now
for a bunch of content releases
I was co-hosting the live stream today
and I had a chance to announce
a new course that Linux Academy released
called the Linux Operating System Fundamentals
First of all, it's done by
a training architect named Kenny
He's a great guy
He loves Linux
but better than that
he's got a great voice
and he's got great production quality
The reason why I wanted to mention this course
and I'll have it linked in the show notes
is it's about the Linux Operating System Fundamentals
but a good 40% of the course
I've taken it myself already this afternoon
before we went on air
is about the history of Linux
and the history of the operating systems
that existed before Linux
and then what led to Linux
and then also GNU
and the Free Software Foundation
and the Open Source Initiative
and then the Linux distributions
that came after that
and the tail end of it
is the uses of Linux
that we have now today
but I just didn't expect
this great history of all this stuff
and as somebody who's been using Linux
since the 90s
I have to say there's areas
that being self-taught I missed
and especially some of this history stuff
I just really loved it
so I'll put a link in the show notes
Right, that's what's really hard
when you are self-taught
you don't learn that
when you go read bash tutorials
it doesn't tell you about
where all this great software
you're learning to use actually came from
Yeah, it was great
and if you're not a Linux Academy student
they do have a seven day free trial
I remember that from the ads
I used to do for many years
so you can sign it for free
for seven days and take it
but I was talking to Kenny about it
when we were prepping for the stream
and I was like, oh, I'm taking this
and then I actually did take it earlier today
because being in Texas
I have two extra hours before the show
so I'm like, what am I going to do?
I'll take Kenny's course
because it's like an hour and a half total
and so I took it
and he just has a great voice
and he has a great production
so anyways, good job to him
and it was a good release
and I'm hoping, by the way
kind of related
I'm hoping that Kenny makes it out
to Linux Fest Northwest too
so that's possible
we could see him there
Now, there's a lot of talk this week
about a new design application
for our beloved Linux
something that's really missing
the ability to sort of sketch out
a general design for other applications
and it's called, is it Arkea, Wes?
Akira
Akira, of course
of course I missed it
of course
and do I have sort of the general premise right?
It's like a sketch application
for UI design?
Yeah, yeah, exactly
it's not something you're going to use
to actually make actual interfaces
it's for designers to play around with
to mock up designs
to ship to your client as an image
to say, does this look about right?
So Akira has been getting a lot of attention
because this is an area
that there's a lot of commercial solutions for
including ones from Adobe and many others
and there's not a lot of options
for GNU slash Linux
and Wes had a chance to sit down with Alex
and talk to him about his Kickstarter
that he's doing to try to raise money
and to try to get people
to develop for this thing full time
it's a fascinating idea
is there anything else we need to know
before we listen to the interview, Wes?
No, I don't think so
Alex is the lead
there's a broader team
which he'll talk about
Awesome, so here we are
Welcome to the show, Alex
and thank you for joining us today
Thank you so much for having me
it's a pleasure, absolutely
Okay, well you're obviously here
I mean, one, because you make a lot of good stuff
actually I first saw your taxi application
it's really pretty handy
it's not what you're here to talk about today
but it might come up again
because you've got quite the background
we're here to talk about Akira
Yes, absolutely
so just a little digression about taxis
it's not 100% mine
it's an old project that I took
and I'm redeveloping
and I'm refactoring and trying to update
so I don't want to take all the credits for taxis
it's not 100% mine
but yes, I'm here to talk about Akira
so I just launched a Kickstarter campaign
for Akira
or someone likes to call it Akira UX
which is a UX design tool for Linux
100% native for Linux
it's not an electron app
and UX design tools means
that it's something similar to Sketch
or Figma
or Adobe XD
that is not for creating GTK
or Qt interfaces
user interfaces like code
is not made to speed out code
That's a great point
so it's not like something like Glade
or Qt Creator
it's not going to make a QXML file
or anything like that for you
so what formats are we talking about here?
So basically, if I'm going to be a user
what are we going to have as the output?
Okay, the output
the name probably is going to be
like.Akira
like a custom extension
but it's just an SVG
everything is going to be based on SVG
we want to go the route of having a custom extension
because we're going to try to save the file
with a JSON format
in order to have version control
baked into your file
that you can activate or deactivate
based on your necessities
so you can keep track of all the different versions of your file
in the same file
you don't have to have a dedicated repository
or like the things that we used to do
having version 1
version 1 final
version 1 final underscore reviewed
this is the actual final
all this kind of good stuff
when you do some design
for a long time
for a client that is never
100% sure what to do
That's fascinating
obviously on the development side
and you play in both these worlds
on the development side version control goes back ages
but I don't see it as often in the design community
or at least not as standardized
Exactly
Sketch
from like
the Sketch app application
that is currently only available on Mac OS
has something like that
but it's terrible
because every time you save something
like you move a square
or you change one letter
and you save the file
it saves completely the entire file
in itself
so you end up with having a Sketch file
that even if you have just one single artboard
it waits for gigabytes
Oh wow
It's terrible
yeah it's like
it's really handy if you lose stuff
and you can go back
but there's no way of
manually controlling what you can
what you can save
or if you want to pause
the version control of this file
and just like
activate it only if you have some major release
or stuff like that
I'd say it's like
it's the first approach
of version controlling design
but it's not that great
That makes sense
Okay well let's pivot back to Akira then
and we were just starting to get there
before I went down the other road
of explaining just what you're targeting
so you'll be outputting SVG
so Akira is for designing interfaces
and then producing vector images
that you then might go share
with the people downstream
who actually built the thing
Exactly
It's mostly for designers
which
someone raised an eyebrows
that oh why developers cannot use it
why
a lot of questions they were asked
why Akira cannot generate code
because we already have those things
we already have those alternatives
and those options
something specifically targeting designers
that they need to create
just images
they can share with developers
or they can put
online
and create presentations
or do some quick mockups
and prototypes
we don't have something like that
right now on Linux
Oh yeah right
so maybe you can talk a little bit more
because this is something
you obviously know well
as a professional
and a Linux user
can you talk a little bit about
the pain of trying to have
both of those things
in today's world
Oh my god it's terrible
okay
so feel free to interrupt me
because I can go on forever
I don't want to annoy everyone
but I'm
I've been doing development
and design at the same time
for more than 13 years
professionally
I was forced throughout my entire
career to just use
all Windows and Mac OS
just because of applications
I tried in
digital studios
or creative agencies
that I worked in the past
to go in and say
hey let's not use Adobe
let's use GIMP
to do our photo retouching
and everyone started laughing at me
not because those tools
like GIMP, Inkscape
or Krita are bad tools
those are amazing tools
and they work great
but the problem
is the workflow
is the user interface
you can
that's something that I always say
you can do a square
gray
like a gray rectangle
you can build a gray rectangle
in Inkscape
in GIMP, in Krita
in Sketch, Figma
it doesn't matter
it will always be
a gray rectangle
but
if you want to build
a user interface
with 20 different artboards
and shared assets
and design system
and something that you can
collaborate with other designers
your options are really limited
and there's nothing like that on Linux
so it's all about
optimizing the workflow
of designers
with a modern tool
that offers a modern interface
that's the main purpose
so making Linux
a habitable platform
for designers
so that someone
you can have everything
you can have your cake
you can eat it too
and design all your applications
whether it's for another platform
or for Linux natively
absolutely
and also the main purpose is
helping Linux
being like
turning to a mainstream
operating system
that is not
unfortunately for
how we want to wish
that this is the year
of the Linux desktop
it will never come
if we don't have
proper native
alternative softwares
that are
comparable
or even better
than what are available
on Windows and Mac OS
and Akira wants to do that
wants to say
okay you don't want to use Sketch
you don't want to pay
$30 a month
to use Adobe XD
come on Linux
we have exactly the same thing
that works as well
but it's open source
it's free
and we don't ask money for it
so that's it
so will Linux be
the only targeted platform
or will someday
I will be able to run Akira
on my MacBook
that's a really good question
for now
it's 100% it's Linux
because on MacBook
or Windows
you have
20 different alternatives
that can do the same
but it's open source
so if there's a crazy user
out there
that decides to compile
and run GTK
on Windows
or Mac OS
they can totally do it
we're not opposed to that
absolutely
but it's not our goal
okay well then
while we're on this subject
what about Linux distribution
is it for all distributions
I also happen to notice
it looked like an older branch
but a branch called
AppImage on there
so are there
are there plans
for these universal formats
yes absolutely
so by default
we're going to start
PPA
like on LaunchPod
we're going to release
daily builds
so pretty much
all the Debian based
distribution
will be able to install it
then in the team
we have
Flatpak maintainer
really great guy
his name is Bilal
we're going to be sure
to release
daily Flatpaks
or like
weekly Flatpaks
installed everywhere
it's going to be released
on the elementary OS
App Center
and we're open to
we don't have the
skill level
right now to do it
but we're open
to contribution
to release also
a SnapImage
and an AppImage
so a SnapPak
perfect
okay well
that pretty well
answers my question
yeah we want to try to
cover as many
distributions as possible
and
that's also why
we want to
buy as much hardware
as possible
in order to test it
and be sure that
every single Linux users
it doesn't matter the distribution
it doesn't matter
how modern
and performant
their laptop
or computer is
they can run Akira
because
yeah
we want to be just
available
to anyone
okay so you said
we there
and that's another thing
we should talk about
it's not just you working here
it sounds like you've got
a great team behind you
yes
I'm the crazy guy
that decided to start
this thing
like a couple of years ago
and I was like
oh it's actually harder
than I thought
like everything
so in the past year
I started
releasing
native Linux applications
like SQLer
and taxi
like you mentioned
and throughout this year
I started collaborating
with a lot of
different developers
in particular
I feel really comfortable
and
these are great people
other three developers
that they helped me a lot
with my applications
or
I contribute to
their own applications
by
offering design and development
stuff like that
the team is
there's myself
of course
and then there's
Felipe Escoto
which is
a Mexican developer
for Elementor US
he released
SpiceUp
and NodeTap
two amazing applications
oh yeah
mind blown
yeah and these
it's a kid
like this guy is
20-ish something
he's like the smartest kid
I've ever met
I feel like
so old
and so behind
when I talk to him
a wonder kid
yeah a wonder kid
absolutely
and then there's
Alberto Vangiole
which is
a software engineer
Agnome Foundation member
is the maintainer
of GitG
which is
a visual
Git repository manager
and then we have Bilal
and I always butcher
his last name
Elmousaoui
sorry Bilal
I apologize deeply
he's a developer
and is an
Agnome Foundation member
and
he's an engineer
student
so it's like
the smartest of the bunch probably
and
he's one of the maintainer
of a lot of
Flatpak
applications
so if
FlatHab
is a
great repository
it's mostly thanks to Bilal
wow that is impressive
clearly a lot of people
who know what they're doing
and have experienced
building these kinds of
applications before
and maybe
that explains my next question
how far along
is Akira
what should users know
is it ready for use
is it
just starting out
where are you
that's a really good question
okay Akira
there's a
barely working prototype
that you can
download
from the
open source
GitHub repository compile
and run
what we're missing
is basically the core
in order to
be actually usable
which is the hardest part
is the canvas
right now
it doesn't exist
a canvas library
that does
what we need
it doesn't exist
a canvas library
that by default interacts
with SVGs
and
whenever you create an object
it creates
separated layers
that you can manipulate
without
having an issue
oh I see
right you need this
sort of
rich environment
the canvas to go interact
so you can make shapes
and drag them around
and layer them
and actually get the work done
yeah right now
it doesn't exist
there are a lot of projects
that they do that
but are really limited
or discontinued
or
it's all
it's not a
reusable library
it's all like math based
and it's C code
there's nothing that
we can simply
grab and integrate
inside Akira
it's something
that we need to create
from scratch
so yes
the application
is up and running
it's a sort of like MVP version
which
comes with
a built-in canvas
that you can
start to interact with
but you cannot
yet
create shapes
and save files
and manipulate
layers
so
the majority of the work
is going to be about
creating this canvas library
which
we want to make it available
as
like
a package
that everyone
if they want to create their own
mock-up
design tool
they can incorporate
that library
and reuse it
oh great
so just sort of a spin-off project
of here you go guys
here's a great little canvas
you can use
yes exactly
because it doesn't exist
something like that
so yes
it's going to be used
in Akira
but it's going to be available
to anyone
that they want to incorporate
in their own project
of two to three months
to release
the first usable
alpha version
that
I'm trying to push it
and not being
an alpha version
but probably
it's going to be an alpha version
but version one
is going to be available
if the Kickstarter campaign
is successful
in three months
after the end
of the Kickstarter campaign
well let's talk a little bit more
about that
you've got a Kickstarter campaign
going on
and I know
our listeners
are going to want to know
what's the money
going to be used for
is there some
corporate structure
behind the scenes
do you have plans
for exactly where
everything's going to go
and how you'll use it
tell us more
yes absolutely
so I
in the Kickstarter
description
I wrote down
a breakthrough
of how
all the money
will be used
because
honestly I'm asking
for a lot of money
it is
totally 65,000
Canadian dollars
which
roughly translate
to fifty thousand
US dollars
and
a lot of people
thirty percent will go in taxes
because
I'm not a corporation
we didn't
create a foundation
on anything like that
on a non-profit
I'm just like
a single user
so
that money
will be
for the Canadian government
is like
income
and I have to declare taxes
on that income
and I have to pay
thirty percent
ish
that money
so already thirty percent
is gone forever
burned
and gave it to the government
but it's fine
then
two thousand dollars
will be used
to hire
these three developers
for three months
that's the main purpose
I want to
pay them
as a full-time job
so they can work on this
eight hours per day
five days a week
for three months
non-stop
is the only way
we can
be able to deliver
something like that
they cannot work
part-time
one hour per day
or during the weekend
right
they need time to focus
if you're going to get
good quality work out quickly
absolutely
so I asked them
I'm going to cover
the entire rate
and then we have an extra
twenty thousand dollars
which
ten thousand
will be
to pay
my
paycheck basically
and
sustain myself
for three months
so I don't need to
I can take
some three months
off of work
and I need to work
I can focus on Akira
a hundred percent as well
and the rest of the
ten thousand dollars
will be used
to buy
hardware
because
yes every one of us
has a laptop
but we just have
a laptop that it's
probably not the best
we don't have
graphic tablets
4k monitors
we don't have
touch
touchpad interfaces
and all this kind of stuff
that
are
standard
in
a professional
design world
when you work in an agency
it's normal
having a 4k
or 5k monitor
it's normal
having
a Wacom tablet
with a digital display
how good
are
those things currently
working
on Linux
not that great
they work
but
they're not the best
so
having the ability
to purchase
that hardware
and
develop Akira
since day one
on
that
different hardware
all those
different resolutions
and different
input interfaces
will give us
the ability to
release Akira
working
in every
single environment
possible
right you won't have to just
try to retrofit
it literally on down
down the stream later
you're going to be planning for it
because you know professionals
want to use it
exactly and
how many times
you use a project
and you go into
their repositories
and there are issues like
this doesn't work
with my
tablet
or this
doesn't work with my laptop
because I have this resolution
and the answer is
sometimes
I'm sorry
I cannot test it
because I don't have
that hardware
right yeah exactly
yeah we want to try to avoid that
it's like
no we cannot fix it
because we don't know
how to recreate the issue
so
that's the main thing
yeah on the Kickstarter page
there's a full breakdown
of everything
percentages
all the money
and
a lot of users
were kind of like
weirded out
by the amount
and
the fact that I actually
wrote down the money
they didn't believe that
30% goes in taxes
or
some didn't believe
oh ten thousand dollars
for
your rent and your food
and I'm like yeah
I have to eat
for three months
but
I want to reiterate the fact that
I'm not trying to
get rich
or
buy a Tesla
I don't know
get a bunch of money
and then disappear
I really want
to make this happen
because it's literally
the only thing
that it's preventing me
from using Linux
every day
I have one MacBook
left in my apartment
just because
of one application
the design application
that I have to use
Wow okay Linux users
out there
if you weren't going to fund the Kickstarter
because you're not going to use
Zekira
you're not a designer
I think that's a pretty good reason
right there
get you
get you Alex
right off that MacBook
help me
yeah that's it
and you know
I mean to just put it
in a little perspective
if you think about
you know several developers
working for
a significant part of a year
at like a major
development company
well that's going to be
a lot more money
than you're asking for
yeah exactly
I'm not paying benefits
to them
I'm not paying
paid vacations
or something like that
so the cost is really
is really limited
compared to
what you're going to get paid
if you work on a full-time job
on an actual
company but
yeah that's
that's the amount of money
I wanted to be
as honest and clear
as possible
I put the full breakdown
of how I'm going to use the money
and also my wife
told me like
you shouldn't do that
because a lot of people
will question you
and will start like
having doubts
of what you wrote
it's
I want to be
open source
also with the money
so if we reach the goal
I'm going to
constantly do weekly updates
of how I'm going to
spend the money
where the money will go
and of course
if I end up
not spending all those
all the money
in taxes
or I can use the
accountant
to help me out
to save something
all the money
that I have left
will be funneled back
inside
the application itself
I'm going to
we're going to set up
some bounty sources
to help other developers
that want to
contribute to get paid
in order to work on Akira
so
it's not
yeah it's not to
get rich
or
take some time off work
and go on vacation
that's not the goal
that makes sense
I certainly wish you luck
I've actually already
backed it
so I hope it goes through
yeah
and we'll have links
to everything we've talked about
in this interview
in the show notes
is there anything else
you want the audience to know?
just one thing
everyone probably
the majority of the audience
is on Linux
and
in our entire life
we always
found ourselves
using an application
and thinking
oh this is great
but it doesn't do
what I actually want
Akira wants to fill that gap
Akira
we want to
give you the freedom
of saying
I'm on Linux
and I don't need
anything else
I don't want Adobe
to
create a port
for Linux
of the Adobe creative suite
because
I don't need it
I'm fine with this
that's our goal
professional caliber
Linux design application
that could be
the future of Akira
yes
where should people go
to find more from you Alex?
yes
there's my Twitter account
which is
at alecad
ddd
with 3d
and then
I'm on YouTube
I do actually
tutorials about Linux
design and development
because
I
don't like to sleep
but it's fine
and
that's it
pretty much
I'm everywhere online
so people start
getting really
really annoyed
by my
online presence
perfect
well thank you so much
for joining us
and good luck
awesome
thank you so much for having me
such a great idea
and I like how
much Alex
has this together
he's got a real
plan of attack here
and
as Linux users
we're often in this position
of trying to decide
do I want to take a risk
on funding
this thing
although I know
that this is something
we really need
it's good
it's good to hear Alex
really seems to have it
we've debated a lot of
kind of questionable
kickstarters
over the years on this show
I don't think this is one of them
no
no you seem like
you had it figured out
so
I'm really glad
you had a chance to chat with him
and
we'll have a link
to their fundraiser
in the show notes
probably worth doing
if you're a developer
because I think
it would be an investment
in a possible workflow
and I like that
he's thinking about
multi distro packaging too
I think that's a good thing
I'm looking at our time here
and I'm thinking
we're going to have to wait
on the Ubuntu 19.04
first look
I've been running it now
since
pretty much
since our predictions episode
but you won't talk about it
I keep asking you
off air
you say no
no Wes
I'm going to tell you on air
and once again
no
I guess it's kind of good
it gives me more time
I just
I feel like by the time
we finally get around to this
it's going to be
just near release time
I just wanted to give a first look
at what's coming down the road
for GNOME
it's
for those of us
that have had
GNOME problems
there's a lot of good stuff
in the works
so we'll talk about that
in the future
but I wanted
while it's still fresh
I want to take a moment
and wrap up the show
with this
interesting challenge
that
I think is facing
open source software
and I think what we'll do
is
we'll open it
and if we
if we get some good responses
we'll conclude it
next week
and
if you followed
me on Twitter
you know that recently
MongoDB
went through
a series of changes
in attempt to
relicense in a way
that
that forced
providers that are
re-hosting MongoDB
to have to pay
a certain fee
get a certain kind of
relationship with MongoDB
and it's resulted
in
Red Hat
and Fedora
and Debian
and other distributions
deciding to no longer
include MongoDB
in the repositories
because they believe
that license conflicts
with free software
and
at the same time
another shoe has dropped
and that is that
Amazon has released
AWS
DocumentDB
which is a straight up
competitor to MongoDB
and even
implements
compatibility with
MongoDB's
API
from the
version right before
they made the licensing
changes
I have all that right so far
right Wes?
Yeah I mean
it's not just MongoDB
Redis, Kafka
there's been kind of
a long line of projects
that are
you know came
from companies
that were all
all in on this
they had this open source
product kind of
freemium right
trying to sell
additional enterprise
services or different
licenses on top
it kind of varies
from company to company
and then
well the cloud behemoths
came into the room
and it turns out
everyone wants them
to run the software
for them so
how do you make money?
Great idea
but now running at scale
is sort of what's happening
oh that open source project
there
great idea
now let's just take that
and implement it
on our own systems
and really
Microsoft kind of
did this first
with their Cosmos DB
over on Azure
it just
didn't quite get
the same attention
that AWS's DocumentDB
did
but they kind of
just straight up
did the same thing
did a MongoDB competitor
that's now an Azure branded
service that you pay for
and what they're selling
isn't the software
what they're selling
is the reliability
and the infrastructure
of AWS
or Azure
in this case
and
this is
I think
a huge threat
to open source software
not because
these large commercial
companies
are taking
open source software
and
re-implementing it
or even just
re-hosting it in some cases
and then calling it
their own service
and charging for it
like that's
that's going to happen
but
in a much
much
bigger picture way
it could fundamentally
undermine
how open source projects
that need to build
at a certain scale
get funded
kickstarters
don't build MongoDB
patreons
large
corporate
VC backed
funding
builds things
that are at that scale
it's just the nature
of the software industry
and I want to
play a clip
from Ben Thompson
who in his
podcast
Exponent
which we will link
in the show notes
he's talked about this
and written
we'll link to this
in the show notes
I want to play this
and then Wes and I
are going to chat
about it a little bit
and then
I'm going to leave it
to the audience
in the podcast
where he talks about
this VC funding issue
this is
driving a lot of angst
sort of in the open source
world
which is
we kind of got this
cool new model
where
open source projects
could
not just be
sort of developed
by hobbyists
or people in their free time
or
people supported by
foundations
or grants
or whatever it might be
but actually
like
getting VC money
and VC makes
so much sense for software
because
software is a lot of work
and tools
and if Amazon's coming along
and basically leveraging
their massive scale
and what they're selling
to enterprises
which is
the sort of
reliability
and scalability
and all those things
that Amazon offers
is that business model
going where
are we losing
what seemed to be
a workable business model
for open source
and that'd be a bummer
frankly
it'd be a bummer for everyone
it'd be a bummer for Amazon
huge bummer
I mean here's the concern Wes
is if
if I'm a VC firm
and I'm looking at backing
a massive threat to that project
as if they ever get
any kind of market share
one of the big commercial
hosting companies
will just re-implement it
See I got a little bit
of a contrarian take here
I think Ben's totally right
and that's a great episode
of the show
but the key
is long term
he says
VC makes sense
for software
because you have to spend
a lot of money
and then you try to be profitable
over the long term
but the VCs of today
that's not how we operate
and I think we all got a little too hopeful
that
things like Mongo
things on the billion scale
things that
you know San Francisco VCs
are funding
was actually a sustainable
business model
but
Amazon was
you know AWS didn't start
till like 2007
so we're really only
one tick in here
we've gone through one cycle
and we're seeing
we got really hopeful
because it is great
you do want
companies that can be like
you know like Elasticsearch
for instance
they're like this is a great product
we've hired great developers
to build it
and now you can have it for free
and it's open source
but it turns out
it's
it's a lot more complicated
I think you can still have
those things
but not at the scale
of you know making huge amounts of money
for people
you might be able to build a sustainable consultancy
on some open source software
but I think the days of
giant
multi-billion dollar companies on them
questionable
it seems like it could be
a huge issue
because then it means
only certain companies
will have the scale
to build those kinds of projects
and
it also makes me wonder
if this doesn't
have something to do with the Red Hat sale
to IBM
here's here's what
before I
before I sound the alarm
and I say that these large commercial cloud companies
are going to consume
open source projects
that ever get successful
I would like to get the audience's take
but it does require
like some serious homework
and thought around this
but I would really love
to either have you join us
next week in the mumble room
or
just go to linuxunplug.com slash contact
but do consider the homework
we'll have it linked in the show notes
the first up is exponent
episode 159 of
Ben Thompson's podcast
where they talk about this
then
I would encourage you
to read his piece on
Stratechery
which we will also have linked
in the show notes
and then additionally
one last thing
is I would encourage you
to listen to
Late Night Linux
episode 55
where the boys just debate
cloud lock-in
versus on-premises
to give you a fully
rounded picture
of the issue here
and then
I would really encourage you
to at least engage in that
even if you're not going to participate
in the podcast
and but then
if you do have the time
come join us
in email and let us know what you think
I would throw into
Brian Cantrell
of all kinds of open source fame
he's been blogging about this stuff too
and it's a little bit different
it's a little more focused on the licenses
but I think it's an important component
from someone who's been through
the open source
and trying to make money
process
yeah
there's a lot of different
moving pieces right now
around this discussion
and it's at a different scale now
because
essentially
the thing that
companies like AWS
are benefiting from
is the open source
community nature of a project
like MongoDB
and Redis and others
has led to
strong developer adoption
but then
and that developer adoption
is super beneficial
for like
creating applications
that use that type of database
it's great for that
right
you want to make it easy
to just pull down a Docker container
so that you can try it out
if you're going to decide
am I going to use this software
in my new project
yeah maybe you're building a prototype
or you're learning
and then
when it comes time
to put it in production
for millions of users
to bang on it
and you want to tell your boss
what system they should use
I mean
who's going to fire you
for suggesting DocumentDB
you could go do
your own bespoke
implementation of MongoDB
up on a VPS somewhere
and manage it
but then who's on call
you?
yeah and really
if AWS has an issue
that's not on you
nobody gets fired
for choosing AWS
just like nobody got fired
for choosing IBM
and Microsoft
back in the day
and so just by being AWS
I think they're going to have
massive success
with what is essentially
a MongoDB
competitor slash ripoff
I mean
ripoff is a little bit strong
but yes right
I mean they implement
the same interface
or at least largely compatible
and they do that
with other things right
they've got Aurora
their database
and has a coming backend
that they implement
some like Postgres
compatibility layers
on top of
so it's just
the commoditization
the world of cloud
where once you've hired
the one ops team
to run your stuff
you don't really want
to branch out
yeah man
I just feel like
there's a lot of expectations
for really large scale
open source
I would love to have
a reality
and a future
where Red Hat
wasn't the largest
open source company ever
free software company
wouldn't that be great
if we could have another
free software
open source success story
that's even larger
than Red Hat
right yeah
let's hope we haven't peaked
right
and that's my concern
is that this sort of
stifles the long term
ramp
and how big these companies
can get
when
we want to the audience
if we get good engagement
people do their homework
and turn around
and give thoughtful responses
we'll continue this
conversation
in next week's episode
and hopefully we'll get
the Ubuntu 19.04 first look
in there too
it's the Gen 2 challenge
all over again
I apologize about that
in the meantime
go get more Wes Payne
and now Jim Salter
over on the TechSnap
TechSnap.Systems
I'm really happy about that
we've already talked about it
but I just think
it's super great Wes
I wanted to mention
well thank you
good work on the first episode
and there is more to come
and of course you can go get him on Twitter
he is at Wes Payne
I am at Chris Elias
and the network
at Jupiter Signal
LinuxUnplugged.com
slash 285
for all the links
to everything we talked about
the community events
the news stories
the Kickstarter
for the
I'm not going to try to mispronounce it
but you know what I'm talking about
Akira
the Akira Kickstarter
we've got it all
I'm hopeless Wes
but you try
and that's what counts
I think
I'm starting to give up
starting to
and also thank you to Alex
for joining Wes
to tell us about his project
best of luck to him
and links to
all of the homework that we have
in the show notes as well
LinuxUnplugged.com
slash 285
for all the links
to everything we talked about
the community events
the Kickstarter
for the
I'm not going to try to mispronounce it
but you know what I'm talking about
Akira
the Akira Kickstarter
we've got it all
I'm hopeless Wes
but you try
and that's what counts
I think
I'm starting to give up
starting to
and also thank you to
Alex
for joining us
to tell us about
all of the homework that we have
in the show notes as well
LinuxUnplugged.com
slash 285
for all the links
to everything we have
in the show notes
I'm not going to try to mispronounce it
he was the one right before Jim
Whitehurst
and
what's really interesting about it
it's a new
model
of
supporting
open source projects
so
you know the Red Hat model is
you buy a subscription
for Linux
and that goes to
basically towards
Linux development
for the most part right
but the
this one
it's far more broad
so like if you have
like a lot of
open source dependencies
in your application
you can
go to
Tidelift
and say hey
I need
to make sure that
this is
getting developed
and Tidelift will go
and pay
the
project maintainer
to continue
to maintain the project
it's like
it's like a
like not a foundation
but
yeah
it's an interesting way
of looking at it
I think
you know
they just got
Series B funding
so we'll see
you know
where it goes
I just heard about them
a couple weeks ago
they've been around
apparently
for a
little over a year
so
yeah
we'll see
where it goes
I'm really interested
to see
where it goes
What's their website?
It's Tidelift.com
Good one, thank you
that's good to know about
thank you Brandon
I've got to take on
the whole licenses
MongoDB thing
Yeah, do share
Yeah so
you know
the typical model
that has become
common for
open source companies
is that
they basically create a market
for their skills
by
creating a product
that
is
sufficiently complicated enough
that
other people require
their skills to support
and also
that they want updates
to that software
so
the problem being is that
you have companies
that
also have the same amount
of skills that you have
and if your project
is popular enough
that
they don't want to wait for you
to do updates
or they find your support
too expensive
on their own
they lose that control
and then
you know
groups like
Mongo and
there's been countless in the past
there's the very real chance
that they'll lose the control
and then they're losing
the whole reason
that they created it
in the first place
I mean there's other
more altruistic reasons
for creating FOSS software
but the typical
I need to make money
using FOSS software
how do I do it
this is a typical
breakdown
path
that happens
but you have to be prepared
for that to happen
if you want to delve
in the world of open source
novels
every open source company
has a
cash flow
issues
especially
with getting people
to buy their products
because
you can just go
get it for free
I mean
Canonical
could easily be
larger than Red Hat
if they could just
figure out a way
to monetize
every Ubuntu license
out there
every Ubuntu
installation
out there right
but that's just
not going to happen
same with MongoDB
MongoDB would probably be huge
but
people can just
go run their software
for free
so that's
it's
got to figure out
a better way of
getting
money in the hands
of developers
I think that
that's the big
problem
is
you have to
one of the things
that I always
have to remind people
is that
software
is not
it's people's time
it's people's
you can't
and they can't just
keep working for free
yeah it's like
the Venn diagram
that's existed
ever since like
1990s when they started
doing this stuff is
there's software
that's
the triangle
you pick two
of the three things
you can have it
high quality
you can
have it free
and
you can't have both of them
like if you want
good quality
FOSS software
you have to be able to pay the people
that are making the FOSS software
to create it well
otherwise
it'll be slow
it'll be somebody working
on their evenings and weekends
it's a fundamental
competition between
people who are quite happy
to use stuff for free
and not
fund the development of it
and
people who aren't willing
to just spend all their time
doing nothing
and not eating
and not living in a house
developing software for you
this is negative