Wes Payne, ladies and gentlemen, bringing in something that smells rather fierce here, Wes.
What do we have here?
It's in a red solo cup, too, so I have legitimately no idea what it is.
It's like a sneaky beer.
That's a very interesting taste.
Yeah, what is it? What is it?
What do you think it is?
Well, it's fruity on the nose.
I'm going to go a little beer is tasty on you here just for a moment, okay?
Yeah, it's definitely fruity on the nose.
It's got a thin, crisp smell.
It has a very thin head, just a thick layer of foam on top, but not a lot of head there.
I'm going to go ahead and go for the mouth test.
The good thing is I don't completely hate it, so that's a good sign.
Wow. Well, it's interesting. It's sort of got a lot going on on the higher notes with kind of a sparkle effect, like a real carbonation, but there's not much in the middle.
There's not a lot in the middle.
I kind of like that.
Yeah, it's definitely very drinkable. You could drink it very fast. It's good. It's refreshing, too.
If it was hot, like right now if we didn't have the AC going, like once we turn off the AC and it starts getting warm in here, I'm going to get warm and this is going to refresh the crap out of me.
It's got a little bit of the bitterness, but it doesn't sit on your tongue.
Yeah, but I feel like it's not hops that I'm getting, but I mean it might be.
I don't know. Citrusy isn't the right word because it's not citrusy.
Well, kind of. It reminds me of grapefruit somewhat.
Yeah. Okay, so tell us what's going on here.
It's real simple. It's just a Sierra Nevada hefeweizen.
Huh.
Oh, that's where the citrus is coming from.
There you go.
That is hilarious.
None of the six packs looked good, so I just grabbed a 22 and split it between us. That's what happened here.
So you combined—hold on, just so I understand what you just did here—you combined soda pop and beer?
Right together.
Where the hell did you get that idea?
What the hell?
Do you not have Shandy in the U.S.?
Oh, no. I guess. I guess. I just—wow, Wes. That's good, though. That's ingenious.
You know what? I applaud your resourcefulness.
Well, thank you, sir.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 212 for August 29, 2017.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux podcast that might be dodging airplanes as we record.
My name is Chris.
That's your go. That's your cue.
Yeah, sorry. What am I doing?
Are you installing Gentoo over there or something?
Maybe, yeah, a little bit. I was hanging the command line challenge.
And, of course, we're joined by Beardsley. Hello, Beardsley.
Hello.
Hello. You know, guys, it's okay if you want to install Gentoo, but wake up. We have a lot to talk about today.
We sure do.
In fact, we'll get to the Gentoo challenge here in just a moment, but first we're going to do big community updates, really big community updates,
and maybe a couple that might make you a little hungry, plus a new segment that might have to become a reoccurring segment, we'll see, called Wimpy Was Right.
We'll talk about that. It pains me. It pains me.
Yeah, I hope not.
Bitcoin was spent. It pains me.
And then we're going to do a little follow-up on your feedback about replacing LastPass, a lot of great suggestions.
Plus, Mr. West there found a great tool that might just do the job for you for your offsite backups.
Then, Purism is getting serious about creating a phone.
They call it the Librem 5, and as we record right now, their fundraiser is about 10% funded.
That's actually a substantial amount of money.
And also, as we record right now, coming into the studio is a brand new Librem 15 to replace the one that I crowdfunded years ago now.
Right here, we're going to do a live unboxing and look at the new Librem 15 that was just sent to us by Purism right here on the show.
Yeah, we'll just do initial hands-on reactions, and then we'll do a review later on.
So, we're going to take a look at that.
Plus, we're going to talk about their new fundraiser.
We're going to talk about all the things I mentioned and community updates.
But before we go any further, we've got to bring in that virtual lug.
Yes, we do.
Time appropriate. Greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Guys, I have to start the show with a plea to you.
I'm going to make you judge and jury here.
There may be a penance that I have to pay.
I don't know what it would be, but we'll discuss that.
We have to punt the Gen 2 Challenge one more week in light of the new Librem 15 hardware.
It's just what we've got to talk about today.
It just came in.
I don't know, Chris.
It sounds to me like you're scared.
It sounds like you're still compiling.
Oh, did you install KDE?
Now it makes sense.
I was going to ask for your guidance, Mumble Room, on what we should do in light of yet another punt of the Gen 2 Challenge.
Where do we go from here?
Because to me, it feels like a fail to deliver.
But to be honest, we've had some really good reasons.
Yeah, I think so.
I'm torn up, and I need your guidance.
Let's just say we're workshopping it.
It's a special distro.
It needs a special take.
Yeah, yeah.
So here's what I was hoping is maybe if I, in exchange for something, some of you would help us with the Gen 2 Challenge to really keep us to it next week.
If one of you in there were willing to also take the Gen 2 Challenge with us, then we would feel obligated at a friend level to really make sure it gets done.
I don't know what that pen seems to be to make that happen, but I feel like that's what it would take right now.
Does anybody understand that in the mumble room?
Anyone?
I think the penance has to be Linux from scratch challenge after this.
I mean, producer Michael, you're trying out Linux all the time, and there could be additional content in it.
Monkey Comm, you've got to be thinking about Gen 2 sometimes.
Somebody in there, Mr. Arm, you have to be a little curious.
Nobody wants to take the Gen 2 Challenge with us.
Ain't nobody got time for that.
Interesting.
I did Gen 2 about four or five years ago, and that's all I need to know.
So screwed.
Maybe Wimpy needs to see what mate is like on Gen 2.
No, he really doesn't.
Wow. What does that tell us?
I tried it, and my boredom threshold got hit very, very quickly, and I was like, screw this, and just switched off the VM.
I've always been of the opinion that the best place for Gen 2 is in embedded systems.
I thought you were going to say the kitchen, just for a second.
Sure.
The best place for Gen 2 is Chrome OS.
There's plenty of embedded systems in your kitchen.
So the Chrome OS is a great thing to bring up, producer Michael, because it's a reminder that it's legitimately a relevant distro, isn't it?
For sure.
And the fact that it's based on Gen 2 makes Gen 2 even more important.
But I think most people aren't going to be putting much effort into Gen 2.
I did it once, just to say I did it, and that's enough I care about.
I did it for years in production because it was the only way to get the versions of CUPS and the drivers I needed to get the bank that I wanted to move over to Linux to move.
That's one of its advantages, right? You have that kind of control.
The unfortunate thing is that Gen 2 is no longer the fastest, and just because it's sourced, people assume that it's going to be the fastest updated. It's not. It's very, very slow in some cases.
I've had software that just was abandoned years ago, and they don't even care.
And people who are trying to get maintainership are not given maintainership.
I just want a hypothetical situation.
We'll step into the transporter.
We'll go into the mirror universe where Gen 2 no longer exists.
Maybe Chrome OS is based off of Linux from scratch or Android or whatever.
What changes?
I mean, they used to be known for really great documentation, but now that's sort of Arch's mantle.
Right. Yeah, it is.
So what changed?
They still have that documentation.
I think Gen 2's documentation is better than Arch.
I think there's a lot of things on Gen 2 that Arch doesn't address and Gen 2 does.
Hmm. Well, okay.
So, gosh, I feel like you and I are...
Although I did fix one of the things on the Arch Wiki that I found on the Gen 2 Wiki, but whatever.
Well, I, in some ways, now am more determined than ever to prove all of you jerks wrong
and show you that there's some value still in my old friend Gen 2.
You know what you should do, Chris?
What?
You should install Gen 2 on that super ancient laptop you did on that last throwback.
You know where Gen 2 makes a lot of sense to me?
It's like a Raspberry Pi 3 where I do the building off the machine.
Like either using...
Well, back in the day...
The CC?
Yeah. Is that still a thing?
Yeah.
It is?
I used the shit out of that back in the day because I had a whole server farm.
Yeah.
And so I would just distribute the builds like crazy and I was like, update, shmupdate.
Yeah, I used to run Gen 2 on a Wii way back when, and it worked very nicely.
Had mPlayer going, could stream things to it, it was great.
Well, let's get into community updates.
Maybe we'll have more from Gen 2 land in the near future.
But this week we're going to talk about the new Librem 15 that came into the studio.
But first, there's a story that has been going steady since January,
and it's picking up more and more momentum, and I'm kind of wondering what we all make of it.
Mazda and Toyota now are getting together on this Linux infotainment system for cars.
It's a project that the Linux Foundation has been working on,
and they've been, to some success, keeping it in the news every single week,
and that seems to be paying dividends now.
With Mazda and Toyota joining forces, they're going to be working together
on the Linux-based connected car navigation entertainment system.
Now, the system that Toyota ships and has been shipping I think since 2012 is called Intune.
It's an in-car infotainment platform, and it's got all the crap that is always sort of hacky and not so great.
It's got the hands-free phone call support over Bluetooth, music streaming, satnav, as they call it,
and it's running on top of Linux.
This automotive-grade Linux project is taking off more and more, though,
with different people getting into Toyota and now Mazda and others that are getting involved.
The reason why they're working together, even though they're competitors,
at least according to a Japanese business newspaper that the Register is citing,
they reckon that the joint effort is at least partially due to a shortage of vehicle-focused software development
and developers, especially in the land of the rising sun, as the Register puts it.
So, Intune and, in broader scope, the automotive-grade Linux project,
I've talked about it a couple of times now on Linux Action News,
and I've done some research into the project, and it seems interesting.
If you are someone who likes to have everything built into your headset,
where it does all the nav, it does your music, it runs your apps, it does your streaming, it has Pandora,
maybe it has some kind of iHeartRadio and Spotify.
Right now, currently, because Microsoft's involved, it includes Bing.
Yeah!
Yeah, and you can get OpenTable for booking restaurant tables and whatnot.
Those things are all inside the Dash and running on this Linux system.
That's the approach of automotive-grade Linux versus, say, Android AutoPlay or Apple CarPlay,
which is more built around the smarts being in the phone and then the receiver,
the headset being more of like a projection, it's a client of the smarts in the phone.
The automotive-grade Linux project does not support CarPlay or Android AutoPlay or whatever,
Android Auto as it's called, so it's sort of a competitor to those.
And so, therefore, I'm a little leery on it as somebody who owns a 2012 vehicle
and is ready to replace that really old, prehistoric, awful computer in the dash.
Oh, man, no kidding, right?
I really don't want to replace it with another one that I'm just going to get driven crazy by later on.
I am more and more thinking about maybe a Raspberry Pi with a touchscreen,
maybe even something as crazy as an NVIDIA Shield, or maybe Android Auto or CarPlay.
All these things, it's not that I'm going to be doing any time soon,
but right now what I can't deny is I have an audio aux-in.
A lot of people use Bluetooth, but I've been using audio aux-in,
and I just play everything from my phone.
If I want news, I listen on my phone.
If I want music, and, of course, podcasts, I do it all on my phone,
and the receiver in my truck is just like a dummy unit.
It could just be a glorified – it could just be a volume knob and an aux-in jack for all I care these days.
So I don't need a lot in dash, and automotive-grade Linux is more about you build your entire system
on top of this Linux platform where we give you these basic functions and apps and UI elements,
and then you deliver an experience for your car on top of it,
which is what automakers are interested in.
But as an end user, I'm good just with my aux-in jack and running it off my phone.
Well, in theory, you could also take the base that you get a car that has support for that.
Maybe, maybe if they don't have some weird locking system or whatever,
you could replace it with whatever system you want.
Sure.
Well, that would be nice.
There's also – this is interesting mainly because Mazda and Toyota already have a partnership for other things,
and it kind of solidifies it even more that they're partnering.
Good point.
Because they have partnerships with a technology of car development technology,
so now that they're doing it with the infotainment part of it, it means that it's likely that –
I mean, this particular one, if this was the first time, it would be kind of weird,
but the fact that they've been doing it for a few years now,
it means that this is likely to be a pretty solid partnership.
Sure. That makes sense.
I agree with you. I'm just going to do this on my phone. I have my phone set up.
But for people who just use a phone as a phone, if those people still exist,
is there value in having a better platform in the car?
Maybe you're a senior and you want to be able to – you know about some of these things,
but you don't want to have to try to figure out how to do that and use the small screen of your car.
Yeah, I think so.
Especially if they can make it better quality connection with your phone calls.
I know a lot of people who are at that age that use the Bluetooth in-car stuff that are just –
it's just an awful experience. It's hard to set up. It's like the worst quality audio possible.
If they can fix that, that would be fantastic.
What about self-driving where there's so much information that all has to be integrated –
speed, traffic, weather conditions, information to the driver?
It seems like having a platform that these car manufacturers – a common technology base
that is sound and proven based on Linux that they can build on top of, they've got to be working this.
Even if as a consumer, like the reasons I just vocalized, I'd prefer to just do it all from my phone.
Three generations from now of drivers, though, they're going to have a totally different set of requirements,
and they're going to need a really refined system to bring all that information together.
So I kind of get why they're working on it.
Is it funny that we haven't even talked about that we're –
like we're talking about it because it's Linux probably, but we haven't talked at all about it being good for Linux or not?
Or is that just – I think that we're just – we assume that this is what Linux does now, right?
It's in embedded systems. It's in cars.
Hmm. Yeah, I guess so, huh?
Yeah. I guess maybe because I get a little lost in the – my thoughts are like, what version of Linux is it?
That's a good question.
What kernel is it running?
There's not a lot of details here even about the product.
No, if there was, I'd be talking about it.
Yeah, you're right. So I haven't really thought about, like, what does it mean for Linux?
I guess I don't think about that much anymore.
I've mentioned this recently, but we used to be supremely concerned with the Tivoization of Linux.
That was a supreme concern for us.
And really sort of the impetus of the GPL3.
Yeah, right. Exactly.
Yeah, that was the Tivo issue of, like, trying to lock down Linux or violating it.
And here we are, and there's a foundation that's – all right, so moving on.
This is something that I think Popey's really going to have to get in on.
I know he likes cryptocurrencies quite a bit.
Popey, we should really make you our cryptocurrency reporter, to be honest.
Yeah, in the field.
Yeah, in the field, on the lines of the Brexit –
In the bits.
On the lines of Brexit, where cryptocurrency will become more relevant than ever, is our field reporter, Popey.
And submitted to the desk, Mr. Popey, was this story by BBC.
And it is Burger King launching a Whopper coin in Russia.
And the reason why I wanted to put this in here is because, of course, this is going to happen.
You open source blockchain technology, of course this is going to happen.
This is the natural progression when you open source a fundamental technology like this.
So Russians will be able to buy a Whopper with virtual cash once they have amassed 1,700 Whopper coins.
Whopper coin.
That's a lot, though.
Yeah, it is, yeah.
And so WAVES is implementing this.
They're going to use a blockchain ledger to keep track of who's gotten coins,
although some people say they've been getting screwed already.
So here you go, ladies and gentlemen.
This is Burger King helping usher in a cyber dystopia.
Thank you, Burger King.
And of course it's Russia.
It's either Russia or Florida.
How is this any different than the half a dozen store loyalty cards that I already have in my wallet that I get no value out of?
I think it's actually better, to tell you the truth.
You know, I mean, you tell me you're a crypto reporter, Poby,
but to me this actually seems a little more legit because honestly, especially if I could trade,
say, you know, you're a big Whopper guy, you want to go get a Whopper in Peru, I could throw you some of my Whopper coins.
Well, not only that, but I'm sure there's going to be a Whopper coin to Bitcoin exchange rate.
Oh, my gosh.
It seems to me you're going to have to eat an awful lot of Whoppers in order for this to be worth anything at all.
Or you've just got to hang around outside and accost everyone who gets their Whopper coins and buy them
when they're clueless people who don't know anything about blockchain stuff, which obviously isn't me.
Well, you can always be right.
Of course, you're a reporter.
But what about, I mean, in your opinion, what about getting into like Whopper coin day trading where you,
but depending on you peg it to like, say, the dollar and when the Whopper coin is strong and the dollar is weak,
you could trade Whopper coins to other people using their iOS and Android apps.
I mean, that seems.
Well, I was thinking just amassing a ton of Whopper coins and then you just hoard them and you wait for the Bitcoin price to crash,
transfer all the Bitcoins and suddenly you just made a bunch of Bitcoin.
Okay.
Which I'm still going to spend on hamburgers, but whatever.
So I guess the only natural conclusion and wimpy, this is just a suggestion.
I'm just going to I'm an idea guy.
I'm going to throw it out here for you.
You can choose to run with this, but I think you should seriously consider implementing a Matecoin.
And then here's the here's the thing.
You what you do is you patch Kaja and people could share their local storage into a pooled encrypted shared cloud storage
using BitTorrent to distribute files.
And the more storage you share and bandwidth you share, the more Matecoin you earn.
So, you know, you know that that exactly what you've described exists.
Yeah.
Yeah. I'm not that original.
Am I?
Yeah.
It's very good, actually.
It's a storage storage share.
Yeah.
S T O R J.
And there's a even a command line version, a terminal version, and there's a version.
That's too funny.
But you don't get any burgers.
There's no hamburgers involved with this.
I'm sure there'll be an exchange, right?
Which is the downside exchange it to Whopper coin.
That'd be OK.
Yeah, I think we need to discuss the most important question.
The Whopper coin be used for chicken fries.
Yeah, yeah.
Especially the Cheeto ones.
Right.
And you did those suckers.
Or is it just Whoppers?
Because I'd be disappointed.
Right.
OK.
I got I have to I have to admit something.
And this is this this technically qualifies.
Yeah.
You know how that makes me feel.
And the value of this is negative.
So Wimpy was right.
Wimpy Wimpy was right.
This never happens.
VR is dead.
I'm going to I'm going to extract this clip and get it to my wife tomorrow.
I'll say it right now.
Nice and clean right up front.
I hate to admit it, but Wimpy was right.
VR was hype.
It's officially dead according to TechCrunch.
And I think they're right because the metric they're using is is kind of sound.
It's this year's E3.
It's the biggest gaming date in the gaming industry.
It's known under its full titles Electronic Entertainment Expo.
Huh?
Woo.
Uh huh.
And there was an Oculus shaped rift where there should have been a lot of showing off
of new games and HTC is dropping their price as well as Oculus.
And TechCrunch's Lucas Matney says over the past several months it's become clear that
the war is no longer HTC and Oculus trying to discover who is Betamax and VHS.
Now they're trying to ensure that high end VR does not turn out to be laser discs.
My kind of point of view, Chris?
That hurts.
It does.
Star Trek bridge crew.
Haven't tried it.
You know, I'm thinking about I'm thinking about why I have a Windows 10 machine trying
it because I have one for like I think I feel like this week I'm going to have a Windows
10 machine and that's about as long as I'm going to make it.
I should give it a go because VR can't possibly be dead if you can play Star Trek on it.
I know.
I mean, I have seen it at like some bars and other type venues that have these sorts of
like and there's at least one in Seattle that has like you can go there and play VR including
Star Trek.
So I think you can have like a party where you rent multiple of their rooms and then
you're all playing Star Trek together.
No kidding.
Yeah.
So that sounds fun.
But it doesn't make it necessarily the same sort of cost benefit for an individual consumer.
I also think that they're they're not counting the fact that PlayStation just added VR to
their system.
Like that's a relatively large user base that they're going to be targeting.
Well, they added that in December last year, didn't they?
And the sales were well, well lower than they were anticipating.
Well, yeah.
But I didn't I didn't know that this was the topic that was going to come up.
But what's interesting is I happened to be thinking about the whole VR thing because,
you know, predictions for this year, you know, December's coming and I was reflecting on
my predictions this year, which have the usual VR is rubbish in it.
And I went back and I listened to what episode number is this of Linux Unplugged?
212.
OK, so I listened back to episode 82 of Linux Unplugged, where Poppy and I have a rather
heated exchange about the relevancy of VR and everything that was discussed back in
episode 82 is the same today.
I had a good experience and I just wanted other people to I just wanted I feel like
the problem was it was the hardware and it was the expense.
Were you going to say something, Poppy?
I was just trying to remember that that conversation, I tried to block out of my mind because Martin
was right.
And you're focused on cryptocurrencies.
Oh, my goodness.
I'm so having that as my ringtone.
I do hope everyone else was talking over me.
So Martin can't grab.
Yeah, no.
Martin was right.
Right.
Talk over, talk over.
So did we talk about only VR or did we talk about AR as well?
I think back then we were only talking about VR.
I think we touched on AR at the very end.
But I think I suggested that that might be the only thing that would be useful.
You might be right on that because Google have announced AR Core for Android.
Yeah, that's the thing today.
So AR Core, which is like AR Kit, can even kind of sounds a bit alike.
And the reason why these are pretty substantial is you can write once and run on both because
you're talking about Unity and Unreal 4 here and then the tools in between will make it
run on AR Kit or, in theory now, AR Core.
And I've been seeing, if you step outside the Linux bubble, I got to say there have
been some significantly impressive AR demos.
I'm sure we've all seen them on Twitter and stuff of the iPhone with iOS 11.
There is some really interesting stuff happening there.
And it does make sense to do it at the phone level because you've got all those sensors
for where you're at in space, the angle of the device, the cameras.
Which has already had a ton of development effort poured into them over the years.
And then a really solid way to deliver new versions of the apps which need cutting edge
development to stay competitive.
It just makes sense to do it there.
But I mourn for the loss of high-end VR on the PC because it's so much better than anything
you could do with cardboard or even AR.
Yeah, see, I don't think VR is dead.
I think just the VR hype is dying.
I think VR is continuing to progress and starting to come more in line with consumer expectations
in terms of price.
That's why the price drops are coming, not because-
I don't think that this is an issue about price.
I think the issue is you have to wear equipment which tethers you to a computer.
And the solution to that apparently is to buy a backpack that you put your computer
in so you can now walk around tethered to this computer that you carry.
And then all of these sensors that you have to rig up in a room to know where you are.
Ultimately you're blindfolded.
You can't actually see what you're doing.
So you're just an accident waiting to happen.
And then there's the expense on top.
So there's a lot of reasons why VR has just got a load of reasons why mass consumer adoption
is a long way away.
Are you saying that VR's problem is the PC?
Yes, to some extent.
Geez, that makes me sad.
But the fact that you're blindfolded, you get these baby walkers that you can stand
in so you can now run around and walk around because you're sort of harnessed inside this
safe space.
The 360 degree-
It's just the solutions that are being created for this are just mental.
I've always thought the escapist aspect of it would be too overwhelming, too appealing
to deny, and that it would take off just because it would be like another drug.
It would be like another way to escape reality.
Yeah, I mean to me, that's not why it has problems.
That's why I want it.
It's putting me in a completely different reality.
It sounds fun, especially with those 360 degree treadmill stuff.
That's why I can see it in bigger places or community events or bars or venues and maybe
not in my home anytime soon.
Yeah, meanwhile though, AR is obviously going to get a lot of attention over the next year.
Especially in the industrial space.
Yeah, but it's the same thing about AR.
People have been saying AR is more interesting than VR, and it's basically gone nowhere.
The same amount of stuff.
I would be willing to bet you at dinner, the next time you're out in this neck of the woods
for an event, I'll bet you at dinner that by this time next year, we're talking a lot
more about AR just because of ARCore and ARKit.
Because ARKit is going to ship on every Apple device that supports iOS 11, which is going
to be 80% of the iPhones in the marketplace.
They're all going to have this AR capability.
And you know the new feature on the iPhone 8 is going to be dual cameras that have depth
sensing sensors that are going to support ARKit.
Yeah, but I don't want to experience augmented reality through my little phone screen.
No, no.
But maybe this is the trajectory.
Maybe you have to start here to get buy-off on this concept.
I don't know.
But do you want to-
Go ahead.
Do you want to experience virtual reality sat down because it's the only safe way to
experience this reality?
Yeah.
No, because that's the 360-
I'm kind of lazy though.
I mean, if I'm going to be in there for hours, I kind of want to sit down.
Wow.
That's true.
See, to me, the only compelling augmented reality thing, and I know I'm on Linux Unplugged,
it's the HoloLens.
If you're going to do AR, that is how you do it.
Yeah.
And then on VR, we've still just got a bunch of tech demos.
There is no compelling titles.
If there was-
Oh, I disagree with you on that.
You know what?
I have more faith-
Rest of the sun's on VR.
I have more faith in ARCore that was announced today by Google than I do in HoloLens just
because Microsoft can't ship anything other than Azure.
That's the only thing they ship these days.
We had this conversation-
We should-
Yeah, okay.
All right.
I have one thing I want to punt to you guys.
Minimac had an opinion about this in the pre-show.
I wanted to bring it up here.
Joe and I, Joe Resington and I, talked about Sailfish charging for their new ROM.
They're customizing for the Sony Xperia X. 50 pounds, I think it was, or I can't remember.
Actually, where's the price at?
50 euros.
I can't tell them apart.
I'm kidding.
What was the price?
I actually, in Linux Action News, I thought, shit, they should charge 100 because what
they're eventually promising is grade A support for the Sony Xperia X running Sailfish.
They're not there yet.
There's some of the sensors that don't work, Bluetooth doesn't work, but the idea is ongoing
support for this device, and they've included licensing for things like Exchange.
Minimac, you want to do a couple of follow-up points from Linux Action News.
2016, I think it was, if I'm recalling correctly.
Why don't you take some of the highlights there, and then maybe we'll kick it around
and see what other people had to add.
Yeah, thanks.
As mentioned before, I'm by no means a Sailfish developer.
I'm maybe a script kiddie for the Nexus 5 port, nothing more.
As you said in the show, the Xperia X is considered to be a first-class device for Sailfish OS.
That includes the license parts.
That means Android support, T9 root prediction, and Microsoft Exchange support.
One part of these 50 bucks is simply license fees, but there is a cool thing about it.
Jolla will publish the source code of the hardware adaptation layer called libhybris
for the device in the coming week or weeks.
There will be a free community port for the Sony Xperia X, and that is the cool thing
about it, because this is a milestone, the Xperia X is the first ARM 64-bit port of Sailfish
OS, and that might be the start of other Sony and other devices running 64-bit chipsets.
So they're doing the legwork to get this working on ARM 64.
Well, okay.
So what about Jolla's point then that, well, if there's a community version available,
where do they get off charging 50 bucks for it?
What's the incentive to pay for that?
I think that's what Jo's concern was, why would I pay 50 bucks for something I can get
for free?
I guess the idea is that you have software for Windows 10 and even Mac OS and Linux where
you can click install the ROM on your existing Sony Xperia X device in the future, but for
now you need a Linux computer, because right now you have to use a console for it.
Producer Michael, what are your thoughts about charging something like this for a ROM?
And let's just for sake of conversation say it was like lineage even, so something that's
super available, but it's just been totally designed for insert Android handset here,
and it's like perfectly designed for that, perfectly tuned.
I would say that it would be, the business model itself is not necessarily a bad thing.
If they were to say make a freemium version where you could get extra features for paying
for it, that'd be cool, but as long as it's not limiting the phone in any way, but it's
just like an extra thing, or it's more like if you want to support us, here's a way to
do that and buy this particular thing.
That kind of thing is fine.
I don't even care if they only did a premium and that's it.
I just don't like who it's coming from.
Tell me about that.
Well, I mean, I don't trust Yola.
You can't trust Yola, in my opinion, mainly because how much of this $50 is going back
to the money that they owe people for the tablet?
Well, I mean, yeah, okay, maybe.
If they still owe people like $100, $150 depending on what level they were in, why would anyone
trust them to buy a software that doesn't even work right now?
Yeah, you can put it on your system and also there's fundamental pieces that do not work.
I'm surprised to hear that because you in the United States have this thing that a company
can fail and Yola failed with the Yola tablet and I was one of the backer, but still they
live on and they try to continue and they try to do something which is really good for
the community.
So I can't agree with you really.
And most of the selfish always is open source.
When they pay money back to the people that they didn't get the money to, that would be
fine.
They are trying to, they are trying to.
Okay, good.
If they say how much money of this $50 per unit per purchase goes to that, that'd be
great.
But until they do that, we don't have any information except trust us.
No, they have a program which says when the Yola is making a profit, they will take a
part of this profit and pay back the backers.
So that was announced at the beginning of the year.
I don't really have an issue with the price either.
The price seems really reasonable.
So it seems like if this is how they're going to pay that back, yeah, it's going to take
them a while to do it.
If this is how they're going to, I bet a big part of how they're paying that back is coming
from the more business deals that they're, that was what I got when I did some digging
for Linux action news is they've lined up a couple of customization jobs for businesses
and that's going to pay some of that back.
But you're right, you don't really know.
You don't know.
If the software was ready to go when they announced this and it wasn't like, Hey, here's
these things that don't work.
And one of them happens to be very important to a lot of people, Bluetooth, like that,
that you, you need to fix that before you ship it.
And like if I would be interested because if they had, if this, if this ROM was fully
functional right out of the box and I don't have to wait for, for like some absurd, you
know, early adopter thing, if it's an early adopter, I'm just picking it up and then just
flashing it myself.
That's fine.
But if I have to flash it myself and have to pay for it, then I expect it to work because
it's a, it's a premium product.
Yeah.
But the Xperia, the Xperia X is a pretty reasonable price phone, $50 extra on top of that, still
way under the majority flagship phones.
So I would be interested as long as the ROM worked.
I have, I have good memories of Sailfish OS too.
All right.
Well, we should move on because we have, wrap it up, go ahead.
For Bluetooth, I think there are two problems with Bluetooth right now.
So first there have been big changes to the operating system.
They introduced Blues 5 for devices that have run kernels that run the Blues 5 API.
And the other problem might be the Qualcomm chipset, which is certified for Bluetooth
4.2.
So I guess they're just filling out these problems and maybe even the community can
help them to fill out these problems.
Well, Manny Mac, thank you for keeping us posted on that.
That is, that is good perspective and I appreciate it.
And if you want to know what sort of inspired this entire conversation, check out linuxactionnews.com.
We've got the latest stuff from there.
And if you think of anything else, let's, let's include it in the post show.
I think we should probably keep going.
There's like,
There's more to talk about today.
You made us an amazing show.
I mean, like, like, like we have so much more to get to, including, I want to, I really
want to unbox this, this Librem and check it out.
I have, I have really no idea what to expect.
So let's, let's talk about how we made this show possible.
It's our first sponsor this week and that's Linux Academy.
Go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
That's where you can sign up for a free seven day trial and support the show.
Linux Academy is a platform to learn more about Linux created by Linux enthusiasts.
From the basics all the way up to the big platforms that make the big bucks these days.
Linux Academy is really something special with human mentoring available, instructors
when you need it, and a community stack full of Jupiter broadcasting members.
Whether you're an experienced sys admin or new to the world of Linux, Azure and AWS,
OpenStack and DevOps, a sharp skill set is an absolute necessity to succeed.
Meet Linux Academy, an online Linux and cloud training platform that uses self-paced video
courses and hands-on labs to give you real-world experience for a wide range of skills.
Train for your certification, learn the latest DevOps tools, and grow your skill set to do
better work.
Linux Academy is not just a video library.
Our scenario-based server labs and quiz system allow you to learn hands-on.
We also have full-time human instructors who answer questions and help you earn that certification
or promotion at work.
We add new training every week so you'll always be up to date on the latest tech.
Sys admins of every experience level use Linux Academy to stay on the bleeding edge of the
Linux ecosystem.
You should too.
Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged, free seven-day trial, it is really a secret weapon.
I can only imagine if I could go back in time.
It'd be like if I was, if I was, uh, uh, Bic, or what's his name?
What's the guy's name?
Bic?
Bic Tannen?
Yeah, I think it's Bic.
Is it Bic?
Why does it sound right?
Is it Bif?
Bif.
Yeah, Bif.
Yeah, if I was Bif Tannen, if I was Bif Tannen and I had the sports almanac, only this would
be Linux Academy.
It would be a Linux Academy.
And I go back in time with Linux Academy and I'd know all the answers.
But now, of course, all them young whippersnappers.
You'd be like, hey, I'm really good with system D.
All them people looking for germs, all those people looking to get ahead, now they got
Linux Academy.
You know what would be even better, Chris?
What?
Is if you went back and you started Linux Academy.
Oh, I should have.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Thanks to them.
And sign up for a free seven-day trial.
All right, let's talk about a couple of quick things in Mumble Room.
Feel free to jump the F in if you got something even better that kind of conclude our conversation
about replacing LastPass.
Do you have any thoughts on remote backup, Wes, before we go any further?
Remote backup in general, because last week we had to talk about CrashPlan was dropping
their personal plan.
And that's sort of like that really good deal that lets you just send a ton of data up there.
And you got to get the F off the service.
We talked about different options.
Do you have any immediate thoughts?
Do you want to chime in anything on offsite backup on anything like that?
I mean, I think you guys did a pretty good job of rounding it up.
I use Tarsnap myself for some things.
And then I also have a couple of friends.
And we do have some, you know, set up some boxes that we can do R6 from, which works
pretty nicely.
Yeah.
Okay.
What about you, Beardsley?
There is one service that we didn't mention that I'm surprised we didn't mention.
At least I don't think we did.
And that's Backblaze.
Well, we mentioned in the context of B2 or whatever, because of their Linux support.
Yeah.
WSHacks wrote in on the subreddit and said, I'm surprised SpiderOak didn't come up, which
is my bad.
I'm a SpiderOak subscriber.
He says, it's one of the few consumer-focused backup services that I know of that has a
Linux client besides Tarsnap and Rclone.
The other options I looked at are rsync.net.
So that was what he had to add.
I know rsync.net now does, you can do like zfs send to them.
So that's pretty sweet.
That is.
If you have a big zfs array.
That is really sweet.
Alan Jude should get into something like that.
Yeah, right?
That would be right in his wheelhouse.
Yeah, I'd send some bits over to Alan.
Yeah.
I just looked up Backblaze.
It is super damn cheap for B2.
It's half a cent per gigabyte per month.
Woo.
So that's really, really.
But B2.
You're looking at B2?
Yeah, yeah.
So Rclone and whatnot does support B2.
Well, not only that, but they now have their own command line Linux client as well.
Is that right?
Yeah.
All right.
Now, Mr. Wimpy, you were going to make a mention about Enpass.
Yes, this isn't a backup utility, but an alternative to LastPass for storing your passwords.
Which you probably need to back up.
Yeah.
And the way that Enpass works is unlike LastPass, they don't provide the cloud storage backend.
It's client software that runs on all the different platforms.
And then you then sync your wallet with whatever backend file syncing service you choose to
use.
Do you want to-
Yeah.
And the price is very, it's free unless you want to do mobile stuff.
And then it's only like 10 bucks per device.
So Wimpy, do you feel like divulging what you've chosen to sync it with?
Well, I have it synced in Dropbox at the moment because it's all locally encrypted.
So there's nothing going into Dropbox that I need to worry about.
I was hoping you'd say because you hate freedom.
I knew there was a low chance, but I just thought that'd be really funny.
Yeah.
That's what I'm using too, myself.
Dropbox is still being used for a lot of stuff.
And for offsite backups, I'm using Rclone and S3.
Ah.
I am.
Oh, and how are you liking that?
Yeah, very good.
I've also got Amazon photo storage and Amazon file storage through Amazon Prime.
And what I like about that is you can actually instigate cloud to cloud transfers.
You don't have to Rclone all of your stuff down locally and then push it somewhere.
You can actually clone it between cloud storage backends without having to pull it down.
Wow.
That is nice.
Yeah.
And I know you weren't here last week either.
Do you have any thoughts on offsite backup or want to share anything you've tried and
had success with?
So yeah, I don't do any offsite backup.
I do it all to a home server.
So yeah, if my house went up in flames, I'd lose everything.
That's bad.
And I keep not quite getting around to anything.
And I've tried most of these.
I've tried...
What was the one you mentioned, Spider Oak?
Yeah.
It's an atrocious user interface.
Slow too.
Yeah.
But I'm keen to know what other people use that are good and reliable and I can just
fire and forget and not have to faff about and worry about it with large volumes of data
because I have a huge multi-terabyte array with all my backups on at home and I don't
know what to do with it.
So...
Hi ho.
What was that?
Hi, Chris.
It's Ben.
How are you doing?
Nice to see you, Ben.
Well, I just wanted to talk about this part of the show.
Well, I've always used...
I've used R Sync a couple of times and I've also used Google Drive and...
What else?
OneDrive and a couple of other different solutions.
And also, can I jump back to the Gen 2 part for just a minute?
I just wanted to say that I'm willing to help you on that front.
That's what I wanted to point out.
Oh, you're gonna take the challenge with us?
Welcome aboard.
Yeah.
Well, I want to help you guys out at any point.
If you get stuck in the installation or anything like that, I'm willing to help.
Oh, I'm not so worried about that.
I mean, I feel like I can do that.
I feel like I'm more like I just want somebody to do it with us.
It's like, you know, when you're trying to...
Yeah, I'm willing to jump on board, that's fine, because I've installed it half a dozen
times.
I mean, Spatry even said I've installed it more times than people change things.
Well, okay.
So to our topic at hand here, so you're using R Sync to offsite what?
Like you're going...
Are you going to...
I mean, I've done a bunch of different Linux respins and different things like that and
different ISOs.
And I've helped out a couple of different people with their Linux respins and I've uploaded
stuff for them on R Sync and different stuff like that.
So yeah, I've uploaded several different files and stuff like that that I've had to back
up the different cloud sourcing like SourceForge, GitHub, different stuff like that with R Sync.
Surf Rock wrote into the show and he says, in regards to CrashPlan, eliminating home
accounts, he says, here's what led me to convert to a CrashPlan Pro account.
He did some soul searching, he did the math.
He looked at the fact that he's got a NAS server with 12 terabytes on it.
He's got some Dropbox systems that he wants to send offsite.
He's got a couple of machines he wants to back up.
He said, now I could do a single backup of my entire home to the local server, all over
like some sort of NFS or Samba mount.
And then still, trying to do all the math, he says, the best thing for me is to just
go for CrashPlan Pro.
It's 120 US greenbacks a year, but the backups not only capture all of your data, they also
capture all of the configs for all of the machines.
Which to him was sort of like the, ah, that's the sensor for me.
I want a utility that'll blast everything back to exactly the way it was, not just back
up the data, but everything the way it was.
And that's where CrashPlan Pro for him.
I mean, that's like on the more managed side of services, and in that scenario, I think
$120 a year, if you can afford it, is a reasonable amount for the kind of protection that you
get.
Yeah.
It comes always back to that question of how much do you, as a sys admin or a similar
person who can do some things, is this something you outsource or is it something you roll yourself?
He says when I kind of laid it all out with the wife, he says the spousal approval factor
is pretty high, especially when I mentioned the pictures.
Yeah, right.
That's an important one, though.
We kind of invented digital cameras and then didn't come up with a reliable way to make
sure you could keep those pictures.
Yeah.
A Spider Oak.
So my thing has always been like, is what I use Spider Oak for is to back up Dropbox,
which is like, it's like my belt and suspenders approach to Dropbox, but it's really excessive
and it's really slow and it depends on one machine running that has both Spider Oak and
Dropbox installed.
It's like that's your sync machine.
Why can't one connect to the other and just do it like cloud to cloud, you know?
I mean, it's just servers.
It's not like they don't need some desktop.
It's all just Linux.
Do they really need a desktop PC in between?
They can't talk directly to each other?
Give me a break.
And of course, you're never going to get that with these closed source.
So one of the things that a lot of people wrote into the show, a lot of people wrote
into the show about was NextCloud.
I don't think we've ever gotten more people suggesting NextCloud ever than we did in response
to all of this.
Off-site sync, but the thing that people really brought up was that's where I store a lot
of my data that is resync.
So calendar, contacts, photos, notes, they just keep them on NextCloud and then they
reload the machine and then the NextCloud syncs that stuff back down.
That's a pretty good way to do it.
Yeah, but at the same time, like if it's critical data, I'm not like a security engineer or...
Are you sure?
That word's pretty legit.
I don't trust myself to be able to take care of that data.
That's why I'm wanting to offload it to another service.
Geez.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's fair.
Yeah.
Because that's what they do.
That's their thing.
Yeah.
They spend their entire day doing that stuff.
I think that's what's sort of great about open source though is there is a good contingent
of us out there that we are...
I really kind of ebb and flow on it.
Some stuff I'm willing to maintain myself and some stuff I'm willing to just like sort
of off-site.
Yeah.
I agree.
For me, it varies depending on how important what you're doing.
How interested it is, how easy it is for you, and that kind of changes depending on what
you do.
How much it would hurt you if you lost it.
Right.
Yeah.
And backups though are...
What I really dream of is something that is like a, is this possible?
But maybe even like a 15-year system.
Is that just ridiculous?
These are your backups.
These are your photos, and your music, and your documents, and your creations.
You're going to want them for a while, right?
And in the past, they would have all been physical things that would have gone in boxes
that you would have stored somewhere ridiculously, and then your family would have to do something
with when you died.
But now I want...
And were you making three copies of that that you put at different people's houses?
Well, that's just it.
The longer I go, am I just building up more and more shit that I'm going to have to keep
converting to newer formats, drag to new cloud storage services, move to new types of open
source programs that come online, hosted by new cloud providers?
Am I just going to drag all this stuff with me?
And the thing is, is the more dispersed it is, the less control I have over it now, the
less flexibility I'll have down the road.
You see, so there is some logic to all of these people writing in saying, use Nextcloud,
because at least then you have some sort of escape hatch.
Like right now, I got a ton of stuff in Google, and Google's going to be around for a really
long time.
Will I be using Google services for 15 years?
I doubt it.
And at some point, I'm going to have to come to that reality of having to migrate all of
my crap out of their crap.
Well, even with like, I've had that with the Dropbox.
I just kind of just stopped using Dropbox at one point.
I still had stuff in it.
And then I have to make sure that my account stays open, or I have to then make sure that
I migrate.
So there are past issues.
I did go through my entire Dropbox and remove everything.
Mm-hmm.
I think this is why some of us feel compelled to build like super NASes in our houses and
just get something that has a ton of disk, and like Popey, just mine CryptoCoin and have
a bunch of disks, and just keep it all local.
You could Vericrypt stuff, maybe, and put stuff on these services.
And use, of course, CFS to prevent bit rot.
Well, that's just important.
I'll just take a nap and let it back up to tar snap.
I don't want to lose my Whopper coins.
Well, you know, and a lot of them are like, duh, Chris, Nextcloud on DigitalOcean.
I don't know if you've heard, Chris, but DigitalOcean is a really easy and quick way to spin up
droplets in less than 55 seconds.
Install BSD and get ZFS and SSDs.
All right.
So now this is sponsor time right here.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go over there, create an account, and use our promo code DOUNPLUGS.
You'll get a $10 credit, and then you can spin up their $5 rig.
I love their $0.03 an hour machine, because you get a lot of resources and a lot of memory
and a lot of core and a lot of everything for $0.03 an hour.
Everything you deploy will use SSDs from their really nice, low-end, like, you can't even
believe how little you're paying for it systems, all the way to the systems that are monsters.
Have you seen, like, their 200-plus gigabyte RAM systems and their new high CPU systems?
High CPU.
Yeah.
And you can manage it all with a simple API, which means if you start getting more and
more droplets, which does eventually happen, because they're great for everything.
You can deploy them all over the world.
You can get set up in seconds.
You can get started with an entire open source stack or a single low-level OS.
You're going to end up using the API.
And the API is so well done, you're going to love it.
Lightning fast networking, highly available storage.
You can attach as you need up to 16 terabytes, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, and
use the FS.
And use the FS, just like the beard was saying, because it shows up as a block storage device,
and you could use that.
Or you know what?
You know what?
You could make the SUSE folks happy, and you could use ButterFS.
You sure could.
You could play around with it.
You know, I hear RAID 5 and 6 are pretty popular.
Give that a go.
See, the nice thing about DO is once you get tired of that, you just blow it away.
One button click, one API call, it's gone.
Yeah.
And something that the ButterFS folks really love is they also have snapshots.
So you can take snapshots of your system before you create some sort of a fence.
In fact, because that API is really nice and well-documented, you'll find that there's
open source projects that might integrate with your package manager that will actually
take a snapshot of your DigitalOcean droplet before it installs all your packages.
So if something blows up, you can revert right back.
That's awesome.
DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
And thanks to everybody out there for using the DOUNPLUGGED promo code after they create
their account at DigitalOcean.com.
So this week, the smoke was revealed from, I'm sorry, the fire was revealed from the
smoke that is the Librem 5, and the Librem 5 is Purism's attempt to build a GNU slash
Linux powered open source phone that respects your privacy and your GNU slash freedoms.
Now it's going to start around $600, which is actually a pretty reasonable price for
a bonafide smartphone.
That's the world we live in.
And it's got one interesting element that out of all of the things about it impressed
me, is its support for matrix phone calling.
Now I have quite a bit of skepticism about a fundraiser for $1.5 million for a smartphone
in 2017.
But I thought before we really even go there, I thought I'd tell you a little bit about
it.
They say it'll be the world's first IP native mobile handset for a new kind of cord cutter.
And that cord cutter is one that's cutting the cord from the cellular network, which
I actually feel like is not to make this a sponsor thing, but sort of why I use Ting,
because I just pay for what I use, and I try not to use the cellular network, because screw
the cellular networks.
Screw those carriers.
And so Ting is sort of like my hack around that.
And now apparently it just turns out I'm a new kind of cord cutter hipster.
I didn't even know it.
And all of you Ting users out there didn't even know it.
And you're not going to get credit for it either, don't worry.
And the other thing about this phone is it's not shipping iOS, it's not shipping Android,
it's shipping PureOS, which is their Linux distribution.
They're working with the Matrix Project to get that calling and texting.
It's going to be like a full-fledged messaging platform.
It's not just phone calls.
It's going to have a five-inch screen.
It'll have hardware kill switches for the camera, microphone, Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, and
the baseband.
That's a lot of switches.
It is a lot of switches.
It's kind of like spiky on the outside of the phone.
Maybe.
I'm wondering.
I'm wondering about that.
They're going to have a separate CPU and baseband.
They're going to have...
Really?
Mm-hmm.
Now, that's something.
So, what do you think, Wes, 2017, to get in, to get a phone of any real substance, to get
a phone and a charger, you got to back it at $599, $600 US, and estimated delivery is
January of 2019.
That's a long, that's a ways away.
And I wonder, it just seems like there's been a hard time in the past to get these things.
Like right now, if I could have that phone right now, yeah, all right, that seems great.
I would try it.
I would use it.
I'm curious about it.
A lot of that appeals to me.
But that's a long time.
We've seen things slip in these kinds of projects.
And the money I'm paying is money today, will that really have sold the same value in a
year and a half or whatever?
Yeah.
This was a pledge that you could get this, they know that there's people who want to
do it and are willing to give them money, but not taking the money even when the campaign's
over, waiting until it's actually like a physical thing.
That I'd be happy to do.
But $600 for a phone in a year and a half, no thanks.
What about something that sort of shakes up the whole iOS, Android death grip?
No, as far as PureS is, what they're saying that they're doing is amazing.
Like there are certain aspects of this phone that I would love it, especially the separate
baseband thing, because that brings so much potential to the mobile platform as the Linux
mobile advocate that I want to be.
That is something that was fundamentally important.
$1.5 million.
55 days to go.
They've raised 8.55% as we record.
That's 128,000.
So I think I was a backer of their first fundraiser.
I think that's how I got the Librem 15.
It's been a little while now.
The reason why I lose track is because I've kind of lost track of how many fundraisers
there's been, because I think there's been a couple of different fundraising campaigns
at this point for different hardware, and I've kind of lost track.
I don't know if this is a bad thing or not.
Does it become a red flag if you're three or four fundraisers in?
Does that indicate that perhaps this is starting to become a business model in which that every
few years, or every year or so, you have to do a fundraiser to keep going?
That was one thing I was kind of bring up, is I would almost have more confidence in
this, at least kind of with the Yala stuff, it feels like there is more of this business
angle and I can kind of get on board, or I have a little more faith that that will have
the sort of traction or momentum to influence the industry, or at least take a bite out
of it.
So like you're saying, this sort of intermittent funding model, does that have the same sort
of staying power that we need to actually get market share, which is what you need to
get apps that people want and users that are using it?
I guess it's a way to maybe fish out consumer demand before you go all in on a product,
perhaps?
Well, to me, it just looks more like they aren't making enough money that they can be
able to do these projects themselves.
Whether that's true or not, that's the perception it gives me.
Hmm.
Wimby, you're suggesting that they've created their own funding platform.
I guess I hadn't noticed.
You're right.
This isn't Kickstarter IndieGoGo, is it?
No, it's that they're using their own platform and I'm just wondering what people feel about
that.
Because if you're taking the money and managing it yourself, do we lose some of the oversight
and having a place to go that's independent of the organization looking for the funding?
And does it suggest this is going to be something that happens more often?
Go ahead, Bobby.
It also means that there's no publicly visible feedback.
Like when I go to a Kickstarter or an IndieGoGo or many of the others, I know I can go and
have a look in the conversations that people are having in the comments and the comments
underneath the updates to see what the general feel of that project is before I'm going to
back it.
So all I've got is the mouthpiece of the people who are making the project, I'm less inclined
to feel I want to contribute to that thing.
And they don't actually provide any policy information like what their structure of payment
is either.
Well, okay.
Not only that, but it doesn't make a whole lot of business sense to them because aren't
they limiting their number of eyes to the people that visit their site?
Well, and maybe they're just hoping that social outreach will...
How do you really get people to your Kickstarter page?
You've got to get...
I think they had to do this in order to be FSF friendly.
You can't make a fully pure, fully free software device and then say, come on to this non-free
platform in order to back the thing like Kickstarter or IndieGoGo because they're all completely
non-free.
I think one of them was on crowd supply, but I can see why they would want to do it on
their own site, but it smells a bit bad to me.
It's not the first people to do that though because the new PG people did it as well.
But I mean, okay, so that is an interesting thing to be aware of and something to consider.
I mean, it does mean that you bypass whatever rules are in place, like Kickstarter and IndieGoGo
have certain criteria that must be met before you can just...
You can't just throw any old project.
I mean, it looks like that on IndieGoGo sometimes, but you can't just throw your project on there.
There are some rules and there's some opportunity for recourse if things go bad.
What opportunity for recourse do we have directly with purism themselves if there's no intermediary
who can say, this project went south and you need to provide some kind of remuneration
for the people who were done out of their cold hard cash.
We also don't know if it's like a Kickstarter style or if it's like the IndieGoGo where
you can do both fixed or you get it automatically regardless if they meet the thing or not.
Fix and flex.
So outside of the payment platform, I mean, is there a bitterness developing around this
concept or is there still enthusiasm amongst us all gathered here today for a open source
Linux powered handset that you can in theory load any distro.
This one will be shipping with a Debian derivative, which would support hooking up a mouse and
keyboard and an HDMI device and quote unquote convergence if you want to start X.
The claim that it can run any Linux distribution is an interesting one given that it's an MX
board and therefore it would need, you'd need to have a target for that platform.
It's an ARM board.
The reason why it would be ARM, yeah.
Technically any distro could run on it, but in practice somebody would have to enable
that hardware for that distro.
Well they also, because of the baseband that, because they're doing a separated baseband
with the firmware built into it, like that kind of.
I understand that, but I'm just talking generally, you know, just, just everything about the
board.
If something's not based on ARM for sure.
Yeah.
Who is that?
Oh, is that Poppy?
Oh, Poppy, you're breaking up.
Hold on.
Say it again.
Oh, sorry.
Go again.
Yeah, there you go.
Now you're clear.
So the thing that gets me is this is basically just a small computer.
Like the GPD pocket that people have been raving about, the small computer that has
an HD display and a full size keyboard is like a tiny, tiny netbook-y kind of thing.
It's not a distant step from that to the Purism device, right?
It's the, there are tricky things because it's a, it's got no hardware keyboard and
it's going to be used in a pocket with expected long battery life, but there's not a giant
leap from existing hardware that can run general purpose Linux operating systems like the GPD
pocket can.
Okay.
Modulo busted drivers for various things, but that'll get fixed.
There's not a big leap from there to a mobile device that can run general purpose Linux
operating systems.
And we're talking some time away for this thing to be delivered.
So it's not unreasonable to think that that could be delivered.
I agree.
I, I, and, uh, I tell you, I agree with all of you that said that if it was shipping today,
it's something I would definitely consider purchasing.
Yeah.
I'd already be having it in my cart right now and checking it out.
You know, something I did notice about their announcement was they are not committing to
specific hardware as well.
Which-
Or functionality.
Yeah.
It clearly states everything is subject to change.
So it's, it's like they're asking you to back it, but they're also not committing to delivering
you a specific product, which is really worrisome to me.
Well, in a sense, like you could say that maybe because they don't want to commit to
the hardware specs because in a year from now or something like that, or six months
from now, the hardware specs would be, would be so much different that they wanted to upgrade.
And if they already committed to a certain thing, people would expect that this way they
could say, well, we're going to upgrade it automatically and then you're going to get
a better, more RAM or a different type of RAM or something like that.
Yeah.
Well, just, just the other day, uh, they, uh, did an update on their blog and they said
that, uh, the general interest in the fundraiser so far has kind of got us talking more with
hardware manufacturers.
And based on their post here, what I grok is that they have a rough idea of what they're
targeting.
They're targeting the processor.
They, I think it's going to be about four gigs of RAM and then they have a couple of
rough ideas, but I don't think they're super committing yet because it's all subject to
change because it is so far out.
I think that's pretty much it.
Um, I wonder if we will be in not too distant future in a position where these kinds of
crowdfunding campaigns will be able to essentially print a device like this every time somebody
backs it.
So the moment you back it, it's just on demand manufacturing.
You don't have to secure 1.5 million orders because you don't have to preorder 300,000
units.
You can, you can just print out a unit as they're, and of course printing, I'm using
loosely as a way to automate manufacturing, but you do have to wonder when will that scale
get to a point where they can do one-to-one ordering and it doesn't require a huge batch
purchase that has to be planned out for a year in advance because in some ways it feels
like that's what's holding back true unfettered development of a free Linux phone.
Because you would need something that was reasonably priced, that was reasonably functional,
and that people could actually get their hands on immediately.
So the moment it started to tip into popularity, people could start ordering it.
Like a Raspberry Pi Zero or a Raspberry Pi when they were brand new.
Like those, there was a tipping point where resources were limited, but there were ways
to get your hands on it, and that's not possible for companies like Purism.
They're in this position trying to get off the ground with a new product like this.
I mean, to be fair, you could think about the fact that they don't have to set up deals
with different companies and OEMs and all this other stuff because they're not making
a software like an OS for a plethora of devices.
They're making one device and one OS for that device.
So Michael, what do you think?
If this doesn't work, is this dream dead?
No, I don't think it's dead because of UBports and Plasma Mobile, what they're doing, and
the Holium project is awesome.
So it's just going to be a different version of the dream.
Instead of having the one ideal device you can buy that just comes all ready to go, it's
going to be you buy the hardware and then load your OS.
Right.
It's going to be flash it yourself kind of thing.
Yeah.
It's going to work for Linux on the desktop, I guess.
I think that's the most likely to happen in general, especially because all the projects,
especially ones that are working together, like the Holium project is a collaborative
project to work with multiple different approaches.
So I like that.
But I hope Purism is successful in this and makes a fantastic device because I would really
love to do it.
I just can't convince myself to pay $600 for a dream.
But I hope other people have money to risk on that.
So feel free to back it so I can eventually get it.
Well speaking of their hardware, arriving just in time for the show to give you a first
impression is what appears to be a brand new laptop from Purism.
So we'll talk about that in just a moment.
Any closing thoughts, gentlemen, in the Mumble Room on the CrowdFunder?
Anybody that decided to back it want to chime in?
I'll kick it to you for final comment.
I really wish them all success.
Having worked on a phone that didn't succeed, I know this is hard, really hard.
And even if you have a lot of people who are willing you on and are willing to get you
like a significant chunk of the way, like Ubuntu Edge got $12 million towards the $30
million target.
And I know we didn't hit the target, but we got phones out in the market and we got an
operating system out there.
It was a lot of hard work and I think they're going to need a lot of help to get this done.
I wish them all the best.
Todd says, just a few years later, all you need is $1.5 million now instead of $30 million.
Do you have any thoughts on that?
I don't know the mobile market well enough to know if that's actually true or whether
you'd get this.
I mean, bear in mind, these are two wildly different devices.
The Ubuntu Edge was a unicorn and with everything that phones now already have, but for a general
purpose device.
Right.
So, I don't think, I think it's probably reasonable to say the numbers are lower.
Yeah.
The phone that they're going to be using is an ODM part, so I imagine most of this money
will go into funding the required software development.
Oh, okay.
Well, we will have links in the show notes and I definitely would say I'm in the camp
if somebody would love to see this work out.
To your point about the manufacturing, it seems like it's a shame that the way it's
gone never really involved the Linux Foundation because it seems like some sort of group like
that or something that could, for spanning multiple projects, facilitate and build those
reliable connections to the actual manufacturing community because we do it like re-spin these
up every time.
It just can't scale.
Maybe somebody's run the numbers and said, we're going to focus on the card instead.
Right.
Exactly.
Oh, I don't know.
I don't know, but I'll tell you what.
If they ever ship it, I'll run it on Ting.
Go over to...
Were you going to say something?
Do you want to...
No.
Oh, okay.
Linux.ting.com, Linux.ting.com.
Not to get a burger, although that does sound delicious right now, but to get something
even cheaper and that's your mobile service plan for just $23 per month.
That's the average cost of a Ting plan.
That includes your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes.
The reason why is it starts at just $6 a month and then it's your usage on top of that.
Nationwide coverage, no contracts, no quote unquote agreements.
You just pay for any pairs that you use.
And by pairs, I mean minutes, messages, or megabytes.
That's what I call them now.
A fair price for however much you talk, however much you text, or however much data you use.
You're always in control with their great tools, both on phone and their web app.
You can buy a device directly from Ting.
Really nice.
The whole line of solid devices.
Things that I think often people don't think of immediately when they think about getting
like a value Android device.
Ting is really good about spotting devices that are going to get updates or they got
good functionality or they got great battery life and they're a great value.
Of course, they've also got all the Cadillac devices, both on the iOS and Android side.
They have really fantastic customer service.
But my favorite feature of Ting is paying for what I use.
Because I feel like I am that hipster cord cutter for the new mobile age.
I live on Wi-Fi.
I download my podcast before I leave.
I pin my music to my device.
I have photos backed up only when I'm on Wi-Fi.
It's perfect for when I'm on the go.
All of it's local.
I don't want to be on the phone anymore when I'm driving anyways.
Those are really only times I'm off Wi-Fi these days.
Or if I may be out shopping or doing something on the holidays.
That's why it's perfect for Ting to fill in the gaps.
CDMA and GSM networks, no contracts, no other termination fee, just $6 a month plus Uncle
Sam's tax and then whatever you use.
I love it.
Some months I'm a little busier.
Some months I'm not busy at all at all.
Really average.
Still end up saving money.
It's amazing.
Also when you're over at Ting, linux.ting.com, check out their blog.
They got a blog post about Ting offering internet, home internet service in the future.
Once?
Yeah.
Read about that.
I'm just going to have to move right over there.
Linux.ting.com.
So just in time for the show, the Librem came in here.
This I believe is a replacement for the one that I kick started a long time ago that had
some cooling issues.
Do you want to do the honors of the unboxing?
Oh sure.
I did a little uncutting of the tape so that way you wouldn't have to like futz with that
on the show.
But ladies and gentlemen, right now Mr. Wes Payne is extracting a sub box from an outer
white box.
It says nothing but purism on it.
He pulls it out.
It says notebook on the box.
All right, Wes.
This looks like your average laptop box just as you would expect.
I would turn on the inside webcam but our Logitech camera died.
If anybody has any recommendations for really great wide angle high definition cameras that
work really well under Linux, tweet me at Chris Elias.
All right.
So he's opening up the sub box right now.
What are your initial impressions, Wes?
Very normal packaging.
Seems fine.
Looks like I bought an Acer at Costco.
Does it feel cold?
Is it metal?
Can you tell?
Oh it does feel cold.
Yeah.
There we go.
Is it in a plastic wrap there?
It is, yes.
Styrofoam on the sides.
Nicely safe.
It was not damaged.
Is it heavy?
I mean it feels sturdy.
In plastic case.
Let's get this out.
Oh yeah.
It's dark.
I'd say it's like a black metal.
It's like a midnight.
It's got that same, you know, there's nothing on the top surface which I kind of like.
It's elegant.
Oh, look at that.
So let's see.
We've got DC power in, two USB three slots, headphone jack, SD card reader on the side,
and then two more USB ports, HDMI out, and USB-C. Interesting.
Not much else though.
There's the power adapter.
It doesn't appear to be much of a manual or anything else.
How big is the power brick?
Just say that.
Oh, not too bad.
No, not bad at all.
Pretty standard.
Yeah.
So it's got a pretty big trackpad.
Typical barrel type power plug here.
Purism button there.
Oh, and there's those, there is those classic kill switches.
So look at there in the latch, in the hinge of the laptop.
You see the kill switches right here along the, just underneath the screen.
Oh, yeah.
Look at that.
Yeah.
That's actually not a bad place for them.
It's out of the way.
Yeah.
So this thing has a sixth-generation i7 processor and it's using Intel graphics.
I think it has 16 gigs of RAM and an SSD in there for the storage.
I'll do a full review after I've had a chance to play with it.
I just got it before the show.
There's a little reset button on the bottom too, so that's like a physical reset.
Like a classic PC reset button.
I kind of like that actually.
Yeah.
That is kind of nice.
I think it's using DDR4 RAM too, which should be, you know, nice and fast.
What do you think about the weight and feel of it?
And maybe give a try of that keyboard too.
I was trying to think of how, I'd say it's like an old-style MacBook keyboard.
So not the new, like the really, not the new really flat touch bar keyboard, but like the,
if anybody's tried those.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
Not like that.
You're right.
It is kind of like that.
Not too much flex.
Or like a later-generation, not like a great ThinkPad keyboard, but like one of the more
modern ThinkPad keyboards.
Yep.
The travel's not amazing.
I don't particularly like this enter key.
Some keys seem to be a little better than others.
What do you think about that trackpad though?
That's pretty good.
Yeah, not bad.
Big size, nicely offset, and it's a little less smooth than I think I would like.
You want to hit the power button?
But it works.
You see it there?
I don't know where it is.
I don't know where it is on that thing.
Top right.
Go ahead and power it up.
Let's see if it's got a charge.
It should be loaded with Pure OS.
Yep.
It looks like it's powering up.
Wow.
Boom.
Right there.
There's the Purism logo right there.
Boom.
Wow.
And it looks like it's going right into a mem test.
I'm not sure.
It looks like it booted right into mem test.
Maybe that's all that's on there.
That might be the hall that's installed.
It's just mem test because it just booted right into mem test.
I'm good with that actually.
That's fine with me.
I don't know what to put on there though.
So that becomes, maybe that's what I should put Gen 2 on.
I thought I'd be trying out Pure OS again.
Maybe it is.
So is that just like their customized like firmware image there that has their, I thought
that was going to be a Linux boot order.
Or it's just an image on the disk.
A rumor has it that beta 1 of 1710 is coming out soon.
That might be what I put 1710 on.
And by the way, it's silent.
You hear that?
That's silent.
You know, I got to give them credit.
You know, it took them a few years, but they really came through.
There is a fan in the same spot on the bottom pretty much.
To be fair, the other one was pretty silent until you put it under any load.
No, no.
No, it was 24.
It was always.
It was just full.
You booted on it, it was full blast.
You're thinking of the Galago.
You're thinking of the Galago Pro.
Yeah, no, the Librem was just full blast.
So the other thing that I really got to give them credit for here is they also sent us
the Librem 13.
They sent it to Noah.
And he didn't give it the best of review.
So in the face of all of that, you got to give them credit for still coming through.
I don't know if they would have done it if I didn't host this here show.
But the note I got from them was as an original backer, they wanted to make it right.
And the timing had nothing to do with the phone kickstarting, because the phone fundraiser
actually got moved up a few weeks, and this has been in manufacturing for much longer
than a couple of weeks.
Well, I got to say, I'll be very curious to see what you think of it, especially after
you load Gen 2.
I just said I think it's 1710.
Sorry, Chris.
Did I hear crux?
I really am feeling like beta 1 is going to be when I jump in on 1710 and start living
the 1710 lifestyle.
And I think beta 1 is perhaps nigh.
The future is nigh.
I wouldn't have expected FreeBSD.
Wow, dude.
That's not what I said at all.
Do you want to hand it over to Beardsley to have him take a look at it?
See what he thinks of it.
See what the beard thinks of the first impressions.
I'd like to hear your thoughts on that trackpad, too, Rekai.
Feels really heavy, that's for sure.
But that's not necessarily a bad thing.
So yeah, so this is the Librem 15, and this is part of the second batch they've done of
these later models.
It has a Core i7 Skylake in it.
I think at 3.1 gigahertz with 16 gigs of RAM, DDR4 RAM at that.
It has a, I think, 1080p screen, and you can do M.2 in it, or an MVME drive.
I think this one has an M.2.
Yeah.
And it's got, instead of the Windows key, it's got the Purism button.
It's got a Theros wireless in it.
It's got a hardware kill switch for the radios, the microphone, and the camera.
I'm not a big fan of the trackpad.
No?
It feels like I'm not just sliding my hand across it, I have to drag really hard.
It doesn't feel very smooth.
It is a little more frictionless than I would want.
Is it grabby?
Yeah, grabby's a good term for it.
The keyboard, though, I really like.
So this is, does it say on the back there, does it say version three?
Is that what it is?
Is that version three of the Librem 15?
Yep.
Version three.
Version three of the Librem 15.
There you go.
I'll let you guys know what I think about it after I've spent some time with it.
It seems like a nice piece of hardware, though.
The build quality actually seems really good.
And it looks nice.
I would not be ashamed whatsoever to have this in a coffee shop, especially with a few
Linux stickers on there.
I wonder if, I rubbed my grubby hands on it for a while, if my hand oils will smooth up
that trackpad.
Do the hardware kill switches look better than the first revision?
Yeah, way better.
Because in the first revision, they were just holes in the side of the laptop with black
toggle switches.
And now you don't even notice them, do you, at first?
Now they're, I wonder if I could, can I pull up a picture?
It feels to me a lot like a very black MacBook.
Now the kill switches are underneath the monitor somewhere.
It's hard to explain where they're at, but they're above the F keys, below the monitor.
There's like a little bit of flex by the hinge on the bottom, but otherwise it's very sturdy.
So there you go.
The new Librem 15 in-house.
How about that?
August 31st, says Wimpy.
So that is, the rumors are true, Wimpy.
Where'd he go?
There you are, Wimpy.
Sorry.
That was my bad.
Say again.
Yes, they are.
It's August the 31st is the release date for beta, 17.10 beta 1 for the participating flavors.
And I'm doing the corralling of the various flavors to do the release management for that
this time round.
And if you go and grab a daily image for any of your favorite flavors today, is a good
chance that that's probably what will get shipped on Thursday.
So at this point is mostly what we're seeing, what we're going to get, like the look of
it and the major software and all that.
Like pretty much now we're there.
Yeah.
So obviously proper Ubuntu doesn't participate in beta 1.
You'll see that for the first time in beta 2 a month from now.
Okay.
But all of the flavors are participating in beta 1, which is out Thursday.
Right.
Okay.
So including-
And the images get made-
Including that abuji mate that I've heard of before, I would assume.
Yes.
That's looking very tasty for this release.
Maybe I should put that on the early room.
Yeah.
I think you should.
You totally should.
I'll turn on Compass.
I'll get my mutiny set up going.
That's exactly right.
I do like Kaja.
And I do like that software boutique.
So you do get in there.
And now that there's the super key, I mean, what's not to love?
That is true.
That is very true.
You probably live in there for quite some time.
And the hud all up in your face and everything.
Which is now locally integrated, by the way.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Nice.
Wow.
This thing is...
This 1710 release, not just for Ubuntu proper, but for some of these flavors, too, is really
something.
What the hell happened?
Yeah.
I think everyone's working really hard on their 1710 releases.
It seems like in the last couple releases, enough things have been changed or stabilized
in the below parts of the distro that there's really time now or effort that can be spent
on making all these things we've all been excited for.
It's good timing for me since I'm distro hopping right now.
So the machine...
You know, what's great is I don't really have a horse in this race.
So the machine that I'm recording this show on is running Arch.
The machine I'm sitting in front of, like showing webpages and stuff, is running Solus.
And the machine the mumble room is on is on Ubuntu LTS.
So I'm pretty much like I'm sitting pretty and whichever way this thing goes, I'm pretty
much happy.
I'm just sitting back and enjoying it and just trying out different distros at this
point.
It's kind of a nice...
Have you heard of the Church of Neon?
You know?
Yeah.
Don't worry, buddy.
I got your back.
You know, it's funny is I do still have...
I still have a system at home running Plasma.
And it's my one like...
It's still my one Plasma system.
And I sit down at it and I fired up and like, you know, this is so smooth and so nice.
I really enjoyed it.
So, yeah.
It's still...
You're just a sucker for Kwin.
It's still a contender.
All right, Wes.
Well, you know what we got to do?
We got to get out of here.
Enough Linux for today.
We must go.
There is TechSnap to be had.
Mumble Room, thank you very much for being here.
I really appreciate it, guys.
I think you just want to play with the purism.
That's true.
That is true.
That is totally true.
Thank you to our Discord chat for hanging out with us at Discord.me slash Jupiter Colony.
Thank you to Beardsley.
Where should people find you, Beard?
Rec.net.
R-E-K-D.net.
You can, of course, get more of Wes on TechSnap.
Anywhere else you want to send folks?
At Wes Payne on Twitter.
Boom.
Check out YouTube.com slash Chris Fisher.
I just posted a brand new vlog today where I go inside a very creepy barn.
Thanks for joining us.
I'll see you back here next Tuesday.
All right.
We did a podcast.
Thank you, Mumble Room.
Thank you, IRC.
Yeah.
That was some good mumbling today.
Thank you, Discord.
So we got to pick our title.
And I thought maybe should we do something around the Librem, the purism, like the hope
of the free Linux phone?
Something like that?
What do you guys think?
Bueller?
Librem free phone.
Phone's home.
What about Librem 5, a new hope?
The new hope thing's played, man.
It's played.
I don't know.
Okay.
How about Librem 5, the Phantom Menace?
What do you think?
Anybody?
Mumble Room thoughts on titles?
Mobile Linux purity.
Uh.
We could just call it Pure Linux.
No.
What about something about the free phone dream?
Should it just be the free phone dream?
Free phone nightmare continues.
Free phone?
No free phone nightmare.
The free phone nightmare is not bad either.
Librem.
The free phone nightmare.
Floss nightly.
Phoning it in.
Oh, I think we've maybe done that.
Yeah, I think that does sound familiar.
It does.
We're so punny.
It's not our fault, it's our culture.
The free phone nightmare is kind of my current leading.
I like that one.
It's pretty good.
Librem phone's home.
No, it doesn't do that, I swear.
That's deliciously ironic, I like that.