Wes, did you see this?
We were talking about this on the pre-show.
Terth in the chat room was, or he is in New York,
and he found a, I don't know if he's like
in a Nixon museum or something.
And he found these Nixon cigarettes.
And if you look at that logo on those Nixon cigarettes.
That sure looked like the Windows logo, doesn't it?
Wow.
Nixon Campaign 72 cigarettes.
These were campaign advertising material.
And they have, that is straight up
the Windows 10 Windows logo on there.
One of the designers at Microsoft
just has that sitting on a shelf in their office.
And you know, you're daydreaming,
trying to think up the next thing.
It's right there.
All that money, and they ripped off a Nixon cigarette.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 169
for November 1st, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that at least 50% of it proudly uses Nano.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
I won't out you, Wes.
Please don't.
I got a lot of slack this week.
I did, I recorded a video in the Linux Action Show
where I was using, God forbid, Nano.
Ooh.
I know.
That's just a recipe for flame war, man.
Don't worry, I'm gonna make up for it this week
with an hour.
Are you gonna show us your VI skills?
Yeah, I got true VIM skills, yeah.
I'm all about the color coding.
You know, that's not how I'm gonna make it up for you.
I'm gonna make it up for you with a great show.
We have what you would probably classify
as an oversized show.
Now, we don't have the markers, so we may get a ticket,
but it is a huge update section.
We're gonna get into some big developments this week
that I'm a little fired up about.
Then later on, as we move down into the show,
we're gonna pick up the speed as we get busting along,
and we're gonna find some alternative devices
to the Roku that run Linux
that look like they may be coming very soon,
and then we're gonna wrap it all up towards the end
with some quotes from Mr. Greg KH.
Our favorite.
During a recent fireside chat
about kernel development happening over email
and why they still use email,
the guy says, like,
are you guys just a bunch of gray beards?
Like, why aren't you using Slack?
As if, like that's, or whatever.
Like GitHub.
Yeah, yeah.
So they talk about why they still use email
for core Linux kernel development.
He talks about licensing in a way
that's actually interesting,
and some other interesting tidbits
about a bunch of ex-Microsoft employees
now working full-time on the Linux kernel.
All kinds of stuff.
So we'll get into all of those quotes
from his fireside chat once we get through all our updates.
So yeah, we got like a lot of heavy stuff up front,
and then we're gonna really pick up the speed as we go on.
And the people that are gonna help us do that
is our virtual log, time appropriate greetings, mumbaroom.
Pip, pip.
Hello.
Time appropriate greetings.
Hey, what's your podcast?
Oh.
Hello.
I'm not sure what that was there.
I don't know what that was exactly.
Who was that?
Hmm, I don't know, probably a mole.
Let's start with some really nice, like, kind of happy news.
Because sometimes we start with like breaking news
with everything is ruined.
Yes, right.
I thought it would be fun to talk about Mr. Robot.
Six ways Mr. Robot is putting Linux in the public eye.
And this is kind of legit.
I mean, really early on,
they had the gnome KDE clip.
Do you remember that on Mr. Robot?
So I see a running gnome.
You know, I'm actually on KDE myself.
I know this desktop environment is supposed to be better,
but you know what they say.
Old habits, they die hard.
Look at that.
That face is perfect.
I'm like, what the?
I'm an executive.
I mean, why am I even running Linux?
I love that.
And that was when we actually watched the show.
And they also, recently they showed a screenshot
of Kali Linux.
Hey, look at that.
Which is totally legit.
Bonafide.
And of course, often they'll show shots
of the command line and real shell commands,
which is pretty great.
So I don't know if you are,
now don't know spoilers,
but have you ever watching like TV
when you see like a Linux thing
and it just like totally like, oh my gosh.
Like if you're watching Mr. Robot,
you're getting that all the time probably,
but every now and then you're watching random television.
It adds that like one layer of depth, you know,
it's like, I mean, you're already kind of,
you know, you're going with the show,
you're buying into their storyline,
but when you're like,
it's like fake terminal commands
and you're like,
you could have just filmed a real terminal.
It would have worked fine.
You don't need to like make up this thing
that just like kind of takes me out of the moment
from the show.
So I appreciate the depth that they go to.
Yeah, yeah.
I was watching a news clip on virtual reality
and you know how the news is about covering virtual reality.
And so they're in a room where the guy's got the headset on
and they're developing new technologies
and it's a typical shot of this guy
making a clown out of himself.
And the news camera pans over
to where the computers are at
and you know, it's VR.
So I'm thinking this is going to be a Windows box.
And no kidding, it was an Ubuntu Unity desktop.
You see that, you see that dock right on the left?
There you go.
Classic dock with that GTK2 looking bar
that hasn't been updated since 1984.
It looks, I mean, it's, you can't misplace it.
It's Unity and it's all its glory and everything else.
That's awesome.
And I was like, wait, wait, wait a minute.
Hold on.
How come they get VR on Linux
and I don't get VR on Linux?
How do we get that?
How did that happen?
I was watching that and I'm like, hold on now.
How does the CBS move?
They didn't have show notes
telling you how to set that up.
That's the problem.
Yeah, CBS needed to put a link in the show notes for sure.
And so I guess there's some VRs working under Linux
because these researchers were using it.
And so that was one of my most recent,
sitting there reviewing clips
and I'm looking at this and going, what the?
Where did this come from?
Okay, so I also wanted to do another little positive story
that I just wanted to throw out there.
This is your official Linux Unplugged reminder.
It's November.
God damn it.
And there's holidays coming up.
No.
And if you take some pictures and something goes wrong,
I want you to remember that in 169,
Chris and Wes hooked you up
with how to recover those pictures.
This is a great post.
Search and rescue SD card recovery.
He has a Canon EOS 300D.
You know, it's an old SLR camera.
And his SD card file system corrupted or something on him.
He lost all his pictures when he went to Mo's Fest,
the Mozilla Festival a couple of weeks back.
Yeah, and so he wanted to do
the entire restoration under Linux.
And so he goes through the different tools he used
to restore his SD card contents
and recover his photos under Linux
and then documents it all right there
with a nice epic wind screenshot
of the Nautilus file browser full of his restored photos.
And I don't really, we don't need to bust through this
because this is really only applicable
to people that are in this situation.
But it is in the show notes.
It's nice to have because you don't want to be worrying
about where to go find the tutorial
and if it's up to date and all that
when you're desperately trying to recover your files.
Yeah, and I also just wanted to kind of spotlight
really good, you know, this kind of blogging is just great.
It's great when you see this kind of stuff come along.
So I just wanted to kind of give it a little attention
as it were.
There is a story that's been percolating around
for about two weeks now
and it doesn't seem to be dying off.
So I've decided we'd talk about it
because at first my reaction was like, this is not a big...
Right, what is it, is it anything?
But you know, it's getting,
it continues to get posted on Hacker News.
It continues to get written about.
And so I thought I'd link to the OMG coverage here.
Linux market share has remained above 2%
on the desktop for the third month in a row.
This is according to NetMarketshare
and it's a data analytics company.
I'll tell you where they source their data from in a moment.
But it looks like this has been holding steady since July
and it looks like it's continuing to climb.
In fact, it's gone up to 2.33% since then.
You know, here's the thing, guys.
NetMarketshare bases its data on the number of visitors
to 40,000 websites.
It's not like it's an insignificant sample size,
but compared to the overall Linux desktop market,
there's no way it's representative.
But it's an interesting data point.
You can also look at Wikimedia, which shows 1.2%
if you include Ubuntu, Red Hat, and SUSE,
but doesn't look at other distros.
But, you know, the reality is we'll never have an idea.
We'll never have an idea, but there are-
Even just talking about that's making me realize,
you know, just think about how would you do that?
And it would be hard.
It's a hard thing to get a good number on.
You know what I have kind of relied on
is aggregating different data sources over the years.
So I look at things like these types of reports
from NetMarket, but I also look at the Wikimedia stuff
and I look at Steam and I look at the W3 schools
and kind of aggregate them all together.
And I will say this, in aggregate, there is an uptick.
There does seem to be a pretty consistent uptick
in aggregate.
It's nothing major, but then of course,
how you measure these things is pretty difficult.
Yeah, that's definitely true.
The graph is sure not that exciting though.
No, no, it's not that exciting.
You know what is exciting?
Freaking 1.9.22 of wine.
First of all, it lets you play Max Payne 2,
which made me think of you.
But coming just two weeks after the previous wine,
yes, I'm actually gonna report on a version of wine.
Doesn't happen often.
It doesn't.
They've added some nice support for Direct2D.
They've fixed 25 bugs and they've added improvement
to multiple Windows games.
But the one thing that really matters, Wes,
the thing that matters the most,
is they have resurrected support for a game
from November of 1996.
It's almost perfect.
The anniversary is right here.
It's very important to me.
It was not a good game at all.
It shouldn't have anybody working on it,
but they have done it and it's called Star Trek Horde.
Hold on, buddy.
We need you conscious.
Don't go to one of your Payne trances.
Ah!
Get off!
Furlong!
Furlong, get out of here!
I'm sorry.
You are in a bajani Payne trance.
Your friend Furlong wasn't able to stop it.
The Borg don't seem to notice, though.
They're assimilating you at this very moment.
At least this time, you won't feel it.
Oh, it looks like you're waking up.
So this is like a quick time events driven game, but.
Oh, I see.
Interesting.
There is a star, so they were filming it
using all the existing Star Trek sets
and Star Trek sound effects and the Star Trek directing.
It's our friend John de Lancie.
Yeah, but there is actually one thing
of rather interest canon addition
that they bring to the Star Trek canon in this game.
So if you're a Star Trek fan,
it's worth playing just for that.
So it's kind of cool that it's a game
that if it passed you by and you kind of want to,
it's an interactive Star Trek episode.
If you've ever seen Minecraft Story Mode
or anything like that,
it's basically that with,
and it was the pinnacle of quick time events games,
which is not saying much.
That's great.
It starts like a legitimate game of,
or it starts like a legitimate television show of Star Trek.
Like here, this is gonna get us pulled down, but.
USS Canali to USS Cheyenne.
We are under attack by Borg forces.
Repeat, Borg forces, re-intercept the two Borg vessels.
Can you just mix this with your VR headset?
I'd be entertained for hours.
Actually, that could be pretty good, right?
Especially if you could move around the entire space.
I have the whole thing,
if you would just want to watch it and not play it.
But it's a first person perspective game
where you walk around the halls of the ship,
interact with officers.
It even has credits and all of the music
just like a Star Trek episode.
It looks like a Star Trek episode
from first person perspective.
This is great.
So it's kind of neat.
Oh, relate, geez.
Yeah, it's kind of neat though
because you can pick this game up for really cheap
or you can find it online
and now you'll be able to run it under Linux.
It's wild that people are working on that and now it works.
Ridiculous maybe, you might add, pointless.
But also, it's what I love about Wine and Linux is
there is something incredibly nostalgic
about taking some of my favorite old games,
even like ones that I bought on GOG a while ago
that I can now play under Wine
and not have to hassle with a Windows crappy VM
or any of that junk.
Any of that.
It's amazing that Linux can do more.
You wonder at some point,
like some of these older games of Wine
will start being able to be a better place
to run them than modern Windows.
Yeah, maybe they'll do like a hard break one day
on the Windows platform.
They're like, okay, this technical debt
has gotten so crazy,
we're gonna move to the next version of Windows.
Well, they'll probably retain the Linux environment
and they'll use Wine.
Wine in the Linux subsystems around old Windows games.
Okay, great, we've called it here.
Yeah, there's our prediction on the unplugged program.
Yikes, but I do think it's really cool
that they added that stuff.
Hey, before we go any further,
let's talk about the opposite of that complicated mess.
Let's talk about something that makes mobile simple
and that's Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com,
where they're on a mission to make mobile make sense.
And here's why.
There's no contract, no other termination fee,
and you only pay for what you use.
Six dollars for each line.
You got one phone, you got three phones,
it's six dollars for each one of them.
It's nice, simple, straightforward,
GSM and CDMA networks that you get to choose from.
And if you're in business,
this is something you should really consider,
especially if you're kind of like a smaller business.
But even anybody that has like,
for me, like with three or four devices,
it's just fantastic.
But even when you go above 10 devices,
the savings is nuts because it's just six dollars
and then your staff's usage.
And if you got Wi-Fi at your office
and they got Wi-Fi at home,
that's ridiculous what you can get away with.
And it's perfect for those things where like,
well, maybe you need like just a backup
internet connection for your office,
but you're gonna use it what, one time a year?
Yeah, yeah.
It's so nice because if you go over
to the Ting Buy page or the Shop page,
you can just get a little SIM card
and you can put it in a MyFi you get off eBay
or you can get one of the MyFis directly from them,
keep that in your drawer,
and the day your Comcast connection goes out,
you fire this up.
Literally, I've done that twice here at JB.
One time.
Six dollars a month for that kind of like,
you know, just knowing it'll work.
One time, this story is a couple years old now,
but it's such a classic and it's so perfect.
It's just a perfect example is Alan Jude
flew out here to record TechSnap in person.
How often does that happen?
You know, a couple times ever.
And he shows up and Comcast is down.
And what are we gonna not record?
He's here for the day.
What are we gonna not do a show?
And I gotta show visuals,
I gotta look up stuff for the stories,
he's gotta read sites.
So we set up Ting, we set up a Wi-Fi hotspot on my Nexus,
and just connected our laptops to that.
Our laptops had connection, we recorded two shows
over the Ting connection that day.
Ting saved it and it was just,
that's just so nice, like tethering and stuff,
or hotspot, it's just a check box.
It's not a big deal.
Also, check out the Ting blog.
They went and pulled their Redditors
and they shared seven different hacks
to help save money on mobile.
That's pretty cool.
They also are pushing now the Moto G4 Play,
a pretty nice mid-sized device at a great price, $150.
No contract, no determination fee.
And if you go to linux.ting.com,
you get $25 off your device or $25 in service credit.
linux.ting.com, and a big thank you to Ting
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
All right, before we get into something really heavy,
I do have something really fun
that I just wanted to give a shout out to.
Users over on linux underscore gaming
organized together to bribe Aspire
into porting Civ 6 to Linux.
And it was looking like it was gonna be maybe murky.
They were evaluating the cost, you know.
There's a Mac version they wanna make as well,
and they were nice and public in commenting in thread
saying, you know, we're not really sure
we're in the research stage.
The bottom line is we need to prove to ourselves,
our partners, and to our partners that a Linux version
can perform to our standards, you know, monetarily.
Right, right.
And so the Linux underscore gaming guys and gals
got together and sent them a box of Tiff's Treats,
which is a local Austin cookie company,
and sent them boxes after boxes of cookies.
In fact, they have another one scheduled
to be delivered on Thursday this week.
And Aspire Media, or Aspire, took notice.
And they said, they tweeted out,
this just came in the mail this morning.
Thank you, you lovely Linux people.
Your guilt trip has been accepted.
Hashtag nom, nom, nom.
Then another tweet comes out, says the Linux team
would like to offer their thanks
as with the majority of the companies,
and thanks to Tiffany's Treats.
And then they posted some more pictures
of people passing out from cookie overdoses.
That's a great strategy.
I mean, at some point, everyone in the company
is gonna have stopped by, they're gonna have enough cookies.
Everyone's gonna have some.
Everyone asked where it came from.
Now everyone's talking about Linux.
Yeah.
And it's also got some interesting details
that Blair on the Linux Gaming subreddit shared.
Blair works at Aspire Media.
He says, their team fluctuates.
The Linux, they have asked,
how many people are on the Linux team?
So the team fluctuates.
Because Mac and Linux teams are shared resources.
I think this is actually a super common setup.
I bet so, yeah.
So it can be as little as 25 or the full company of 70.
Actually, that's not true.
We have a couple of guys dedicated to Android
and an internal IP team working on some secret stuff.
So it's more like 60.
Here's what I want to underscore.
The topic we're about to get into.
We're gonna talk about stuff from a tools perspective
and what end users need perspective.
But I want you to keep in the back of your mind also
the value judgment that companies have to make
when they watch user bases.
Now we just talked about the Linux user base growing.
It's nothing major.
We talked about growth there.
I want to transition from this
and talk about something that I also think
is gonna contribute to more Linux users
which may change companies like Aspire Media's calculus.
It is the elephant in the room
and I know this is a Linux podcast,
but there is definitely a Linux angle on this.
And it's what everybody on the internet
is freaking out about this week.
And that is the new MacBooks.
The new MacBook Pros with the touch bar.
Everybody is freaking out about this.
And I guess to highlight,
I won't repeat the things that I've said
in Coda Radio this week,
but I think it is probably worth touching on
the couple of major limitations of the new MacBook.
16 gigs of RAM is gonna be a maximum.
Is an unbelievable limitation.
I mean it's just a ridiculous limitation.
The cost premium too is astronomical on these new MacBooks.
I understand.
It's not like it's got cheaper.
Yeah, this is, I feel like this is gonna be a prime time
to switch a lot of people to Linux.
And here's why.
System76 has been tweeting a bit about this.
They say due to high website traffic after Apple's events
they've had to add more infrastructure.
Emma, the person that takes a lot of the sales calls
at System76 tweeted out that she's getting
more Apple switcher calls than she's ever gotten.
Wow.
Coming into System76 right now.
I wanna kinda, and also a longtime Apple blogger,
John Gruber over at daringfireball.com
took some shots at System76 as a result of this.
So I wanna talk about all of this.
But does anybody in the Mumba Room wanna open up
with their reaction to the new MacBook?
It's all cocky.
I mean when I say, why though?
I mean let's be critical, but let's do it
in like an informed way.
Cause I mean we can't just hate it because it's Apple.
Right.
Let's be realistic here.
Pretend Dell made it.
Yeah, pretend Dell made this or something.
I mean this seems like to me,
but actually you can't do that.
See the reason why you can't do that
is Apple is the only company that makes computers
that run Mac OS.
True.
And so if you require an application
on the Mac OS platform.
That's where you're at.
You are forced to buy Apple's products.
And so that, I think in this context,
it's way more important that Apple
gets these product releases right.
It's not as easy to forgive a mistake on Apple's case
like it is on Dell.
By the way, do any of us give a shit
that the XPS 13 has a max of 16 gigs of RAM?
Did you know that?
No, we don't.
Because it's not Apple.
Because it's Dell.
It's Dell.
The Dell XPS 13 that we've all lovingly talked about,
the one I own, the one you own,
has a max of 16 gigs of RAM right now.
But it doesn't matter because it's one
of a hundred different products that Dell sells
and it's one of a million different products
I can run Linux on.
Exactly.
So it doesn't matter.
But when Apple makes this mistake,
when they ship a pro product that only supports
16 gigs of RAM, there is going to be a class
of high-end users that are gonna look at that
and say, that is a ridiculous limitation
and I'm moving to another platform
and it sure as hell is not gonna be Windows.
And it's not just me saying that.
This is, there is threat.
I thought about doing like just a roundup
of all the different hacker news posts
and Reddit posts and blog posts
and Medium posts about this.
There is hundreds of them right now.
And you know what?
It is, if you do word searches in the comments sections
and in these posts, they're talking about
switching to Linux.
It's wild.
But it makes sense, I think.
It's interesting.
It's because Apple is following the path
of we want thin, light, and high battery life.
And so they can't have two so dims
to support 32 gigs of RAM.
And they're not gonna put a GPU in there
if they don't have to, or at least a beefy GPU.
Because that would take up too much room
and reduce battery life and it would reduce thinness.
Yeah, it appears, so it appears the true reason
behind the lack of 32 gigs of RAM or DDR4 is Intel.
Skylake doesn't support LPD DDR4,
which LP stands for low power.
And Kaby Lake is set to include support
but only for U category of chips.
So again, no LPD DDR4 until 2018 in mobile.
Yep.
Surface Book only goes up to 16 gigabytes too.
But if they had two so dim slots,
so if they sacrifice some space
and some more board real estate,
they could actually do 32 gigs.
Which is what other people are doing with DDR4.
They're doing two so dims that are 16 gigs each.
Now the argument is those types of boards
get way worse battery life.
They do.
And they sacrifice room that you could put batteries in.
And I think a lot of Apple professionals
would sacrifice battery life
to have a machine that is capable.
Oh absolutely, I think Apple didn't make the compromise
of having a really high-end workstation replacement machine
and they only went with like a lighter, smaller,
better battery life type machine.
Right, when you're making the play
to the everyman Apple product,
you miss the people in all the businesses
who they get their managers to get them the Mac
and then it sits on their desk plugged into nice monitors
and they want it for the environment that they're used to
and for the Unix command line.
But yeah, if you look at a competing product
like the Surface Book Pro, or sorry, the Surface Book,
and you look at say the X1 Carbon
and you look at the XPS 13,
those also gimp and sacrifice those same features
that you want on a workstation.
Again though, I say the scale of aggression there
or egregion there is much lower.
And I'll get into my personal take on it,
but I wanna give Mohsen Rath a chance to jump in
because he thinks we're just hating on the leader.
So Mohsen Rath, you go and I wanna get your perspective
on it real quick.
Okay, you guys were talking about this a few days ago
on one of the other shows, if I'm not mistaken.
And my understanding with when I'm hearing
all the different arguments
and what I'm seeing in the chat room,
a lot of it tends to be, well, Apple should do this,
Apple should do this,
but you gotta sit there and think to yourself,
Apple's gonna think of the bottom line.
So if they don't think that there's gonna be people
that are going to want to pay for it
based off of the scale that they're going to price it at,
and we were discussing this in the chat room the other day,
well, not in the chat room,
gone to the IRC the other day,
I didn't actually try to do the math,
but you guys have complained about how much it costs
for stuff for Apple before.
The people at RIP Tech Syndicate
complained about this stuff for Apple before
in terms of the prices and the pricing.
Do the math yourself, seriously.
Spend some time on the show right now.
Go to the website, do the scale, right?
Eight to 16 or eight to 12 or however you want to do it.
Do the arithmetic sequence,
see how much it would be for the 32.
Anything else about sizing, battery life at all,
take a look at where the actual price point
according to their would be based off of everything else.
And then you sit there and ask yourself,
who's going to pay for that?
If you can't see yourself going to pay for that,
then how are you going to see
anyone else going to pay for that?
I think the difference-
If Apple figured that someone would pay for it,
they would do it.
I think the difference here is that
there is a significant amount that,
that would matter a lot to me in my personal life,
but for the business world,
I'm not gonna be paying for it.
My company's gonna pay for it,
and they don't care if it's two grand
or three grand for the most part.
Yeah, I really don't think it's worth,
I mean, it's worth mentioning the base price
in terms of value to the consumer,
but anybody that's gonna use these tools to make money
is gonna think about the price for about two days,
and then when they get to work and start making revenue
based on their work output from this machine,
they're not gonna care so much that it costs them $3,000
and it's a tax write-off.
So the price is worth discussing,
but it's absolutely not one of the primary issues.
I think hands down,
the primary professional issue here is
no expandability internally,
and these machines only get updated every thousand days,
and the 16 gigabyte RAM limitation
for anybody that's working in 1080p plus video is atrocious.
It is, after effects,
I don't know, unless you've used these tools,
you have to understand that they work
by caching things in RAM.
That's how they are usable,
and you can't work at these resolutions
unless you can cache some of this data in RAM,
and if you don't have RAM, you can't use the machine.
There's actually, the part about the pricing thing,
you gotta point out that Apple has always overcharged
for inferior products,
like them having a higher price.
I don't know if that's totally fair.
I think they start with a base configuration
that's more competitive,
and they don't even bother with a lower end machine,
and then they gouge you on things like RAM and storage a bit.
Yeah.
But I wanna, okay.
You can get every single,
even the MacBook Air when it was out,
you could get his Inbook for the same amount of hardware
for like 300, $400 cheaper.
Yes, but tell me,
how great is ASUS support compared to Apple support?
There's a lot of things.
I mean, there's, yeah.
Apple support is not that good.
Apple support is not that good,
but you can take it into a store,
and they can usually fix your issues there.
ASUS will take at least two months to get back to you.
But again, I don't really wanna get into the,
I don't really wanna get into the price.
I don't wanna get into the price discussion,
because if I'm gonna get a Lenovo laptop or a Dell laptop
that's actually worth me using,
it's also gonna be expensive.
See, I think that's,
I think the price thing is a bit of a misnomer
in this conversation,
because I think you can remove it from the conversation,
and we still have a perfectly viable argument here.
And Popey, I wanted to give you a chance to jump in.
So one of the questions you asked was,
why is it that we hold Apple to a standard
where we complain that they only have 16 gig yet?
All these other manufacturers like Dell
with their XPS 13 and Lenovo with their X1,
they don't get the same kind of flag.
Yeah, they have the similar specs.
And the simple reason is Apple ask for it.
They put themselves up on a pedestal
and do a gigantic PR exercise
to get the whole world watching a live stream
while they announce their products.
And if that doesn't get people critiquing their products,
then I don't know what does.
Dell and Lenovo don't do that.
And so they put out their products,
people buy them, and people move on.
They don't scrutinize the minutiae of those products
anywhere near as much as they do for Apple devices,
because Apple invite that.
So let me tell you about why this matters to me,
because I've spent the last three weeks
trying to exclusively edit segments
for the Linux Action Show in Cadian Live.
And, ooh, will you check that?
I will, yeah.
That might be UPS, thanks, Wes.
The UPS just got here.
And I have mad respect for the work that project is doing,
and I am really happy with their trajectory
on where they wanna go with it.
But it is not, I thought to myself,
it's usable for me when I wanna produce
one 10-minute segment a week.
If I wanted to produce daily video,
or I wanted to move our entire workflow
over to Cadian Live, I still don't think it's,
I think it's still, I think it could be six years out
from where they're even getting close to Final Cut 10.
And the issue is that in the three years
that Apple dropped the Final Cut 10 bomb on the world,
they've progressively made it better and better and better.
And now it's actually a competitive product
that is faster in some regards
than any other editor in the market.
It uses the GPU in a way that most editors
don't even get close, and it is,
the UI is functional, and it's one of these applications
where if you have very little experience,
you can begin to use it,
and then as you grow as a professional,
or as you grow as an editor,
you can learn more ways to take advantage
of this application.
And there is a company, hold on one sec,
there is a company behind it
that is working with the market.
They're working with companies like Canon.
They're working with companies like Blackmagic.
They're creating hard, they're working with partnerships
where they create hardware that works with the product.
And that is something that simply Cadian Live,
or OpenShot, or Shotcut, or any of them,
simply don't have the resource to do.
And last, final point, and this is the really bad one,
is there is a giant pool of talent out there
that knows how to use Final Cut,
and is creating Final Cut professional templates
that look broadcast good, that you can buy for 25, 30 bucks,
and then modify for your own use.
And there's nothing like that for the open source projects
at any scale, at any quality.
And so the fundamental issue is,
and you guys can write it off as Crazy Chris
and his podcast, but the reality is
there is a ginormous market of millions of professionals
and businesses now that produce video content
for this tiny website you may have heard of
called YouTube and many others,
and none of them are doing it under Linux
because these tools are not good enough.
And so people are still gonna be buying Macs.
And this Mac is less Linux friendly
than any Mac Apple has ever shipped.
So it is, the platform is worse,
the people that use these tools are getting locked
into a less and less appealing platform,
and the hardware they are shipping
becomes less and less capable of running Linux.
I just wanted to ask, if you really think Apple's the leader
and everybody else is trying to follow,
or do you think it's the other way around somehow?
I mean, I don't know.
I think they probably just have 15, 20 years experience
making editing software, and they have 15, 20 years
of business relationships to make it a viable editor
for the companies to support.
I think they're kind of experimenting
for the future though.
Go ahead William, what was that?
Yeah, so I think with the whole touchpad thing,
I think eventually what they're going to do
is turn the whole keyboard into just a big LCD panel,
and this is the first step of doing that,
and I think it's kind of an interesting change.
They're experimenting it with the keys
that are less important to you,
so it's not your normal QWERTY alphabet keys,
it's just the F keys which you only use every now and then,
and eventually they're going to expand that downward
into being the whole body.
Maybe.
Maybe?
Okay, Popeye, I wanted to give you a chance to jump in,
and then I'll go to Mohsen Rath.
And then Rath.
All right, that's cool.
Okay, Mohsen Rath, go ahead.
Okay, we had this discussion already,
I think it was like my first or second time
I was graciously allowed to talk on your show there,
about why with your open source argument,
why it is that there's nothing
for the open source argument.
We already had this discussion.
Remember that wishlist of yours?
One of those things is, where all those people go
that crump out, that fail out?
Why is it that they don't just link up,
legion up to one of those open source projects
that is hitting it, that is working out on the same thing?
Where does all that money not go to?
Oh yes, open source.
Where does that money go to?
The people that already are making something.
So remember you were talking about the 15 to 20 years of?
They also have at least, at least 15 to 20 years
of cash in hand, cash invested, cash coming in.
Notice that word that keeps on showing up, cash.
And I say that on purpose because
all those open source projects,
they're going off of donations.
They're going off of people being generous.
They're going off of people doing it for the love of it.
Or some of them are doing it for the hate of it
because they just hate the other products so much.
They're just like, I'm gonna make something
to compare against it.
I'm gonna make something to compete against it.
And until those people,
all those legions of people who are doing
all that hard work, get the same kind of money,
get the same kind of backing,
get the same kind of backup.
And when I'm talking about backup,
I'm talking about those legions upon legions
upon legions of people.
People like, I'm gonna call him out here
because he's awesome, Tilnesh here, who's brilliant.
And he's talked about some of the stuff that he's done.
People like him, people like Rekai, people like yourself,
people like Noah, people like Wes there.
At the same thing, people like Alan
and people like the other Chris.
Without legions of people like them,
not just two, not just five,
we're talking hundreds of people like that
who also have hundreds of thousands of dollars
following them to show up to these projects,
they are not going to be at the same level.
It's not like a sport where you could sit there
and train by yourself and learn the stuff by yourself,
like basketball or football or hockey
or something like that.
Most of those things, you can get yourself
to the state where you need to be
and then it's just a matter of getting the equipment.
It's not like that.
So you gotta remember all the efforts
that all these people are doing,
of course they're gonna be playing catch up.
They're always gonna be playing catch up
until someone gives them the leader position
by literally dumping a ton of people
and a ton of money and a ton of influence
and a ton of equipment in their lap
along with a ton of testers.
I do feel like for the basic editing timeline
and stuff like that,
KDN Live is sitting in a pretty good spot
and they wanna continue focusing on polish.
And so on that note, Rot,
and I wanted to give you the sort of the final word
on the KDN point.
Yeah, I started doing some video tutorials
and stuff for YouTube
and I decided to exclusively use only Linux tools
and I'm using KDN Live for all the editing and everything.
And I disagree that it's not usable,
but I totally agree.
Oh, it's usable, yeah.
I totally agree with your point about how it's very limited
and it's so much so that I experienced a couple crashes
just by trying to do an effect
that I eventually gave up and just,
I created animations in CSS on the web browser.
Yeah, I've done a couple of work around.
So if you watch this most recent segment
on the Linux Action Show
where I go over to Angela's house
and set up Open Media Vault,
that was edited under KDN Live.
Oh, cool, wow.
Yeah, so I mean, I've been using it to success,
but I'm experimenting with ideas for next year
where the output volume needs to go up a lot more.
And so that's where I'm worried about these tools
not being up to that task.
And I am sort of in a position of somewhat privilege
right now thanks to you, Wes,
where you set up Arch Linux on my MacBook.
Oh, right, yeah.
And so if push-pull comes to shove,
I can boot in, I got an older version of macOS on there.
I wonder what happens if I update that to Sierra.
I'm not really compelled to do so,
but I have no idea what would happen.
You think it'd still boot into Arch?
I mean, I imagine it would change the UEFI variable back
so that it would boot into macOS, but you could change that.
And I could boot into macOS, do my final cut thing,
and then boot back into Arch
for like everything I actually wanna do.
And so I don't have to have a solution today,
and I can continue to try to use KDE Live,
but on the same hardware,
because I'm just dual booting,
there is a 20x speed improvement under Final Cut
than there is under KDE Live.
And it's just where it is right now.
I do wanna make one more point.
Technically, if you look at the track record
of development for KDE Live,
they were not working on KDE Live for like two
or three years.
They would like do a little bug phase here and there.
For the past six, seven months or so,
they have made incredible strides.
Like they have fixed most of the crashing bugs
on most issues,
and the stability is like astronomically better
than what it used to be.
So I think by far, KDE Live is the best free editor
on any platform.
Yeah, I would say it's better
than even Lightworks and everything.
Yeah, I agree.
And I've been really impressed with how well it's done.
That's kind of why I wanted to give it
some try the last few weeks.
But one last thing before we move off of the new MacBooks,
just as you might expect,
there is already a fart app for the new Touch Bar.
It's called Touch Fart,
and it's right there.
You run it.
Three different fart sounds.
Yep, yep.
And the two emoji and one word that say fart.
So it works with Touch Fart macOS app
to allow a selection of playbacks
and predefined fart sounds.
Right there on the Touch Bar.
Told you it's useful, Wes.
Who needs an escape button?
Yeah, right?
Just keep using that on hearts.
All you need is a fart bar and a headphone jack.
You're good.
Yeah, I wonder, does it,
huh, too bad they don't have any preview.
Sorry, guys, I can't preview for you.
I think that fart bar will pair well
with the Cloud to Butt extension.
Ha ha ha ha!
Yes, Wes.
Well said, well said.
Speaking of the cloud,
let's talk about DigitalOcean.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go build your own cloud over at DigitalOcean.com
and use our promo code.
Did you know we have a promo code, Wes?
It's D-O-Unplugged.
Do you know that?
D-O-Unplugged.
It's new, it's brand new.
Brand new promo code, D-O, not really.
Be the first to use it.
Yeah.
D-O-Unplugged, one word, lowercase.
I'll give you a $10 credit over at DigitalOcean.com
and you can go spin up a droplet in seconds.
And they have data centers in New York,
San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam,
London, Toronto, Germany, India.
And you can either do a monthly plan,
like they start at like five bucks a month,
or you can do their hourly pricing.
I love their three cents an hour rig.
They have a simple, intuitive interface
and a really nice, straightforward API
that's really well supported by the community.
You can really just probably take advantage
of the code already written.
Or you could quickly bang something out
because the API's well documented.
And man, speaking of documentation,
they got tons of good documentation over at DigitalOcean.
You'll be impressed in the community section.
There's a how-to up that was posted just three hours ago
on how to configure Nextcloud on Open21604.
Wow.
Yeah, so you can go build your own cloud
over on DigitalOcean with Nextcloud.
It's such a neat, like, symbiotic relationship
between the open source community and D-O.
Yeah, yeah, and I like that they work
with the upstream projects, like the different distros
and even FreeBSD that they have on the systems.
That's really cool.
It's in D-O's interest to let you run whatever you want.
Like, that's what they're there for
and they're great at it.
You wanna go kick the tires on something
or throw it in production, go to DigitalOcean.com
and use our promo code D-O Unplugged
and a big thanks to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Okay, guys, you know I'm always looking
for something to replace the Chromecast and the Roku.
And your Amazon stick, Chris.
I do have a fire here at the studio and I hate it.
I'm sorry, fire lovers.
I don't, I got it and I hate it.
But you know what else?
I would love to eventually replace my Shield TV.
I had an upgrade, big props to Nvidia.
They ship monthly updates to this thing
so you get the monthly Android updates.
Can I use it as a phone?
I know, right?
And so I installed the latest update
and it began rebooting every three minutes.
Yikes.
And I thought I was in a bad situation.
So I had to do like a mad dash on install applications,
which turns out for some reason on Android TV,
if you go into the Android mechanism
inside the system settings to uninstall applications,
it doesn't uninstall the application.
No, you have to go through the Play Store.
So I went through the Play Store,
found each application, uninstalled them,
and then it finally stopped rebooting.
And even though I love the Shield TV,
it's the best set top box I've ever had,
it sort of made me look for something else
because for a good solid 25 minutes,
I gotta explain, it's the weekend.
It is the Pacific Northwest.
Precious relaxation time.
It was pouring down rain outside.
It was miserable.
Slash beautiful.
Yeah, at times it was like also like
right as I needed to go trick or treating.
So kids went trick or treating on Saturday
and about a half hour before they went trick or treating,
it stopped raining.
Nice.
And I was like, this is perfect.
But earlier in the morning at about like 10 a.m.,
it was miserable outside.
And I'm like, okay, let's watch a movie.
Well, watch a movie.
And dad goes to start a movie
and it starts rebooting all the time.
And there is nothing worse as a father
when you go to like, here children,
here's the media system I've set up
powered by all these fancy things that I've figured out.
And I've got this movie on demand.
Oh, what?
And it reboots.
And dad.
And then you're sitting there like,
oh, just a second, just a second, I'll fix it.
Yeah, yeah.
So that got me looking at Remix.io,
a nougat-powered all-in-one 4K device
that you hook up to your television.
You know your television, Wes,
where you have the Android Shield TV hooked up right now?
That's right.
You maybe hook this up instead.
It's something that's on Kickstarter.
It's got 3,960 backers.
17 days to go, they had a goal of $250,000.
And holy smokes, they've already blown past that.
Woo!
And they're at $484,000.
["Danger is Better"]
I hope this doesn't get us pulled down.
But you can probably guess what they're doing right now.
Danger is better.
Whatever.
I know how a TV works.
Yeah, but can your TV do this?
Clashing my clans in one click.
So what do you think of a UI on your television
that uses a mouse and keyboard?
I have mixed feelings, at least about wider applicability.
But you know, maybe you get one of those
little Logitech wireless ones with the built-in trackpad.
Or it includes its own.
Let's just say it comes with a nice wireless keyboard,
mouse set up, maybe a remote combo.
And this is a little Android box,
you set it up on your television,
and you can play, you know, you can play,
Android, a mouse works surprisingly well with Android.
It's like they intended it to have a mouse.
Would you, no?
You instantly don't like it?
You wouldn't do it?
No, I think I would.
I mean, I have a Upadubat Mate box running on a TV,
so I think I'm open to it.
Honestly, it might be my preferred way.
I think I would still like.
You know how many people email me and say,
my media center is VLC hooked up to my PC?
Right, for me it's Kodi, but same thing, yeah.
And this is by the same people
who do the Remix OS, right?
Yes, and remind me, Remix OS.
That's the Android Spin 4 x86.
Yeah, the one that we've actually, I think,
featured as a, I don't know if we've reviewed it
on this show or we featured it on last,
but we talked about it not too long ago.
I think I even have it on the USB stick still floating around.
So they got the Remix IO, which is 99 bucks,
a 4K TV box, an Android game console,
and then they have the Remix IO Plus, $130,
a performance beast to bring out the potential of your TV.
What the?
So is this running on an ARM board?
Do we know, is it x86?
How do I get the potential out of my TV?
Is that what you're asking?
Yeah, it is a ARM processor, yeah.
The RK399 with four gigs of RAM.
Okay, four gigs, that doesn't sound bad.
No, not bad, no fans either, they say,
so that's kind of nice.
I'm gonna take that.
What do you think?
Does the Mumba Room have any thoughts on this thing?
I remember that Popey talked about the license
of Remix OS when we talked about Remix OS the first time.
Oh, can you remind me?
I don't recall.
Did I?
I think you, in fact, you're giving China access
to your computer, I think.
That sounds like Popey.
Don't think that was me.
He hates the Chiners.
I remember hearing they were completely ignoring
the TPL in some cases.
Yeah, it's been claimed that they've violated
the GPL and Apache licenses, yes.
We're about to get to that topic, as a matter of fact,
in a little bit.
Oh, you guys in the Mumba Room,
you know why I'm covering this.
I've been desperate to replace the Chromecast,
and I would love to have something that is usable,
that has actual useful streaming apps like Netflix
and Hulu on it, or whatever it is, whatever,
on a device that I can hook up to my television,
and honestly, I'd like to be able to buy a couple of them.
I'd like it to be something that's a product.
Yeah, affordable enough, something that you can,
you don't have to build it yourself.
And it can run Kodi.
It has to run Kodi, is that a requirement?
Well, I think, I think so.
Because, like, is the Roku not good enough?
Just curious, because I was actually thinking
about going the Roku route.
If you want to use Plex, the Roku's good enough.
The Plex app has gotten, just in the last six months,
nine months, the Plex app has gotten pretty good
on the Roku.
But if you want to use Kodi, and I honestly feel
like Kodi is a better experience.
Do you really care what the hardware is?
No, I don't so much, as long as it's something
that is sustainable.
Are you more interested in the software
that's running on it?
I am more interested in having access to Kodi and Netflix.
The software, like Kodi and Plex and stuff?
Yeah, and Netflix, yeah.
That's really true, and I want something
that I can plug in, and God, I would just love
to not have to worry about it for three or four years.
Like, I would love something that I could run
for three or four years.
Something that, like, had the notion to support
the open source stacks that you're gonna run,
but could also interface with the proprietary stuff,
and was an appliance.
Yeah, yeah, Roku looks awesome for, you know,
the price in which you get it.
It's the kind of thing I'd like as well, yeah.
What are you doing right now?
Do you have a Roku, or do you have a device like it?
Uh, Chromecast.
No, it's all Chromecast here, but I would like something
that I could install on.
So anytime you want to watch something on the TV,
you're using your phone to cast it?
Or a computer.
Hmm, that's a lot of work.
That's how we do it here in the studio, too,
and it's just, it's a lot of work.
And it doesn't always, like, sometimes the phone
loses connection with the playback control,
and that's really frustrating.
YouTube in particular?
Yeah, which just doesn't make any sense.
Or you, like, get the volume, and then you can't,
the volume's all offset, yeah.
The other thing, too, is if you don't have an Android TV,
and you haven't experienced this,
the YouTube app on Android TV is actually really good.
Really?
It's my favorite YouTube experience.
It's way better than on the desktop.
I feel like it surfaces more interesting videos
than the desktop does, and it displays them in a way
that's easier for me to see them.
Playback is phenomenal.
You don't get comments, you can't click on, like,
when people say, like, click this link or something.
Oh, it doesn't support the annotations
or anything like that, but for just playback
and the way it buffers really intelligently,
and it auto-scales the resolution perfectly,
which, trust me, I'm working on MiFi here.
It really does a good job.
240p is your best friend.
Since I've gotten the Shield TV,
it has transformed my television watching to,
I have stopped watching traditional television.
Like, I only got to season one of Mr. Robot,
and I stopped watching.
Yeah, me too.
Because I'm watching everything on YouTube now.
It's really kind of fun, because I'm getting
what feels like much more real, genuine content.
Yeah, exactly, and it has, thankfully,
pretty good Linux support and interface, too.
Yeah, and so we'll see, we'll see.
I'm on a mission to eventually,
I would like that set-top box that I could get
for family members for Christmas,
or I could get for myself.
The Shield TV is very expensive,
and it feels like it's not Nvidia's even top three priority,
so like, when's my long term?
Am I gonna get three years out of this?
Right, they could drop that, shift, whatever, anytime.
It is a good demonstration of their chipset platform,
so from that perspective, it's particularly fun,
because there are some great games on there.
It has sort of a console-like experience.
It's a tuned, complete little package, right?
But you know what I kind of fantasize about
is like a Intel NUC type thing, but with a real GPU,
running Steam OS with Kodi included in it,
so like, it's Steam OS, but it's primarily a Kodi box,
that in Kodi, there's like a Steam OS option,
like you don't have movies and TV.
Oh, like a Kodi plug-in to list your games
and then watch them.
And then it flips over to a Steam OS desktop,
which is running big picture mode or something like that.
Maybe it's even like X on another...
Yeah, yeah, on another TTY or something,
and it's like its own dedicated big picture mode,
and then I've got a full-fledged Steam OS machine,
and then if there was some sort of in menu,
I could flip back to the Kodi experience,
and now I have a multimedia machine.
Even if it's gotta be like a little PC, I would love to have...
That would be amazing.
That's what I want, and I want it to run Steam OS,
because then it's more of a Linux box,
and I can play the games I really like.
See, the one thing here...
Oh, go on.
You wouldn't want it to run Steam OS at the moment
because it's just broken and crashes.
Oh, well, okay.
But the caveat, the Steam OS isn't sucking at the time.
Okay, one of the better runtimes for Steam
and then the Steam games.
See, I think the caveat for me is I kind of enjoy
some of the Chromecast that I can sit
and then queue something up easily.
That is nice about Android TV.
I'd like them to build the Chromecast stuff into Shield.
Yeah, or if there's...
I know I've seen a couple, like...
The Shield has it.
I've been to Steam OS.
That's a nice thing, too, is...
Yeah, you still have that functionality with Android TV,
is that...
Yeah, and so I think I've seen a couple
attempted open source type replacements,
or even something where you could take a link
and then get a plugin that could go like,
hey, send this to my Kodi box and play that,
play the link from YouTube with YouTube DL.
Michael's working on that.
Yeah, go, tell him about it.
Yeah, it's a cast, spelled with a K, for Kodi,
and it's basically exactly that.
It's more of a plugin structure like you just mentioned
where you tell it a URL,
and then the plugin figures out what add-on
and what player in Kodi.
Ooh, that sounds beautiful.
Kodi already does that using the core app.
No, that's just on the phone.
That doesn't work on the desktop,
so you can't send the information on your desktop.
Yeah, it only works on your phone,
so the core app is fantastic for the solution on the phone,
but it doesn't support every single plugin structure,
so I'm gonna try to submit some of my code to the core app
so they can fix the arbitrary add-ons
that are not necessarily common,
and then that's basically the idea,
is just to take the casting idea
and put it to the improved core
and also make a laptop version so you can just,
my version actually works with local files
on your computer as well.
Oh, that is slick.
I'm gonna check that out tonight.
Yeah, that is, yeah, I love Kodi.
I just love it so much.
It's come so far.
I got the...
Mine uses Samba for the local stuff,
and it's going to use NFS as well.
Nice.
I've been really, it's such a simple, obvious plugin,
and I forget what it's called.
I've mentioned the name before, though,
so it is linked somewhere in the JB site.
It is just the dumbest extension or plugin
or whatever you call it on Kodi
that just plays the next file in order,
like Netflix does when you get to the end
of a Netflix episode, it autoplays the next episode.
This just auto, so if you're watching DuckTales
and you got two seasons of DuckTales
and you're on season one.
You know what you're doing for the next 12 hours.
Yeah, you got automatic DuckTales.
Yeah, right?
And so that's, I love that feature.
I love it because I can just sit back
and I don't have to look for the remote.
I just, it's nice to be able to modify it
in a way that feels like it's genuinely my setup.
I also, I want to encourage you
to make something also feel like your own,
and that's your education, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Linux Academy just announced another round of funding.
Huge congrats. What?
That's great. Yeah.
Every time they do this, they invest deeply
into Linux Academy content, and they get staff on board
to make sure old content stays relevant.
They get new staff to write the good stuff
that you've been looking for with products
that are exploding right now.
They have research and development.
Of course, they even have instructors
that you can access to get real mentoring
from a human being, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Hands-on, scenario-based labs
that give you real-world experience.
You get to SSH into the server and own it
and bang around and alter the distro
based on your preference,
so that way you can learn on the distro you need.
You can prepare for a cert
using their practice exams and quizzes,
and I think one of the things that I like
is these features that we're introducing
that involve the community.
First of all, I like that the community
is stacked full of Jupyter Broadcasting members,
but they have these custom randomized decks of cards
where you can study and practice,
and these cards can be forked by community members
and improved upon, kind of like an open-source project.
Another thing they've recently introduced
is public profiles, so you can brag
or demonstrate the hard work you've been doing
at Linux Academy.
They've got also courses if you wanna get your search
and new iOS and Android apps.
They're busting out new stuff all the time,
and now they just secured another round of funding.
It's just gonna get better.
It's gonna keep going.
They've recently also launched seven-day free trials.
Free?
Seven-day free trials, so you can go get a little taste
over at Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged,
and a big thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring the unplugged program.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
That was my Fox News swish.
Did that work?
I think it landed.
It's...
I'm just gonna say that regardless.
It's supposed to sound...
No one tell him otherwise.
It's supposed to sound a little bit like this.
Speaking of breaking news,
this happened a couple of weeks ago,
but we just got the audio and video online this week.
Linux maintainer, Greg Kh, he supports the LTS kernel,
the USB subsystem, and a bunch of other subsystems
that are absolutely essential to the function
of your Linux box, and he's been around
in Linux development since, well, forever,
and he was at a Linux Foundation event,
and he was doing a fireside chat.
Ooh, did you hear the bombing?
We have a bomber plane.
Oh no.
Duck and cover everybody.
They knew we were about to talk about this.
They knew this was coming,
and he had a couple of choice quotes.
We were just talking about licensing
and other things like that,
and I wanted to kind of jump in on some of this,
but let's start with an interesting stat.
Do you have a rough guess, Wes,
how many people join the Linux kernel development team
per month?
Man, I have no idea.
Let's go with 10.
Okay, that's a good, that's what,
I would probably would've,
I actually would've guessed like four,
because it seems like a pretty tight-knit team, right?
I would've guessed like four.
Greg actually shares the number with us,
and it turns out, Wes, it's a bit larger.
Freshman.
But we have high school students working on the kernel,
so, yeah, but I mean, there's always new people,
our community, again, 200 new developers every three months.
That's huge.
200 to 300, is that what he just said?
Community, again, 200 new developers every three months.
Yeah. Wow.
That's huge.
So we have people coming in.
Yeah, and it's not, I mean,
we're not just talking about young people,
people who switch from other industries, right?
There's a whole, there's a learning curve,
no matter where you're coming from.
Now, catch this little stat.
Oh, yeah, I mean, if you look at Seattle,
so that's where I used to live,
I mean, Seattle is filled with ex-Microsoft developers
working on Linux right now.
Amazon, Facebook, Google, Valve,
all ex-Microsoft developers contributing to Linux,
which is great.
We want those engineers, we want those people,
and they're doing really good stuff there.
I didn't know he moved out of the Seattle area.
Yeah, I didn't know he was on Mercer Island.
I was always gonna go have dinner with Greg.
Just waitin', waitin'.
Does anybody in the mobile room know where Greg lives now?
Anybody?
Shower him, anybody wanna go be creepy and find out?
Cause I've been fantasizing about getting a burger
with Greg for a while now and recording that.
So that's gotta be a thing, that's still gotta happen.
All right, but that's not what was interesting.
I thought that was a fun to know fact.
Just a tidbit.
But we recently tried to cover the two
very different approaches to license enforcement
that are developing in the Linux kernel.
There's the Greg Linus method of a long burn,
work with these people over a decade.
And then lazily you could say
there's the software conservancy method
where you try to work with them and when things fail,
you quickly escalate to lawsuits.
And Greg was asked about that.
And I think you can tone, you can tell by the tone
and you can tell by the slight awkwardness at the beginning.
This is an extremely sensitive topic
for Greg and the Linux Foundation and the Linux community.
So pay attention to sort of the awkwardness
of this question too.
Healthy discussion on the kernel summit mailing list
on the topic of licenses.
And how can I describe it?
You're gonna let me go here?
I'm gonna let you go.
Well, as much as you want.
There's some interesting points raised.
And I guess, well, let me,
do you wanna describe the discussion?
I think you probably remember it.
Awkward.
Yes, so the discussion came up about GPL enforcement.
And what to do about that.
And people's statements saying,
making the claim that if we don't enforce the GPL,
it's the same as the BSD license.
And I called bullshit on that.
Oh, dang.
That's flat out false.
And because that's not true, that's flat out false.
And what we're seeing these days,
I mean, yes, people violate our license.
That always happens.
It's gotten better.
I don't know if anybody remembers the 1990s
when people were shipping close source,
ethernet drivers, SCSI drivers, controller drivers,
everything, it was crazy.
We are a lot, lot better.
One of the biggest violators of the GPL used to be Intel.
And now they're our biggest supporter.
On more ways than one, financial, code, contributions,
everything else.
And that happened due to us working with them.
And so my main point about GPL compliance is
everybody owns their copyrights.
You're free to do however you wish
with those copyrights and enforcing them
and getting the code.
But use your judgment.
The judgment should be not necessarily
you have to get the code.
Because if you go into a company with lawyers
knocking on the front door,
you're gonna get, the walls are gonna come down
and you're gonna alienate everybody in that company.
Let's stop right there.
I think this is such a key argument.
And it's one that if you come at it
from a pure legal argument or a raw analysis of the license,
that it doesn't resonate, it doesn't make sense to you.
And this is where the software conservancy is coming from.
And it's easy to be on that, right?
Like we wanna protect these rights,
that's what the license is about.
But you also have to consider the bigger picture.
And I think unless you have spent decades
working with developers and changing their mind over time
and working with them to be more interoperable with Linux
and then reaping the benefits of that,
you fail to understand how important
that particular process is.
And what he's talking about here is
when we get into these legal enforcement battles,
these companies shut down.
And any contributions we were gonna get go away.
And all of the naysayers in the company
are all of a sudden proven right.
Use your judgment.
The judgment should be not necessarily
you have to get the code.
Because if you go into a company with lawyers
knocking on the front door, you're gonna get,
the walls are gonna come down
and you're gonna alienate everybody in that company
that was using Linux.
Because inside every company when you start using Linux,
you have two camps.
One is like, oh, those hippies and punks,
we can't use this crazy stuff.
And then you convince them and you finally get that.
And if one of those people, those crazy hippies and punks
shows up at the front door with a lawyer,
boom, you proved them right.
You were wrong, doors come down, everything works bad.
But if as a developer you go to that same company
and contact the developers in there and say,
hey, what can I do to help you get your code merged
into the kernel?
And that's a totally different way of working with them.
That says, hey, the community's willing to work with you,
willing to invest their time with you,
willing to make your product better.
And that's the best way to work forward.
We have seen it time and time again
that when you go in with lawyers or representatives
of the developers and not the developers themselves,
the walls come down, all contact gets shut off.
I'm working with a silicon company today
that has been shipping Linux on their product
for eight, nine years.
No code has ever come out of them.
The developers inside the company reached out,
I met some of them and they're saying, help us.
I'm like, okay, great, we'll work with you.
And the thing is, the code from this company
is usually almost always is crap.
We don't want that code.
We really don't.
I mean, you might want to get that one device working,
but you really want is that company and those developers
in that company to become part of our community
and then label us to grow.
Because the only way we're gonna survive
is if we continue to grow
and continue to bring more people in.
We're gonna age out, we pass away,
we move on to other things.
We need more people in our community in order to survive.
So you work with that company,
you make them reliant on Linux,
you make them realize that working with the community
actually saves them time and money,
which has been proven over and over and over.
And then they're now reliant so much on Linux
that they have to invest.
They are part of the community, they rely on it.
And it works.
Look at all the sponsors and look at all the people
who've been contributing to Linux over time.
Again, I'll point out as Intel
is the perfect poster child for this.
They now do everything on Linux
and they used to be our worst violator.
It can happen, things can change.
And we're in it for the long haul.
We don't want just the instant code dump.
We want you to work together
and become part of our community.
We're in it for the long haul.
We don't just want the instant code dump.
I like this.
I like everything about this.
Mohsen Rath, you had a comment on it.
Go ahead.
Mohsen, oh sorry Mohsen Rath, you're muted.
Start over again, that was my bad.
Sorry about that, okay.
So I believe that you guys had this argument
a few times over on both Linux Unplugged
as well as Linux Action Store.
Are you accusing me of repeating
because these clips are brand new, sir.
These are brand new clips, certified.
The clips are new.
The clips are brand new,
but the argument is an old one.
Which argument would you say that it's enforcement?
Yeah, yeah.
As Talness put it right there,
coders versus lawyers in terms of
do you want to take the open hand
or do you want to take the closed fist?
But as I remember watching,
actually I wasn't watching,
I was reading it in a comic book,
the closed fist can still be used to protect
whereas the open hand can be used to harm.
So the end result is you have to sit there
and take each company as a fresh approach.
You take the most genial, the most open approach.
You start with that one first
and you work your way down the line.
Because as they said, they used to have beef with Intel.
Intel could have said,
hey, you know this open source thing?
You guys don't have real lawyers and stuff like that.
We do, we now own you, your family,
your entire genetic line, your computers,
your cars, everything.
Thank you for being our work slaves, enjoy.
They could have done that because it's Intel.
Much like Apple, much like Google now,
they had the money to do that.
But they instead, they were just like, you know what?
We want them to use our product in a fashion
that everyone can benefit.
So we're gonna just walk to them real nice
and talk to them real nice first,
see if they see things from our perspective first
before showing up with lawyers, quote-unquote,
showing up with the FDA or whichever law enforcement it is
kicking down the door and saying, you stole our stuff.
Yeah, I would say, what I think,
what I like to look at this situation
as regular everyday Linux users,
it's happening at a level that is really kind of obscure to us.
We're not really cognizant of these kinds of things going on
but there is, between the core contributors to the kernel
and the software conservancy, which is a new group set up,
I mean, there is a new level of argument brewing
that we don't really have any involvement with.
We can only just sit back and watch
and it doesn't directly affect us,
yet it could have long-term ramifications.
And it's fascinating that there's this disconnect there.
There's this whole thing brewing under the surface
and we just get little glimpses of it from time to time.
I think it's been an argument,
as Moser Rath has pointed out,
it's been a conversation for as long
as this has been a particular issue,
especially as GPL software
has begun to get widespread adoption.
I think it really marks the distinction
between the Linux community and the wider GPL community,
free software community, et cetera.
And I wonder if it's not turning
to a more significant volume now,
now that you have the conservancy
and you have new offenders that are in the mobile space
that are particularly egregious.
ARM platform has a lot of issues around it.
I wonder if it's not being ratcheted up to a new level now.
And I don't wanna go as far as to call it a cold war
because that feels like it's adding a hype spin
that's undeserved,
sort of like that airplane bomber in the background.
But I do feel like it is definitely something
that desperately is getting close to needing a resolution.
And I don't know if there's one on the horizon
because there's some big fiefdoms being set up.
And you have people that are in positions that are,
I guess what I'm trying to say is I'm worried
that people like Greg and Linus
could eventually get burned out by this kind of stuff.
Or there could be some sort of developer loss
as this battle goes on.
And that's the part I look at and wonder
if we'll have longer ramifications
on the quality of Linux code.
That's the only kind of point.
I know that's an extrapolation,
but if you think about it,
if I'm Greg and I'm 20-plus years, whatever, into this,
you know what, I've made my bones,
I've made my reputation, I don't need this bullshit.
I don't need to go to events carrying two lawyers
because of what this has led to.
I don't need that hassle.
You know what, guys, I've made my peace,
good luck with everything, I'm moving on.
I don't think that's a reasonable thing
when you're getting down,
because as somebody in Greg's position,
you have to look at this and go, this is obvious.
You are getting in the way of my ability
to make this thing better.
And all I wanna do is make this a better thing,
and you're making it harder for me to do that,
and I've dedicated my life to this, and I'm done with this.
And that doesn't seem like an unreasonable position
for someone that's worked as long as he has to do this.
And I'm sure it can feel like other people
who may feel that they have a legitimate claim
or are representing those who do have a legitimate claim,
I can see how that might feel like an outside influence
that's trying to hurt or do something
that you don't feel is best for you.
Imagine, say, Greg or somebody like Greg
felt they were on the precipice
of finally getting a company to come along
and really get involved at Linux,
and another group starts up a legal battle,
and it totally shuts down all of the progress
you've been making for the last three years.
How excruciatingly frustrating would that be?
And that's where I worry it's going.
W.W., you wanna jump in?
Go ahead, sir.
Well, I do understand your...
I fully acknowledge that your point
of him possibly getting burned out
and getting sick of being open
and just trying to be nice to people and get them in.
I don't think when he does get people in,
that's all he's doing.
When you really want to impart something
to a lot of people,
and you want to make it great and open source,
you don't just want to impart just the code.
You want to impart your passion
and what drives you to do this
and put in the effort that you do
to make it great and open source.
And I would like to think that maybe Greg
and others of similar mindset
would be putting in that effort
to have people not just contribute back
and contribute open source code,
that they try to contribute that sentiment
that they feel of why they're doing this
to other people so that they continue
to have that feeling
and they continue to want to make open source great.
Yeah, I think you're probably right.
I hope so.
And why don't we wrap this all up
on a more positive, just sort of funny,
tongue-in-cheek note.
Why the hell does the Linux kernel team
still use email for so many damn things?
So, doesn't the reliance on dusty old email,
doesn't that just make us look
like a bunch of old gray beards?
You know, like get off my lawn type.
So, you know, it's 2016.
I mean, come on, Greg.
Email, that's our patch review system.
Can we do better?
Give me the 30 second pitch.
30 second pitch is there's nothing else better.
There's nothing else faster.
There's nothing else more in use by the whole world.
Email, plain text works great
for people who can't use GUIs,
have intermittent email access to the internet.
English is not their first language
and connectivity issues again.
And for review, I mean, as proof in the talk before mine,
I reviewed 53 patches and accepted 13 of them in 15 minutes.
And, Garrett, there's no way.
There you go.
Greg, you don't need no Slack.
Although, seriously, you should check out Mattermost
and Matrix.
Or Rocketrat.
Yeah, Matrix.
Yeah.
And then, eventually, maybe one of them.
Well, I think with Matrix, they'll all work together.
Oh, it's beautiful.
You know what else works together?
Our Mumble Room.
Go over to jblive.tv on a Tuesday.
Do Bang Mumble.
You'll get the info and join us.
You just have to have a working mic
and you can join our virtual log.
The times are at jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar.
Get your topic into the show at linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Send your emails to jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact
and be sure to join us right back here next Tuesday.
Say goodbye, Wes.
Goodbye, everybody.
Bye!
I secretly use Arch Linux damn Popey made it for the whole show I mad respect sir mad
respect I I hope you had at least yourself something delicious to sip on
while you sat there hold on sorry muted hello sorry say again say again sorry
they like they like savings here means it's an hour earlier right that happens
this Sunday here in the States that you know we have a double last coming up
this Sunday by the way everybody and it's getting screwed by daylight savings
although I'll have an extra hour of sleep so it's interesting see yeah you
guys already did that that was Bush thing huh well you guys oh man it's
still confusing the whole thing how many years later has it been since this got
out of sync and it's still confusing yep well I'm glad you made a Popey I really
appreciate it connection issues earlier I don't know why yeah I saw that he sent
me a note that sucks that sucks hey you know what I forgot to mention during the
cadian live discussion is today I've been shooting a video behind the scenes
here JB just a little bit bits and pieces specifically to do an editing
comparison in cadian live and an editing comparison and final cut it's like
science if I remember I will do follow-up next week on the episode and
tell you let's all remind him yeah I am supposed to ask you something before I
start poppy before are you if you have you bailed already yeah no he's still
there he's still there I guess I'm supposed to ask you was it it's um I
forgot I forgot what I'm supposed to ask you about a quote the cloud being other
people's computers what is this what am I what is it did know I put you up to
this I think I think maybe if you go three steps remove that may be the case
I'm not sure it's been passed to me through a series of messengers who I'm
sure this conversation have you what is it well I don't remember much these days
but I do seem to recall I get irritated when people say it because it doesn't
have to be the case the cloud or the cloud is other people's computers which
one the cloud is other it's the cloud is other people computers because the fact
is that doesn't have to be the case you can have your own orchestration of
computers that you could call a cloud and it's your own private computers but
yes not to be someone else's would you agree though when people say the cloud
they're generally referring to hosted services generally referring to a public
cloud but you could still have a private cloud is yeah well of course which is
your own yeah of course but you could but I mean I think in general when
people refer to the cloud they're referring to Azure Amazon digital ocean
rackspace certainly micro services things like that that's what they're
referring to I I think don't you depends who you ask because some people for some
people cloud is Dropbox and for other people cloud is just you know a picture
on a diagram it depends who you ask and I think you and people of your level of
intelligence saying that know exactly what it means and I think you know what
public and private clouds are I feel like if you're like private clouds are
like local clouds could be the fog I'm looking across the room well at my next
cloud box right yeah I guess I see your point but I also feel like it's good to
remind people that the cloud can also be a sort of a marketing obfuscation tool
sure can be but it doesn't it's not it's not a blanket whenever I hear it it's
it's it's always seen as like this is the only state that like the cloud is
somebody else's computer fact end of story and that just doesn't tell the
whole story that's because when most people set up a server they don't call
it the cloud they call it my server that's because they only have one if
they had multiple than they would call it like I call my own I don't call I
have I have a bunch of servers I don't call it my cloud no but mine orchestrate
with each other in a way that it's not important which one I'm actually hitting
okay well so then that okay do you okay all right so it's more sort of obscure
and you can't really tell where you're actually going necessarily I'll tell you
honestly I generally prefer this version because it makes the cloud less
bullshitty hype but they were it but I still think the main issue is when you
if you were to take a room of a thousand geeks a like you're at a conference and
ask them what's the cloud I think they would all think it's it's a it's
services hosted by it by a third party I think to an end-user where the cloud
terminology is important it's just to emphasize that they don't have to worry
about storing their own data that someone else is going to handle that
when I think of cloud I think of managed infrastructure yeah exactly it's
yeah yeah yeah contract service level agreement with that company and you know
they're providing a service in the same way that you're paying for your
utilities at home hey it's not the water utilities it's somebody else's water
it's not okay I like that argument too I still feel like though that this is
pretty down in the weeds and that's your main core issue with this is it so far
down the weeds is like it's like arguing that you shouldn't call a tissue paper
Kleenex no no no no I it's it's just that I don't like that that's the only
side of the argument that's ever expressed and it's and it's used as a
stick to beat cloud as if cloud is a bad thing and you should never use it
because it's somebody else's computer it's bullshit all your services were
already running on someone else's computer they were just maybe doing it
less scalably yeah yeah mm-hmm I guess I see your point I see your point I just
don't see like it's I think that's a losing battle it's a language battle
that's been lost so it is thanks for bringing out yeah I guess you know how
about this is a line build your own cloud yeah I've done that thanks