So don't tell Noah, but I'm kind of becoming more of a Kodi guy and less of a Plex guy
and less of an MB guy.
I just have such a crappy internet connection at home that having local media is, not only
is it way faster to play and makes fast forward and rewind possible, but I can do full resolution
video like Blu-ray quality video and it plays.
And Kodi is so great.
Kodi's awesome.
When you have multiple audio sources in a file or subtitles or anything and you just
want to quickly use the remote to turn it on or switch audio tracks, it's so good at
that.
And the playback is so flawless with Kodi.
That's awesome.
I just, I am such a huge fan of Kodi and I kind of had moved away for a while because
I was using Plex and having central storage, but that only works when you have a really
fast connection.
Right.
When you live in society.
Yeah, exactly.
Wes, I just wanted to say thank you to Kodi and the Kodi folks.
I am really looking forward to Kodi 17 when it comes out.
Have you tried that MB plug-in?
Not that it might not work for you now.
No, you know I should have.
Because I use that.
I still have it.
I've had plenty of experience with it.
Now tell me about that.
Well, because it just makes Kodi's library basically transparent to the MB back in store.
What I haven't tried is using that and having your own local files.
That'd be interesting because then you could have your local stuff and if you got back
on the network you could have the full MB.
So I have that set up with some friends and they stream it over the network so then it
doesn't tax my MB server.
But Kodi plays it locally.
And you know what all those files are, Wes?
All those files are freaking DRM free.
That way we are celebrating International Day Against DRM, May 3rd, 2016.
Oh yeah, here comes the weaponized lawnmower.
It's coming again, Wes.
Do you hear it?
I've closed the windows.
I've battened down the hatches.
I took out the fan.
We still have a weaponized lawnmower out there.
So today is the 10th International Day Against DRM.
And you, Wes, need to take a few steps to take actions against DRM.
Are you ready?
Here we go.
Take a selfie.
My beautiful face.
Yeah, okay.
So we need to take a selfie.
Okay?
So are you taking a selfie, Wes?
So this is what it says, affectedbydesign.org.
Take a selfie and sign the petition.
Envision a future victory against DRM.
So this is something you could do.
So while you're taking a selfie, I want you to envision a future without DRM.
This is how you can help me.
You look really good there, Wes.
You can add your graphics to your social media profile or your blog.
You could submit a DRM horror story to the EFF.
You could make a blog post or video or a song.
Or you could share their DRM-free living guide with your friends.
Those are statements that you can take for actions against DRM.
Now, this is less stupid than telling everyone to go and DDoS the Apple store.
Okay, all right.
Okay.
That was years past.
Yeah.
This is a positive campaign, raising awareness.
I could get behind this.
I'm not sure what my anti-DRM face is going to be that I'm going to pull when I do my
selfie, but I'll have a good go.
I have a recommendation.
Shave your mustache.
Definitely.
Yeah.
That's all you need.
Oh, it's a little breezy in here on the lip.
It's a little breezy.
I just don't know about this defective by design.
It just seems like it's been a bit of a snoozer from day one.
It's never for 10 years now.
It's failed to really get my interest.
I do support it in principle.
Yeah?
Maybe I will post something.
So hang on.
Let me get this straight.
I'm going to shave my mustache so that I look like an Amish person.
Right.
Is that what you want?
Yes.
Ideally.
I'm watching.
Okay.
That sounds like a great idea.
You're watching.
Wimpy's watching the playback right now.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 143 for May 3rd, 2016.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that already has your gift
picked out for Mother's Day.
Yes, it's almost Mother's Day.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Here's your official reminder before the weekend, everybody.
Hello, Wes.
Guess what?
We've secretly made a big show for 143 coming up on this week's episode of the Unplugged
program.
We have some fascinating open source updates from funding to projects that are missing
deadlines and targets.
Oh, I'm not saying anything.
Shh.
I'm not saying anything as well as some great updates.
Another look at VR under Linux.
We're going to discuss Subsonic going to closed source after years of open source.
What?
Yes, yes.
And then don't tune out.
We're actually not done talking about Ubuntu 16.04.
No way.
But don't worry.
We wouldn't be doing it for a third week in a row unless we actually thought there was
something genuinely worth your time to talk about.
So you'll just have to trust us coming up in a little bit.
Yes, and yes, it's true.
I am mustache free this week.
That's me brushing where the mustache once was.
If it wasn't, but he's still handsome.
We're going to power through it.
And to help us, Mr. West brought us some extremely unique and delicious beers from Diamond Knot
Brewery, a place special in my heart.
I did not know this.
No, you didn't.
I'm drinking the Binnacle Ale, the summer ale.
I think that's how you say it.
I believe so.
And you'll be drinking.
The brown ale.
Now why is Diamond Knot near and dear to my heart?
Now we're going to get into all the Linux-y stuff first, but before we do that, I want
to go back in time, if we can, just really quickly.
A different time in Chris's life.
You know what's crazy about this?
It was May 7th that we released this.
It was probably about May 3rd in 2010 that I shot this video.
So think about this, Wes.
You brought me a beer almost like on the six year anniversary since I shot this video.
That is kind of remarkable.
Here we are at the Diamond Knot Brewery, the very place we are drinking these beers from.
For beers tasty, which you may recall from days past, which, hold on, sorry.
Hold on.
So where we're at right now is the very highest point.
We can look down at all the people of what we're getting into today.
That's Wes.
Yeah.
So there's a, if you're watching the video version, a little tour of their brewery, which
is nice.
One of their breweries.
We're going to go to their locations now.
And the beard on this guy we're about to talk to.
Oh, what's that in your hand?
Oh, that is a delicious Bursky.
All right, so here we are.
We are still here at Diamond Knot and we've got Pat.
Now Pat's the guy you want to talk to at Diamond Knot Brewery because he knows all about the
different beers here.
He is, I kid you not, the brewmaster.
I want that title.
What does a brewmaster do at Diamond Knot?
Makes all bow to me.
That's pretty rad.
Nice, dude.
So tell us a little bit.
So we're in a, we're kind of in a, maybe for you, a kind of an older location, right?
These are still in production, but this.
I spent my first five years in this tiny space alone.
This was a fun episode.
So as brewmaster, I'm responsible basically for all beer operations here at Diamond Knot.
So we do a series of interviews with these guys, find out about the brews they make.
And if you guys are curious, I will put a link to this old shenanigans in the show notes.
It is actually pretty cool to go behind the scenes and see all the different stuff they
do.
Yeah, it really is.
Old episode of Beer is Tasty and we do an interview with the brewmaster from the very
place that we're drinking beer from today.
So that's pretty cool there, Wes.
How neat is that?
Thanks for bringing in the good old Diamond Knot Brewery.
That's a fun one.
All right.
So let's not go any further without bringing our virtual lug.
Time Appropriate Greetings, Mamba Room.
Hello.
Whiskey.
Time Appropriate Greetings.
Hello.
Yes.
Good to talk to you.
But I wanted to, before we get into the super, super heavy stuff, I did want to maybe discuss
really quickly DuckDuckGo.
I'm personally a fan of DuckDuckGo.
I like kind of what they're about.
They've worked with JB in the past and so I wanted to just mention that they're still
out there.
They're still out there contributing to open source software and they've made some pretty
big contributions recently, including some serious cash to some of our favorite open
source projects and some important ones like SecureDrop.
My name is Gabriel Weinberg and I'm the founder of DuckDuckGo.
Six years ago, when DuckDuckGo was just me and the servers were still in my basement,
I started donating to free and open source projects that I depended on every day.
A lot of these projects were like DuckDuckGo in that they were labors of love by just a
few people working in their spare time.
I wanted them to know how important their projects were to me and to lend a little financial
support where I could.
So we've got $25,000 to the Freedom of Press Foundation for SecureDrop, which is a secure
way for people to communicate like leaks and stuff like that.
$25,000 to the FreeNet Project, $25,000 to the OpenBSD Foundation.
Crypt Tech Project is $25,000.
The Tor Project is $25,000.
Fight for the Future gets $25,000.
Open Source Technology Innovation Fund for FairCrypt gets $25,000.
That's interesting.
Yeah, I thought so.
GPG Tools for GPG Mail, $25,000.
Couple other ones in here.
Pretty neat, Wes.
That's a lot of money.
Good old DuckDuckGo.
Remember, just a reminder, if you haven't used them recently for your search.
Go send a few searches their way.
I imagine Popey's probably exhausted.
However, I don't see him in this screenshot here, so maybe not.
I imagine he was sitting in and watching both Baited Breath.
But Michael Alibril over at Ferronix is bringing us the latest from the Ubuntu Online Summit
for Ubuntu 16.10.
16.10, Wes.
Oh, yeah.
The future.
Get off your 16.04 high horse.
Fine.
Well, it's another setback for Unity 8 and Mirror, Michael writes.
It's been confirmed that the Unity 8 desktop and the Mirror display server will not be
the default for the desktop spin in Ubuntu 16.10.
Yakety yak.
That's a fun name.
Unity 8 and Mirror will be available as opt-in features for users wanting to upgrade their
desktop.
But Unity 7 and Xorg will be the default for 16.10.
So disappointed, Wes?
I mean, I still want to try it.
I'm curious to see when it lands.
Maybe it makes sense to be in the next, you know, big update, but I'm not that surprised.
Popey, was it ever really planned that 16.10 would be where Mirror would land?
By default?
Was that ever really a thing?
I don't think so.
It's a setback, Popey.
It's a setback.
Is it?
Or is it just a really good idea to not dump stuff on people when it's not ready yet?
Exactly.
Which we learn from, you know, past experience.
See also PulseAudio and Unity 7.
Yeah.
We've learned this.
You know what would be a setback is it being a bomb and people hating it.
That'd be a bit of a setback.
Yeah.
However, I do appreciate Larbal tuning in and following this stuff at the same time.
So I don't want to give him too much crap because I am actually glad he's reporting
on it.
There's not a lot of original reporting in the Linux community.
So it's actually nice to see some getting done.
I don't know.
A setback?
Well, you can read it both ways.
You know, either people want stuff to land like, come on, you need to have this stuff
ready.
I want to see it now.
And then when we land it like now, they're upset because it's crap or it's not finished
or there's something wrong with it.
And then it's like, OK, well, what we'll do is we'll wait until it's ready.
Oh, no, that's a setback.
You should have landed it now when I asked you to.
So move your entitlement and shove it somewhere else.
I think where I kind of connect with it is that, well, once we finally switch over to
X, that's going to be solved.
Once we finally get to Y, that won't be a problem anymore.
And where I felt like that came up a lot was Michael Dominic's recent tryout Linux series
that he's really done for the last five weeks of Coda Radio, where he was trying out, you
know, I'm going to create an app, I'm going to do this, I'm going to move over to Linux.
And there's a lot of questions.
It's like, yeah, yeah, I know that's a little weird right now.
But when Unity 8 ships and there's an officially blessed sort of UI look that things are supposed
to have and there's a clear path for distributing software and there's these snap packages to
make it easy for you to be in control of updates for your user base, you're going to love it.
And so there's all this pent-up anticipation for a payoff that we've all been waiting
for now since Mir was announced.
And so it's a setback in that, oh, we have to wait longer.
That's how it's a setback.
Yeah, you don't get your new toys right away.
They're going to be available for testing, but they won't be available for general availability.
And that's, if there's a setback, that's what it is, and I don't think it's a big deal.
There was also at the UDS, I don't know, I didn't actually get a chance to watch it before
the show, but Michael says that there was more talk about conversions apps, Ubuntu discourse
closing unless Microsoft steps in, and handling legacy apps with Mir and Snappy.
And in regards to Ubuntu Touch, it looks like there's consideration of skipping Cyanogen
Mod 5 and going right to Cyanogen Mod 7.
It's not necessarily there's anything in Android 6 everybody's excited about.
It's more that there's things in Kernel 4.4 that everyone's excited about.
Interesting.
And I don't know, Pobi, if you have any information on this, this is the thing I'm the most interested
in is I don't really understand the relationship between Canonical and UNAV, but it sounds
like UNAV is going to be the way you get navigation under Ubuntu Touch, and there's more discussions.
It already is.
Right.
It already is a default app on the phone.
It's a community-maintained app, and we had a session where we discussed the future plans,
and Nick Lesh and Marcos showed off some of the stuff they've got in development for the
next release.
Yeah, you sure did.
There's your mug right there when I go to the UNAV.
Yeah, sorry about that.
Yeah, you look at that stash.
You've got way too much facial hair on your face then, let me tell you.
So anything of interest to know?
Is there new developments coming with UNAV, or just better integration, what?
I don't come here for my living shoes.
I come here for advice on my facial hair.
I know that.
And your smell.
You're doing good on that front.
So what can you tell us about the UNAV stuff?
Because as somebody who seriously would be considering Ubuntu Touch, good navigation
is a pretty essential feature for me, especially somebody who likes to drive around.
The stuff we were talking about for the next release was more to do with making the app
work well on tablets and using the space well on a tablet, rather than just having one giant
map and then when you click on something it takes over the whole screen.
Having a split screen user interface where you have like a tab down the right hand side
with your list of restaurants and then marks plotted on the left hand side showing the
map.
Kind of split screen like you've seen on some of our other applications, that kind of thing.
It's early days.
I'd like to try that.
Yeah, I love doing nav on a tablet when I can.
It's so much nicer than on the phone.
All right.
Well, before we get totally off of Ubuntu Mobile Touch and before we get into Mr. Skooky
Sprite's HD Vive experience under Linux, something caught my attention.
I don't know what this all means, but the title is Plasma Mobile, a new base system.
At the last Academy, the Plasma team revealed their first prototype of a new Plasma Mobile.
Now I know what you've all been thinking, finally, another rebuilt mobile platform based
on Linux that nobody will use, finally.
Well, Plasma Mobile is designed to work with any existing operating stack, so they're hoping
since it works with any OS stack out there, you'll pick it up pretty quick.
And so far, they've based on reference images that were based on Ubuntu Touch using an Android
system inside an LXE container to make use of Android hardware abstraction layer.
Their initial touch base was Ubuntu 15.04.
Eventually their images started to diverge from Ubuntu Touch.
For example, they upgraded the libhybris to an upstream version because libhybris or whatever
it is, is too old for their context.
They also got to a newer QT version.
They upgraded Ubuntu 16.04 for the base, and they've integrated some neon packages.
To simplify things further, they wanted to experiment to see if they could get their
own operating system stack that can run on mobile devices.
After they looked at their requirements, they have a base system of Cyanogen with ASOP-based
Android or AOSP, and the Ubuntu neon system inside a Chirrut or container.
So this is the new Plasma Mobile stack based on top of the hard work of Ubuntu Touch.
Two things surprise me about this story.
Number one, that they're sort of starting over again with their Plasma Mobile base.
Number two is they're sort of unceremoniously using Ubuntu Touch, and I find that ironic
because I just remember some of the biggest pushback came from the Plasma group about
Canonical going off and doing their own thing, and here they are now using it as a base.
You see in the irony there, Wes?
I do see some irony there.
And they're like, but we've totally diverged.
We're no longer using Ubuntu base, well, except for 6.04 and neon packages.
But other than that, we're no longer using Ubuntu as a base.
I don't know.
Maybe I'm being too hard, but that was just sort of the waft I got off this.
Anybody in the Mumble Room have thoughts on this story?
Another mobile platform, guys.
Hey, I'd be curious to talk to someone who likes it, just tried it, but now it's new
again.
Can you hear the plane crash?
Yeah.
I just, I mean, I'm a fan of it.
I'm a fan of, you know, people creating things with their passion.
And it would be interesting if it was like, you know, on multiple types of devices and
you could just be like, hey, I got a new device and the KDE mobile stuff works, Plasma mobile
works great.
Well, device isn't limited to you because that's the problem I have with so many mobile
stuff coming up.
It doesn't support like a simple tablet that I have, so I can't try it.
Well, you know, being based on CyanogenLOD and AOSP.
Hopefully that will help.
Yeah.
They're using LXC for the, you know, for Android, this is, LXC is very interesting, funny that
we're going to be talking about that later today.
Okay.
So apparently not a lot, not a lot of comments, but they have proof of concept working on
a Nexus device.
So if you are curious about it, they do have it up and running.
Using Ubuntu 16.04, Ubuntu TouchBase, and some of the Neon packages.
They talk about moving quick, right?
Talk about moving super quick.
So a couple of weeks ago, we had a chance to talk about the HTC Vive.
You know, that's the VR solution that has Valve's cooperation.
The creators of SteamOS, you may remember them.
Do you remember Valve?
Oh, yeah.
They make that Debian-based app.
Yes, right.
And so we all thought that if they were going to release a VR solution, theirs would have
the best likelihood of supporting Linux.
I mean, it's from Valve.
Because you want to use it with your Steam machine.
Their very own platform is SteamOS.
So none of us were willing to put our money where our mouth was and actually try it.
We're cheapskates.
Yeah.
We're just not crazy enough.
But Mr. Skookiesprite did just that.
He went out there, put his money where his mouth was, and got himself an HTC Vive, set
it all up, connected it to his Linux box, and here's to report how it went.
But first, before we get off mobile, let's talk about Ting, sponsor of the Linux Unplugged
program.
Linux.ting.com.
Go there right now, won't you?
I tell you what I did, and I think this might be a great way for you to go.
Get yourself a Nexus device from Google Play.
Just do it.
Don't play.
Go get it from Play.
You know what I'm saying?
Don't think about it.
Just order it.
Here's why.
If you're going to get yourself a mobile device, you know, I'm getting messages right now that
are pretty funny.
I love this Nexus 5 because I have been able to experiment with the heck out of this thing.
And Ting is just like, oh, you want a mobile service provider?
Yeah.
It's smart in.
It's mobile on demand.
It's no contract.
No other termination fee.
You only pay for what you use.
So I'm sitting here on Wi-Fi right now.
I got Noah to set up a 5 gigahertz Wi-Fi network while he was here with his fancy Ubiquiti
routers that he likes so much.
I won't touch them.
They're freedom hating.
But he loves them.
So he set up a 5 gigahertz network.
I put the Nexus 5 on that, the 5X.
I rolled back to Android M. Ting was honey badger about the entire process.
They're totally cool.
They have such a great service.
And they have CDMA and GSM.
So if you have a device that does both, you can pick and choose.
If you have one that's compatible to the network, you can bring it over to Ting and get a $25
service credit.
I got three devices on my line.
I'm paying like this.
This is including Linux Fest, including the Linux Fest stuff, $40.
That is impressive.
Yeah.
It's really great.
Super nice dashboard.
They have all kinds of devices from the Kyocera Dura, which starts at like $47.
How do you even say that again, Chris?
Kyocera Dura.
Yay.
XT.
Also, the LG 450 starts at $58.
These are just really nice feature phones that have like a battery that lasts a week.
You know, you just want a phone that lasts a week.
Then they've got things like the LG Volt 2, $66.
Motorola E, $74.
Apple Internet Phone 4, $87.
No contract.
No early termination fee.
You only pay for what you use.
Unlocked.
You own these devices.
LG K7, just added to the Ting store, $143.
Antutel One Touch IDOL 3, $178.
Under $200 for a nice Android device.
They go all the way up to the Samsung latest, the Motorola X, the Moto X.
That's a nice phone.
That is a nice phone.
Internet Phone 5S, still a pretty good phone.
Samsung's, the latest Samsung.
Oh, what's that one right there?
That 6P.
Ooh.
Look at that 6P.
Yeah, totally.
I know, right?
They also just added the Galaxy S7.
They've got all the great devices with no contract, no early termination fee, fanatically
good customer support, unlimited devices on one account, no mysterious line items, no
add-on charges, no contracts, no early termination fee.
You just pay for what you use.
You get started by going to linux.ting.com.
Also check out their blog.
They always have great app pics and stuff, and they're doing a giveaway of the Galaxy
Note 5.
Yeah.
Linux.ting.com.
Thank you, Ting, for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
All right, Mr. Sprite, Mr. Skookie, Mr. Writer.
Tell me about your experiences with HTC Vive.
Do you mind telling us how much you spent, just sort of starting from there?
How much you spent, how long the setup took, all of that?
You know, Chris, I'm not sure you can see the incandescent rage that is fueling me at
this moment, but those I've had interactions with in real life have been like, what's wrong
with you?
I'm like, it's the Vive!
Okay, yeah.
So my Vive arrived yesterday, took about two and a half hours to set up.
Now hold on there.
Hold on there.
Two and a half hours.
Wow.
And it's not like Skookie Sprite is some slouch here.
It's not like-
Right, no.
So what takes two and a half hours to set up about it?
Okay, well, one of the great strengths, I think, about the Vive as a device is that
it gives, quote unquote, full room virtual reality.
So that means that you have to set up two base stations that are ideally positioned
higher than you standing that have unimpeded line of sight between each other.
And that means like either you're drilling stuff into walls or you're jury rigging, as
I did, jury rigging a bunch of tripods and stuff.
Right, that's how I would think you'd have to do is put them up on a bunch of tripods.
Yeah, pretty much.
And so that is, the cool thing is those don't have to actually be wired to the computer,
but they do each have their own separate power adapters.
So it was a challenge.
And is this Windows only software to configure them?
Like where do you start running the limitations here?
Okay, so yesterday, I mean, I was so pumped, especially like, I was like, okay, this is
great.
Like I'll be able to have a whole week with this before I have to talk about it in the
podcast, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And I cleared my entire afternoon, and so I started setting it up.
And I'm just so pumped.
I'm like, finally, because I mean, I had an Oculus SDK too, but long before they dropped
support for it and blah, blah, blah.
So I was super, super pumped about this.
And I'm setting it up, and it's taking longer and longer.
And I get it all set up, and the cables are just enormous, and it's a big, big nightmare.
And that's when I realize, oh, wait, I haven't checked to see if this actually supports Linux
because I'm having some problems.
You know, getting the display to work correctly, and I'm like, oh, well, let's just go to the
support site.
And there's nothing for Linux.
So then I'm like, okay, fine.
I'll go to Steam VR, you know, because Steam VR, I mean, that's Valve, that's Steam.
That's Steam OS.
That's got to work.
Linux.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's Windows only too now.
So can you believe that?
So not only do you have to have at least a decent modern graphics, you have to have a
nice CPU.
So what?
I mean, realistically, you got to have a minimum $1,000 PC to run this thing, right?
Well, yeah.
Okay.
So my pre-order or whatever, which I placed in like the eighth of the month, like two
months ago.
Yeah.
So it took forever to get here.
I think it was like 950 bucks all total.
Not including the computer?
No, of course not.
Oh, right.
Wow.
Dude, are you kidding?
I got like 28 terabytes in this here that I built.
Yeah.
This is a winner.
This is a real winner.
Well, no, here's the thing.
Okay, so the Oculus doesn't include any control surfaces.
This control, the Vive has these two really interesting, innovative little paddle sticks
that you hold and they're actually really cool.
It was very depressing when I had to pack it all up and file for a return yesterday
after just deploying it.
But Linux support, here's the bottom line.
They say that Linux support is coming now.
Meanwhile, they had promised Linux support from day one and they were very open about
that in both their marketing and in their media campaign.
And then they just rolled back on it on evidently the 22nd of last month after they shipped
my unit.
And I was the last person to hear about it.
So that's a bummer.
And do you feel like, I mean, Linux setup, Linux support aside, a two hour setup with
this is an investment with these things you have to put up on tripods or mount to your
wall.
And this, are you kidding me?
You know as well as I do that virtual reality is absolutely unbelievable.
It's going to be the next transformative technology for the next three years.
It's going to be a multi-billion dollar marketplace, you know, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
You're telling me.
I don't know.
I thought so.
But then Wimpy started to convince me that virtual reality is a hoax and that you give
me this story about a two hour setup.
They don't even support their own platform.
Forget the two hour setup.
That's the big thing.
Like the biggest thing that really depressed me about this and I, you know, because I had
to do, I need some official quotes from HTC and Valve and so I was, you know, calling
the PR people this morning.
The most depressing thing to me is that it shows, first of all, even for getting Linux,
it just shows like a total, I would not be confident in investing in this platform even
if I didn't run Linux now because like, oh, well, you can't even, like you said, develop
your own frigging platform, you know, wow, that's amazing.
Wimpy, you must be listening to this.
Do you hear this and think to yourself, this is exactly what you're saying.
This is never going to be a consumer platform.
Well, kind of.
I mean, it's very early days at the moment, but certainly the barrier to entry in terms
of the technology you need once you've got your bridle is expensive.
Your bridle.
Wimpy, have you ever actually sat down with any sort of virtual reality headset?
I have.
Okay, cool.
So, all right, fine then.
That's all I need to know.
Then I will respectfully disagree with you.
I've used three different generations of virtual reality headsets and other equipment and the
graphics get better and nothing else about it is any more convincing or compelling than
the very first iterations I saw in the 80s.
You see, I totally disagree because I was there in the 90s and because I live in Vegas
and we had the best arcades back then and we had some pretty compelling virtual reality
stuff and so I wrote it all off until the Oculus Rift, which blew my mind.
Like, awe for the awesome was just incredible, I thought.
I think that eventually it will work for some games, but I think we're going to get a lot
of rubbish games with rubbish implementations of VR and I've used 3D TV as an example of
why VR isn't going to work and it's more to do with the fact that you have to have something
on your head and this is worse than 3D TV because you have to have something on your
head with a multitude of cables coming out of it.
Yeah, that is problematic.
Yeah, that's a big deal because it's not really virtual reality, you're just tethered to a
computer somewhere.
It's just ridiculous.
There's a lot of issues that people, general consumers, just won't get over.
They won't get over the cost, they won't get over the inconvenience and they won't get
over the average implementation of games and more importantly, I think that the games are
going to try and play to the VR capabilities in the same way you get 3D TVs for 3D.
Yeah, totally, but by the same token, every new medium, especially in terms of the history
of video games, has come with the same set of challenges and generally speaking, the
new and better looking and more immersive technology has always won out, at least over
the last 30 years in my opinion and I do agree, it's a big pain in the ass, but one of the
cool things about the Vive that I really liked and was really hopeful about is this full
scale, room scale virtual reality, like if you've seen the video of the chick using Google's
tilt brush to paint in 3D, when you actually end up using that application with the Vive,
it's really impressive except for the fact that it was on Windows so I packed it up and
it's being returned.
The reason for that is we all know how long that to-do list is when Linux support is on
that to-do list.
That to-do list never gets done.
Those features never get implemented.
Five years later, if you're lucky, they'll add Linux support and I, for one, I was comfortable
paying my money, taking my chances with the Oculus SDK 2 because I wanted to develop for
it specifically and I was like, okay, fine, Linux support is body whatever and then eventually
six months later, they had the balls to come out and say, you know what, we're dropping
this.
We just want to do Windows stuff, which was okay.
I paid my money.
I totally, I totally bought, but these guys, these guys sold me this unit, not just like
is rumored marketing, but one of the key selling points was this is being developed in, not
just developed, but this is totally the partnership of Steam and Valve and HTC for Linux.
Day one, Linux support, they dropped that.
I mean, what?
I'm going to wait two weeks until I can't return it and then find out six months later
that they're not going to have Linux, you know, at all?
I mean, cause I don't have time to play anything on Windows.
I have to, I play 15 games a week for my podcast.
So it's like, wow, you know, like I have no time for anything other than games that weren't
on Linux.
And the other thing that's depressing about it though is that I think this was a big moment
for Linux from a hardware perspective to hit a general consumer market that actually has
money.
Video games are money.
That's why Steam is such a big deal, you know, blah.
It leverages the market share, makes FOSS and supporting free and open source products
and hardware more important for, you know, graphics card manufacturers and stuff like
that.
And this is a big failure.
When I see this too, I see it as a sort of a huge disappointment, but one that I, here's,
here's where I'm going to get my temperature from, Skooky, and this is what I want to ask
you.
How much of the like configuring or aligning or calibrating or whatever you want to call
it, how much of the setup of the devices requires like a Windows application?
How much is...
Basically all of it.
You can't...
So they're going to have to recreate all of that.
They would theoretically have to redo all of that as Linux software to set this up.
Well, hang on a second.
The thing is, and they've been saying this for two years almost that they're, they were
going to hit the street.
It's not that they canceled Linux support.
It's just that now it's on the to do list and they decide to do that, you know, two
weeks ago, you know, after they've been shipping units to people.
So it's, it's theoretically, it's still coming, but no, and I've, it's, it's almost impossible
to, you need either HTC to, and I think it's legally complex for them.
I haven't gotten an official quote from them just yet, but I should at four o'clock this
afternoon.
Anyway, it's legally complicated for that, for them because of the, their partnership
with Steam and Valve, it's legally complicated for them to release their own Linux drivers
because they're like kind of tied at the hip is my understanding.
Makes me sad.
If Steam VR can't run Linux, then, you know, HTC Vive can't run Linux, which doesn't make
any sense to me because Steam VR is supposed to be built inside of Steam OS and that's
supposed to be.
I hate it when Wimpy's right, but right now Wimpy's right.
So yeah.
Okay.
All right.
So your closing thoughts, Mr. Wimpy.
I told you so.
Well said.
Oh, hold on guys.
The weaponized lawnmower is on its way back.
Well, Skookie, thank you for giving it a shot and letting us know how it went.
If people want to find your podcast where you talk about Linux gaming, where would they
find it?
Bestlinuxgames.com.
Hey-o!
And if you want to stick around towards the end, I wouldn't mind at the end of the show,
maybe we could talk a little Tomb Raider.
Oh, cool.
Oh, yes.
It's awesome.
New Tomb Raider came out for Linux and I want to give you my thoughts on it.
Before we jump into more stuff, I did want to mention briefly that OpenWRT got forked
by some of its own developers, which is always actually, I think, kind of a good thing in
a way.
It means drama, but it also means the people with the new project...
There's a passion there.
Exactly.
And they're calling it LEDE.
It appears to be a move by new project leaders.
It's a group of OpenWRT developers announced LEDE.
Their fork of the project consists of a spin-off of OpenWRT with many of the same goals.
It's, by the way, LEDE, short for Linux Embedded Development Environment.
Brilliant, really.
It will continue to focus on being a great embedded Linux distribution with a predictable
release cycle and transparent decision-making.
Hmm.
I think that could go a long way.
That's really one of the big limitations in that community right now, I think, is there's
a lot of... Especially on the DDWRT side, there's a lot of things that are up in the
air or a lot of you get your information from a forum post.
And they say, look, we just looked at doing this because the core developer count was
super low, unreliable infrastructure, and there was a lack of communication.
No hard feelings?
I mean, it sounds like maybe some, but I mean, it doesn't sound like it's a big dramatic
thing.
So LEDE, recently announced.
You can find out more.
We'll have a link in the show notes if you guys want to check that out.
Now, a question came in that struck me yesterday that I thought, well, let's just briefly touch
on it in the show.
Yeah.
XMittal points out we have LEDE, LXDE, LXLE, and LXQT.
And don't forget, later today, we're going to talk about LXCE, or LXC, right, LXCE, and
LXD.
Uh-oh, weaponized lawnmower is back.
Do you hear it?
Weaponized lawnmower.
Okay, so Tetra wrote into the show and wanted to know about our power management solutions.
And the reason why this struck me, Wes, it struck me deep, the reason why it struck me
deep and hard was because it turned out to be the first bit of feedback I read right
after my battery died.
My battery died.
Oh, boy.
I couldn't work for like two hours.
I got plugged back in, and I go to read this, and that's the question is, what's your power
management strategy?
And I thought, well, how freaking... What is it?
What is it called?
Serendipitous?
Yeah, there you go.
What's it called?
Serendipitous?
Serendipitous.
The reason why I read this is that my battery dies, and I open up my laptop, I go to get
working again, and this is what I see.
Clearly, you need a better solution.
Yes, sir.
There you go.
Right there, Wes.
So we're going to talk about that here on the show in just a moment.
I want to find out what our virtual lug does, maybe what the chat room does.
But first, I'm going to tell you what I do, and that is DigitalOcean.
Head over to DigitalOcean.com and use our special promo code, DOUNPLUG.
I love that promo code.
All one word, Wes.
It's lowercase.
Just put it together.
DOUNPLUG gives you a $10 credit.
Now, DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering you the most
intuitive way for you to get a super badass rig in the cloud in no time.
Less than 55 seconds, you'll have the machine spun up.
And if you only want to spend $5 a month, DigitalOcean's got you covered with 512 megabytes
of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte of transfer.
Now, we've been using DigitalOcean Droplets as our go-to Linux infrastructure on demand.
We need a system.
We just go to DigitalOcean now.
Pin it up.
It took a long time to increase our infrastructure for Linux Fest Northwest to make it possible
to do what we needed to do.
DigitalOcean, it was a no-brainer.
And I'll be honest with you, one of the things I've done to make my management a little easier
is I've added Noah's SSH key to my DigitalOcean profile.
So now, when I want to collaborate on a Droplet with Noah, I can just add his key as a checkbox
to any Droplet I'm creating, add my key, and I can add Rekai's key, boom, boom, boom.
Now we all have SSH login to the new Droplet I've created.
There's so many nice things about the DigitalOcean UI.
You should totally check it out.
They also have a great API.
If you want to take advantage of some OSS code built around that API or you want to
write some yourself, they have a really nice interface.
But on top of that, they got locations, New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam,
London, Toronto, Germany, all up in that business.
Go get yourself a super fast, super fast Droplet.
And they start at $5 a month and they got Ubuntu.
They got Debian.
They have Fedora.
They have CentOS, CoreOS.
And then you look at those hourly pricing, oh man.
That is really slick.
You can get a nice rig for like a couple hours and it pays very low.
You want to do something for a little while, no big deal.
If you have a horribly slow connection like I do at home, sometimes I'll spin up a DigitalOcean
Droplet to download my distro of choice over Torrent and then I'll just suck it down over
Wget later on.
Last night it was like 80 degrees in Seattle.
I didn't want my fan to kick on, but I wanted to compile a kernel, boom, DigitalOcean will
do it for you.
Seriously, it's nice.
Also, they have one-click deployments of software just ready to go and they have fantastic,
fantastic documentation, probably one that we've almost taken for granted.
How to install the LAMP stack, Apache MySQL, PHP on Ubuntu 16.04.
How to install NGINX, MySQL and PHP, the LIMP stack, LEMP, LIMP stack, which is NGINX on
Ubuntu.
How to install WordPress on Ubuntu.
What's new in Ubuntu in 16.04.
How to use NGINX and Let's Encrypt together.
An introduction to configuration management.
You can go from zero to like Linux Admin Hero on DigitalOcean.
Or you know what, it's not just Linux, it's also FreeBSD too.
I know, that's one of their more trickier things.
They also have extremely good documentation on FreeBSD.
But all the different distros, I mean everything they support, it's a really great, great service.
And you can use our promo code DOUNPLUCT to get a $10 credit, try out their $5 rig, two
months for free at DigitalOcean.com.
Big thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Okay Wes, I've talked about Subsonic before.
In fact, Subsonic, when people would come to me and they'd say, hey Chris, what are
you doing for media streaming?
Hey Chris, what are you doing to listen to those sweet tunes?
Yeah, exactly.
Or what are you doing for podcast management?
And this was a big one, and man did I love it, dude.
I would have Subsonic centrally download my podcast and then I would listen to them and
oh man, Subsonic was a great way to essentially set up Plex for your audio.
And I had it installed, loved it, used the web UI, used all the different apps built
off of it.
Well, we have a little breaking news right here on the Unplugged program.
Subsonic is going closed source.
Starting with 6.0, Subsonic will no longer be open source.
The main reason, according to one of the developers, is that the source code now contains software
license codes that they purchased, literally what they said.
Software license codes that I have purchased that shouldn't be used by Fork Projects.
Now Subsonic West is one of these projects that has sort of been slowly moving towards
this position for a while.
It's one of these things that if you've been following the project, you kind of suspected
this was coming.
And it does happen from time to time in open source.
And a couple of first reactions come to me like, well, who the hell are you?
How dare you?
Right?
Of course, they're the developers and creators.
They get to do whatever they like.
Yeah, that's exactly who the hell they are.
And then my other reaction is, well, screw you.
I'll go find something else, right?
Forking Subsonic by.
Yeah.
Anybody in the Mamba Room a Subsonic user before I move on from that?
Because I think that's kind of a big deal.
If you've been dependent on this open source project, it's been around for years and years,
all of a sudden, closed source.
Yeah.
It sucks.
I understand like with the complexities, especially like the licensing open source and keeping
things free and open source is more difficult now than it's ever been.
Keeping straight all the licenses of the stuff that you actually use to assemble your product.
Anyway, Subsonic looked heavy handed to me anyway, but it still sucks.
It was efficacious.
Yeah.
Now, Wimpy, you're a Subsonics user and donator.
Tell me about Subsonics.
Well, there are several tools like this, but I've had good success with Subsonic over the
years.
And once you start building up your library, I've got not a DigitalOcean droplet, but a
VPS somewhere that runs my Subsonic stuff and it acts as offsite backup for our music.
And it's my on the internet streaming service.
So Subsonics is, is it a fork of Subsonic?
No, sorry.
Subsonic is what I'm using at the moment and yeah, and I understand there are forks of
Subsonics that I haven't used.
And I've got a couple of that I'll talk about.
So you, you are using the project that has now gone closed source in the new version?
No, I haven't upgraded to the new version.
And how do you feel about this?
I mean, this is something, the only reason I ask you is because, you know, as longtime
Linux users, from time to time this happens.
Do you just roll with the punches when something like this happens or are you outraged and
ready to take to the streets with pitchforks and a fire?
I'm not outraged.
I'm a little bit disappointed because I thought the reason that I was donating to this project
was in order to keep it open source and now I've ended up funding a proprietary project.
So I'm not super enthusiastic about that.
This is my complaint right here.
You just, yeah.
I will be looking elsewhere in due course.
What about if it's just remains free?
Is that all it really takes, as long as it stays free, then you're good?
I'm talking free as in freedom, not free as in beer.
I have no problem paying for any, anything, like, you know, a service, you know, or like
a podcast, like, you know, like Unfilter or whatever, or NPR, or any sort of software
solution that's, you know, efficacious, I have no problem paying for it so long as it's
free.
I mean, it has to be, you know, free as in freedom, not free as in beer.
Trevor Burrus So like Wimpy just touched on, there are several
alternatives.
Now, Subsonic kind of, it gives you a centralized on your land Spotify using your own library
if you will.
It also, it works with multiple media formats.
It could also do some transcoding.
It is in a lot of ways a lot like Plex too.
It could go out and get metadata information, centralized playlists.
So in that sort of same vein, Madsonic is one that I've heard a lot.
Madsonic is a web-based media streamer.
It's a fork of Subsonic.
It is based on some Java.
It runs on Linux.
And one of the nice things about it, if you have constrained bandwidth, you can set upper
limits on the music and it can re-encode some of the music for you if you want to stream,
which is kind of nice.
Matthew Feeney That is very nice, especially on, you know,
you're on the bus or whatever.
Trevor Burrus Yeah.
And it's supposed to be easy to use.
If you have, you know, 100,000 files in your music library, you're not going to have any
problems.
It's GPLed.
And so that's, this is madsonic.org.
You can find it at beta.madsonic.org.
But you know, Wes, I'm going to tell you about the one that kind of caught my attention.
The one that I kind of liked was Cherry Music.
Matthew Feeney Ooh.
Trevor Burrus Yeah, same thing.
Matthew Feeney That's pretty cherry.
Trevor Burrus GPL, easy to set up, get a go, blazingly fast
search.
Yep.
They've got apps that work with it.
It'll automatically go get the cover art.
Super quick setup, which I think is really nice.
Matthew Feeney I might stand this up pretty soon here.
That looks awesome.
Trevor Burrus Yeah, it does.
Here, I'll show you a few screenshots.
This is Cherry Music, kind of the same deal.
For those of you that are familiar with Subsonic, the functionality will look familiar.
Oh, the screen.
Oh, there it goes.
But the UI is a little nicer.
So this is a really easy way to have like, if you want to have a bunch of your audio
music on a central file server, but then have everyone have the same playlist throughout
the house.
This was always a problem that Angela and I had is we had the same music library a lot
of the time where she'd have like, well actually for a long time she had her own library, I
had my own library, we had our own playlists and all this.
And then we wanted to like, well, we're going to have people over, let's have a playlist
that plays in the living room.
Okay, well whose computer did you know, and it was just like, oh, do you want to bring
it up?
Matthew Feeney Now you're choosing between them and switching.
Trevor Burrus Yeah, and so then all the energy and effort
goes into one spot.
And that's why we set up Subsonic and we're able to have like party mix playlists and
like Christmas playlists and she could go set it up on the thing and then I would just
play it.
Matthew Feeney That's awesome.
Trevor Burrus It was a very nice setup.
Plus, you're taking advantage of the centralized network storage at that point and you're just
throwing this on top of it.
So Cherry Music, which I like a lot, the URL is a little weird, so I'll just, you'll have
to go find the link in the show notes, but I like that one.
Amachi?
Apanchi?
Inagogo says it's
Matthew Feeney Ampachi?
Trevor Burrus Ampachi.
Ampachi.org.
A-M-P-A-C-H-E.org.
And also, it looks like Rekai is recommending Syrenza, which is another one there.
Boy, there's a few of these.
Cherry Music is the one I picked, but it looks like if you're in the chat room, you could
totally score some links for a couple other alternatives as well.
I'm going through all of them right now.
There's a whole bunch in here.
I like that one.
You know, I should also mention, like Grandell is mentioning in the chat room, Plex is aggressively
going after this category too.
Plex is aggressively going after music.
So this is another
Matthew Feeney I was about to say, yeah.
Trevor Burrus This is bad timing on Subsonics' part because
Plex is attempting to go this way too.
Matthew Feeney And so many people have Plex at their house
already.
Trevor Burrus Well, Syrenza looks nice.
This looks really nice, Rekai.
Good find.
That does look like a good one.
And Ampachi.
Ampachi.org.
Ampachi or whatever.
It looks really good too.
Ooh, visualizers, Wes.
Look at that.
Hey, what's up?
What's up?
You get those visualizers.
Yeah.
So I guess I wanted to end just a quick note on
I don't know about you.
You know what?
I'll ask Wimpy because Wimpy has actually donated money.
So let's ask Wimpy.
Wimpy, did you have a sense this was coming?
Because I'll be honest, I had a sense this was coming.
Watching the Subsonic project, I had a feeling they were going this direction.
Did you have that same feeling even as a donator?
What was it?
What was it that sort of set off your spider sense, if you will?
Matthew Feeney It's the fact that when you install it, you
have to put a license in to use it fully.
It sort of very heavily influences you to donate in order to get a key.
To use the product completely and it nags you and it felt like it was going this route.
Some of the wording on the website sounded a bit plaintive about not getting the appropriate
donations for the number of people using it and I just sort of got a sense that it was
on its way.
So yeah, I'm not surprised.
I also am a Plex subscriber as well, but in my opinion, Plex isn't really there for music
playback just yet.
It's improved significantly in the last year or so, but it is not a good music manager
and playlist organizer and player at all.
Aaron Powell I agree.
That's essentially my assessment of it too.
So before we move, I did want to mention just really briefly the power management strategies.
Is it still a thing in 2016 to go through a bunch of hoops to set up the perfect power
management?
And I ask you as someone who has sort of taken a backseat to this recently, I don't bother
doing things like installing and configuring TLP.
I don't really consider watching Power Top to see what's eating up all of my battery.
I just assume that in 2016 I can install a modern operating system and not have to worry
about power management.
But maybe I'm wrong.
And I'll start Wimpy with you.
It sounds like you still think TLP is worth loading on if you have a laptop, correct?
Wimpy Wimpy Yep.
It's installed by default in Ubuntu Mate, has been for several releases now.
Aaron Powell Now, what do you notice the difference?
I mean, it must be a huge difference to make it default.
Wimpy Wimpy Personally, I've noticed a significant difference
in the power savings.
That combined with managing your screen brightness appropriately because that can make a big difference.
But there was another podcaster recently installed Ubuntu Mate on their main laptop.
I won't say what distribution they replaced, but they were quoting a two-hour battery life
improvement as a result of installing Ubuntu Mate.
And the only significant difference there is that it comes pre-installed with TLP.
And on some of my older computers, I can definitely measure the improvement in hours rather than
minutes.
Aaron Powell Hmm, Skookie, you said yes, definitely, if you're
using Arch.
Why do you say that?
Wimpy Wimpy Oh, well, okay.
So about three years ago, and I don't know if you remember this, but I got a Galaga Ultra
Pro from System76.
And I slapped Integra, I still run Arch on that.
It's great.
It's awesome.
But in order to get anything other than like, literally, basic, basic, I mean, we're talking
like, I would get like an hour and 15 minutes out of the battery until you had to go through
the whole Arch horrific documentation, you know, that whole hour and a half long wall
of text to configure everything appropriately.
But now, you know, like I get, you know, four and a half hours.
It's an older laptop, but it's still awesome.
Aaron Powell Okay, Popey, I'm turning to you because I'm
hoping you're going to tell me.
I do nothing.
I install Ubuntu, and I use it like a regular user and I get great battery life.
Is that true?
Or does Popey jump through hoops to get good battery life?
Wimpy Wimpy So I recently had to reinstall on my new laptop.
And I just installed it and I didn't do anything at all.
However, I have somewhat worked around the issue, because my laptop has two batteries,
one internal and one external, and I bought a second battery.
So in the event that my power dies, I can just swap out the battery while I'm running
and not have a problem.
So I've kind of worked around the problem.
Aaron Powell So you're kind of like I am sort of like that
because with the Bonobo, the battery life was going to be two and a half hours, three
hours regardless after a couple of years, right?
It's a big desktop killer with a small and I just got I just became honey badger about
the battery.
But here I am with the Apollo now it was Skylake and I'm getting almost six hours without a
lot of effort.
And I'm starting to think, all right, well, maybe if I dial this in a little bit because
I was in the middle of an awesome Minecraft mod exploration with the kids last night and
then my battery died and I and my dad, my son was like, Dad, why didn't you bring your
power cord?
Well, I normally I don't need it.
I didn't plan on running Java, son.
I mean, right.
Oh, my God.
Do you ever just run power top and change all the configurable and this is the other
thing is I have in the past, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
This is CNN breaking news.
Wimpy you're telling me seven hours and 30 minutes on your Apollo.
Yes, comfortably.
And it's OK.
All right.
There you go.
I got to do it.
I mean, if I could get another hour and a half out of my machine.
Yeah.
Holy smokes.
I will say I also was using that Apricity OS, which based on Arch for a while, they
have TLP installed by default.
And that also I've noticed is run for quite a long time.
All right.
I'm going to put it looks here.
Look at the archway.
You pretty much just install it and start it and I'm going to do it.
I'm going to have no excuse.
I will give it a go.
I'm going to put the link in the show notes.
If you guys are curious about that, I will toss it in there.
So it sounds like TLP in 2016.
Still worth doing.
Not that I didn't think it was.
I'm just a little disappointed.
Is that weird?
I just wish that I just I guess I look at I look at like those love the frickin MacBook
with the single USB port that supposedly gets 12 years of battery life and you breathe on
it and it gets another two hours of battery life just by like breathing on it.
I look at that and I go, man, I wish we had something kind of similar to that.
But then with the Apollo, I get so damn close.
Just seems like it might be worth a little bit.
And the TLP setup requires no config.
All right.
Well, there you go.
Yeah.
So there you go.
That seems like the way to go.
Not to report back next week.
See how long you can go.
Yeah.
I mean, I was also considering for a little while doing battery life tests more more like
standardized.
Yeah.
But to me, it's a lot of work.
It also it seems like it's so dependent on your workload, like your screen brightness
is a huge part of it.
So it feels like a little bit of black magic.
Like people can talk big, but you have to put in a fair bit to like get a workload that
you can use as an example consistently.
Yeah.
OK.
And you know what?
If those of you out there in the audience have experimented a little bit with TLP and
your different experience, I would just be I would like to know.
I would like to know what you have seen out there.
So links to everything we've talked about so far, including Cherry Music, Madsonic, TLP
and all that stuff over at Jupiterbroadcasting.com.
Just go look for episode 143 of the Unplugged program.
We are about to talk a little bit about Linux containers, yes, Linux containers, everybody,
and how they can be relevant to you and I. Wes, you are a soldier, sir.
You have experimented and gone off and upgraded a bunch of your servers to Ubuntu 16.04.
That's right.
You've begun experimenting with Linux containers.
So before we get to all of that, I want to mention Linux Academy.
If I say the word container and you go, I don't actually know what that means.
If that thought has crossed the back of your head, maybe you should check out Linux Academy.
Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged.
Go there to take advantage of the unplugged discount and support this show.
Linux Academy.
Just so you guys know, this is the essentials created by people that love Linux and want
to spread the word.
They wanted a platform, so they went and found a great group of developers and enthusiasts.
They came together.
They created the Linux Academy.
They now have 2,379 self-paced courses, comprehensive study guides you get to download.
You can be like a Skookie Sprite there and listen in the shower, download them.
I love that story.
And you know, Seth might have been the first person to tell me that he listens in the shower,
but he was certainly not the last person to tell me that, which I think is kind of funny.
They have scenario-based labs, which will put you right in the middle of every day,
common tasks.
They have nuggets that will go deep into one single topic, you know, might last about
two minutes, might be an hour, depends on the topic.
They have live events.
They have instructor mentoring, which is huge.
They'll teach you how to use all of the technology around Linux, the essentials, the advanced
topics and the stuff that will make you money on Linux, the stuff you can use to improve
your career, the stuff you can use to charge clients, the stuff you can use to better your
knowledge set.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Graded server exercises will give you real results.
It's nice.
Seven plus distros to choose from.
They're always updating the content.
You know, I talked about containers kind of jokingly, but seriously, I can't envision
a better resource to learn more about containers.
Like they are passionate about this stuff.
They were writing a courseware on Docker while other people were joking about it.
They understand where things are going because they are so enthusiastic about this and they
have a great, great set of courseware on containers.
Now we're about to get into containers and if anything we talk about intrigues you, go
check them out at LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
All right, Mr. West.
So you said to me, OK, Chris, I know we've talked about Ubuntu 16.04 a lot, but let's
be real.
We've mostly focused on the desktop where we've trashed on it a little bit.
I mean, does anyone even use Linux on the desktop?
I don't know.
No, I kid.
Obviously.
Oh, my gosh.
But, you know, there's the whole other element of the Ubuntu server.
The server where it's actually hugely successful.
So have you used it at all?
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Andr, wait, do I have any local 16.04 servers?
No.
No, I don't.
I only have, I only have digital ocean droplets, but we've got a handful of them now.
And I don't really have anything to say.
I guess that's a good thing.
Yeah, they just they just freaking run.
We've set up a software on them.
We have some 14.04 droplets.
We want to move to 16.04 because we I'll tell you one.
OK, OK, OK.
I'll tell you one thing that I have noticed.
OK.
It is a pain in the ass now to like it is a major pain in the ass to write and it scripts
for upstart.
And it's like the last thing I want to do.
It's the last thing anybody on the JB crew wants to do is learn upstart at this point.
Oh, my gosh.
Yes.
Who wants to learn upstart?
No.
It's dead.
Yeah, exactly.
And here's the other thing is that tons of the projects I've been using for a while now
have system dnit scripts.
Yep.
They come.
They're right there.
Yes.
So that is sort of the nicest thing about 16.04 is now I'm just like looking.
I can use those examples and things, but that's pretty much the entire summary of my review
from servers.
It works.
I don't really have any complaints.
And it does everything I expect, which, by the way, exactly what I want on my server.
It just it just it.
Yeah, it's consistent.
So you, however, you, however, have had a bit of a bigger route.
I'm in the weird position of like, I mean, I use arch for a lot of things.
It's the most what I'm most familiar these days with I know how to, you know, bend it
to my will get whatever I done need to do done with it.
I'm in the position where I'm considering switching to Ubuntu for for a lot of my larger
services, mostly because of Lex D as they call it, which is Lex D 2.0 is just released
and that's their container lighter visor, they jokingly call it and it's and it's meant
to be a new way to interact with the Linux container or Lexi subsystem in the infrastructure
they've set up.
So if you're not familiar, you can go to Linux containers.com, I believe.
Yeah, Linux containers.org, dot org, backslash, Alex deep backslash, try dash it, which we
will have a link in the show.
And you can give it a try right now.
And it's a now hold on.
When you say give it a try.
You mean I can go to a web page and I can spin up a Alex D container in real time?
Yeah, let's do it.
Let's do it right now.
You want to do it?
OK, here we go.
So I am at Linux containers.org, slash Alex D, slash try dash it again, link in the show.
Yeah, where's the IPv6 connectivity, Chris?
Oh, the studio.
I know, right?
So I'm going to say I've accepted the terms of service because, of course, I do.
They're pretty reasonable.
Now, they are going to start the container on the fly now because we just gave up the
URL.
It's going to get slow here.
But before it gets slow, you can see right here, Wes, right here, boom, I got a console.
I got an Alex D container.
I'm now root inside a container nested inside an Alex D install, which is sort of like Alex
D inception.
Yes, right.
What am I seeing here, Wes?
What am I seeing?
You're seeing they ran Alex C exec container name bash, and it just gets you executed as
root inside the container, a bash shell.
This is pretty cool.
This is a pretty cool way to do it.
Yeah, it's pretty neat.
So one of the neat things that they've Alex C was pretty complicated to use.
It's really neat to use if you've ever tried it, if you need like system level containers.
But there's a lot of things to learn and a lot of configuration things to set up.
Sure.
Alex D or Alex D, it's a lot simpler.
And so you can kind of just get an image going and they have default profiles set up.
So the default one, it runs as an unprivileged container, meaning that it actually runs in
a user namespace.
So that root in the container is no longer root on your host.
It's actually matched to like UID 1 million or something like that.
So hopefully that get you some added security.
But it also has like default profiles if you want to run Docker in there, you just change
your container to be on the Docker profile and they tweak some of the security settings
and the like nesting settings so that you can run Docker inside your container.
So you're just starting to play with this.
But how's the workflow?
But is it pretty easy to use?
It's neat.
So Alex C used kind of a template workflow, so where you'd use something like pack strap
or bootstrap or whatever to like get your container implemented on the machine you're
running it on.
Lex D uses an image-based format, so you actually just have like a tar gz of your container
root file system.
And it also takes great advantage of ZFS.
It's awesome.
So like in 16.04 you just install the userland tools, the kernel module is built for you,
you just load that up.
It has a pseudo LXD in it and it'll walk you through and it'll even set you up like a loopback
mounted ZFS file system if you want.
So that's what I'm using on the laptop here.
Or if you want to have, you know, you have actual like pool of disk to use, you can use
that or use one that you already have.
And so what that means is when you want to use like a new, they give you some image servers
by default with the like, you know, Ubuntu 16.04 container image.
You can just pull that down.
But once you have that image, every new container you start, it's just a copy on write copy
of that, right?
So it's basically free except for what you change it.
That's slick.
And all, again, super easy to set up.
And I've already set up like an archiver.
So they don't have, they have like Alpine, they have Fedora.
So you're saying, you're saying you have, okay, so for example, if I were to do this
on a, on a droplet, I could have an Ubuntu 16.04 droplet, but in the container run arch.
Yep, absolutely.
So they don't have one provided on there.
They have like an image, images.linuxcontainers.org, where they have like Fedora, Cora, like lots
of prebuilt stuff for you, but arch wasn't one of them.
But you just take a, you know, you make a reasonable arch file system, you package it
up in a tar and it's really easy to get it as your own.
Then you can, they, the other neat thing is it's a networked, like it's all done over
a REST API.
That's like, that's how the client talks to it.
That's how you can talk to it.
They have Python bindings and it also talks over the network.
So I can have a server here and then a server on a droplet somewhere and I can go make myself
a new image, have containers here.
And if I make a container I really like here, I can just push it over to the server and
it will run there.
That is nice.
Talk about rapid development.
You can even snapshot up here, then push the snapshot up to this.
It's I'm really excited.
I might have to change a lot of my infrastructure to use this now.
That is super, super neat and sounds like it didn't take a ton of time to figure out
how to get down.
I'm consistently surprised with how easy it is.
Huh.
I got to play with that.
Cool.
Okay.
So the chat room has been talking about a topic, Wes, that I want to cover before I
get to my Lara Croft review because there has been something we have done a few times
on the show is we've given Mr. Leo Laporte a hard time.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
About his Linux coverage.
And so I feel like it's only fair when Leo sits down and does his homework and does a
pretty good job of it at that, that we give it some attention.
So I want to just play a moment from the recent, the new screensavers on some help he gave
on Linux.
On the line.
Let's do it.
On the line with us right now.
I don't know your name, sir.
Who is this?
Jason.
Jason is on the line.
Hi, Jason.
Where are you calling from?
Hi, Leo.
Calling from Manhattan, Kansas.
I want to talk to you.
There he is.
So, Jason, tell us, tell us your question.
Well, I've been a long time Linux, sorry, Linux user.
I grew up calling it Linux.
I know.
A lot of people did.
Yeah.
But I've got a handful of older computers, netbooks.
We're talking core two duos, nothing really older than that.
I've tried some of the slimmed down versions of Linux, either Laboon 2 or LXDE, even Puppy
Linux.
Puppy's a little too techie.
I'd like something that, a slimmed down version that'll run well, looking to run Flash, DVDs.
Flash?
Flash.
I know.
Still trying to run YouTube.
Well, you don't need YouTube, doesn't need Flash anymore, so you can...
Oh, that's true.
You're right.
Yeah.
I'm hoping that...
By the way, who needs Flash?
Twit.tv still runs Flash, because we use a player.
We don't have control of it that plays back Ustream and BitGravity, and they're using
Flash.
Although they're moving away from it, as our providers do.
I'm hoping we won't see Flash much longer.
It's dying, as everybody knows.
As it should.
So...
I'm looking for suggestions for something else that's...
Maybe not something else, but a different spin of Linux that works well with older hardware,
but not too techie.
Something that I can put on it and basically hand to my mom.
There's the kicker.
Unfortunately, this is almost a contradiction in terms, right?
I think this is kind of non-intuitive, but I've always said that the more a person is
a novice, the better the computer they need.
Not the vice versa, because...
So he's been...
The vice versa.
He's been talking about Linux a lot.
He goes into a whole description here about Cinnamon.
He does a whole...
Professor Leo.
Yeah.
He gets all...
We use this kind of generic term Linux for something that's really so much more.
The only thing that's Linux is the stuff way down here.
This is the kernel.
And that's the stuff that Linus Torvalds wrote back in 1994 or 92 when he was a graduate
student in Finland.
He wrote...
I feel like I'm in school.
What's nice about...
I know.
And you know what's funny about this?
And I'll leave the link in the show notes if you guys want to watch the whole thing.
What's funny about this is it tells me two things about Linux adoption.
Number one, we are so screwed.
And number two, it's great to have Leo as an advocate.
Yeah, it is.
The first thing it tells me is, and I'm not joking when I say this, you need a fricking
whiteboard if you're a Windows or Mac user to figure out, or I'm sorry, chalkboard in
this case, how to use Linux.
Like Leo talks about the fact that he has a dozen thumb drives with different Linux
distros on there.
He talks about trying Debian.
He talks about trying Mint.
He talks about trying Zubuntu and Unity.
And he talks about trying Antigros.
He has gone through a sludge of crap to get to where he's at now.
It's too much.
Right.
It takes an average savvy Windows user to do what he's done.
So anyways, it's interesting.
And I'm glad he's trying it.
And it's a good advocate.
But yeah, he actually seems to know what he's talking about.
I'm impressed.
Yeah.
Now maybe he could play with LXDE and LXD or LXC, not LXDE, and tell us what he thinks.
I'm excited about that, Wes.
OK.
So let's get to it.
I've been teasing it all episode.
Tomb Raider is finally here for Linux.
The 2013 edition of Tomb Raider is available for Linux.
And I had a chance to give it a try.
And I've got to say, I'm not too disappointed.
If you're watching here, Wes, this was something I played a little bit earlier on the livestream.
This was me playing a little Tomb Raider.
And the graphics are pretty good.
Now if you're watching this back on the video version, you're watching an encoding of an
encoding.
So you know, the graphics are going to be what they are.
Careful.
But I'll tell you, this game is fun.
First of all, it's very immersive.
The one downside I'll have is there's a lot of quick time events, like this right here.
You're running around.
All of a sudden, it just takes over.
Now you just watch.
You have like a token key you have to press from time to time.
But they do a good job of making Lara Croft feel like a real character.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
And I'll tell you, Wes, I have a special connection.
Look at that.
Very painful.
Yeah.
They are violent with Lara in this game.
They get really rough.
Lara.
They are.
They are really rough with her, like ridiculously so.
But you know, when I first played Tomb Raider, it was when I had a Matrox video card and
I upgraded it.
Oh, Matrox.
Never heard that name for a while.
I know.
And I popped in four megabytes of VRAM.
I had a grand total from two megabytes to four megabytes.
And my four, my two megabyte upgrade came with the Tomb Raider CD.
Oh, very cool.
Yeah.
That was my first Tomb Raider experience.
I remember the original Tomb Raider.
Yeah.
So even though it's a 2013 game, it's still very fun for me to be able to try it.
And it supports Linux mail.
The graphics are great.
Yeah.
It looks beautiful.
Sorry.
The actress who does the voice work for Lara Croft, Keely Hawes, was recently on a TV
program talking about this, you know, and the work that she had to do and how much work
that she did in this new Lara Croft thing.
And she talked about the fact that her son loves to play the game and it's a bit weird
for her to hear her own voice screaming out at her son.
Yeah.
But it's awesome.
Yeah, it is very cool to see these great games coming to Linux.
And yeah, it's maybe not the best game ever, but I've really enjoyed playing it.
So if you're looking to buy a Steam game-
How are the system requirements, Chris?
Well, you got to have, that's actually one of the nice things I like about it is you
got to have, while you do have to have a decent system, Wes, they have a built in benchmark.
Oh, nice.
So here, I'll launch it right now.
So you can get a sense of if it's going to work on your rig.
And I know how nice of a machine you have now.
Oh, so, and I don't know, Mr. Skookiesprite, have you had a chance to try out the new Tomb
Raider?
You know, doing your best Linux games podcast, you got to be trying these things, right?
Are you kidding?
I beat it in the first 14 hours of it coming out for Linux.
It like launched on Steam at like 11 o'clock at night.
I was just going to bed and I'm like, oh, Tomb Raider, okay, well, I better probably
play this.
So I played it in one 10 hour sitting, and then I had meetings that morning and three
hours later, I finished it off 10 hours later.
I think it's awesome.
It's one of the best adventure games I've ever played.
And it's easily the best looking game I've ever played on Linux.
So I'm running the benchmark right now, which you say, benchmarks not so accurate, is it?
Oh, God, no, it's like, on mine, it says like the average is like, the average frame rate
is like 222 frames per second or something like that.
It's just out of control.
It's like, it's old and weird.
So what I think it is, is I actually think that, I don't, I get like 80 or something.
I can't remember.
I'm benchmarking right now.
I'll tell you in a second.
But I think the game still has some glitches under Linux.
There's a few performance glitches here and there.
I'll get a one benchmark for the frame rate and then I end up with a completely different
thing during gameplay.
But as you watch this benchmark, you can see they add cool effects and stuff.
It's pretty nice.
Go ahead, Scooby.
One of the things that's weird, because like the second I beat it, I started playing it
again because that's how much I enjoyed it on hard.
And this time, I had some problems with janky camera angles in my first 20 hours of the
game.
And it seems like either they pushed an update to it or something, but I have not had any
camera problems.
And especially if you run it on normal instead of like high, to like the settings, it makes
a big difference in the performance because it cuts down on the reflections, I think.
Yeah, I agree.
The benchmark is a little crazy.
So I just got on the benchmark.
I got 80.6 minimum as my minimum frames per second.
And I got max of 170.3 with an average of...
Yeah, that's not happening.
That's crazy.
That's totally crazy.
That's so ridiculous.
It's like during the menus.
Yeah.
Well, it's like they do like this cool panorama view where they like load more and more stuff.
So you'd think it'd be accurate, but it's got to be like some sort of best case scenario.
I don't know.
A couple of other just quick notes, Steam Sync works, so I played it for a little bit
on my computer upstairs.
It's able to resume right away.
Oh, I love that.
Yeah.
Also, Linux Game Cast and the Linux Gamer gave some great reviews of this game.
I'll have links to those in the show notes.
And Mr. Skookiesprite, again, give people a plug where they can find your podcast.
I assume you'll be talking about this.
Oh, yeah.
No, I already reviewed it on Saturday.
Atta boy.
Bestlinuxgames.com.
Check it out.
.com.
I will have a link to that as well in the show notes, so that way you guys can follow
the reviews of all of that.
I'm excited to see a good game come out because this was like one of my first, like, I built
a PC and then I upgraded from two megabytes of VRAM to four megabytes and got Tomb Raider.
So yeah, right?
That was a big deal for me.
I really thought that was huge.
Anyways, that'll pretty much wrap us up for this week's episode of The Unplugged Program.
If you want to give us some feedback.
Please do.
LinuxActionShow.reddit.com.
That's where you go.
Or jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Slash contact.
Mumble room, is there anything else that the collective hive mind wants to cover before
we wrap up on this week's episode?
Going once.
Going twice.
I've never installed GNU slash Linux.
Oh!
And there you have it.
There you have it.
RMS runs GNU slash K Windows.
Thank you for joining us on this week's episode of The Unplugged Program.
We do it over at jblive.tv.
Go to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to find out what is live in your local time
zone.
Like we said earlier, LinuxActionShow.reddit.com is where you go.
Now that virtual log, that's powered by Mumble.
Woo!
Open source software.
Yes it is.
And you can find out more about it by doing Bang Mumble in our IRC room, which is irc.geekshed.net.
If you stream this on YouTube live.tv, join us on jblive.tv next week.
We'd love to see you there.
Okay everybody.
Thanks so much for tuning in to this week's episode of Unplugged.
And we'll see you right back here, next Tuesday!
Hot tip from crack editor Rekai.
It looks like the Steam Controller is on sale right now.
Have you ever given that another chance?
You know, I should, huh?
Especially with newer kernels?
40% off.
It seems like it might be worth time to give it another chance.
That's a good deal.
That is a good deal.
So you know, when I shaved the stache on Sunday, I didn't think about how the children would
react.
Oh right, that's a big deal.
I remember when my dad shaved his beard as a young child.
Yes!
It's like, who are you?
It is actually a big deal, and I totally didn't think about that, because I remember when
my dad had a beard and then went to no beard.
It's a big deal.
It was a big deal!
And so I shaved on Sunday afternoon, right, and then I saw the kids Monday.
And I gotta tell you, the reaction was not good.
No.
Abby told me it was dumb.
Oh, wow, that's cold.
But you know what Dylan told me?
Dad, my dream is to grow a beard and a mustache.
How could you shave it?
That's what my son said.
So how'd you explain it?
Did you tell him?
Dad, it's too funny.
Uncle Noah did too well.
And then my youngest, my youngest said, Daddy, did you do that for Noah?
And I said, yes, Bella, I did it for Noah.
I hate Noah now.
He took the beard away.
You know what Bella said?
It's okay, Daddy.
I still like your hair.
I love my kids, dude.
So perfect.
So it was like, yeah, okay, good, good, that makes me feel better.
But all of them unanimously agreed, I gotta grow it back.
I gotta grow it back.
Now- Or you could shave, go all the way.
Go all the way?
Yeah.
I don't think so.
Oh, man.
You know, I am a geek because I totally love this post.
And this was such a, this was clickbait for Linux users.
If I was a Linux fish, I would be cut, filleted, and served on a Alder wood platter right now
because Tech Mint totally got me with 20 funny commands for Linux.
Okay, all right.
Let's do it real fast.
So first of all, did you know that there's something called, there's a package called
SL?
Do you know about SL?
Oh, yeah.
You do?
You do know about it?
Steam locomotive.
Oh, look at you.
All right.
So let's, I'm gonna do a packer search for SL right now.
I absolutely never install it, but I am familiar.
So oh boy, there's a whole bunch of stuff.
I don't know, of course, a whole bunch of open SSL stuff came up when I searched for
that.
That was a horrible idea.
What was I thinking?
Of course, this is a total, absolute and complete, look at this list, dude.
This list is 20 pages long.
I just, okay, you know what I'm gonna do just for sake of content, I'm gonna just install
SL and see what we get.
Because why not, right?
Let's just find out.
Well, I've got my container right here.
All right.
So now I'm installed on my machine.
I'm gonna run SL.
Are you ready?
So first of all, I want to launch it in a terminal window.
So I'll hold it.
Here we go.
Let's go find out what SL is.
SL.
It's a steam locomotive.
Look at that.
Isn't that beautiful?
It actually is really cool.
That is really cool.
So there is this, there is this post over at TechBind about the 20 awesome Linux commands.
You know what?
Hold on a second.
Telnet.
I don't even know if I have Telnet installed.
Telnet and then blinkinglights.nl.
Let's see.
I don't even know.
Oh, classic.
Oh, I do have Telnet installed.
All right.
So here we go.
So what do I do, Wes?
Do you know what I do after this point?
Just watch.
Just stand by and watch.
Okay.
I'm watching.
I maximize.
Maybe I don't need to maximize.
Hmm.
So this is supposed to be the 20th century.
Oh yeah, here we go.
Yeah, it's Star Wars.
It's Star Wars and the Terminal.
Oh yeah.
I knew it.
Star Wars and the Terminal.
Oh, what's this one?
Command toilet.
I don't think I've heard of that one before.
No.
Are you serious?
Number nine.
Hold on.
Scroll your ass down there.
Terminal.
Okay.
Toilet.
Install toilet.
All right.
Do you think toilet is a package in art?
Let's find out.
It's a package everywhere.
It's been around for years and years and years.
How come I don't know about it?
This is what I'm asking myself.
How do you not know all of these?
I know.
This list is, not only is it horrible, obvious clickbait, but it is totally old command.
Some of them are like, message of the day, like, okay.
I know about-
Yes.
Yeah.
All right.
Okay.
I'm installing toilet right now.
All right.
And I'm going to run toilet.
I've never had a toilet command.
Hold on.
I don't want to run it in Guake.
I want to give toilet its own dedicated terminal.
So let me open up its own dedicated gnome terminal just for toilet.
Okay.
All right.
Here we go.
Tab completing toilet.
Are you ready, Wes?
I've never been more ready.
What happens when you run it?
You have to give it some text.
Okay.
Oh, okay.
Off fart.
Oh.
Okay.
So that's all it does?
Is it just-
Do toilet dash dash gay.
And then the piece of text.
It's much nicer.
Dash dash gay?
Yes.
Dash dash gay and then do I do the text on the same command line or do I wait for-
Yeah.
Do toilet dash dash gay space.
Hello world or something.
Okay.
All right.
Hello.
Do I need to use quotes?
No.
Hello world.
Okay.
Oh.
Now that is great.
Look at it.
It's a rainbow.
And if you do toilet dash dash gay dash dash IRC hello world, then it gives you all the
ANSI codes that you could paste into IRC.
You know, I think I have seen this before now that I see it.
How did I not know about this?
This is so wonderful.
Thank you, Popeye.
You're welcome.
I like that Popeye is our official expert on the toilet command.
Thank you, Za.
Of course.
There's a snap package in the store for toilets.
Oh, beautiful.