No one can fully replace the Fedora Project.
Absolutely not, exactly.
Don't worry, Ian, it'll be just a pale comparison,
but you know what?
Rumor has it you have some experience with Fedora Atomic,
which is kind of topic irrelevant right now.
Relevant, not irrelevant, so I think it's gonna slide.
Absolutely, and Dusty does even more than I do,
so that'll be great.
All right, there we go.
All right, gentlemen, well, let's start the show.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 255 for June 26, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's deploying containers with cockpit like a madman.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Brent.
Hello, Brent.
Yeah, Wes is out on vacay this week.
I think he's on some kind of road trip.
Who even knows, but we'll get into that.
Coming up on this week's episode of the Unplugged program,
we have many community announcements to make for you,
including some great news for the Blender Project,
a little bit of a background Skunk Works project
that I'm working on, a Flatpak history,
and then a couple, perhaps three, maybe two gentlemen
from the Fedora Project.
It's all still getting ironed out.
We'll be joining us to talk about Fedora Core OS
and many other things that are happening
in the Fedora community.
Plus, GTK 3's got a big update.
Neon's going for the 1804 push and looking for testing.
But be careful before you make the plunge.
Firefox is back.
And they've got a lot of attention.
And they think, perhaps, local processing, not
cloud processing, might be the future of their success.
And are you ready to replace MP3 at least for your podcasts?
We'll tell you about a new, yes, a new open source codec.
It's not Opus.
It's not Theora.
It's a brand.
It's not Vorbis.
It's a brand new codec called Codec 2.
And it's designed to fit an entire,
a long arse podcast on a floppy disk.
Yeah, I said a floppy disk.
I'll tell you about that.
Plus, we've got a new release of GitLab.
And I got a small, sweet, but really kind of to the point
interview with the GitLab CEO about what the hell
auto DevOps is and why it's landing in GitLab.11.
But Brent, let's not go any further
without addressing the elephant in the room.
You're not Wes.
I think I sound a little different.
He's probably the Seattle version of me.
I wasn't going to.
Or maybe I'm the Northern Ontario version of him.
I wasn't going to say it.
I wasn't.
But that is so true.
So I'm really glad you said it.
Because you guys are like, if I ever travel to Ontario,
you're my guy, Brent.
You're like my guy.
And if anybody ever travels to Seattle,
Wes should be their guy, not me, but Wes.
But he's out driving around the Pacific Northwest right now.
And you hit me up and you said, hey, I'd
love to join you on the show.
And it was just the timing worked out perfectly.
And the audience might remember Brent
because he was on the show ages ago during Linux Fest Northwest
talking about his photography workflow on Linux.
And Brent, since you've done that episode,
I've probably gotten an email a week asking,
how can I make that switch?
So it seems to be an area, pro photography,
where we're picking up a lot of users on the Linux side.
Is that all still?
You're still rocking Linux to do all your pro photography,
still using Darktable and all that goodness?
Absolutely.
I don't see that changing anytime soon.
And the software is just getting better and better and better.
So no looking back.
Yeah, I'm surprised that so many people are giving it a go.
I'd really love to get more insights into that.
In fact, if you're a pro photographer,
photographer that has switched, I'd love to hear why.
Go to linuxunplug.com slash contact.
But before we go any further, Brent,
we've got to bring in that virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
What's up?
So in the Mumble Room right now, we have Dusty joining us.
Dusty, are you with technically Red Hat,
or do you consider yourself with the Fedora project?
What's your delineation there?
Both.
Oh, well, that's not confusing.
No, I work for Red Hat, but a lot of what I do
is related to the Fedora project.
And if I were to leave Red Hat, I
imagine I would try to still stay involved.
So nothing that I do there is really tied or specific
to Red Hat.
Specifically, I mean, I could do that job for another company
if I wanted to.
Fascinating.
And Ian was going to be joining us too,
but it looks like he just stepped out for a moment.
He might come back.
I'll keep an eye out for him.
Where are you, Ian?
Where are you?
Oh, yeah, there you are.
Jeez, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
The screen's across.
Ian, you're also over, again, same question to you.
Do you consider yourself Red Hat?
Do you consider yourself primarily Fedora?
Explain that to me.
I thought Dusty gave a great answer.
All right.
I think a lot of people in Red Hat would say the same thing.
We can shift hats, sometimes strategically,
depending on what we're trying to argue for.
Nice.
So you can chew and walk at the same time of that bubble gum.
I like it.
Well, guys, we're going to get to the big news surrounding
the Fedora project here in just a little bit.
But I wanted to start with an update around Blender,
because this is personally extremely interesting to me.
As you recall from last week's episode,
YouTube had blocked all of the Blender videos, the Blender
Projects videos, the open source Blender Projects
videos worldwide.
Now, on Thursday after the show, YouTube
turned their channel back on, with the exception of one
video from Andrew Price, which is still blocked in the USA.
And apparently, they are requesting
that the Blender Project signs a new monetization
agreement, which sounds really bad just in general.
I mean, Brent, is there no longer a space just
for uploading your stuff for free
and sharing it with people?
Isn't that still something that's worth pursuing?
Well, maybe it just means you don't do it on these platforms.
Yeah.
Yeah, maybe it does, doesn't it?
Maybe it means we need things like PeerTube.
PeerTube is what Blender turned to when
YouTube shut down their channel.
And we covered it a little bit last week,
and I'm really happy to say this week,
that they were undergoing a fundraiser
and they reached their goal.
In fact, they've exceeded their goal by just a bit.
They still have nine days left to go,
and I think maybe it'd be worth kind of pushing this
just a little bit further.
Right now, they've raised 23,000 euros,
and their goal was 20,000.
With nine days left to go, they've reached 118% of funding.
But there's still work to be done.
They talk about their next milestone.
They say there are important features
that they want to get in version 1,
and those are video redundancies.
You can share bandwidth between instances
or as a fallback of the original instance if it goes down,
and the ability to subscribe to users and channels
throughout the entire federation of PeerTube.
So for those of you that maybe aren't familiar with PeerTube,
I did a little deep dive this week.
I loaded up on a Fedora 28 cloud instance using Cockpit,
and as you know, I love it.
And you just go right into Cockpit
when you have all the Docker stuff installed,
and you go to containers, and you just search in there,
and it will search the entire Docker hub,
and it will pull down PeerTube.
And you can get started with PeerTube in five minutes
using Fedora 28 and Cockpit.
It's great, and I have that running on top of a DO droplet.
And I gave it a go, and it's a little rough at this point,
but holy crap, if this doesn't have some potential.
As you probably guessed, it's using BitTorrent
as the backend with a web seed.
So when you're the first person to watch it,
you get a web seed, and it plays pretty fast.
But when you're the second person to watch it,
you get the web seed, and you start streaming it
from the other person watching it.
And I think this has massive potential
for Jupyter broadcasting content.
So I wanted to load it up and give it a go.
And you know, it's early days, it's early days.
But like, when do you decide to make a jump
to something like this?
Like, take you, Brent.
When did you say, all right, I can make a jump
to a totally different technology stack,
even if it doesn't have 100% everything I need?
How do you make that decision,
especially when it's like a creative endeavor?
Yeah, I mean, it's most certainly gonna be a personal choice
as far as how much risk you're willing to take.
Yeah, exactly.
But for me personally, at least in the photography sphere,
it was keeping an eye on the tools
and knowing that, okay, they're in their infancy.
Maybe six months from now, they're gonna have
the very basic of the tool set that I need.
So for my transition, it was like, okay,
this has 70% of what I use on a daily basis.
Is that enough?
And for me at the time, yeah, okay, 70% is enough.
And maybe I can fill in with that extra, you know,
that remainder with some of the other proprietary tools
for the moment as the open source
or the alternative tools develop further.
Yeah, so what I like about PeerTube right now
is that I could self-host it.
And then when I upload a video
to my own little lonely self-hosted instance,
it's in development, it's kind of working now.
It has an announcement feature where it can announce it
to the rest of the PeerTube network,
which are a bunch of federated servers.
And so you could be a member of one server
and if you have everything turned on right
and that server has everything enabled,
you can cross-pollinate the content options,
which sort of addresses this issue
when you go self-hosted about discoverability.
That's one of the things that's really driven GitHub
is that when you move to GitHub,
you automatically get discoverability.
People can search and find you in one central location.
And when you switch to GitLab or your own self-hosted repo,
you kind of go off the grid a little bit.
And that's why Jupyter Broadcasting
has always published to YouTube and to Google Play
and to iTunes and Stitcher and all of the other ones,
because you gotta go where the audience is.
But this sort of squares those two things.
PeerTube is letting you self-host
while also spreading the word
when you have new content available.
And I'm kind of all in.
I kind of, I'm thinking about ways
maybe I can contribute to the project financially.
Jupyter Broadcasting is a company, I mean, not me personally.
And I've played around on a container
and it is at a stage right now
where it needs more of my attention
than I have time to give it.
It's a little rough and it's gonna have more updates.
But I will say this,
if somebody in the community wants to reach out
and work with me to set up a PeerTube hosted solution,
I would be more than on board
with importing all of our YouTube catalog
and setting up PeerTube as an option
for the Jupyter Broadcasting audience to consume our content.
100% would be on board with that.
I would even consider starting doing the main embeds
on the JB website using PeerTube
if the experience is 70% there,
because I think the audience would be with me too.
So if this sounds appealing to you,
setting up a PeerTube server on a DigitalOcean Droplet
or something like that and working with me over Telegram,
I put this out there to the community right here right now.
Let's be early adopters, Jupyter Broadcasting.
Let's be early adopters of PeerTube.
Let's push this forward.
Let's help collapse the YouTube monopoly on online video.
And let's do it with, in my opinion,
some of the best Linux and open source content out there.
And if you wanna work with me,
contact me on Telegram at ChrisLAS.
Let's set it up,
because I think this could be a great opportunity.
It's so close, I would almost do it all myself.
It just needs a bit more babysitting
than I have time to give and I recognize that fact
and I want it to be successful.
So I want somebody in the community to work with me,
but this is the solution.
It'll be this and a million other things.
Instagram has just recently launched IGTV.
Facebook has their YouTube competitor,
but I feel like PeerTube, for our audience,
could be the future.
It won't necessarily replace YouTube,
but it could be, one day,
the predominant way people watch
Jupyter Broadcasting videos.
I'm pretty excited about it, Brent.
Do you think it would isolate anyone at all?
I don't know.
I mean, I like their federation spreading the information.
It definitely is not gonna reach people
on the proprietary commercial platforms.
And so I feel like, for a period of time,
I'm gonna have to publish in both locations.
You know what I mean?
Like a transition period?
Yeah, yeah, like a transition period
and then once people know about it
and the word of mouth is starting to spread,
kind of make it our primary platform.
And how awesome would it be if I could self-host that stuff
and use BitTorrent to absorb the primary bulk
of the bandwidth?
Isn't that great?
Fabulous, yeah, yeah, fabulous.
It makes me wanna do all the things over torrent.
I've always wanted to.
I was ready to use BitTorrent Sync
as a way to distribute shows,
but that didn't work out either.
So we'll see.
We'll see where that goes.
Do you think torrent can handle the bandwidth?
You know, if we get like, you know,
thousands of these servers going,
can it do all that?
I think it gets even better.
That's the thing.
You know, have you ever used any of those apps
like Popcorn Hour or whatever it was
that would live stream torrent files?
No.
It works because if you think about it,
you do segmented downloads.
And if you synchronize the download with the player,
like if the download mechanism is aware
of the player position in the video,
it can start trying to chunk up the section
of the video you're watching.
And so it actually lends itself pretty well
to video streaming.
It's a little bit slower in some cases,
but the nature of BitTorrent where it can download
different chunks of the file at different times
from different locations happens to fit pretty well
with the nature of video streaming.
So I actually think it could be a pretty good experience.
I guess we'll have to wait and see.
In some ways it seems like a meant to be transition, right?
It's just about time that this comes along, isn't it?
I hope so.
I really hope so because I've had many concerns
about YouTube now for quite a while.
Let's shift gears for a moment.
And there was some great progress that came out of London.
Over on the Ubuntu blog, there is a report from Will Cook
about the GNOME software design sprint.
And he writes, a couple of weeks ago,
representatives from across Canonical met in London
to talk about ideas to improve the user experience
of GNOME software.
We had people from the store team, Snap Advocacy,
Snap D, design, and the desktop team.
But we also were fortunate enough to be joined
by Richard Hughes, representing Upstream GNOME software.
Now Richard's name may ring a bell
when we've talked about the Upstream firmware project
that I'm a huge fan of.
And Will writes, we started off this week
by making a very quick, a.k.a. long, list of features
or improvements we'd like to see in GNOME software.
They broke it all down, did a big whiteboard session.
And some of the things they talked about
were adding a verified publisher's identity
to GNOME software to show where a publisher has undergone
some kind of formal checking so you can be assured that they
are who they say they are.
Also, they thought about adding a way
to report problems within applications
right there in GNOME software.
Maybe it's a link to submit a bug to their bug tracker,
something like that.
Or maybe it goes back to some central repository
and then gets sorted out from there.
They also had whiteboarded some better layouts and the ability
for publishers to add extra theming and artwork
to their application page.
So you could have, for example, FileZilla
could have some slick branding when you click on the FileZilla
icon.
Also, they worked on a refreshed home screen for GNOME software
to surface new applications, application add-ons that
are related to things you already have installed,
and news and updates for your favorite applications
from the software developers.
Their initial designs are going to be
added to GNOME's community design pages on the GitLab
just to get feedback and things like that.
And then hopefully, they'll begin engineering work,
and it'll be done to a branch that's
upstream of GNOME software and be proposed
for upstream and general inclusion
if all agreed seem to like it.
Interesting that these sprints are still going on now
that we're done with 17.10 and 18.04.
It's an interesting thing that happens is different commercial
interests, in this case, Canonical,
who has a pretty wide interest in GNOME software,
will bring folks in to sort of forward the things
that they see are critical.
And then it's kind of up to the rest of the community
to adopt their changes.
And this is sort of the groundwork where forks begin.
Not necessarily where forks happen,
but this is sort of the groundwork
where forks could begin.
Say Canonical really gets invested
in some of these changes, like publisher verification, which
is a pretty good one, especially after the Snap Store
stuff and the Docker Hub stuff we've talked about recently.
That's a pretty good one.
But maybe for some reason, let's say
GNOME upstream doesn't like it.
Now Canonical will have a decision on their hands.
Do we fork our version of GNOME software,
which will be superior?
Or do we go with upstream, stay upstream, keep it simple,
but lack the features we want?
It's kind of a interesting semi-uncomfortable situation
that crops up in open source development.
You agree, Brent?
I do.
But in a way, it also allows us a whole bunch
of different options, right?
If there's two camps that are in this stuff every single day
who feel differently about a project,
certainly there are other users out in the world who do as well.
So to have two options sometimes is the best.
It is sort of an organic way to let things work out,
sort of an evolution versus intelligent design, if you will.
And whichever one's stronger in the marketplace
sort of wins out.
I know myself, I want to see continued improvements
in the way I can ingest flat packs and flat pack
repositories and snaps.
They've done a lot of work there.
But just recently, I was trying to add,
I can't remember if it was Atom or Visual Studio code,
but there was a flat pack repo for it.
And within step two, I'm at the command line.
I'm adding repos.
I'm then installing software.
And honestly, I just wish I could click a link in my browser
and have it launch GNOME software
and do all of the work for me, maybe
prompt for my password once.
And we're just not there yet.
So that's what I'd like to see is improvements
with these universal package formats.
Speaking of flat pack, it's been almost four years
since we started talking about it.
Can you believe that?
You might not actually think that's true,
because when we first started talking about flat pack,
we were talking about XdgApp.
You might remember your humble host here talking about XggApp
and how I was excited about it being a universal installation
format.
It used osstree, XggApp, and used the osstree
to store and deduplicate applications.
It used kernel namespaces via a helper called XggAppHelper
to do unprivileged containers.
It had a split between applications and runtimes.
It was very much like what we see flat pack today.
But there was a great renaming for flat pack
from XggApp to flat pack.
And that's when, in this show, we
could tell things were going to the next level.
And flat pack, the name itself, has a great history
that goes back way, way, way, way, way back
to the ancient Egyptians.
I'll link to the post in the show notes
that explains that at linuxunplug.com slash 255.
Go check that out.
So in 2016, we got the new name of flat pack.
That was version 0.6.0.
Version 0.80 was released in December of 2016.
And that was the first long-term stable edition
that landed in Debian Stretch and RHEL 7.
And we've had another stable release since then, version 0.10x.
It's always been a decentralized system
that anyone could host their own applications.
But since then, they've realized it is kind of beneficial
to have a centralized hub called Flathub.
So the Flathub project was launched
where you can find most applications these days that
are available in Flathub and flat pack.
But it's not finished.
And it's not necessarily bug-free either.
In fact, Alexander writes in his blog
that they have a lot of things on the list for flat pack 1.0.
And there's a few core things they
want to have done before they announce flat pack.1.0.
So if you keep your eye out, in this next week,
you'll probably see the first release candidate
for flat pack 1.0 called 0.99.1.
It'll probably be later on, as you're
hearing this episode, a couple of days afterwards.
And then later this summer, we're
going to finally get version 1.0 of flat pack.
So we've got Snap and flat pack 1.0's.
And actually, Snap is further along.
And they did a little bit, I won't say much faster,
but noticeably faster development pace there.
But flat pack, since XGD app, since 2016,
has been really kind of progressing
in this nice, orderly fashion.
And the summer is going to be the summer of flat pack.
This is going to be a big summer for both of these formats.
And it's just a couple of months away.
And soon, some of your favorite applications
will be packaged up, if they haven't already.
As I wrote these notes for the show,
I realized I was using a Snap of Telegram.
I'm using a flat pack of my editor.
I can't remember when I even installed that.
I'm using an app image of Etcher.
Like, I have all of these different applications
I use on a daily basis that are installed using
these universal package formats.
And what we've ended up with is like three instead of one.
Really, it's three, because you've got to include app image
in this conversation.
Is three manageable, Brent?
What do you think?
Is that too much?
Or is three, if we just landed on three solids
for application delivery, is that good enough?
I guess let me throw a question right back at you.
Do you see anyone pulling ahead?
Or is it kind of everyone's keeping the same?
I kind of feel like it's different use cases
are emerging.
So you're answering your own question.
Like, snaps are emerging as a great solution
for complicated commercial applications,
or applications where you really want
to have a high availability of discovery.
Flat packs have been extremely useful for, like, for example,
I run, on some systems, a development build of GKedit.
And I use a flat pack to do that.
That's really nice.
It's like flat packs, to me, are in a way what
PPA should have been all along.
Like, Canonical tried out PPAs, and it kind of sucked,
as far as I was concerned.
It was great for a lot of users.
I didn't like it a lot.
Whereas flat pack is, like, the perfect PPA.
If I could have had PPA as this, I'd
have been a lot happier with it.
Whereas snaps feel like XYZ vendor
has just released an application for Linux,
and now it's available.
And JJ, you're pointing out, like, a lot of these,
both flat pack and snaps, also have, like, this wine
compatibility layer now.
Yeah, and it's pretty interesting.
I actually got to test out the GOG Galaxy app on my system,
and it works relatively well, although there
seems to be some focus issues online, particular system
that I don't know if anybody else is having with regards
to if I go away from the game that's currently playing,
I cannot put my mouse inside of the game again.
So that's a bug that I might need to report.
But it sort of is interesting, because I
wouldn't need to have any sort of complicated setup of wine
in order to run all these applications.
And it sort of gives me a little bit of hope for Linux,
for users such as myself who have infrastructure
slash universities that refuse to, quote unquote,
officially support Linux.
I agree.
Yeah, it's been nice.
And the bundling of, like, a compatibility layer,
in the case of Skype, one day it's
going to be to fix audio issues.
In the case of some others, it's to load a wine library.
It's very useful.
And I've also seen CM2 in the chat room
is saying that it's a good way to have
GNOME stuff, the newest GNOME stuff, in CentOS 7.
So you can have, like, a rel stable base,
but you can have the newest user land applications.
That obviously appeals to me too.
Maybe beta software as well.
I think Firefox beta is also available in these package
formats.
Yes.
And Tenbit, you're pointing out that it
is getting easier for folks that like to use these GUI
installers, like the GNOME Software Center or KD Discover.
Yeah?
Yeah, it seems to me like if you're on the desktop anyway,
you've got some options for not really caring
which one you're using.
It makes it way simpler, doesn't it,
when you don't do it by the command line
and you just use, like, Discover or GNOME software?
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah.
Now, I want to talk about Fedora Core OS.
Yeah, I said Fedora Core OS.
Matthew Miller on June 20 posted over at fedoramagazine.org,
welcome to Fedora Core OS.
Everything you know is changing.
Now it's time for us to figure out
how we can welcome and include container Linux
into the circle of Fedora friends.
The Fedora editions strategy intentionally
makes space for exploring emerging areas in operating
system distributions.
Core OS will help us push even further
and bring new ways of doing things as a project.
Now, Fedora Core OS is going to be built from Fedora content
rather than the way it's made now.
It won't necessarily be made the same way
we make Fedora OS deliverables today, though.
No matter what, we absolutely want
Core OS's user experience of container cluster host OS
that keeps itself up to date and you just
don't have to worry about it.
That's the experience they're going for.
Fedora being a community-driven project,
community-driven project, though obviously this
is your chance to get involved.
Now, I read that.
I just quoted you word for word.
I just read it from Matt's post.
And it barely makes any sense to me, barely, barely
makes any sense.
From what I grok, Fedora is becoming
something completely different, but it
sounds like it's something that's even more awesome
than it currently is.
So I've invited Dusty and Ian on the show
here to help me sort this out.
They're both involved in the Fedora project,
involved with Red Hat, and they have a better insight into this
than your humble host here does.
So guys, welcome into the show.
And Dusty, because you were here first, I'll start with you.
Where do you want to begin the conversation
around Fedora Core OS?
Are we talking about sort of a refactoring of Fedora here?
Are we talking about a new Fedora in a sense?
I think what we're talking about here
is kind of taking the use cases that Container Linux
and Atomic Host have been targeting
and trying to bring the best of both of those worlds,
so the best from Container Linux and the best
from Atomic Host, and to also try
to bring those two communities.
Obviously, Container Linux has a large user base,
and Atomic Host has a very engaged community.
Trying to bring those two together and make something
better, more focused, if we combine our efforts,
hopefully it'll be better and it'll be more rock solid.
Now, Ian, you kind of come at this
from the atomic side of the house.
And I got to ask you, is this kind
of where the puck was going to skate regardless
of the Core OS merger?
Because to me, I've always kind of wanted
Fedora to go more atomic.
Yeah, well, I think it's funny to me
to hear you say that that almost makes sense to you.
Because I saw Matt shared that announcement with me,
and I saw it go out.
And I thought, oh, yes, this is exactly what I wanted to say.
There's something that occurs to me when you did say that.
I think a realization that we came to,
if you've been in the Fedora project for a long time,
I've always thought of it as something
that was very nimble and very quick.
And certainly, as someone in Red Hat who's also
trying to manage an OS that we want to have a 3, 5, 10-year
lifecycle, it seems extremely nimble.
But some of what Fedora does now seems a little bit less nimble
than, for example, something like Container Linux
was able to do.
So I think a big element of what Matt was trying to get across
in that announcement is that we're
going to be open to slightly different ways of perhaps
constructing this subset or this sub-distribution of Fedora
that maybe we weren't necessarily
before we actually talked about marrying up
with the Container Linux community.
Because looking at some of the ways that they do things,
how they put stuff together, the rolling update model
and things like that, it is really quite nimble.
And it's something that I think we aspire to do more of as we
merge those two upstreams.
I see.
So in your perspective, this isn't necessarily
a huge shift for Fedora, the main project itself,
but maybe for one of the additions of Fedora.
Am I tracking?
Yeah, and I think Matthew also used this concept.
We've had a concept in Fedora called Spins, which
is meant to be another place where people perhaps
experimented a little bit more with the way
that the distribution was composed.
Again, it doesn't mean that we're
going to go completely off piste, as it were,
and start pulling in content that comes from nowhere else.
But we do have a fairly, and Fedora's very,
this is one of the things that makes Fedora great,
as a full-fledged distribution that's
released every six months or so, have a very rigorous process
for composing the entire thing together at something
like 20,000 source RPMs.
They experiment with all sorts of different ways
to do interactive installs, all sorts
of different combinations of install configurations.
And they do that quite well.
But we don't necessarily need to be constrained by that
when we release an update of our minimal container host that's
meant to support an entirely different use case, right?
So these are the kind of things that we're
hoping to create a little bit more space for now
that we've created Fedora Core OS
and have sort of announced some of the guardrails
for that community.
I see.
So if I today am a Fedora Atomic user,
and I'm just a minimal installation,
but I found it to be a pretty competitive, pretty great
server OS, what should I expect now as a Fedora Atomic user?
Long term, what kind of shift should I expect here?
Because it sounds like Core OS and Fedora Atomic
had a lot of the same goals in mind.
So as a user, essentially what I'm
trying to get out of the project sounds
like it's staying the same.
Some of the technical implementations might be shifting.
This is where I get to sign Dusty up for whatever I want,
since I told you what to expect on that one.
I love it.
Dusty will give him.
I'm going to give him a second to try and compose
an answer to that, too, before I write my wish list.
Yeah, what do you think?
As a Fedora Atomic user, should I be a little concerned
that the thing I've just started to fall in love with
is about to change from what I come to expect?
I don't think so.
I guess it depends on how you look at it.
But like I said earlier, we're trying
to take some of the best technology from both.
So one thing that Container Linux users really liked
is Ignition, which is kind of like an early bootstrapping
tool that runs in the init remfs.
So if you've ever tried to add a new system d
unit to your cloud instance using CloudInit,
you realize that adding a system d unit via another system d
unit is actually pretty, it gets pretty hairy pretty quick.
So running and modifying the system in the init remfs
before you switch the root is actually pretty powerful.
So that's one thing that we're kind of carrying forward.
Another thing is some of the update technology
behind Container Linux was forked off of Chrome OS.
And it's something that had not been maintained very well.
And it was kind of something that
was a little more scary for some of the Container Linux
maintainers.
However, RPM OS3 and OS3, we have
some of the core developers for that technology
in-house at Red Hat.
So if there are things that we need from those technologies
and the future new features or whatnot,
we can easily add them because we have the people,
the expertise there.
So as far as Fedora Atomic goes, it will actually continue.
There will be a Fedora 29 release of Fedora Atomic.
After that, Fedora Core OS will take over.
But in the long run, it's not going
to be much, much different than what you have today
as far as if you know RPM OS3 already.
I'm going to put Dusty on the spot here and say,
Dusty, would you anticipate that there's
going to be a continuous upgrade path between, say,
Fedora 29 Atomic Host and whatever
comes out of Fedora Core OS?
Is that already something we're thinking of as a goal?
I think it might be possible.
I just don't want to commit to that.
Interesting.
Very clever.
Yeah.
Probably a good move.
What we're doing as part of this merging of the two communities
as well is looking at it as an opportunity
to get rid of bad design decisions
that we may have had early on.
And if we get to a point where we decide,
hey, there's this change that we want
to make that means that we couldn't in place
upgrade Fedora Atomic Host to Fedora Core OS,
now's the best time to do it.
So it's very early days in the development of Fedora Core OS.
But we're building off of pretty stable technologies.
Obviously, there's a community behind Container Linux
and a community behind Fedora Atomic Host today.
Those technologies work.
So we're starting from a good position.
We're kind of throwing everything in the middle there
and then coming out with something better, I believe.
Yeah, you get to pick from the best, really,
in this situation.
It's sort of you have more good things to pick from
than you can really kind of make sense of.
It kind of sounds like an ideal situation in a way.
Now, all right, so that's all fine and good.
But as a Fedora user, I've got to wonder,
eventually, does this become main Fedora?
Is it too soon to even say that?
But it seems like, to me, this would really
be a standout differentiator for Fedora
if this wasn't just like one of the additions of Fedora,
if this was Fedora.
Right, so I think, at least the way I think about it.
So for example, we have Fedora Atomic Host, right?
We have Fedora Workstation.
We have a new Fedora IoT edition.
We have Fedora Server.
The technology behind Atomic Host
and the technology behind upcoming Fedora Core OS
is already starting to branch out
into some of those other additions, right?
So for example, Atomic Workstation,
which was rebranded as Fedora Silverblue,
uses RPMOS tree and OS tree in the background.
So you've got your get for your operating system
like approach with the transactional updates.
But it's just a different package set, right?
So to answer your question, is Fedora Core OS
the future of Fedora?
I mean, I think Fedora Core OS is more or less
an addition of Fedora.
But the tooling behind it, the tooling behind it,
the tooling behind it, what we were doing with Atomic Host
and what we're doing with Silverblue today
is possibly the answer to your question,
is that the future of Fedora, right?
Because it could Fedora Core OS be the future of Fedora?
Well, there's a lot of users that use Fedora
as a workstation and Fedora Core OS,
we're not including GNOME, right?
So that's kind of hard to answer that question,
unless you look at it,
is the underlying technology the future?
I think that is an open question and that is,
it will be interesting to see what happens there.
Yeah, that's kind of where I was going, exactly,
is it seems like that fundamental technology
that's making this such a great option
would be just as useful on the workstation.
Because I guess I think about this and I think,
this is kind of confusing to the average user,
there's a lot going on here.
It's not like open SUSE levels of confusing yet,
but we're like getting there.
And I wonder, this is kind of a nebulous question,
I don't know if it's better for Ian or for Dusty,
but how much do you guys give thinking
to the messaging around all of this
and the end user's ability to track this?
Seems like it's pushing it.
You know what I mean?
Well, so I think the messaging initially on this
is that this is a continuation of the interest groups
that grew around Container Linux
and the Fedora Atomic Host, right?
So the focus of this is very much that use case.
I would reiterate Dusty's point,
is that the idea of having a largely immutable host
with this sort of atomic update
has at least two other major applications
that people are able to experiment with within Fedora,
what's now called Silverblue and some initial work on IoT.
And I think that's a very natural way
for it to be allowed to develop sort of in parallel
with contributions coming across where there's commonality,
like again, at the OS tree or our PMOS tree level.
But if you're a Fedora user and you're confused by this,
but you haven't been involved in the Atomic Host project
and are not interested in containers,
it's probably not an area
that you need to be looking at right now.
But if you were part of the communities
that were interested in container technologies,
if you're interested in container orchestration,
or if you were actually part of the Atomic Host community
or Container Linux on the CoreOS side,
then I hope you're not confused by Matthew's announcement.
And get involved, right?
Yes, yes, please.
Yeah, that's what I like the most
about what you guys are doing really,
is because in a way, and my co-host on Linux Action
has pointed this out to me, it was obvious,
but I hadn't thought about it.
This could trickle upstream to RHEL eventually,
what you guys do here, yeah?
So it's in a way, it's a way for the community
to impact RHEL, which is one of the largest commercial
and open source products in the world.
Yeah, and we'd like, I mean, I would say that that's true
of many things in Fedora, and that's quite explicit, so.
Yeah, fair enough.
Okay, so I don't know if this is a Dustin or Ian question.
Dusty, maybe this is more towards you,
but can somebody explain to me what the difference
between a Fedora project leader is
and a Fedora program manager?
Because you guys just got yourself
a program manager over at Fedora.
It looks like it's Ben Cotton,
and he is pretty excited to take the new role on,
but what is a program manager, and what's that all about?
I'm not sure exactly.
I imagine the Fedora project leader
is more of a community facing, you know,
let's kind of organize and get people inspired
to, you know, contribute and collaborate.
And the program manager is probably more, you know,
looking at what's coming down the pipeline.
Do we have people working on these things?
Are we gonna be able to, you know,
get this feature into Fedora 29, that type of thing.
Yeah, so very much sort of like a,
sort of herding the cats role,
which can be a absolutely full-time position.
In fact, it can be one of the most arduous positions, so.
Herding cats in the community, fun.
Oh, I can imagine, let me tell you, Dusty.
I can imagine, and it is a pain in the arse, let me tell you.
It is the hardest thing I do for 12 years,
maybe 13 years now of podcasting.
It is the hardest thing I do.
So it does take some serious dedication.
Well, guys, is there anything else around this
that we should talk about?
Anything else you think the audience
would probably walk away with knowing
about the recent announcements,
the merger of Fedora and CoreOS?
Is there kind of like a takeaway
that you want to make sure you hit on?
I would say that we're deadly serious
about the ability for people
who want to get involved in the community
or are already involved in either of these two communities
to come on board in the sort of early requirements
gathering phase of this.
We're absolutely, we have a number of, I think,
interesting avenues of exploration right now
that we're going down,
and we would love to have people come on board.
Yep, and I believe we'll have
our first community meeting tomorrow.
I think we're going to try to have the same time slot
as what we were doing for the Atomic Community Meeting,
which is Wednesdays at 1630 UTC,
but we'll see.
We should have our first one tomorrow.
So if I wanted to get kind of in the ground floor level,
wanted to maybe influence some of the decisions,
is that sort of the first thing I should start attending,
is that Wednesday meeting and start contributing there?
Yep, that's a good place to start,
but if you're not able to come there,
we have a mailing list,
we have a discourse set up for discussions.
Really, there's a lot of different ways to get involved.
We have an IRC channel.
If you have any questions and want to get involved,
drop by our IRC channel,
and we can point you in the right direction too.
Awesome.
Guys, here's what I love about what's going on.
First of all, it really is something where
Joe, sysadmin, or Joe developer can get involved
and push the direction of this thing,
which eventually will trickle upstream
to Red Hat Enterprise Linux,
which is, that's remarkable, if you think about it.
That right there itself is remarkable,
but the other thing I really like about it is
this is about as transparent as it can get.
I mean, I appreciate and understand
there was some business sales and behind the scenes stuff
that had to happen,
but really, even before this thing is completely formed,
you guys, two of you, Ian and Dusty, are on the show.
Matt was gonna make it, but he couldn't.
Three of you were gonna be on the show to talk about this.
The blog posts are out there.
The weekly community meetings are happening.
This is about as transparent as it gets
with something like this,
and the reason why I think it's worth underscoring
that a couple of times is
this really will affect the industry.
It goes from Fedora and it trickles down
to so many systems, so many enterprise-grade systems,
the things that people in our audience
make their living off of.
So I really appreciate you guys taking the time
to come on the show and helping me wrap my brain around it
because it's part of that transparency.
So thank you, Ian and Dusty.
You guys are totally welcome to hang out with us.
We're gonna keep going.
All right, thanks for having us.
Thank you, Chris.
Yeah, so let's talk about GTK 3 for a moment
because it hasn't gotten a lot of attention for a while.
GTK 4 has sort of been the new big promise,
and we've all kind of been holding our breath,
but it's taking a little bit longer than initially thought.
So over on the GTK Plus development blog,
we have ourselves a post from Mr. MC Lason,
and he talks about GTK 4 being just a little bit out.
So in the meantime, we're gonna see ourselves a GTK 3.24,
and it's gonna be a maintenance release
that has some nice new features,
including, Brent, I know your favorite feature,
new emoji support, yeah?
I mean, that's gotta feel good.
How did you know?
I don't know, because I feel like you and I
could have a conversation in emojis, you and I.
You had this very special emoji that you sent me.
It might have been someone with a beard.
Those are stickers.
Do not confuse the emojis with the stickers.
I do love my Putin stickers.
Yeah, I got Kim Jong-un stickers,
and I got Vladimir Putin stickers,
and I'll use them all the time.
So the long and short of this is really
kind of a practical acknowledgment
by the GTK community that GTK 4 is taking a little bit longer.
So we're gonna, I know we've been telling you
that you could just plan on GTK 3.22 being final,
and it was just gonna stick around,
but we're gonna make some changes.
But it's not just emojis that they're including.
There's gonna be support for new open type font features
and other nice things and bug fixes, so keep an eye out.
The GTK 3 cycle is still alive,
and I wanted to give you just a heads up about that.
Another bit of community news for those of you
that are running KDE Neon.
If you are crazy, you can now update to 18.04.
KDE Neon is sort of this promise of an LTS Ubuntu release
with a rolling KDE release.
They can come within hours of the new hotness
because the developers are using Neon themselves.
And this, since the project's inception,
is the first time they're hopping LTSs.
They're going from 16.04 to 18.04,
but it hasn't been done before.
So they're looking for your help to test,
and I underscore test.
It is not recommended for production systems.
But if you are a lunatic and a masochist,
you can go try it out.
I'll have a link in the show notes and help them test it.
I myself will be doing this upgrade
after enough of you throw yourselves on the sword
testing this.
I'm not going to try this one myself.
I don't need to break the last remaining Neon systems I have.
And in their post on community.kd.org,
they say it's likely to break your system right now.
And it's gotten better over the last few days.
I've been following the Telegram conversation around this.
It's a full-fledged upgrade.
And I advise caution.
But if you're willing to try it so that way I don't have to,
it's available for you.
Brian, what desktop environment are you on over there?
Are you a gnome guy?
Oh, no.
KDE.
Really?
And that's actually a recent thing for me.
I was on, and don't hold me against this
if you feel strongly about it, but I
was doing Cinnamon for a long time
and suggesting that to a lot of people.
But I've had my eye on KDE since forever, maybe 10 years,
and just sort of tracking what they were doing.
And I felt like, OK, I'm going to jump.
So about a year ago, sure enough, did that.
And like you are discovering now, there's no looking back.
I'm really enjoying it.
It's just super slick.
It does exactly what I need.
It does a lot more, but it just gets out of the way.
And so that's me.
I, for some reason, did not know that.
Last time I talked, I don't know if that came up.
But that's interesting to hear.
Because you were using, let's see, when you were here at JB,
you did use a KDE desktop to do the photo stuff, as I recall.
Right at home.
Yeah.
I hadn't even thought about it.
That's why I didn't complain about it.
Yeah, it's funny you didn't.
You just got right to work, actually.
I got a link in the show notes for you guys to check out.
It's just worth mentioning.
There's not really a lot to it, but Google
has completely ignored Windows in their release of a VR video
editor, a virtual reality video editor.
It's mostly for 180 perspective video.
But they released it for Linux and Mac, but not
Windows for a VR video editor.
Now, what does that mean?
Maybe nothing.
But I thought it was worth mentioning.
And if you're interested in grabbing a VR editor,
maybe like Wimpy might be, go check the show notes.
I'll have a link there.
But Brent, you sent me this link to DigitalOcean's post
about cracking the Enigma encryption in 13 minutes
using 2,000 droplets.
How great is this post?
How great is this post, Brent?
This entire post, and I have to say I came to it
not directly from DigitalOcean, but a roundabout way.
And when I saw that it was a DigitalOcean post,
I thought, jeez, it's even better.
And so this is an article that is wonderfully placed
between the tech lover and everything DigitalOcean
is capable of and more.
It sounds like they pushed the boundaries here,
but also some really neat historical challenges.
Yeah.
Of course, you guys are, when I say the Enigma machine,
I bet you that everybody in the audience
knows what I'm talking about.
It was a complicated encryption system during World War II.
The apparatus consisted of a keyboard, a set of rotors,
an alphabet ring, and plug connections,
all configurable by the operator.
For the message to be both encrypted and decrypted,
both operators had to know the two sets of codes.
A daily base code changed every 24 hours,
which was published monthly by the Germans.
Then each operator created an individual setting
used only for that message.
The key to the individual code was
sent in the first character of the message in a coded,
and it was coded in the base.
That then created over 53 billion possible combinations
that changed every 24 hours.
Because of this, the machine was widely
considered unbreakable.
Now, as you know, we did eventually crack it.
Now, it still makes for a great challenge,
especially when you're trying to get AI to crack it.
So Lucas Kunzowicz, which I'm not sure
on the pronunciation there, but he
is the head of a data science division.
He's Polish, and he was working on this problem.
And he decided to recreate the most complicated version
of the Enigma machine, the Nazi's Navy
version of the machine, which was the most sophisticated
iteration.
His team started by recreating the machine's rotors and plugs
in Python.
In Python.
Let's just take a moment and appreciate now
that one of the most famous encryption machines
from World War II has been recreated in Python.
A moment here, if we will.
And he recreated all of these functionalities in Python.
Initially, they tried to teach their AI
to decode the Enigma code itself,
but it just didn't work.
And they also tried to spin up lambda functions from Amazon
to do the computation.
But the problem was, lambda functions were not very quick.
And some of the limits around execution time
bit them in the arse.
So they decided to keep pushing forward.
They started blogging about this.
And somebody at DigitalOcean noticed that this was a thing,
contacted them, and quickly agreed
to provide what they call their ML one-click droplets,
their machine learning one-click droplets.
It's like, you know, this is by one of their R&D engineers
who noticed this.
It's like, this is kind of what we do, guys.
We're kind of like super focused on developers.
You guys are developing code to do this.
Just come over here.
We'll consider this a marketing thing.
So they worked with their R&D engineer.
He set up these machine learning droplets.
And they contacted DigitalOcean's help desk
and said, hey, can you spin us up 1,000 droplets,
1,000 droplets, 1,000 droplets.
And they did it.
They spun up 1,000 droplets for them in a day.
And they call it, they have a cute name for it.
They call it, they hydrated.
They hydrated these droplets in one day.
They hydrated 1,000 droplets.
So it took the team about two weeks
to train the machines to create the Python code.
And then it took another couple of weeks
before they had their first success.
The way they train the machine learning, though, to read
German is kind of weird.
They fed the machine learning children's stories
and a few military telegraphs and things like that.
But fairy tales written in simple language,
like Rumpelstiltskin, Cinderella, Grimm's Fairy
Tales, Hansel and Gretzel, those plus 200 others
were the data set.
They fed the machine learning algorithms
to pattern match German language.
Really, it came down to simple language.
Because these messages were generally short and very simple,
it actually worked to train them on children's books.
And really interestingly, at the end of the day,
the German language wasn't understandable by the AI
in any shape or form, but it could pattern match.
It could pattern match.
And so it didn't need to learn to speak German.
So they did that for two weeks.
And they ran the Enigma code through 1,000 droplets.
And after they trained it how to read German, or pattern match,
I guess.
And they threw 1,000 droplets at it.
After 24 hours, they broke the Enigma code.
And they were able to read the message.
And that was interesting.
That's not bad.
But what if we threw another 1,000 droplets at it?
What if we had 2,000 droplets to break this code?
Once they threw 2,000 droplets, they
were able to crack the code in 13 minutes, 13 minutes.
But if you think about it, and this is the author.
He says, you really have to accept the fact
that even if you have 2,000 droplets,
you still have billions of combinations to be checked.
And the neural network that we used
is really only good at spotting German language patterns.
It's not a speed demon.
And because it uses recurrence, which
gives us a boost when dealing with languages,
but you pay with calculation time.
So for the AI to shine, we actually had to use 2,000
droplets to do all the tedious work.
Everybody praises AI.
But it was actually the droplets that did 99% of the work.
Like, right?
We wrote one minion in Python.
And then DigitalOcean has a very nice API for storing images.
So you create one minion.
And then you tell DigitalOcean, create this as an image.
And then please, go create 2,000 copies of this image.
And it's off.
The code simply just runs.
But because we could add more systems,
it meant there was no state.
They were not coordinated in any way.
Each minion doesn't know anything about the others.
They're fully autonomous.
And that's great.
Because it means we can have 200.
We can have 2,000.
We can even have 20,000 of them.
The more we have, the less time that it
takes to break the Enigma code.
Wow.
And the hard numbers here?
The 2,000 virtual servers ran through 41 million combinations
per second.
It took them 13 minutes for the minions to do the work.
That's a lot of Python.
That's a good one, Brent.
I love how they call the servers minions.
Yeah, that's good.
That's good.
And it really shows you how easily
that these things are going to be cracked in the future.
When you can just deploy 2,000 droplets,
it's just a whole other game.
It's really a whole other game.
Why don't we mention DigitalOcean right here,
right now?
do.co slash unplugged.
That's where you go to get a $100 credit.
Now, DigitalOcean is an easier way to deploy servers.
It's a way to get infrastructure on demand.
Now, I could tell you that.
But why not have the professionals
with great voices tell you?
DigitalOcean's cloud computing platform
was designed with simplicity in mind,
giving development teams the ability
to easily manage infrastructure.
That's why thousands of businesses around the world
are building, deploying, and scaling their applications
faster and more efficiently on DigitalOcean.
Using our simple control panel, or API, you and your team
can seamlessly go from deploying to scaling
highly available web, mobile, PaaS, DBaaS, or machine
learning applications.
In just a matter of seconds, quickly set up
one to thousands of virtual machines,
easily secure servers and enable performance monitoring,
and effortlessly attach more storage.
Plus, you'll always know exactly what
you'll be paying every month with a predictable flat pricing
structure across all global data center regions.
By using DigitalOcean, you'll get the infrastructure
experience that development teams love with the features
your business needs.
Sign up for DigitalOcean today and experience simplicity
at scale.
It's true.
My favorite rig is $0.03 an hour.
They've got these flexible droplets now,
do.co slash unplugged, to get a $100 credit.
They have a great setup with a fantastic dashboard.
Also, a big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program now for years.
And while I'm giving out thanks, let me thank Linux Academy,
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
That's where you go to learn more about their platform
and sign up for a free seven-day trial.
It's everything you need to learn
about Linux and all of the stuff that runs Linux.
And if you've been a subscriber for a while,
buckle up, because your membership
is going to get way more valuable.
In July, they're launching 150 new challenges and content
and courses.
And some of the new topics they're launching
are going to get your attention.
I know you've been thinking about security a lot lately.
So have I, and so has Linux Academy.
And they're stepping up.
They're also helping you get a salt stack certification
and the Red Hat certification of expertise
in virtualization and architect full support.
They also have an AWS security specialist certification
courseware now and, speaking of Lambda, a Lambda deep dive.
And that's like four things out of over 150 new things
that are launching at Linux Academy.
They're going crazy.
They're going nuts.
Linux Academy is blowing out the doors.
Crazy Linux Academy is going to give away a seven-day free trial
when you go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Now, they're doing a live stream to celebrate the big giveaway.
And I just am super nervous about this.
In fact, I'm going to fly down to Linux Academy.
They're going to pay for it.
But I'm going to fly down there to help
make sure the stream goes well because it's all on Linux.
It's the whole new OBS setup that I did for them.
And now they're going to do this big content
launch on the OBS system.
I'm a little nervous, but I'm also crazy, crazy excited
because I've heard what they're working on.
I saw the effort.
And I'm going to go down there because they're not
paying me to do it other than paying for my flight
because I just really am excited about what they're doing.
I think it's great.
And it's going to bring even more people
into Linux and open source.
So linuxacademy.com slash unplugged,
where you go to get started.
And then you can also read over on their blog
about all of the new stuff that's coming.
It's a big, big deal.
And I'm going to be there to help them announce it all
and grok it all.
So if you're in the Texas area, I'm
going to be there again in about a week or two, about two weeks.
Because the big announcement, the big live stream
is on July 10.
And I'm going to get down there around the 8th or so
in the Dallas area.
And I'm going to need to have dinner on the 9th.
So if you're in the area and want to get dinner July 9th,
let me know.
I'll be in the Dallas Keller area, Fort Worth, really.
Let's do it.
Because I'm going down there again
to make sure this thing's a success.
Because damn if I'm not going to switch a company to Linux
and then not back it up.
So I hope you tune in live to watch how it all goes.
And if you're a Linux Academy subscriber or if you're not one
yet, go check it out, linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged.
Also, a huge thank you to Ting for making my entire road trip
to Texas and back possible.
I'm in Seattle again.
And the month that I was away doing shows on the road
was powered by Ting.
They have a CDMA and a GSM network.
And damn if I didn't leverage the hell out of that.
It's $6 a month for what you want, just one line.
Boom, $6 a month.
Then you just pay for your usage on top
of that, your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes.
However much you talk, text, and data you use, you pay for.
It's a fair price regardless.
And they have nationwide coverage.
And like I said, they've got two networks.
So there's a lot of devices you can bring.
Check their BYOD page.
There's no contracts, no service agreements,
or no weird loopholes where they try to get you
for a couple of years.
And they've got the best control panel
in the business for mobile.
So check it out by going to linux.ting.com.
That'll take $25 off your first device.
Oh, and it'll give you $25 in service credit
if you bring a device.
And they've got a lot of compatible devices.
I'm just saying.
Now every now and then, Crazy Ting has a crazy deal.
And they're blowing out the doors right now with $1 SIM
cards.
I'm serious.
This is it.
This is what no one I tell you about all the time.
Go buy 10 of them.
Seriously, go buy 10 of them.
Why not?
They're a dollar a SIM card.
And they don't even charge you until you activate them.
And then when you do activate them, they're $6.
So both Noah and I load up on these suckers.
I just bought five of them.
Go buy 10 of them.
Seriously.
I bought five of them because I'm poor.
But if you can afford 10 bucks, go buy 10 of them.
Because you can put them in your bag.
You can hand them out to people.
You're in an event.
Nothing says a baller like you're handing out data.
So go get the GSM SIM.
Go get the CDMA SIM, whatever you're about.
I don't care.
But the $1 deal on the Ting SIMs is about once a year.
And hallelujah, it is here.
So go grab it.
But first, start by going to linux.ting.com.
linux.ting.com.
So a big thank you to DigitalOcean,
a big thank you to Linux Academy,
and a big thank you to Ting, linux.ting.com,
for sponsoring this here episode of your unplugged program,
linux.ting.com.
All right, back to the news we go.
Brent, have you noticed the uptick in positive coverage
around Firefox OS?
I have in the show notes a link to a New York Times article.
Headline, Firefox is back.
It's time to give it a try.
In the freaking New York Times, Brent.
How about that?
You sent me this article, and I didn't think it was real.
But I love it.
I love it.
It's great.
That's a funny way to put it.
Yeah, when I first saw it, too, I was like,
that's not the New York Times.
That's something else.
Yeah, and they make the case.
They talk about how the web has become a dumpster fire.
Of course, they have a bit of an interest
there as an advertising-based company.
But they say Mozilla recently hit the reset button
on Firefox about two years ago.
Again, this is the freaking gray lady here.
About two years ago, six Mozilla employees
were huddled around a bonfire one night
in Santa Cruz, California, when they
begun discussing the state of web browsers.
Eventually, they concluded there was a crisis of confidence
in the web.
They write, if they don't trust the web,
they won't use the web.
That was Mozilla's chief product officer.
They just felt to us like, actually, it
might be the direction we're going, that people
might stop using the web.
So we started to think about tools and architectures that
brought a different approach.
Now Firefox is back there, right?
Mozilla released a new version late last year,
codenamed Quantum.
It's sleekly designed and fast.
Mozilla said the revamped Firefox
consumes less memory than the competition,
meaning you can fire up lots of tabs,
and browsing will still feel butterly smooth.
That's about as positive as it could possibly
get when you got the old gray lady writing about a web
browser, don't you think, Brent?
That doesn't get any better.
It feels to me like it's not actually the New York
Times that wrote that.
And they just write it.
It feels like, oh, yeah, oh, this is easy content,
feels really good.
And we're getting an audience that we don't typically get.
So maybe it's a win for everyone.
The Verge has got a podcast.
And in their podcast, they had an interview
with the Pocket CEO.
Pocket, as everybody knows, is baked into Firefox now.
So Nate Wiener went on the new Verge podcast, the Converge
podcast, and he said that they're
going to try something radical, something new, something
unheard of in the industry.
They're going to process your local data
to figure out what you like.
What?
By analyzing the articles and videos people save into Pocket,
Wiener believes the company can show people
the best of the web in a personalized way
without building an all-knowing Facebook-style profile
of the user.
They call it a personalization system within Firefox.
And I grabbed a clip from that interview in the Verge
podcast.
Yeah, we're testing this really cool personalization system
within Firefox, where it uses your browser history
to target, like, personalize, but none of that data
actually comes back to Pocket or Mozilla.
It all happens on the client inside the browser itself.
Because there is this notion today, I feel like, that,
and I feel like you saw it in the Zuckerberg hearings.
It was like, oh, users, they will give us
their data in return for a better experience.
And there's like, that's the premise, right?
But I feel like, yes, you could do that,
but we don't feel like that is the required premise,
that there are ways to build these things where
you don't have to trade your life profile in order
to actually get a good experience.
Oh, if that isn't music to my ears.
So they can use what people are saving
to Pocket and your local browsing history
and do the computation on device, which he goes on
to say later in the interview is how they're doing it.
They're looking at your web browsing history
on your device, all local.
None of it's being sent to Mozilla and comparing that
with what people are sharing in Pocket,
or saving, I should say, in Pocket.
And without ever having to build a huge online profile of you,
they're able to determine what you might be interested in.
I love this.
I know Pocket is controversial, Brent, but I love this.
It sounds almost like they're pushing in the right directions.
It's a nice mix of features that they're offering the user,
but also some privacy consciousness that
is refreshing, really.
Yeah.
It shouldn't be.
You know what I mean?
At this point.
It should be the standard, right?
Yeah.
It should be.
But it does feel refreshing.
That's a good way to put it.
Speaking of refreshing, Debian has been refreshed.
There is an update out there for those of you
still using Debian 8, Jesse.
Now, this is the last release.
It's the end of the line for Jesse.
So this is your public service announcement right here
on the show.
I know.
I know it's working fine for you, and you love it.
But look, your buddy Chris is just the messenger.
It's time to move on.
Why not upgrade to Debian 9, perhaps?
Now, the 8.11 release has a number
of bug fixes and security issues,
and it's shipping a new Nvidia graphics driver.
So you get some life out of it, but it's the end of the line.
It's really time for those of you still running Debian Jesse
to upgrade to version 9.
Because really, in terms of Debian,
10 is just around the corner.
Buster is kind of tentatively scheduled for a release
from a year from now.
So it's time to upgrade on the Debian scale of things.
Now, I don't think there's much wrong with MP3 these days.
Now that the patents have expired,
I'm more of a fan of MP3 than I ever have been.
You combine that with the crazy industry support from services
to hardware that MP3 seems to enjoy,
it's never going to be replaced.
Even when something better comes along, perhaps like Opus.
However, there is still a gap in the market for audiobooks
or really long podcasts, two, three, four-hour podcasts,
or longer.
There's not a good codec for that.
Opus isn't great for it either.
And our friends over at Alphonic,
which I'm going to tell you more about here in a moment,
you can find it at A-U-P-H-O-N-I-C.com.
Alphonic, it's German.
They have an idea called Codec 2.
Codec 2 is an open source designed for speech,
and it aims for compression rates between 700 bits
per second all the way up to 3,200 bits per second.
So it's really, really low bandwidth.
The man behind it is David Rowe.
He's an electronics engineer currently
living in South Australia.
He started the project in September of 2009,
with the main aim of improving low cost radio
communications for people living in remote areas of the world.
With this in mind, he set out to develop
a codec that would significantly reduce
file sizes and bandwidth required when streaming.
Let's check in some boxes.
Rowe's perceived applications included VoIP trunking,
voiceover low bandwidth, HF and VHF digital radios,
as well as worldwide remote area communications,
including military, police, and emergency services.
But Alphonic believes that it could
be used for long podcasts, presentations,
like talks at events, and audio books,
allowing for low storage and minimizing the effect
of bad network connections.
I think this is great, and I want
to tell you why I'm giving this so much credence.
It's from Alphonic.
And these guys, they really know audio.
They know audio so well that at the beginning of this year,
I switched out the entire Jupiter broadcasting backend
encoding system to Alphonic.
You probably noticed this maybe if you have a really tuned ear.
Our compression has sounded better recently
in the last three or four months.
You've also probably noticed chapter markers
in our podcasts, like this very here podcast.
Chapter markers and those features.
Also, the new YouTube videos that YouTubers don't really
like, but the ones that are automatically generated
with our album art that get published to YouTube
automatically from the main edited podcast file.
All of that is powered by Alphonic,
the service we are using now.
And that was the final piece that made us 100% Linux, too,
by the way.
I do plan to document all of this
at some point for the studio.
But the last bit, when we converted the entire studio
over to Linux, was we still had a Mac in the role of editing
and encoding for commercial software purposes for editing
and encoding purposes for software
that could add chapter markers.
We were able to convert the editing,
and now we have been able to convert
the encoding using Alphonic.
And I can tell you, as somebody who's been encoding podcasts
for 13 years, these guys have a great algorithm.
They have a great sound.
They have a great system.
It's a super good service that does way more than just
encode and upload video.
It does way more than that.
And if you're a podcaster, and you're
struggling with chapter markers, and you're
struggling with audio encoding, and you
want to publish to YouTube and SFTP and other services
like Libsyn, check out Alphonic, A-U-P-H-O-N-I-C.com.
Not open source, but the back end runs on Linux,
and they make it possible for us Linux podcasters
to do a complete 100% Linux solution.
And now they're throwing their weight
behind Codec 2, the podcast on a floppy disk codec.
I'm all about it.
I love Opus.
I love MP3.
I even think AAC is great.
But there is room for that audio book length
podcast or audio book that is just super long, four
plus hours.
That's where our current codecs just kind of fall down.
What do you think, Brent?
Am I crazy, or is this something you've run into yourself?
Well, some thoughts I had around that
was building giant libraries for ourselves.
If we're collecting content, especially audio books
are getting everywhere these days.
And sometimes that's the limit on some of these devices
that we own is space.
And so if you're able to hold, let's say,
a whole year's library worth of books,
audio books, on the devices that you take on a plane
or something like that, then all of a sudden you
don't need to buy devices as often,
perhaps, if that's your main limitation.
I know a lot of standard everyday users.
Fair enough, fair enough, yeah.
Yeah, you just want to have your own big library of,
I probably own 300 Audible books.
And it's not lost on me that they're all wrapped up
in the Audible DRM.
If there was a solution that wasn't Windows based
to rip that DRM out, I'd probably rip it out and just
store them somewhere.
And if I had a codec that was better for keeping them
long term, I absolutely would use it.
So that's a great point.
We're almost done.
Just one last story for the day.
I wanted to talk about GitLab because after Microsoft's
purchase of GitHub, it's been a huge, huge topic
of conversation.
And without missing a beat this week,
GitLab announced that they're moving off of Azure
and they're switching to Google Cloud, which
I think makes a lot of sense.
But they've also released their auto DevOps management system.
Now, that sounds fancy, right?
Auto DevOps?
I didn't know what it meant.
So I had an opportunity in last week's Coda Radio,
episode 313, to ask the GitLab CEO what
is auto DevOps in our interview with him.
And here's what he had to say.
Now, a little birdie tells me, speaking
of some of those features, that there's
something called auto DevOps that's coming along.
And I was wondering if you could share little details
about auto DevOps.
Yeah, so we're really, really bullish on auto DevOps.
On a week from now, June 22, we'll release GitLab 11.0.
And auto DevOps will be generally available.
And what you do is you just push your code
and GitLab does the rest.
It will build your code, run your tests, check the quality,
do static application security testing, dependency scanning,
license management, container scanning.
It will boot up a review app, kind
of like a staging environment, per merge request,
dynamic application security testing, and deploy it.
It will do browser performance testing,
and it will do monitoring of all the vital metrics.
So all of that just by pushing your code,
nothing to configure.
We think that is the future, and we're
really excited about having it out to the world.
Doesn't that sound fascinating?
They're just hustling.
It was a great interview we had with the GitLab CEO.
Go check out coder.show slash 313
if you'd like to get the entire thing.
Sid is really sharp.
He talks about how 100% of the GitLab staff are remote.
And of course, because it would be negligent if I didn't,
I asked him what his thoughts were on the whole Microsoft
purchasing GitHub thing and how that is going
to affect GitLab long term.
So again, go check that out, coder.show slash 313
if you want to hear that full interview.
Brent, man, thank you for making it today.
I don't know what your availability looks like,
but if you are around next Tuesday,
I would more than be happy to have you join us again.
I don't see any reason not to hang out
with everybody on Tuesdays.
Atta boy.
You know what?
Everybody, everybody, everybody should have that philosophy.
In fact, you could.
If you go over to our IRC room, you can get the secret details.
But if you just Google Jupiter colony mumble,
you'll probably find it.
But if you're in our IRC room, irc.geekshed.net pound
hashtag Jupiter broadcasting, you can chat during the show,
and you can also do bang mumble and get the mumble info.
And then you can join our virtual lug,
just like many folks did, like Ian and Dusty and many others.
You can find out all of that at the Jupiter colony site
or in our IRC chat room.
We do this show live on a Tuesday.
You're more than welcome to join us.
Get it converted to your local time at jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode.
Links to everything we talked about at linuxunplug.com,
as well as our subscribe links.
Thanks for being here.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Bye.
Oh, there we go, Brent.
We're officially in over, or not overtime, in post-show.
Overtime's for something else.
Thank you, sir, for making it.
Appreciate it.
Now we need everybody to go to JBtitles.com and vote their heart out, because there's
a lot of good titles, 36 titles over there.
There's some good ones.
Fedora to the core, at a drop of a hat, contained in a pocket.
Get your pocket, quantum is a sign of the times.
Oh, get it?
Do you get it?
That's good, right?
That's so good.
I got to make good, I want to do on the show, because there's so many web apps we use these
days that I never, ever, ever have talked about Netafire, and it is a wrong that I must
write right now.
It's NPM, so you got to have all the NPM stuff installed, which is pretty straightforward
these days, on any given Linux distro.
But it's called Netafire, and it does exactly what you're probably guessing, is it takes
like a web application and makes it a standalone, like Node.js style, Electron app.
Catch your breath.
So take for example, you want to take Google Docs, or in my case, IRC Cloud, or something
else that you always have to use in the damn browser, and you'd like to just have it as
a standalone application on your desktop that gets its own taskbar entry.
That's where Netafire comes in, and it's just NPM installed, Netafire-G, I'll have a link
in the show notes, it's solid.
I've been using it now for months to run IRC Cloud, to run Source Connect, to run a whole
bunch of other stuff.
I just want to give it a plug right now, Netafire, if you're stuck using web applications that
you really would rather have their own damn desktop entry, check out Netafire.
I think it's pretty good stuff.