So you hear all the hype about mechanical keyboards, but they're really expensive, let's be honest.
So that's where the Buckle Spring project comes in.
It's nostalgic keyboard sounds that emulate the sound of the old faithful IBM Model M
keyboard.
The author of the project has painstakingly captured the sound of each key.
This is a real conversation that I typed up to Westpane, and this is what it sounds like.
And it runs on your machine, in the background, and as you type, it makes these sounds come
out your speakers.
Finally an answer for that problem where I'm at the coffee shop, but no one knows how nerdy
I am, and now I can bother all of them.
It's on-demand Model M typing.
You're welcome.
We'll have a link to that in the show notes.
A lot of fun.
Hello friends, welcome into your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Lance.
And this episode is brought to you by a Cloud Guru, the leader in hands-on learning.
The only way to learn a new skill is by doing.
That's why ACG provides hands-on labs for Cloud Linux servers and much more.
Get your hands cloudy at a CloudGuru.com.
Coming up on this week's episode, we're finally doing it.
We have gotten so many requests into the show, and it seemed like now, at the beginning of
the year, when there's so much left to happen, it was the time to try out OpenSUSE.
We gave it a go, essentially wrapped up last week's episode, and Wes and I loaded it up.
Been running it on some metal directly, and I think we both opted for the tumbleweed route.
Wes and I have not been telling each other much about our experience to save it for the
show.
Secret, secret.
You went tumbleweed though, right?
I sure did.
Yeah, I mean, our kind of thought here was, we feel like there's a lot in the air for
OpenSUSE.
Like, some stuff's going to happen this year, and there's also a lot of momentum behind
rolling distributions, and Arch is always the go-to example that's cited.
But SUSE has been at this for a while now, and is it a viable Arch alternative?
Is it a workstation rolling OS?
So we wanted to give it a go and relay our experiences to you with OpenSUSE at Tumbleweed,
and we'll do that in a little bit.
But of course, we also have some really great community news.
We have a pick that's fantastic, it's going to make you way more productive, and a lot
more.
So to help us get through all of this, we have to turn to our crack team.
Time appropriate greetings, Momorub.
Hello.
Greetings.
Howdy.
Buenos tardes.
Happy New Year, everybody.
Here's a New Year's taco for you.
And thanks for being here.
We have some community news to start with.
And I don't know what's going on here, so I just wanted to have an open conversation
in the show, because I bet a lot of you have seen the recent news about Steam data.
It appears that Linux market share has slid badly over the holiday period.
And one of the reasons I wanted to talk about this is because the numbers are so dramatic,
it's going to kind of make its rounds.
And I think we can explain what's happening.
Steam published their annual, or no, monthly, whatever it is, their frequent survey that
I never seem to get ever, ever on my Linux box.
Have you ever gotten a Steam hardware survey, Wes?
Actually for the first time ever this year.
I mean, I've gotten it a ton of times on my Windows gaming box that I seldom mention,
but on all the Linux ones, no, never, except this one.
So I was glad, and of course, I immediately filled it out.
Yeah, well, so I think maybe once ever in all of the years, but according to the published
numbers from Valve, this came out on January 1st, so it was like a real kick in the stomach
at the beginning of the year, the Linux market share on Steam had a pretty significant drop.
It was just 0.5%.
We were hoping to get to 1% soon.
It was a drop of 0.33%, which is pretty major in these numbers.
And Windows picked up a pretty decent market share, just over 1.6% additional market share.
Mac OS didn't do so well either, but the first round of numbers out of Valve looked kind
of devastating just because, you know, over the holiday period, you hope more people are
playing video games.
Yeah, and there's been some updates there, Valve's updated those numbers, but they still
point to Linux regressing, really doesn't look great.
After being at 0.9% for the month of November, Valve's revised December 2020 numbers, put
the Linux gaming market share at 0.74%, or a drop of 0.16%.
Yikes.
Yeah, so not as significant, but still not good, and kind of hard to understand when
Proton is making it possible to play more games than ever.
The library of available Linux games is greater than it's ever been, and the compatibility
is greater than it's ever been.
But I think you have to consider, I could be wrong because who really knows here, but
you have to consider Cyberpunk 2077 came out around the time that the survey was conducted.
That is true, yeah.
And I think, although people could confirm in the chat room, but I'm pretty sure that
you're more likely to get the survey on a new install.
So perhaps people were setting up Windows 10 machines or reloading Steam after not having
it for a while.
Oh, that is interesting, you know, I did get mine on a fresh Pop OS setup for gaming that
I recently set up.
Hmm.
Mm hmm.
There's an increase in Chinese users that are running pirated versions of Windows 10
on Steam.
So that makes a difference as well.
I'm not kidding.
That's actually one of the one of the things that's been attributed in here.
And then you have to kind of just think that just increased usage in general.
So people that maybe weren't normally online, but are on Windows came online to play Cyberpunk
2077.
I mean, it was the most hyped game of the year.
Well, and even just over the holiday periods, I know I've seen some friends I don't always
or even frequently see on Steam suddenly popping back up with, you know, a little time over
the holidays to boot their Windows box back up.
100%.
Same here, Wes.
You know, I'm on Steam a couple of times a week at the most really just to play games
with my kids.
And I see more people on there than ever playing Cyberpunk and other games right now.
I've been trying it out on Stadia, figured put my Stadia subscription to use.
And I've been playing it on the Koda radio pre show for about three weeks straight.
And it's been fine, you know, just fine, really.
Stadia has actually done a pretty decent job.
You're almost making me want to check Stadia out again, just because I mean, I'm not probably
not going to build a rig just right now for Cyberpunk, but I could play it on Stadia.
No problem.
Yeah, especially if you can get like a Stadia credit like I had or something.
So you're not paying full price for the game, because remember, you can't use it off of
Stadia.
Right.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
But yeah, so as things now point, it looks like the Linux market percentage on Steam
is around 0.74%.
So we were at, we were really close to 1%.
We've now slid back to 0.74%.
And Mac OS is at 2.74%.
And Windows 96.51%.
We're coming for you, Windows.
We are.
And it does make me wonder, how do the folks over at Valve actually view this?
You know, because we're looking at it from one direction, surely there's a bunch of folks
over in the, you know, Windows gaming camp laughing at us as usual.
But it doesn't seem like Valve has really slacked off on continuing to build and work
on Proton and continue those things.
I just hope that, you know, some of the folks there internally get the sense that I think
we've had on the show and in the community that it's a better time than ever to be a
Linux gamer.
I'm gaming way more than I have in like the past five years.
And I just hope that momentum continues.
Great points all around.
I'm gaming more on Linux than I ever have in a while too.
My kids are as well.
And I think your point is well taken.
The reason why we care about this number, even though it is, I mean, let's be honest,
it's a rather insignificant number, I think maybe that's why we care about it so much
is it clearly has made such a difference that Valve has invested as much as it has into
gaming on Linux.
And we are trying to understand the logic, justification and likelihood that it will
continue.
That's what we're doing here with these numbers.
That's the conversation that's not being had is we are just trying to piece together what
is Valve's motivation here and my God, will they please keep doing it?
And if these numbers go the wrong way, I think the unspoken worry here is that Valve will
just give up and say, Jesus, look at this 96.5% of our user base is on Windows.
We're kidding ourselves here.
They never built that store that put us out of business.
Right.
You got to hope that, you know, Gabe's involved in that there's not some bean counters somewhere
that looks at that and then looks at the amount they're spending on engineers or contracts
working on it and say, this doesn't add up.
And Eric, you're pointing out that they could do a better job at just answering some of
these questions around how the survey works.
Yeah, I've always been kind of frustrated when you see these surveys out there.
But I did like Knochel's approach back when Will Cook was on the desktop team and they
did that nice blog post on kind of the metrics that they got at a glance.
But as a numbers guy, I do wish there was a bit more information on how they exactly
identify which, say, Linux user they send the survey to.
Like you said, Chris, you didn't get one forever, it seems like.
I mean, what's their policy or what's their procedures around that?
It just would be nice to know.
Yeah.
And it's definitely not just if it's a new install or not, because I install Steam on
just about every laptop or machine I review.
And that's about one a month or somewhere around there, right?
And I'm doing that 12 times a year, and I'm still not getting the survey.
So yeah, I agree, Eric.
Some transparency there.
We at least have to answer some questions about how that all works.
All right.
We can probably cover the rest of that if you guys have any other comments from the
Mumble Room in the post show, because I think people probably care more about this next
story to tell you the truth.
Because I got fired up when I read this.
I agree with Linus, ECC RAM matters, error correcting code memory.
And he says it quote, absolutely matters in a fun holiday mailing thread.
As ever, Linus was happy to share a little more detail around his opinions and said that
Intel has been instrumental in killing the whole ECC industry with its horribly bad market
segmentation.
Intel has been detrimental to the whole industry into users because of their bad and misguided
policies with respect to ECC.
Seriously, the arguments against ECC were always complete and utter garbage.
Now even the memory manufacturers are starting to do ECC internally, because they finally
owned up to the fact that they absolutely have to.
And the menu memory manufacturers claim it's because of economics and the lower power.
But they are lying bastards.
Let me once again point out Row Hammer and how these problems have existed for several
generations already.
But these effers happily sold broken hardware to consumers and claimed it was an attack
when it was always just we're cutting corners.
Man, this is a classic brutal Linus take down.
He went on to say in this rather lengthy post, the modern DRAM is so reliable that it doesn't
need ECC was always a bedtime story for children that have been dropped on their heads a bit
too many times.
Yeah, I'm pissed about it.
You can find me complaining about this literally for decades now.
I don't want to say I was right.
I just want this fixed and I want ECC.
AMD did it.
Intel didn't.
Wow, man, like I thought, OK, here's what I really liked about why this happened is
I thought I was the jerk that was just going on about ECC all the time and that it really
was just like in my head that my systems with ECC were way better because obviously, if
ECC RAM actually made your system more stable, this is what I thought, obviously, if that
actually worked, it would be everywhere.
It'd be in our phones.
It'd be in our desktops.
Right.
Here's this better way to do it.
Why are we doing it?
But I always like, gosh, you know, I've had workstation desktop workstation machines and
servers with ECC RAM, and I've had lots of desktops and laptops and even servers that
don't have ECC RAM.
And unquestionably, in my personal hands-on experience, those systems with error correcting
code are more reliable.
I like this reminder of Linus's deep hardware background and interest here.
And the whole history is kind of interesting.
I know there was a lot of stuff being discussed around Google's rise as suddenly the data
center was taken over by, you know, just cheap Intel boxes and some of these bigger companies
just sort of trying to handle all these corrections in software and sort of preaching like, look,
you can save on your hardware budgets.
Don't bother with the fancy ECC stuff.
You know, just make sure you've got redundant calculations and that you're handling these
sorts of sometimes failures in software.
But especially these days, it just seems like if we need our computers to work right, security
is more important than ever.
Everything's interconnected and online.
And we've already solved this, right?
I mean, why can't you just buy it for the machine that you want to run your software
on?
Yeah.
And it also, I think, really gives us kind of insight into some of the blame that Linus
puts on Intel for harming the industry.
You and I were just doing a review of a lot of the stories for 2020 on the latest Linux
Action News.
And when we were going through those, you see several times where Linus is pinning something
directly on Intel.
And I think you might agree, although I'd be curious if you don't, when you kind of
go through what Linus has said about Intel over 2020 chronologically, the more the year
goes on, the more hostile towards Intel he seems to be getting.
And then you start to see even Greg Kh starting to take shots at Intel as the year wraps up.
Oh, yeah.
No, I definitely think that's true.
And it's interesting because obviously they've got, you know, a long history, both in the
industry at large and, of course, just working together because Intel's, you know, contributes
a whole bunch of great open source work to the kernel and to the Linux and open source
community generally.
But I think we're all really starting to feel some of their missteps that they really aren't
on a solid course or at least haven't been.
Yeah.
Yep.
And that's starting to hurt.
I know we have AMD, but it's interesting times ahead for Intel.
It's clear that the pressure is on like never before.
So you have Linus laying this pressure down.
He even goes on later in the post to compliment and commend AMD for their more broad support
of ECC RAM, even on consumer desktop hardware.
You have Apple, of course, with the M1 chip.
Even RISC-V applies pressure.
You have all of these pressures that are getting applied.
And then you bring in AMD, who is compatible with the x86 platform.
It's a tremendous amount of pressure.
You have to figure something's going to give.
It'll be interesting to watch anyway.
I mean, there's even more pressure from like investment advisors and capital groups who
maybe even are pushing for Intel to sort of abandon their own system of having their own
fabs.
Now, I don't know that that's going to happen anytime soon, but probably the next two, three
years will be very instructive for what's next.
I have thoughts about where Intel's going right now with their current processors.
But we'll get to that later.
I'll mention that maybe in a bit in the show.
There's so much really, boy, you look at it from a New Year's perspective.
It's kind of exciting how much is going to, you can tell there's a lot that's going to
shift this year.
It's going to be a big year for this kind of stuff.
lino.com slash unplugged.
Go there to receive a $100 60-day credit towards your new account and you support the show.
And $100 in like Linode terms is a lot.
You can really build out some significant cool projects, try things out, do a test migration
of Nextcloud.
I mean, you name it.
We right now are using Linode for everything.
The show notes now that we're doing this on, we've recently spun up, thanks to Alex's help,
a new instance of HedgeDock.
If you're not familiar with that, it used to be called Code EMD.
It's a real-time markdown collaboration tool.
Just dominates.
Anything like Google Docs, if you're doing real-time markdown collaboration.
And you can self-host it on Linode in seconds.
Just get started by going to linode.com slash unplugged.
You know, I was just looking at our Matrix server that we have on Linode.
And Matrix is an interesting use case because there's some scenarios, like when a user connects
that has a lot of rooms and stuff, that initial login can put a significant load on the Matrix
server, Synapse.
Yeah, there's some work to do over there.
I'm just reviewing the CPU usage from the last few days.
You can even see as the shows are live, the things spin up, the disk I.O. rate spins up.
The way Linode makes it possible to view all of this in their dashboard is really, really
smart.
It's laid out in a way where you get all the information you need right away.
So it's kind of in these sections.
The first section up on the screen, and by the way, it's all beautifully designed.
But the first section up's like, it's your details you need to know.
How many cores?
How much RAM?
What's your IP?
And what's your SSH access?
Like you hit this button, copy it to your pasteboard, copy it to your clipboard, and
log right in using this.
And then you scroll down and you get all of the CPU and disk and network information.
And we actually get a fair amount of IPv6 traffic too, but nothing like we do on the
IPv4 side.
But you get all of this.
And I can see, you know what, we're doing really well.
We've proportioned this when this system burst during the start of a live stream.
We're getting up there in usage, 85%, maybe 90% on a really busy day, but we're not maxing
this box out.
And I can tell that, yep, we have specced this one just right for what we're doing.
And it makes it so simple to see that or add storage or tweak things or do backups, which
again, because this is a community server, as a responsibility to our community, we want
to make sure that we have a backup of this thing if something goes wrong.
So I can go over to the backup tab and I can see, yeah, three minutes and 17 seconds ago,
there was a backup.
It's really great.
You can also take manual snapshots, like we might do that before a big matrix upgrade.
There's all kinds of things you can do through the dashboard that make managing a cloud server
really simple, even if you're not an expert.
And if you are an expert, things are just a click away to really take it to the next
level.
And the node costs 30% to 50% less than major cloud providers like AWS, Google Cloud, or
Azure.
So it's a nice balance of technology for the price with the optimal machines, SSD storage,
40 gigabit connections, 11 data centers all over the world.
And they're true Linux users, like as a company, like they're fans of Linux and God, I just
love that about them too.
And they're independently owned.
They've been around forever.
They started three years before AWS.
They're independent and they're the largest independent cloud provider.
So go check them out at linode.com slash unplugged, get that $100 credit, support the show.
And it lets Linode know that, yeah, we're getting some investment when we support open
source media, when we support independent media, and they can then turn around and make
that for free.
We get a return on that investment and everybody wins.
So thanks for supporting our sponsors, linode.com slash unplugged.
So I have a story in here that I think at first pass.
It's like, why is this on Linux Unplugged?
Because the story headline is Microsoft is building a new Outlook app for Windows and
the Mac powered by web technologies.
Chris, this is a Linux show.
You know that, right?
Right.
And you know what's also funny is how the tech press doesn't know what this stuff is.
They don't just say electron, right?
This is windowscentral.com.
Microsoft owns electron.
Why not just say they're going to use electron?
Why say web technologies?
But the idea is that they're going to build a universal Outlook client for Windows and
Mac as far as the press calls it, that also replaces the default mail and calendar apps
on Windows 10 when it's ready.
That's how far they're going to go.
The new project is codenamed Monarch, and it's based already on the Outlook web app.
So if you're familiar with Outlook web app, which I am roughly familiar with, that's essentially
what it's going to be.
Yeah.
And I mean, this kind of makes sense.
Outlook Monarch is basically the end goal for Microsoft's one Outlook vision, which
aims to build a single Outlook client that works across the PC, Mac and the web.
They really just want to replace existing desktop clients with just one app built with
the same technologies that they already have to use to leverage those web versions.
And I don't know about you, but even on the platforms I have that have that native Outlook
app, I end up just using the web one anyway.
Yeah, it is a lot better than the battle days of Exchange.
It's gotten a lot better, and it works just fine on Linux in a browser.
Microsoft told Zach at Windows Central that they will do native integrations where possible.
They're going to try to make it feel like a native application, look like a native application,
offer offline storage, notifications and more.
But you have to figure, like they are doing now with some of their other applications,
VS Code, which is also an Electron app, they're probably going to release the sucker for Linux
too.
And I think it will totally freaking dominate on Linux when they do.
I think it will destroy the Thunderbird market share for anyone who's in a corporate environment
that needs solid calendar integration with the rest of the company, be it Google Apps,
Microsoft Exchange, Office 365, whatever it might be.
If you are in the corporate world, and I think this even applies to you, Wes, imagine if
you could have an Outlook client that ties in perfectly with the day job, it does good
with the reminders that you can accept meeting invites, you can create meeting invites, you
get the directory, everything works as a full-fledged client like your coworkers on Windows and
Mac, you'd probably be compelled to use that.
Yeah, I definitely would, especially if you've got some of those nicer features.
The web version works well enough, but yeah, there's some nice desktop integrations you
get if you go the full Electron route.
Yes.
And I have a ton of old school nostalgia love for Thunderbird.
I still think it's a great personal email client.
I have it installed.
I have it.
Totally agree.
I like that's like all the family like, happy holidays and Merry Christmas emails that I
sent out, did them all from Thunderbird, you know, connected to my Gmail account.
That's great, but for the two years that I was an employee at a company that had lots
of meetings and did everything by calendar, it was a big part of the company culture,
I spent that entire two years struggling on a daily basis trying to make things work.
I tried MailSpring, I tried applications that house web apps inside a giant local application.
I tried Kmail, Thunderbird, Evolution, Geary, everything, MailSpring got abandoned, which
was already a mail Electron app that sort of had the best integration and made it really
easy to work with calendar invites, but MailSpring was abandoned.
And to this day, I've just kind of resigned to using the Google Gmail web app whenever
I am working on any kind of serious correspondence, even just serious correspondence and where
I want my address book and I want calendar abilities and all of that, I just use the
web app.
Yeah.
Same here, right?
I mean, the web email, basically.
Yeah.
And I pine for a local email client.
I prefer local email.
I prefer a local window.
I like actually having as few applications in my browser as possible.
And I would absolutely give this a try.
I'm at that point.
I wonder, too, if this might be, you know, just one more bolster sort of to reassure
corporate IT departments, you know, sure, like you can have your Linux desktop maybe
and you've gotten some special permission or you've just set it up without asking.
But suddenly, one weird thing doesn't work and they're like, well, you know, we were
tested just fine in the desktop app on Windows and Mac and I don't know what your problem
is.
But if suddenly there is this, you know, single blessed web powered version and it runs on
Linux, I mean, I remember less of four years ago and I had to run Windows VM just for Outlook
integration because there was some stuff that OWA still couldn't do.
That future, I mean, that looks like we're way beyond this.
I bought every version of Crossover Office.
I bought every release of Xandros OS, which was a Debian based KDE desktop environment
that shipped Crossover integrated so you could even put the Office 98 or whatever it was,
2003, probably into the CD-ROM drive and it would even recognize the autostart file and
just give you the full install experience.
But think about this Wes, for better or for worse, think about the complete picture once
Outlook is released, Fedora and Ubuntu out of the box during the installation offer Active
Directory integration.
You log in, you've got Microsoft Edge to browse your corporate intranet.
You've got Microsoft Teams to do all of your team collaboration Slack style chat.
You've got Microsoft Outlook to do all of your corporate email correspondence.
You see where I'm going with this, VS Code, et cetera.
Don't forget.NET Core, right?
That's available too.
And let's be honest, they're not going to stop with Outlook.
Microsoft didn't add Electron to their arsenal of technologies that they own so that way
they could just let it piss off in the corner.
They're starting with Outlook because Outlook is the high bar.
They're starting high and they're going to knock out Outlook and they're coming for Word,
they're coming for Excel, they're coming for PowerPoint, they're coming for the entire
Office 365 suite, which are already web apps.
And then they're going to ship them on Linux.
It's interesting too.
It does sort of seem like it's a more reinforcement that the Windows side of the house really
is no longer the dominant, you know, tastemaker internally because they've clearly aligned
to the goal of like, we just want to get our stuff in the hands of as many people as possible,
regardless of if they have to use our other platform.
It's pretty wild to see this coming and it may not be until the end of the year until
we really see anything materialized.
And then it may be a while after that before we see the Linux support.
Just like with Edge, I wouldn't be surprised that if Microsoft takes the approach of they
focus on the Mac and Windows versions first because it's a narrower problem scope.
And then once they have those shipping, they begin working on a Linux alpha and beta.
Yes.
And I mean, the same thing happened with Teams.
It was quite some time before the Linux version came out.
But hey, now it's here and seems to be working pretty darn well.
Oh, live update from Popey in the IRC.
He just checked around on their GitHub and it looks like the developer popped up 20 days
ago for Mailspring.
Oh, thank goodness.
So I'll be looking into that.
So maybe Mailspring is still alive.
It may save me yet from an outlook future, but yeah, they're not going to have anything
until like maybe even 2022 is when you may actually see it start replacing the apps.
They may have like an early version build client that you can get on Windows or Mac
by the end of this year, but replacing the default application on the Windows desktop,
that's a 2022 thing.
So it's going to be a bit and the Linux beta will be somewhere in there, right?
We shall see.
There's also just a couple of community things we want to touch on before we move on.
Number one is Fosdom, which is a pretty significant conference every single year, Europe's largest
free and open source conference.
Thousands of people, I think last year it was nearly 9,000 people, take over a campus
in Belgium for a weekend and turn it into quite the event, 800 talks, 50 tracks, hundreds
of exhibitors.
It's really intense.
It's like I guess the most intense of all of them.
I've always wanted to go and maybe this year I can because it looks like the Matrix project
reached out to them and said, hey, we know you want to be virtual for February of 2021.
I think we can facilitate that.
Isn't that interesting?
I mean, Matrix has all kinds of great technology under the hood to make this happen and well,
you know, thankfully Fosdom 2020 snuck in just a few weeks before this whole pandemic
really got into full swing.
Of course, with Fosdom 2021 happening just in February, this upcoming February, you got
to start figuring this out right now.
I don't think we're going to be in any state to, you know, do an in-person one yet.
So they just have to start planning for it.
But Matrix, Wes, I mean, it's brilliant, right?
It's an open protocol.
There's something great about that for an open source conference like Fosdom, but the
video stuff and all of that is really still early on Matrix and really Elements the only
client that has the most complete implementation right now.
Yeah, I suppose in one sense, maybe that's risky or we'll see what parts all get adopted,
how far the integration goes.
But on the other side, that might be a really good sort of dogfooding stress test for some
of those technologies.
The other part that I like about this is it seems like more and more of the Matrix team,
they're reaching out, they're pushing Matrix, they're trying to get it into places that
make sense, whether that's, you know, various government things that are looking for protocols
or open source conferences.
And I both like that as a way to build Matrix.
But I think it also speaks well to just the project structure and internal organization
and they know they've got time for this.
This is something they can take on and actively continue to develop Matrix.
So it's just a good sign to me.
Yeah, and I'll push forward certain things in Matrix.
It looks like they're going to use a good helping of Jitsi in here to handle some of
the video heavy lifting.
Of course.
That's brilliant.
So what you're going to see from this is a notch up in the network effect of Matrix.
And that I'm particularly excited about because I think you're going to see several projects
over this next year switch their chat and collaboration infrastructure over to Matrix.
There's some that are in conversations about doing it right now.
That's going to increase the amount of Matrix users.
An event like FOSDEM taking place on Matrix, that's going to increase the number of Matrix
users.
And we're going to start to see this network effect where something that's based on an
open standard that has open source implementations that is really kind of this next generation
protocol for the web or its own layer on the internet, it's going to have more users now.
And that's going to be a net win for free software just in general.
So by FOSDEM doing this, I actually think the contribution is more significant than
just their event.
It's actually fairly significant.
And even if the effect just has the Matrix team and the element team work a little bit
harder in more of a sprint style to get ready for February to have some of these features
more polished, even that is a great net benefit for all of us.
And then last, rounding out the community news, just a brief mention that KDE Plasma 5.20.5
shipped today.
And it's just a real nice polishing of the 5.20 series.
And this is, I think, a great indicator of the stage that the Plasma project is in right
now.
They announced today as we're recording this release, and it just fixes for visual glitches
that maybe impacted GTK3 apps or System Tray had an arrow problem that was hiding some
things.
And the one that is the most significant that drove me fricking batty, and I'm very happy
to see it patched, is there was an issue with the Plasma Network Manager applet that would
jump to a different network.
So as you're searching and it's finding the networks of Wi-Fi networks, you click Connect
and start entering the password, and then it jumps and the connect registers for a different
wireless network.
And then you go through it over and over again.
It was infuriating.
And it actually struck me while using OpenSUSE of Tumbleweed, and at first I thought it was
some weird bug, but I quickly figured out it was a Plasma thing.
So nice to see that fixed, because if you've been using recent Plasma and you've run into
that, you know how painful that was.
It was really bad.
I was also pretty pleased to see better support for WebRTC-powered meetings and screencast
and stuff like that if you're using the Plasma Wayland session, which I know not a whole
bunch of people are, but it's exactly the kind of thing that needs to get solved if
we're going to have more Plasma Wayland adoption.
Yeah, if you're using Plasma for your day job and you're on Wayland, you sometimes need
to participate in meetings where you're sharing your screen.
And so to see that kind of stuff get plumbed in is really nice.
So 5.21, so the next big release of Plasma, which is scheduled for February, has a new
system monitor app in it.
And I gave it a go because it's available already for some distributions.
It's just Plasma System Monitor, and it's going to replace ksysguard.
Now these are the tools that let you look at memory usage, process usage, CPU usage
on the Plasma desktop, sort of like akin to Task Manager on Windows.
And it's getting a really nice upgrade in Plasma.
I'll leave the link in the show notes for you guys to go check it out, but it's a completely
rewritten UI, and you can now also easily create and edit pages where you can put your
own items on this dashboard, sort of akin to Perfmon on Windows.
Just tons of categories of stuff in there, and you can put a nice heads up display.
It looks good.
And this, in my opinion, Wes, these types of system monitor apps where you get an insight
into what your box is doing, they can never be good enough.
Like there's always more work to be done, and this thing's sharp looking.
Yes, it is.
And actually, as noted by Nate Graham, who we just had on the show in episode 385, notes
that it's been in development for almost two years.
And hopefully, it will eventually replace ksysguard once it's a little more tested out
in the wild.
But for now, it stays independent.
But you're totally right.
I mean, even Windows, they've improved a lot of their resources.
They've got pretty graphs now.
If you want to go just pull up your task manager and check out what your system is doing.
And even though we're going to promote all the next latest top replacement tools in the
shell, of course, or just talk about NetData, I think for users who just, you know, are
into Linux, are starting things up, or just want to have a native app that shows what
their system is doing, it's important that this works well.
Because the kernel in our user space, we have all the tools there.
It just needs the plumbing and a little bit of prettiness.
All right, we have a spot of housekeeping this week, a few things to mention.
Number one, I just kind of referred to it earlier.
But if you have not yet checked out Linux Action News 170, there was a lot of open source
development in a very crazy 2020.
And we recap some of the standout moments that you should know about.
And there's a few items in there you may have missed.
So it's a great episode to get caught up on some of the things that happened in 2020.
With linuxactionnews.com slash one seven zero.
Also, I'm going to encourage you to check out this week's coder radio episode 395 coder
dot show slash 395.
It's not out as we record yet.
But I've already recorded it with Mike.
And I was sent the XPS 13 developer edition that comes pre installed with Ubuntu.
And it has the 11th gen Intel CPU with XE graphics.
And I think you're going to be really surprised by my review of that laptop.
And we're going to talk about more specifically the XE graphics aspect in next week's episode.
Wendell from level one techs is scheduled to join us and geek out on the XE graphics
under Linux.
So it'd be good context if you check out coder radio 395 to get an idea of what I was able
to do with that laptop and sort of the situation I find myself in now.
So that'll be coder dot show slash 395 later this week.
And then that brings us to Sunday, where you can join the love plug every single Sunday
at noon Pacific three p.m. Eastern, you can get the mumble information at linux unplug
dot com.
And mini Mac, you wanted to put a word out to an upcoming special love love.
Yes, indeed.
So first, I hope you all had a good start in 2021.
And yeah, we had our first love love meeting for this year last Sunday, and we scheduled
a new recording session.
So the subject will be access accessibility features in Linux.
So we are talking about assistive tools like screen magnifier, screen reader, and so on.
And the recording will most probably be the 24th of January.
We have a community member that would like to share his experience with us.
And he also contacted a special guest whose name I will not yet reveal.
All I can say he is a developer for a well known desktop environment project.
Now what I would like to do is a call for participation for that talk.
If you have some experience with accessibility features in Linux and want to be a speaker
during that talk, please contact me either on IRC, Telegram or matrix.
So just send a message to Minimac or even simpler, just join the next love love session
next Sunday and we can talk about that.
So that's all for me.
Thanks, Chris.
Yeah, great.
That sounds like a fantastic topic.
Again, that's going to be held on the 24th.
And there is a love love matrix channel.
If you'd like to get involved in chat there, you can find our matrix info on the website
as well.
matrix unplugged.com Okay, so after the show last week, Wes and I looked at each other
and said, What are we going to do about open suits?
Because we get a lot of requests into the show to try it out because it's not a distribution
we cover very often because neither one of us run it on the regular.
But we we know there's a lot in the works for open suits over 2021.
And we feel like it was time to check in.
And I am intrigued by the idea that I could throw tumbleweed the rolling release on my
laptop.
And we could do something like leap on the server, which is the more LTS release.
Isn't that a nice thought?
Because there's so much you know, I know we both love arch running that.
But even though we do have a server with arch, we acknowledge that probably you wouldn't
want to have a whole bunch of servers that are arch, right?
Why would you do it that way?
But it's nice to stay in the same ecosystem, we don't have to suddenly switch things out
or get used to all the little differences between things.
If you could have just one system that could run everywhere, including all those pies that
you have.
I mean, wouldn't that be the dream?
Yeah.
And it it does run I'm told, although I have yet to test it, although I think I will put
it on the pi 400.
Just to give that a go, I was running it on a Dell laptop that I had in for testing.
And I went with the DVD release.
So they still kind of like old school style, I love it, offer various sizes.
And then they even offer like an i 586 image if you want, along with the arm and x 64.
And then you pick like DVD or net install and as you as the name implies, net install
is just what you need to get the live environment up and then the packages are pulled down from
the repo.
And if you have a fast internet connection, I think that's probably the way to go.
You tried the live version though, Wes, and that was kind of different.
Well, I was confused from the start because I mean, you go over to the you know, the get
tumbleweed page, and they've got some tabs, if you want to go get you know, you can get
their cubic stuff, you can get the installation and they do have a they have a live tab with
live images.
But right at the top, they say please be aware of the following limitations.
They should not be used to install or upgrade tumbleweed, please use the tumbleweed media,
which I think they mean the installation media for that instead.
And they also note that these have limited package and driver selection, so they can't
be considered an accurate reflection as to whether tumbleweed will work on your hardware
or not.
And you know, that's a fair point and can probably be said of all live CDs.
But it was a little strange to me that although I could kind of try it out, I had to then
go get a totally separate installation media just to get things installed.
So I ended up just downloading the net install and doing it that way.
Well, see, that's just as confusing as it was for me, because I think about 97.5% of
the reason I would get a live disk would be to test how that distribution works with my
hardware.
And then if it works, I run the installer.
Now once it's once it's a distro that I know works great, and I'm just going to deploy
it all the time, I prefer having something that just boots right to the installer like
their primary media does.
But I just thought that the wording around limited package and driver selection, that
could just be implying, you know, there's no Nvidia driver here.
Or it could be implying that like it's some sort of super slimmed down kernel, it was
very confusing.
And I'm like, but that's why I use a live CD.
I've also kind of just been spoiled over the years of you know, okay, maybe it doesn't
matter right now when you've got like a test machine that you're using, you still got your
desktop.
But if you're someone who just has the one Linux machine, it's really a luxury that unlike
in the Windows world, I can still browse the internet with Firefox from the live CD while
I'm installing these new OS on my machine.
And it kind of sucks to not have that option.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, that I remember how cool that used to like Linux is so powerful.
I can I can play solitaire while I'm installing the OS.
But so you know, you had to hang around while I'm sitting here downloading the 4.6 gigabyte
or 4.28 gigabyte DVD image, which is kind of quaint.
I remember DVDs, but I wanted the full offline experience because I was going to take my
laptop home after the show and just do everything from home where I'm on a pretty limited connection
and I actually I want the DVD stuff.
So I sit down and I you know, after the download completes, I write to my media and you know,
you and I go our separate ways.
I sit down at home, and I boot off the live media.
And I've always really liked the SUSE grub boot screens.
I've always thought they just have always looked the best beyond like any other distro.
And I think that still holds true.
They're just they really get that first power on experience nice.
No kidding.
I definitely have that written down in my notes of just this feels slick and professional
and wow.
Things kind of then took a bit of a tumble, if you will, but when the installer loaded
up and I'm on a 4K screen system and the UI for the installer was so tiny that the entire
EULA fit on my screen.
There was no scroll bar.
The entire EULA fit.
It was absolutely teensy weensy and I couldn't see a way to magnify, you know, to double
it or whatever during the installation.
But I powered through and the installer got to the point where it seemed like this was
the opportunity for me to put it on Wi-Fi if I wanted to do that.
And boy is that an experience.
It's really old school because you set like you first have to set the encryption type
and it's like default to web and that's on one tab.
But then you on a different screen tell it to go scan for SSIDs and then on a different
tab you you set the IP settings and so on and so forth.
I mean it was a very strange experience and I wasn't even sure if I was connected to Wi-Fi
after all was said and done.
Did you experience this?
No.
You know thankfully I was installing from an ethernet cable old school so I didn't run
into that.
Although I did actually install a few other times in a virtual machine and had some similar
problems getting things connected which surprised me.
I obviously did have it connected because later on in the installer I got a prompt that
came up and it said the installer has detected a network connection.
If anybody's installed SUSE you've seen this.
Would you like to enable online repos?
And I thought well what are they asking me here?
Like the you know Ubuntu will phrase it would you like to pull down the latest packages
or that is that what they're asking me here?
Or they asking me that should I do I just want to make sure I add additional repositories
which I did.
So I said yes and then I saw which ones are checked and I said okay.
But then during the install it seemed like it was clearly pulling down packages from
the repository even though I had implicitly decided to use the offline media and it just
seems by opting to have online repositories I then started getting packages from the repos
during the installation which is fine except for I was again on a limited LTE connection
and would prefer to save the bandwidth.
You had planned to not do that.
You know interestingly on my you know the Netver install version it asked me the exact
same question and I didn't try this maybe I will after the show.
I don't know what happens if I would have said no because there weren't any other package
sources to use.
Yeah that's a good question right yeah especially on the net install and then the other thing
that seemed particularly challenging with the large Dell trackpad is it was registering
clicks weird.
I had to get really far down in the corner of the trackpad in a way I don't normally
have to do on any other Linux distribution and to kind of make the situation a little
more frustrating although yet helpful at the same time every time I would try to like click
next and I wasn't in the precise bottom of the of the far left corner of the trackpad
I would get a dialog box that came up by Yas that says you seem to have misclicked would
you like to swap the buttons but the way the dialog is stated is not actually really clear
I wasn't sure what what I'd be swapping and how and I didn't actually mean to do it so
then I had like a dialog I had to clear and then I had to go try to click my next button
again and I have never had this with this trackpad happened before and I'm not quite
sure what was going on there it felt like it was acting like a ps2 mouse but again not
really a deal breaker it just made it not quite as smooth as maybe setting up fedora
or Ubuntu but you know at the end of the day it was easy to get through I think that's
another version where you're not in the same environment right you're not on just a regular
desktop that has a program that runs and installs you're in a dedicated installation environment
which is simpler it might work really nicely especially at scale but you don't know how
it works or have any of the tools to go fiddle with like display settings I do feel like
you get a lot of nice user choice and if that's your thing and it is my thing that's something
I love about the openSUSE install I mean you can get access to something like six different
desktops depending on how you what options you choose but you get presented with plasma
or gnome or other desktop and that's where you get access to more or you get things like
transactional server which is really neat and they give you a little brief descriptions
of all of that but once you make your final decisions I really like that it's just it's
just it goes man and then I stepped away to go get a snack and came back and I was at
my desktop it was just done because I chose to use auto login for the test and it was
kind of nice to be honest it like the computer just took care of itself and just finished
the installation and brought me to my desktop and I thought that was a slick experience
yeah no that waiting for you to remove the USB drive or any of that other stuff that
you you figure out and you know I was I was kind of impressed with the installation in
general it it did feel kind of enterprising I mean like one of the first things that
it said to me was searching for available products yeah probing the source type and
I was like okay what's going on here and of course as you sort of skipped over a little
bit there's also a license agreement that you're prompted with right at the start which
is not something I'm always used to when I'm installing Linux but the flip side of that
is that it felt mature there's a ton of translations available and as someone who loves to complain
about Anaconda more than I should I was really impressed with the disk setup tooling the
partitioning yeah especially how I could go into expert mode and it gave me a choice of
do you want to start fresh or do you want to keep things how we've set them up and then
just tweak them a little in expert mode and I thought that was really well done and I
liked its suggestions I thought they were solid and I wasn't sure what it would do since
I had an existing distro on there and it took care of just tidying it all up for me and
doing a nice you know better fs setup which is part of what I wanted to play with I was
disappointed to see that the Wi-Fi setup that I did in the installer didn't hold over to
the installed OS so then I had to go through setting up Wi-Fi again which is where I got
bit by that current plasma bug of the menu jumping around so like oh I always think that's
nice you know when you get like a like on Ubuntu or something you get the live environment
on the Wi-Fi network and then you reboot into the installed OS and it still has all the
Wi-Fi stuff like I just think that's slick and I'd love to see them be able to do that
if they could but I was plagued immediately with performance issues on the plasma desktop
on open Zeus a tumbleweed on this Dell with an NVIDIA graphics card and the easiest way
you'd see it manifest was I'd fire open krunner which is the plasma application launcher it's
such like a muscle memory thing that I do alt space and I start just typing the command
I hit enter but on this installation I hit alt space and I'd start typing I hit enter
and then I'd see like my web browser or whatever I'm using freak out because all of the input
had gone into my active window and then even after after I'd come to that realization of
what had just happened then the krunner menu came down and it was consistently laggy like
this throughout the system so I thought well this has to be a video acceleration issue
because this is a ginormous 4k display and it's doing it all in software right so or
whatever whatever the whatever it does I better install the NVIDIA driver do you have any
systems where you tried to do the video driver Wes you know actually not yet it's on my list
to try I think I'm gonna be leaving the tumbleweed around on at least one system for a while
but on on the Intel systems I was testing it on no no problem I was I was yeah I was
really pleased with performance yeah works great now I don't mean any disrespect to the
project but holy shit this is bad oh my god I cannot believe it's still in this state
so I found some great documentation that even as a 20 plus Linux user your user Linux user
I can I can kind of understand what they're saying but I essentially have to use a series
of tools to figure out what type of NVIDIA card I have and then I have one of two options
to install for an NVIDIA driver but none of their documentation covers the use case of
using a quadro video card so I was completely left on my own to assume what I'm supposed
to do and then once I even get the process of adding the NVIDIA repo and then going through
yes to find the different NVIDIA package options for a 50-50 shot of which one might apply
to my video card yast would hang during the installation the first time around 64% I'm
legitimately long enough that I stepped away came back sat with it for a bit and pondered
well I guess do I reboot my system even though it's 64% through installing the NVIDIA driver
and got up came back again still there sat down thought hmm yeah I think I'm gonna have
to reboot it and then it finished so I reboot my computer and after I installed apparently
what was the wrong of a 50-50 shot driver I tried the newest driver there seems to be
like a version 400 series and a version 300 series I installed the 400 series because
it's a fairly modern quadro video card apparently that was the wrong one so I reboot no video
everything's on the Intel still still running real choppy real laggy and and yast helped
me uninstall it but I wasn't sure if it cleared up everything or not and so then I installed
the older driver and I mean at this point I'm kind of desperate to get the NVIDIA GPU
working because the performance is basically unusable the input leg was brutal I was screwing
stuff up I just found it to be kind of an awful experience then you combine that with
just the newness of having to set up a desktop environment and it's not working right it's
it's a frustrating experience and so I thought okay I'll clear out what I installed I'll
install the older driver I install that I reboot I mean I'm following the instructions
that are on the wiki and I reboot and it still does not work I've got no real errors that
I can follow up on and to this point to this day I just kind of gave up on it so fear I'll
come back to it and I wanted to test out other things on the system but that that experience
of the process I had to go through feels like it's barely evolved from what it was like
seven or eight years ago on desktop Linux to get proprietary graphics working when it
was a legit exercise in system administration to get a driver enabled on your box and now
we live in an era where it's a checkbox on Fedora and Ubuntu and every other desktop
environment or on arch it's a single package you install or a series of packages a meta
package some folks even you know some distributions and projects even have dedicated media for
that if you already know that's what you want you know comes with it right there and it
was painful it was I remember thinking how this used to be and how it just doesn't need
to be like that anymore and I was shocked at the experience was that bad and that that's
not something people talk about a lot more but there's other things that it just seemed
like off that nobody talks about both Wes and I on different systems couldn't get the
ISOs to download using Chrome that particular day we were doing it I don't know why you
should go try it see if it downloads on Chrome for you we had to switch to Firefox I actually
switched to it just a dedicated downloader to get the ISO to download nobody's talking
about that it was weird because it was clearly a link right I could right click and copy
the link and I did the same I just pasted it and you know curled curled it down to my
file system but it was it was strange and you it's surprising to me maybe it's a new
bug I haven't downloaded open source especially tumbleweed for quite some time I will admit
but not ideal so then things really went wrong when I tried to get slack working so there's
obviously a pretty significant lead that the snap store has in SEO when you search for
getting slack on open Sousa because the first like three or four results for me who are
all like do it with snaps but when you go beyond there you discover and maybe you had
a different route on this I don't know if you tried this but when you Google around
you can find that there are different community repos that are hosting slack for you and this
is kind of like PPAs to the next level because instead of it just being a simple straightforward
process to add a personal package repository you have to go through this process through
yast where it asks you all of these questions and I chose the community repo that looked
the most legitimate based on absolutely nothing and then went through the yast process where
it had to add five additional repos to make it work and of course it aired out on adding
the third out of the five repos and the process never completed and I never got slack installed
on the machine oh no that is interesting I did I um I kind of cheated there and I went
the easy route and I installed it via flat back yeah that's what I'm gonna do that's
what I'll have to do and honestly I did that because that's kind of been my go-to for a
while now there's just that sort of set of applications that I just rely on having in
you know these sort of containerized universal package formats now just because I know that
they're there and I'm pretty sure they'll work wherever I'm gonna run them but you're
right you know software availability was one of the things we were wondering as a can I
run tumbleweed in place of arch sort of meta question because with arch and you know that
it's probably just in the AUR and the AUR might not be simple you should acknowledge
that right you're learning more about how the ecosystem works here whereas you're already
familiar with arch in the AUR but this sounded a bit more complex.
I think it just kind of it really feels like the experience is downgraded when you begin
managing software via yast and I know that's probably the opposite opinion that every every
user that's listening to the show that loves to use sues probably has the opposite opinion
of me and I'm sure the development community for your open sues has the opposite opinion
for me but in my using it and mind you I've had sues enterprise server in production I've
used yast extensively in production years ago and I think one of the reasons I was first
drawn to SUSE when I was new to Linux and I was deployed in production was because I
felt like yast was sort of an insurance policy for me.
I knew there were certain things I was always going to be able to configure on these Linux
boxes because yast gave me that option and I could do it in yast and that as a configuration
tool is powerful and it it it also breeds a lot of loyalty by the user base but now
having been away from SUSE for a long time and coming back to it my experience dies every
time I go inside yast it it is arduous, tedious, slow, it feels bloated, it never feels native
and the software management has to be the absolute slowest and most clunky and require
the absolute most user input of any package management system of any popular Linux distribution.
It's an absolutely paper cuts experience at every point and I think people that use SUSE
and that have used this for so long are just so used to it being this way or perhaps like
the benefits of of what yast brings that they just don't even see it but for me coming from
the outside it's a deal breaker for me with this distribution.
I kept debating how to feel about it because on one hand I'm kind of really impressed like
it's almost a different style of how you interface and manage like a Linux system and there's
a lot in there that I like I mean they've thought about a lot of things it's been a
project that's been around for a long time there's clearly areas where it's very mature
sophisticated and I could really see if I was deploying this in a corporate environment
or some sort of you know I was trying to administer all these boxes I needed sameness yast would
be killer but as someone more used to assembling arch systems yeah it was kind of a weird black
box and I didn't feel it felt like a rogue agent on my machine that left me more confused
than enlightened.
And I don't think it's just the pro user like coming from arch angle I also thought about
it from a skill set that's applicable to the wider market and when you learn how to do
things in yast and you learn how to do it the SUSE way the open SUSE way you're not
you're not really learning a skill that's directly translatable to CentOS, RHEL or
Ubuntu and early on in my career I think I would have really have disserviced myself
had I only learned how to do things the yast way I initially started with Red Hat servers
and I just did everything on Red Hat and then when Ubuntu started coming along with their
LTS releases I heavily advocated that for my clients because I really liked apt back
then I remember this is a long time ago and apt was a significant competitive advantage
in my opinion for managing a distribution and I was able to take by four or five years
of only using RHEL to Ubuntu because I understood what I was doing in RHEL and I could translate
that to essentially almost everything that was the same on Ubuntu with maybe a few things
in different places or a config file that's in a folder instead of directly in Etsy or
you know small differences and so it made the skill set that I learned on RHEL applicable
to other platforms which made me more employable and it was a net plus that way but I don't
feel like you would get that with yast so not only is it not appealing for people who
are used to managing their systems from the ground up like an arch user might be but I
think that people that want to participate professionally in the industry unless they're
in a niche that serves applications that run on SUSE servers which in that case this is
an obvious non-problem you kind of are limiting yourself because you're learning how to do
it the yast way and not the way that every other single distribution might be doing it
even if yast is just pulling those same levers for you under the hood and so I think it's
a bigger problem than just the power user perspective and I know this is going to sound
crazy to anybody who might be listening from the project because yast is kind of like their
you know competitive differentiator but from where I'm sitting at it feels like something
that when Linux needed everything set up for you when everything out of the box needed
to be configured like your X config file and all of your devices and your printers and
your USB scanners wouldn't just work or your SCSI devices like it made so much sense back
then but today outside of maybe managing things like boot managers and snapshots and stuff
like that I just feel like it's a brutal experience that really kind of turns me off the distribution
completely like I'm never going to want to be dependent on that tool I'm never going
to want to just isolate myself to one distribution and one way of doing things and I guess I
find it I find it really kind of disappointing that I couldn't get over that because I can
see how appealing it would be to people to have tumbleweed on your daily driver and leap
on your server and leap on your raspberry pies like I can really see the appeal of having
it all with one distro and one community and I really wish that could have worked for me
but at the end of the day it just doesn't I'm wondering did you have any fun or not
notice at all butter fs by the default you know didn't really get a chance to dig into
a great question I feel like that's another thing I need to spend a little more time with
so I'm going to keep it on the box I'm going to try to get the Nvidia card working I'm
sure I'll get some tips on how to do that and I want to try it on the Raspberry Pi 400
as well I think that's an important note we should add really just to be clear about in
this you know it's it's this is not an assessment of fact around hope ensues tumbleweed who
it does or doesn't work for anything like that really this is just us getting our toes
wet again in this ecosystem and yeah like you Chris I'm going to keep it around for
a while keep playing with it keep it on one of my machines and just see what it feels
like to live the lizard lifestyle for a bit live the lizard lifestyle I like it I want
to I want to make a kind of an important announcement moving on our unplugged core contributors
we had a bit of a snafu with the founders promo code a learning moment you could call
it that I think may have run afoul of a platform bug I'm not sure so I had to remove the founders
promo today as we're recording however the platform support folks are at memberful are
trying to see if they can figure out who was in the founders discount and just get it reapplied
to you that may happen but if that doesn't happen if you notice like you got a price
bump or you just want to get in and become a core contributor at the beginning of 2021
and get the whole year in I have a new promo code that will take two dollars off the price
I I'm never really doing this anymore because honestly you know it it's a big discount but
with this oops and the founders promo code getting removed I wanted to make it right
and so the new promo code that anyone is welcome to use if you want to get this locked in at
the beginning of 2021 is just 2021 so if you go to unplugged core.com and you apply the
promo code 2021 you'll get two dollars off the membership and that should remain on your
account for the entire time you're a member I apologize for the snafu with the founders
stuff I think I'm just gonna probably get to the bottom of it in the next couple of
days I'm working actively with the memberful support who has been awesome and super responsive
about the situation but it got kind of gnarly and this really sucks it resulted in like
a lot of our OG core contributors not renewing by mistake so 52 percent of you have been
accidentally unsubscribed it's just it really stinks so if you could double check on your
membership and if you've been unsubscribed or it's not the right price you can put that
promo code 2021 on there I think I'm gonna leave it open for a couple of weeks and you
can support the show that's unplugged core.com and then you get access to a limited ad feed
if you'd like the show with the same full production but just limited ads we make that
available as a perk additionally we have a bootleg feed it's the full live stream all
of our screw-ups all of our resets the stuff that never makes into the show with much larger
pre and post show that's essentially a whole other show that's also available to you as
a member and I mean two dollars off the membership price is pretty pretty great so unplugged
core.com and my bad I'm actually not 100% sure it was my fault but I'm taking responsibility
for it I'm making it right so use the promo code 2021 all right Westpain we have a really
great pick this week and I believe you and I are both Todoist users for a little over
a year so maybe you even longer yes we are and Todoist has released like an electron
version of their to-do tracking application but you know me I like something local so
if you want to keep track of your projects your tasks your goals in a local app that
looks really really nice I do I do that sounds like you will then check out planner at use
planner.com it's a it's an example of one of the beautiful apps that's been designed
for elementary OS that I mean because it's based on native local Linux technologies as
impossible it's possible to get another distros I'm I'm running it on on a plasma box and
if you're on arch you want you want the the version of the package that has elementary
in the name it's elementary dash planner there's two planners in the arch repo or in the AUR
you want elementary dash planner if you're on arch and the beautiful thing about it
is if you just want something super simple local it can do that you don't need any integration
with anything it'll just be a really nice local app it's a beautiful GTK app but it
looks just fine on plasma too then if you are a todoist user you can connect it to your
todoist account it will sync and import everything from todoist and then you don't have to use
their electron app that I was pretty impressed with it just worked right away no problems
had to you know log in like usual I like that now I installed the flat pack which there
is a flat pack available which made it really easy also on a plasma desktop I've got some
sort of strange black borders around mine but otherwise it seems to be working very
nicely and I think I'm going to keep it you can go into the preferences and change some
of the appearance options so you might want to play around with that you know like put
it in dark mode ops and then the other thing you might want to check on is what your GTK
theme settings are right now for plasma there might be something walka there because it
is a GTK application but hot damn is it great and todoist is admittedly not free software
um it's not an open source hosted solution but it has a lot of collaborative features
it has integration with freaking everything it's got an API for days and so I just sort
of eventually fell into using it because they have mobile apps they have web apps they now
you know have third-party client apps and that's that I like a lot and over the years
I've tried a lot of things but I keep coming back to todoist because of this kind of flexibility
and the idea that I can have this nice well-designed todoist client that's native on my Linux desktop
and then have a native app on my phone kind of puts it in the sweet spot for me so check
that one out it's it's worth it it's totally worth it so we have a bunch of feedback this
week mr. Westpain and it's hard to say if we could get to all of it but I did want to
get to the tuxes feedback because we've heard a lot from that I'm I'm really I'm really
happy that people seem to really enjoy the tuxes it's been really well received people
who won the tuxes are are excited and I it was a nice it was a nice way to say thank
you at the end of the year so Roy writes in regarding the award show he said you hope
for more people to vote I think you should have mentioned the voting on other JB shows
as well and I think he's absolutely right I I will attempt when my goal is for next
year's tuxes is by around Thanksgiving to have a URL that is just you go to a URL directly
that we maybe even launch a week earlier than we did this time around and that we do promote
it on other shows and if you're out there and interested in maybe helping me build like
a static website that we could use to also show who won because that was a request that
came in by some of the tuxes winners was hey we'd sure like to be able to share something
just to tell the team and that makes a lot of sense so a site that that could that could
hold the winners for every year and then maybe you could click on it and get like their individual
award page that says you know fedora project for this or or whatever who was a winner and
then maybe even an embed of the YouTube video with the time code and just something that's
easy simple fast that we could update every year with the tuxes I think would be great
and so if somebody's out there that wants to help me with that get ahold of me you can
use the contact form or you can email me directly Chris at you better broadcasting.com or probably
telegram or whatever too I I don't know if that's a good idea but you can you can give
it a shot probably the show contact is the simplest for everyone yeah yeah so anyways
that is feedback we are taking in and we'll try to get like a visual representation of
that as well we also had a suggestion from Sandro about the tuxes you want to take that
one with yeah Sandro wrote in and actually a lot of advice for us but thought that it
might be overkill for the kind of contest we're doing but we could consider having a
nomination phase first and then a voting phase you know sort of accept proposals for each
category make a big list and then in the voting phase only allow entries from that list you
know that might make some of the tallying a little bit simpler but wouldn't mean we
need to get things started even earlier so like almost like a bracketing system where
you kind of like have a phase one that we take the submissions and then we have a debate
and discussion about that one and then move a subset of those to the final round yeah
exactly that's an interesting idea that I don't know how we would do that in a way that
wouldn't drag it out forever though yes Sandro even linked to some some voting theory and
some more technical resources that we can take a look at to see how we might actually
implement such a system thank you everyone for bearing with with us on this you know
I think it was a lot of fun and interesting but it was definitely a rough first year for
the tuxes but I'm already looking forward to the next year and I think there's lots
of stuff that we can do to improve it so if you do have further ideas suggestions tools
things we just shouldn't try again please do let us know yeah it was definitely a minimum
viable tuxes we weren't sure if the idea was sound we wanted to try it because it's something
that we've kicked around for years and um I think it showed that it was worth investing
more into and we're interested in doing that and it also could become a yearly tradition
that we get to look forward to kind of like the predictions and reviews that as a team
is kind of like it's it's almost the biggest indication that the holiday season is here
is that we start working on those shows so it has some sentimental value it's not like
a milestone in the production year of the show like when we get to those shows we know
we have done a solid year of shows by that point and it's it's kind of a moment so it's
something we want to do and we would love to get your suggestions we'll take one last
email that comes in from five on gnome 40s impending changes it says happy new year's
I am a gnome user and gnome has a killer workflow for me that no other desktop offers without
a ton of customization I use the auto hide top bar as my only extension to create a clean
desktop I'm slightly nervous of the new changes proposed to my bread and butter activities
overview which if you're not familiar listener there is some significant work going into
how the overview section of gnome will work I'm sure the changes will be welcome but the
activities overflow is what I use most to move quickly to other applications it's much
quicker than sequential alt-tabbing and doesn't require crazy key combos or memorizations
I also like how I can easily manage my work and home workspace within the overview before
the pandemic I did a magic trick and replaced Windows 10 with Ubuntu at work my co-worker
quickly noticed how changing from Windows 10 the company standard to gnome desktop was
really key for my workflow and productivity that's interesting find that you had other
people's notice that as well yeah I think gnome users are sitting here a bit nervous
at this point with gnome 40 looming out there it's one of the things we're watching for
it's sort of the upside and the downside right if you if you click with gnome and the workflow
and the way it's set up it can be really really nice but because it is so specific it also
means that any changes to it are going to be way more noticeable than say on plasma
I want to believe that they've they've they've received and kind of internalized some of
the feedback over the years and I think really since the gnome 310 311 and 312 series we've
seen a a a more compromised approach to some of the design choices and some of the changes
and we've seen a real increase in performance and stability so it seems like the last the
last solid bit of gnome history has shown us that the developers are working in the
right direction and so it is possible that gnome 40 lands and people have a lot of strong
feedback about it but so far history has showed us that over time they'll work some of that
back they'll they'll modify some of it to meet user demand it may be jarring at first
and as a as a project they have to figure out okay what are people freaking out about
because change is hard and it's jarring and what are people freaking out about that is
legitimate and we have to improve and they'll just have to have to sit with some of these
changes for a bit to be able to pick pick out the signal from the noise and as a community
I think we kind of have to give them some of that grace for a bit and we'll try it we'll
be honest about what works and doesn't work but at the same time we're not getting the
pitchforks over it you know they'll refine the process we hope just have to wait and
see we'd love to have you join the show live we do it Tuesday at noon Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern
see you next week same bad time same bad station we'd love to have you join us because of course
we got the chat room the mumble room just gives us that live vibe but we like that too
but if you can't get the show live well then you're like 99.9% of the audience you can
get it every single week by going to linuxunplugged.com subscribe with all the links there our contact
form is linked there our matrix and mumble info and show notes for this week's episode
are all at linuxunplugged.com thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the
unplugged program also should mention we're at Linux unplugged on Twitter I never do that
bad about that but you can get show announcements and stuff if Twitter's your thing either way
whatever you do we'll see you back here next Tuesday
okay everybody go vote JBtitles.com one of the meta themes about this episode that Carl
just started touch on before the show kicked off is how distributions sometimes do things
differently you know can you have an Ubuntuism can you have a Seussism and there is different
that's maybe a little more local and there's a different kind and Carl you were just starting
to touch on and I said wait wait wait save it for the post show do you want to pick that
back up you remember what you were saying yeah I think the gist of it was is that every
package in the distribution is sort of like a soft fork in a way unless it's just a direct
build of the upstream software exactly how they intended which a lot of them are close
to that but you know there will be compile time options and other things like that but
most distributions will diverge each package slightly with patch files and you know some
of those are just to adapt it to the build system other ones are to fix other bugs or
fix features maybe it's something that's already upstream that isn't in a release yet that
they just want to back port to them most recent release but the key thing is is that every
patch that's applied it has a potential to cause problems a non-zero percentage chance
and if a distribution is adding patches that the distribution came up with that aren't
sent upstream if those patches cause problems it's up to that distribution by themselves
to fix it they don't have any help but if a distribution practices what we call upstream
first and they are working with the upstream developers that they don't they won't apply
patches that aren't at least proposed upstream and that way if some one of those patches
does cause an issue that it's not just on the distro maintainers to fix fix those problems
they'll actually be able to collaborate with the upstream developers right it's kind of
where the upstream first mentality comes from i totally totally track and but at the same
time i have to do that well but thing you know couldn't i mean doesn't that seem like
a little ideal scenario because you know for example this is a really small example but
i could totally see this hitting an outfit like canonical for example you hire a developer
to make some changes to an open source project they create the code they package it all up
and you submit it as a patch and then the upstream project says no we're not interested
in going that direction no thanks and then you're like yeah but i have use cases or end
users that do want this and you're kind of left well i can make the changes as open source
software i have the ability to fix it for my users i mean isn't that kind of in a way
what kind of drives some of this forking to begin with is just a difference in directions
for projects so people just have to do it themselves yeah absolutely i mean and that's
the thing is whenever whenever a distribution is evaluating whether or not to apply the
patch in the first place they need to weigh that risk so if there's a something proposed
upstream that the distribution you know doesn't have any idea if it would be fixed or merged
then maybe that's not a good candidate to apply as a patch in the package yet but if
it's something that you know the upstream has already said like yes this is an obvious
fix we we you know thank you for the contribution we're we plan on merging this or we've already
merged it into the master branch and it'll be in the next release those are those those
are the things that are a slam dunk to go ahead and add as a patch to the package because
you know that it's it's going to it's at least likely to be you know you'll be able to collaborate
with the upstream developers on it so it's a risk evaluation whenever you're first applying
that patch in the package yeah they got to do that math of like oh boy do we want to
take this on and be responsible for all the bugs and never really being accepted by by
the upstream yeah i i agree every patch has that risk and has to be evaluated it's complicated
you know assembling all these different pieces from all kinds of different people organizations
and groups into what we view as one cohesive operating system