I think all right, but that's not what I want to discuss in the pre-show
You know what I want to talk about in the pre-show is this might just make fedora work for me. You ready for this one?
York in fedora, you know that is the art user repository management tool
What yeah, yeah, yeah, so basically the art user repository in fedora
This is okay. That is like it right there. You think so you think this could be it I?
I think that would be sweet. Yeah, so yet another repository tool is what your it stands for
It's a wrapper for pac-man which adds automated access to the a you are you word has the same syntax as pac-man and for now
And now fedora you just couldn't use your to install a you are packages in fedora
This is no joke. I wonder if anybody that in the chat room has tried this
This is amazing because fedora 22 is really solid, but at the time I tried it
I was having a hard time getting a couple of apps. I needed her upad mumble and telegram. Yeah, definitely right
That's why that's one reason. I never really used it because I couldn't get the apps for it. Yeah, in fact
I think I just read somewhere that
What was it? I think they said that essentially that I can't remember where I just saw this
But there were fedora repositories have essentially kind of stopped growing in terms of software and this could really help that
I mean the a you are in in in fedora would be really I don't know how well it could possibly work
Yeah, so does it make me that actually I'm or dnf. I guess now I would think it downloads the tar. GZ stuff and builds it
Right you're just building it. So it's almost like our own version of ports from freebsd. Yeah, kind of like the a you are is really
It's yeah, it could be crazy everybody out there. Try gotta if you try it out there a dear listener. Let us know
Maybe I'll try it. Yeah, I might try to put in a VM
Well in fedora is so easy to recommend, you know
Especially people with Macs or other things where you just get a nice setup environment. Yeah, but you don't have all the packages you need
Yeah, yeah, that is always the killer. Mm-hmm. This is Linux unplugged episode 103 for July 28th
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly talk show that surrounded the 100 mark
My name is Chris and we have a great show and I'm happy to say that Wes is in studio. Hey Wes. Hey Chris
Hey, how's it going buddy? Oh, it's going great. How about yourself? Thank you for making it right after the big move to Seattle
That's pretty cool. Oh, I'm happy to be here. So are you good? Are you exhausted?
I mean, come on be honest. This is my recovery session got a nice beer hanging out with the fine folks in the room
What could be better? Well, we got a great episode today
so we're gonna do a couple of updates on some stories that are relevant in the community of the Linux unplugged show and
kick those around with our virtual lug and then after that I
Have some really awesome clips from OSCON. I went down there armed with a portable audio recorder
Just to record interviews exclusively for the unplugged show and it turns out going down there with this tiny little recorder as opposed to a big
Camera you get a lot more intimate personal interviews with folks
And so we've got some really good chats coming up in today's episode of Linux unplugged from OSCON
2015 can't wait to play those for you and then later in the show
radio is about to be over overtaken by an open source gunk works project right here in our community and
The very creator of that project joins us in the mumble room today to give us a little insights on his plans to overthrow
The proprietary hold on radio broadcasts. It's a big deal
We're gonna talk to him today and maybe maybe just maybe you might see it worked into a future Jupiter broadcasting initiative
And then if we have enough time at the end of the show
I got a few things I want to reminisce about
Where we were just doing the back of the napkin math in the pre-show and we were like wow
we are in the 10th year of the Linux action show unbelievable and
Anytime you've been doing something for 10 years you get a little bit of an itch. Sorry, honey
I'm not talking about you. No, no, no, baby, baby. I love you. I'm not talking about you, baby
But I'm talking about the show sweetie. God what you see that look I'm getting West. That's I'm in trouble. I'm in trouble
Anyways, we're thinking about making some changes to the show and if we have time later, I'll talk about that
If not, maybe we'll just cover it in a future episode, but why don't we start our buddy?
Wimpy who sometimes joins us from time to time is the guy behind the Ubuntu Mate
Matai mate
like the drink and
He made a lot of news this week and I'm just curious. I wanted to kick it around with you guys
Do you guys think this is a really huge deal or not?
I was and why did this get so much traction when when wimpy announces that the Ubuntu Mate version of 1510 will not ship
With the Ubuntu software center. It has been
Removed is it just me or
Were you surprised? I mean West I'll throw it to you first and we'll throw it to the mumble room
We haven't brought them in yet. I should do that time appropriate greetings mumble room
So I'm gonna ask you in a second
But I'll throw it to West first West does it make sense to you to pull out the software center and why do you think?
This made so much news when wimpy announced I I've seen it covered on pretty much every Linux news outlet
It was the top of the our Linux subreddit. I was in the Ubuntu subreddit
It was the number one voted story in our subreddit this weekend. What do you think why?
I mean, I do think that you know being a being a spin of Ubuntu itself, you know the Mate edition people do
You know, they kind of assume there'll be a certain underlying familiarity in the architecture the infrastructure
Yeah, the underpinnings of what you've come to know and love about Ubuntu. Yes, exactly
Well, many of us may not use the software center
I could see how people who are more into the Ubuntu community in general. Yeah, here's my question to you
It seems like if I if if I'm a new user
So when we when we had chase switch to Linux
The first thing he did is anytime you wanted anything from Steam to Chrome. He went to the software center
That's just kind of like their expectation now. And so if there's nothing there, let me ask you this if there's nothing there
Is that better than having something that's not very good in fact rotten? Do you want to start all I can toss this to you
Rotten corpse. Do you think having nothing there is better than having something? That's awful. Yes
But that's not what a bunch of money is doing
so that's not even that's not even at all on the
Like in the page right now because they're replacing it. They're not removing it. Yeah. Well, don't go there
Yeah, cuz I want to get there but just yeah, we'll talk about that in a second
But I mean, but yeah, if because the Ubuntu software center is atrocious. Yeah, it should be removed by Ubuntu
Then yeah, it is a bad thing because when someone's using something and it takes, you know
It take the the software center to get new software takes longer to open than to install the software
That's a bit problem. So you think they'll run honestly, I mean, I mean bashing the software center aside, honestly
Is it better to have nothing at all?
than to have so the reason I'm asking is
This aside from what the Ubuntu Mate project is doing is it maybe just better to just remove it than have nothing at all
So Chase's experience when he went to install steam he got two different entries for steam
He was then prompted to create a canonical account and then he had to try to give it his address and his payment information
To canonical to download the free steam installer and he was completely lost and and it just stopped him dead in his tracks
And he had to come to me and say what should I do? So rotten? Do you think is it better before there's a replacement to pull it?
Yeah, I'm for that particular
software center, yeah, it is by far the worst and
It there are so many bugs with it that it's that that they have I mean
They've they've made one update in two years and they're fully and canonicals fully aware that it's awful
So yeah, they should remove it because people who are coming to Linux without having any connection to it. What's before whatsoever?
They're gonna be googling stuff anyway
So all they're going to do is see the first example of a software center. That is awful. Mm-hmm
Especially if it we've been conditioned with you know, nicer Mac stores
Even the Windows Store and now mobile and now mobile everyone thinks about it
It might be easier to teach people we don't do that this way in Linux then to give them the half-assed
Version that we might have so wimpy. I'm glad you could make it
So tell us about this update and where now the Ubuntu Mate project is gonna take this
What's the Ubuntu Mate's answer to this problem that we've kicked on for I mean, it feels like since the inception of the show
Yeah, I've just literally just joined the chatroom so I
I love you wimpy. No excuses. I want to know if I want to give you a big hug and a kiss right now
But I was just I just a recap really quickly
I was just mentioning like first of all, holy shit. Did you get a ton of coverage about this change?
Congrats to you and number two
And number two you didn't are you joking? You didn't notice maybe now I now I saw some of it
I saw I because I because I follow all of the feeds for all of our shows to me
When a story shows up more than a dozen times, that's a lot of coverage and your story got a ton of coverage
You've got the top of our Linux you were the top voted story on the Linux action show subreddit
Which is actually a fairly large generates quite a bit of traffic you got you were on softpedia
You got you got coverage all over the place. Plus not only that you got six reshares on Google Plus
so I saw it in my Google Plus feed constantly and you generated a ton of discussion the Ubuntu subreddit and the our Linux subreddit and
And the thing that got me the most about your post wimpy is you say we have something lined up by way of replacement
And it's not synaptic and that I was like, oh, what is it? So wimpy why this change and where are you going?
You got to tell me. Okay. All right. Okay, so
There's a new
So I've only seen a couple of articles on this and I've had some feedback through the Ubuntu Marte community. So, okay
I've written a new utility for Ubuntu Marte called Ubuntu Marte welcome. Oh
and
One of the features that that has is a simple one-click install for applications
that are
popular and or
Difficult to install and or proprietary and difficult to install. Hmm. So in there, it's a highly curated
selection of applications and the list of applications that are in there are built around
tasks that
Myself and my immediate family and friends that using Ubuntu Marte
Need to accomplish and the software that they need to install to do it
so my father-in-law said to me Ubuntu Marte is great and
Once you've set it up for me, I can do all of these things I need to do
But if you're not here, I can't you know install the things I need
Yeah
So I've just put those things in there that people need to get stuff done and that's really what it's about
It's one-click install get stuff done
So I've developed the means of installing software and it doesn't necessarily have to be stuff that's in the official repositories
So for example, there's a one-click installer for Steam. There's a one-click installer for Google Chrome
There's a one-click installer for the Hangouts plugins and so on and so on and behind the scenes it enables the necessary
PPAs only if that PPA is from the developer. So rotten knows about this
They're not human said said go and get your developer for you get to put a build
for widely into the PPA and then I can turn this on and you can have you get installed from the PPA and
You then get a conservative stable
distribution with rolling applications
so Wow now I have I
Love it. That's that's brilliant
And I love that you're you're basically getting the low-hanging fruit first there with Steam and Chrome and things like that
Which is like going to be like the checklist of the first apps that pretty much everybody I've switched to Linux asked me about
Yeah, I mean, okay. So, you know those yeah, you know those articles that say, you know
The 27 things you need to do after you install. Yeah, that's right
This is the antedote because those 27 things are all a button, you know
lip DVD
CSS well
I'm kind of what you're doing too in a lot of ways is you're taking a
lot of the distro tweak tools where you go out there and you you copy a
W get command with it runs as root from the from their website and you paste it in your terminal and then it downloads and
Installs and add stuff to your repo and then all of a sudden next thing, you know
Uh, like a Lua interface app comes up or some GTK app comes up. You know, what is this?
Okay
I'll check these boxes and you don't really quite know how legit it is and what you're doing is you're sort of legitimizing that process and
Saying well, here's a sanctioned way to get this low-hanging fruit and it's brilliant. Yeah
It's also more than just the most common things people are expecting. So that's wimpy said there
Hey, he asked
We he's he mentioned to me about getting you get into the welcome as well. And we didn't have a 1510 branch
So when he asked for it
We immediately just launched one so we can get it in there. So like
This it's a lot more important than just you know, the the stupid 20 things after you install. Yeah
But like it's actually getting people to in some ways
It's sort of greasing the the wheels for 1510 when it lands because people are gonna have to move forward on that
That's cool, too. Exactly. Yeah, and the other thing is if there's an application
Let's say for example Dropbox Dropbox is a one-click installer in there Dropbox apps Android and iOS
Application so where there's an Android and or an iOS application
There are buttons to take you to the app stores for those companion applications on the mobile platforms
So it tells you what they are equivalent to so for Kim, for example, it explains. This is a little additive to
Photoshop you like that? That's very nice. One of the things we've done is added the CMYK plugins for GIMP
You know, oh wow
It adds all the extra bits and pieces
This is incredible. Wimpy, I love this and so Wimpy are you I mean, you know, this is not obviously not the replacement
Yeah, I mean this is like this is like this is like a stopgap, isn't it?
I mean this is you know, honestly Wimpy though
I could see companies that would be wanting to partner with your distribution to maybe get a button in there, too
Yeah, we'll be the process for changing the software that's added for this. Well, it's it's all at the moment
It's the simplest thing possible. So it's just so effectively welcome is a very simple
Webkit browser with my own protocol handlers to hand handle things like
handling installations handling software removals
Launching executables and doing things so instead of having just hyperlinks that navigate you have actions that trigger things off
now behind the scenes it's it's using apt daemon, which is all the same technology that the
Ubuntu software center uses for actually handling the business end of installing the software, you know and resolving all of the dependencies and all of that
Yeah
But because I've now got this mechanism of saying here is an application click this button to install it
Yeah, and the undercurrent of feedback that I've had
From the Ubuntu Marte community up to this point. We'll get to that in a moment
But up to this point has been why is the Ubuntu software included? You know, it's it's slow
It's bulky people always explain what the alternative is that they install. It's all synaptic
Yeah
So I thought right well now I've got this option to install things after the fact
I'll remove the Ubuntu software center from the default install
To satisfy all of those people that say they didn't think it should be there in the first place
And I'll add a link in the welcome to install it
So you can still choose to install it?
But given that people have said they weren't keen on it
I've been out and I've looked at all of the alternatives that are out there. So I've looked at the
The deep in software center and considered forking that but that's a bit
A bit too much like hard work mostly because a lot of the comments in the source code are in Chinese and my Chinese is
Well, I don't speak Chinese
Just a small area
Yes, it's a small problem. I've looked at the Ubuntu software center, which is nice and lightweight
but the problem there is that that doesn't have the facility to
Log in with your Ubuntu one account and access prior purchases
So that's why the Ubuntu software center is relevant. Anyway, right cut long story short
I've contacted the author of app grid and
He has agreed to me adding an install option for app grid
You know the Ubuntu Marte welcome
No
So now you'll be able to choose whether you want to install the Ubuntu software center or a grid and use that as your
That's your interface perfect. That is perfect
Wow, you know wimpy and I I think what I love about this is
I mean, I what the hell do I know but it seems like to me you could develop out that welcome screen
if I was
I'm trying to think of a good fit
But if let's just take the mirror media player or whatever if I was an open source project
I would or there is a you know
There's some really cool apps being built for the elementary OS like some of you may have seen this weekend a news reader for gnome
Going around that's sort of built for elementary OS first, but it works on any platform
There's some really neat apps that are being developed these days and they could reach out and say, you know
We'd love a little time a little a little welcome
You know a little welcome space here because and and of course your taste and preference would pick which ones get featured there
But it could be a really neat way to expose users to some some I guess like curated well picked and well placed apps
Are you thinking about that or are you resistant to that?
No, I am thinking about that
So I've got a long list of applications that I haven't added yet some I definitely will and some I'm considering but basically the selection
criteria is
Does this integrate well with the Ubuntu Marte desktop?
So so long as it it installs and it works and it integrates and for example
Some applications say some of the KDE applications which are very nice pulling so much of KDE
Underneath that it fills the menus and what have you with a load of KDE applications, which makes it look a bit messy and confusing
Yeah, I have to touch those. Yeah, which is unfortunate because some of them are really good. Mm-hmm
So yes, so long as it integrates well, so yes, you know things like, you know
Do we remove Thunderbird from the default installation and put that in welcome alongside Geary for example? Yeah
Yeah, you know so I've but this is a way because you know, sometimes you get these derivatives of a distribution which are
in name of distribution
Ultimate version. Yes gaming edition or whatever. Yeah, they've got everything imaginable install and it's great
Cuz you install this one thing and you've got everything. Yeah
Well, this is a way for me to make Ubuntu Marte do everything, you know easily access everything
But you don't actually have to ship right, you know a five gigabyte, you know distro
Yeah, I get to pick and you can choose what you want and welcomes asynchronous as well
And so just to clarify like API 984 in the chair
I'm saying what are the sources you're working when a lot of case with these developers to say hey
Give me a PPA that I can you're going to develop and for the 1504 directly, right?
Or I mean 1510 directly so a lot of cases like it's best case scenario for the source, right?
Yeah, so I'd say half of the applications that are in there are just coming out of the official archive at the moment
So it's just an apt and an under the hood. It's doing an apt install. Yeah, I'd say
25% are using a PPA, but it's the PPA from the developer
So I'm not just finding an app that happens to be in some random PPA and enabling a random PPA
I'm actually going to the developers and
Finding their stable PPA or if it doesn't exist asking them to make one and using that and then in other cases for the likes of
Virtual box 5 for example and Dropbox and steam it's actually enabling the steam and Dropbox and
Virtual box sure third-party repositories and doing all of the so you get the updates right from them stuff
Yeah, so you are getting the official, you know latest versions from their archives. That is cool
Nice wimpy. Well, I'm glad you're able to stop by and give us an update on that because that's I will like somebody
Mentioned isn't is an app grid proprietary and the answer to that question is yes app grid is under a proprietary license
Which is why I contacted the author to ask if I could
include an installer for it
Yeah, and upgrades written in Python so actually you can go and look at the source code
Oh
As long as if I get a little suspicious I can take a look is that what you're saying right? Yeah
If something's installing something in my system, I want to know what it's doing underneath
But as far as it's licensing, I don't care. Mm-hmm
Yeah
But that's why I'm going to continue to include a link to install the Ubuntu software center and clearly label that as an open source
You know tool and then upgrade as an alternative to that
But yes under I mean for example, there's in sync is in
Ubuntu Marte welcome, which is a third-party proprietary application. That is a
Google Drive sync. Yeah utility
In my opinion is the best to the job, but it is a commercial application
But it says so in there
This is a commercial application after the evaluation period if you still want to use it. You will have to pay for it
With a link to yeah, you know, yeah much it costs. Yeah
Because well, you know, there are open source alternatives, but my choice is
The best-in-class application like integrates well with the Ubuntu Marte desktop
Yeah, and I could go for gripe, but gripe is not the best-in-class application. Yeah, and I
Found out it's some unpopular, but I don't think Ubuntu software center is the best-in-class software center for Ubuntu
I think app grid is there you go
Well put and I support you a hundred percent on it
And I like to see a little taste involved in some of these desktop app pick selections
And you know truth be told people that think there's maybe like for example in sync
If you think there's a better solution, then you're probably the person that knows how to go get it and install it. Yeah, definitely
yeah, including including the
Plugins for the cars your file manager, for example, so it does all of that, you know
Yeah, stop integration now this business about Ubuntu software center considering how much you know, I've heard
Oh, we don't like it. We'd rather you choose something else now
I've suggested that I'm gonna remove it man. Am I unpopular? This is the biggest misstep. I've made in
I've started the project
Silent the silent majority of risen up and they're not so silent anymore, huh?
No, no, they've all found their voice and they're making it plainly clear that all I can imagine that's where cheerleaders popping up and screaming
No, I imagine it goes something like this
The only reason I move people to Ubuntu is because they expect a software center and it's the only one that at least has a software
Some of them for the use regardless of how good it is. Is that essentially what you get?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, it's your choice
You choose the Ubuntu software center or you can choose upgrade and a friend of mine has just popped in and chapter chat room
Joe Ressington and we've been exchanging some message earlier on
On hangouts. So so Joe now I won't be compiling at the grid
Grid is written in Python and it's an interpreted language. It will be installed from the app grid developers PPA
Wimpy you should give Joe the pro tip and have him join us in the mumble room
I mean, come on, he could he could give you Joe in the UK. Yeah, he's
Known as the Linux podcast, right? I mean, I know he has a microphone. So I know he probably knows how to make mumble work
I'm just saying he does know how to make mumble work. I'd love for Joe
Conversation because I know he's got some strong feelings about proprietary software being listed in there and this is the place
I'm just saying I'm just yeah, okay
Wimpy is there anything else you want to mention on the exists? No, no, no, I guess I'm going to be
Just as his wife is asleep. So yeah, that's always a good excuse. Yeah, I think I think he I think you'd have been up for it
Yeah, well keep us posted on how it goes. I'm sure we'll check back in
He may have another chance to give it to rib you because I have a feeling this is gonna be something follows interest
Joe's like Joe's on at least four other podcasts. So he's got plenty of opportunity to call me
I know it's happy just happens to be during this one. The wife is sleeping. I will I'll try not to take it personally
I'll die honestly, I know I know his wife has very good sleep practice and she likes an early night
I'll get poppies joined in as well. Oh goodness, but let's let's change the topic. All right. Well wimpy. Thank you very much
I appreciate your welcome as always
You know, there was one story I wanted to get to that maybe I'd like to poke poppy about but before we get to that
I'm not gonna say it's about plasma mobile
But before we get to that I want to talk about ting our first sponsor here on the Linux unplugged program
Go to linux.ting.com to support the Linux unplugged program and check them out because what I love about ting is there's no contract for your
Service and you only pay for what you use
So just put that in your brain organ for a second and think about that
It's a flat six dollars a month for the line and then it's just your usage on top of that and that is select
So when we went to OSCON Noah had a ting phone Noah's wife had a ting phone
I had a ting phone my wife had a ting phone and we were rocking the communication down there and what's super slick
Was Noah had a rental and so we were driving from where we had the family staying to OSCON and I turned on the Wi-Fi
Hotspot mode and connected Noah's car his rental car to the Wi-Fi hotspot on my s6 as we're driving down
I-5 and like the media system on his car is like pulling down track information from the internet and
All it's totally cool, and I don't care. I'm honey badger about it because I'm just paying for my usage
I don't have to be like in some sort of special
Shared data plan to have wife Wi-Fi tethering or anything like that and you can try it out to go to linux.ting.com
And try out the savings calculator and see how much you'd save by switching to ting
I'm saving over two thousand dollars every two years no contract right so there's no early termination fee
And if you're in one of those duopoly contracts ting has an early termination relief program. Yeah, dude. They're crazy
They got early termination relief program
They're gonna help you get out of that contract and here's something else that's different about ting when you call them you get to
Speak to a human being you call them a 1-8-5-5 ting FTW is anytime between 8 a.m.. And 8 p.m.. On the East Coast
In fact check their site because they do they do move that window depending on demand
And you get to speak to that human being a human being and they also have one of the best control
Well they have the best not one of they have the best control panel in the business that way you can manage your account turn
Devices on and off name them check your usage set alerts that set thresholds transfer devices deactivate devices
When no is heading out of here at the end of our oscon trip. I went into my ting dashboard
I removed my Nexus 5 from my dashboard within an hour to he was able to add to his dashboard, and he had a Nexus 5
Never had to call anybody all through their super slick website no termination fees no contract hoop
That's like hey man. You want to try out the Nexus 5 for a little bit here you go
And I just move up click a thing click a thing boom. We're done. It's so nice
I just did it right from the ting dashboard in seconds and everything's like that with ting and just for six dollars a month
For the line if you got a few people in your family, or you got a small business
There's no cheaper way than going with ting, but it's not the kind of cheap you're familiar with it's cheap in the way
That's inexpensive, but still the service is awesome, and they have something most carriers. Don't have
Two networks to choose from they have a CDMA and GSM network
So you can figure out which one has the best coverage or data speeds in your area and pick that one like in my Nexus
5 I get to bounce between CDMA or GSM and because they have GSM and CDMA network
There's a ton of devices you can bring and if you're gonna bring a device you go to linux.ting.com
They'll take $25 off your first month of service that more than paid for my first month. That's how that's how I really $25
That's a little I mean I when I think about a smartphone 25 now now that I got now
I got a couple of phones
I'm down
I'm only down to a couple of phones now because I've been given a couple away now now I'm like around 35 37 40 bucks a
Month that's still not that bad though for three smartphones that with unlimited data just pay for what I use right
I don't have to worry about going over some origin getting some crazy charge when I turn on my my hotspot or tethering and if I
Pay a little more one month that all washes out because most months
I'm saving a ton of money cuz I'm pretty Wi-Fi savvy so I just when I wrap my head around this
I think how else would I have been able to do this?
Especially for Jupiter broadcasting where we don't have the budget to spend hundreds of dollars a month on cell phone lines
I don't know how I would have done this without ting go to linux.ting.com try their savings calculator
See how much you would save remember they have an early termination relief program on top of that and give them a try
tons of great devices do if you just want to buy a device starting around $60 for a feature phone all the way up to
The best devices in the market linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged
So this week one of the big stories that we saw hit the interwebs was plasma mobile a free mobile platform created completely from scratch
Totally from scratch no no other
Distributions or projects that they are sitting on top of and it has hit the web and images are ready for the Nexus 5 and it
Is based on freedom user friendliness and privacy and of course the plasma desktop now in reality I Josh
Just like so many other great open source projects. They're standing on the shoulder of Giants
I'm sure there is tons and tons of Ubuntu mobile work in here. We do know that they are using live hybrids to get
Android video drivers working under Linux and of course all of the work under Qt
But rotten corpse you've had a little bit of heads up about there's a little bit of time to look at this
What were your first impressions when you started to learn about this new project?
I was really excited. They actually told me I talked to a developer for
Plasma mobile and they said that
It's it is based on
It has a lot of Ubuntu stack, but it also has like one of the graphics drivers for Android
But everything else is all Linux based. So it's it is sharing some stuff that it that I could bunch who has
They've also built a lot of their own stuff too for the shell. Mm-hmm
And and there are their app system and the widget system is completely unique and there's the demo of it is it's pretty cool
So I'm actually looking forward to it
And it's the best part is that the plasmoids that are based on the desktop are actually to work in the phone, too
Yeah, that's pretty nice. So those are ready to go
I
Guess I mean, I don't I I probably I'm sure you have nothing but nice things to say
But what are your first impressions when you see a project that in a lot of ways?
Is somewhat competition for Ubuntu touch. Do you think this is good? I'm sure you do right? I think it's great
Yeah, of course you do the whole idea of having lots of different
Lots of diversity in the Linux mobile market. It's great. Okay. Why would I say anything?
Well, so here's the yeah, of course, why else could you say anything else?
You know what? I've noticed is the particular group that is putting this out has been particularly vocal about their feelings about canonicals efforts in
This area I would say perhaps they've been discouraging about those efforts a lot of claims about duplicated effort a lot of claims about
Reinventing code that already exists, but in reality
I'm not so sure. I think there's a few
I mean you can you can always hunt down individuals who can be vocal and negative about any particular project
I could probably find someone negative about anything
Of course, of course, you know, I don't think I don't think it's fair to paint the entire
You know KDE or plasma community as negative towards one thing because there are a bunch of individuals who each have their own idea
I think it was interesting that one of the things they showcased in this video is out of the box
They're planning for support for Ubuntu touch apps
Yeah, that's cool. I mean
You know what you got to remember is what we're using on a bunch of touches
You know QML and I know there have been comments in the past like oh look
I want to have finally come around to Qt being like the right way to do things and and
You know this so it's no surprise that they support that kind of stuff as well on on the plasma mobile because you know
That's that's that's their bread and butter. Yeah
I'm I'm I find it a great that they put an image out for the Nexus 5
It makes me want to try although I don't have my Nexus 5 right now
But that that's kind of neat is anybody in the mumbroom actually flashed a Nexus 5 with it and tried it
Yeah, I should know what I'm doing tonight
That's neat, I guess I'm excited
Anything that puts more development momentum behind mobile Qt apps
I'm actually all for because I really think that'd be good for everybody in general
I think Qt's a great great great toolkit for this and I would love to see more Qt development
Especially around mobile because not only would it make great apps for plasma desktop
But it would make great apps for Ubuntu touch and make great apps for the unity 8 desktop
I would imagine I mean, I think it's a it's an amazing toolkit with a lot of runway
And so I'd love that about this. I also the other thing I love about this is actually getting more people to dogfood Whalen
That's a really good thing and that's something that Ubuntu touch doesn't give us right now. And so that's awesome, too
That all said I don't know how far this is gonna go
But I'm totally willing to sit back and willing to wait and watch and I'm really curious to know what they have in the works
Like app store wise and integration wise and partnership wise. I really want to talk to them soon and rotten
We're kind of in the background setting up something to talk to them in the future, but we just don't have a nail down, right?
Stay tuned and find out. Yeah, so that's neat. That's neat. So
The what's the web browser says peacemaker? I don't know. Does anybody know what the web browser is on plasma mobile rotten?
Are you up to I think it's the Ubuntu browser, but the one for their mobile version, but I'm they haven't
Specifically said yet. Okay, so that that's yeah
The the image I tore apart the image to have a look at it when when it came out and
There's some yeah, there's some Ubuntu components in there
I I wouldn't necessarily expect those to be in there forever. I would I would expect there
You know things like our in the image and in the demo
There's our weather app and the music app and the calculator and the web browser
I wouldn't be surprised if those get replaced with more natural, you know
K KDE bedfellows than than the ones we have but I'm you know
I'd love to share work with those guys and for you know
If they've got patches for our apps that are appropriate for them or if we've got things that we need to do to make it
Work on on their platform. That'll be awesome. Does it feel validating a
Little bit to some degree. Yeah, there's there's you know, the fact that someone can take that image and
You know if you if you rip the image apart inside it
there's a shell script and that shell script basically takes an Ubuntu touch image rips out the
Yeah, mear and unity and here the bits that they don't want adds a PPA and puts in you know
The KDE stuff which is exactly what you know
Many derivative Linux distributions are is they rip apart that's the initial that's what you do with your preview version is you rip apart somebody else's
Distro and then you put back in the value that you want to put in and then you distribute that for people to play with
People play with it and then you maybe you'll make a more robust solution
So I don't doubt they'll have image creation servers and all the kind of infrastructure that we have for hours
But they'll be generating their own images and it may well be that they don't they don't use Ubuntu touch underneath forever
That's yeah, you know, they may well choose mere or someone or something else gentoo who knows that was the meta story
I took away from this is that
The Ubuntu project has created something that a bunch of really smart people felt it was worth basing their project off of
because I think in a lot of ways that's sort of
One of the better validations of an open source project is that another group of really talented people can look at it and go there's some
serious merit here and we want to incorporate this and start from here and
Regardless of how long they use that as the base
I think in some ways it adds legitimacy to the efforts that canonical is working on here
Is that another group of really smart people think it's worth their time and maybe inspires other people to do the same thing and create
interesting other spins
Yeah
and now we have
prerequisite to maybe KDE taking a page out of Microsoft's book and making KDE hearts canonical
I'm just waiting for my next
Yeah, I think you're pushing in
No kid, but maybe just a little softer touch. All right. Well, that's fascinating. Thanks for the updates guys
I want to transition to OSCON. This is the meat of today's episode is I got some really great stuff down at OSCON
I I'm really happy with the way everything turned out and I want to cover that
So before we jump into our exclusive OSCON coverage in Linux unplugged
I'd like to mention DigitalOcean next sponsor of the unplugged program and boy to DigitalOcean come through all of the clips
You're about to see all of the interviews you saw on Linux action show all of it transferred archives stored moved between
Destinations using DigitalOcean and why not?
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to get your own rig up in
The cloud I'm talking a Linux big bay Linux rig based on KVM
SSD for the IO
Top-tier internet connections and HTML 5 UI to manage all of it and you get started in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans start
Only five dollars a month for 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a freaking terabyte of transfer a freaking terabyte
They have data center locations in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam
London and a brand new one in Germany
But what I love about DigitalOcean with keeps me coming back is that sugar of their interface that UI is done
So well, first of all, it works in all your devices. So that way you don't have to worry about that even even the console
They've written a web console in go that watches the machine from post all the way up to boot
You don't have to worry about needing Java or ActiveX or anything like that
And then you can do a pretty much all the functionality you'd want, you know
You can manage your snapshots. You can do DNS management. You can deploy applications. You can back up replicate archive
Expand the storage all the stuff you'd expect
But if you just decide you want to automate that s you know
You want to take it to the next level you want to do it at scale or you want to integrate it in with your update
Systems or your puppet management infrastructure DigitalOcean has a very slick API that allows you to do all this stuff very straightforward
In fact, there's a ton of really good community applications already built around this slick API that you can take advantage of right now
Absolutely as just part of your DigitalOcean service and remember all of this starts at just five dollars a month
And if you use our promo code do unplugged one word lowercase do unplugged
You'll get a ten dollar credit. You can try that five dollar rig two months for free
This is a Linux powered rig that is unbelievably fast up in this up in the cloud up in the sky up on somebody else's computer
Whatever you want to call it it rocks and has only five
Dollars a month and you can choose from fedora 22 Ubuntu LTS current versions. They got free BSD
They've got Debian they have really nice one-click deployments
If you want to get a ghost powered
You know ghost is a great blogging platform markdown powered if you don't need WordPress if you don't need something as advanced as WordPress
You just want to post and go check out ghost
Why not host on a digital ocean drop you want own cloud you want to do google file your life check out digital ocean
Do you want to have a minecraft server a mumble server check out digital ocean you want to have a gitlab server check out
Do you get the point it can do all of these things at five dollars a month and of course you're relying on Linux is
A fantastic memory infrastructure to just keep going and going and going and you could up it as you need it grows with you and
If you use the promo code do unplugged you get the ten dollar credit you try it two months for free
We also have incredible tutorials to take it to the next level as well go to digital ocean.com use our promo code do
Unplugged one word and a huge. Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program. It's a really great setup
I've got tons of droplets Noah's got tons of droplets West you got to go over there and create a droplet
I have done. Oh, that's right. You do. What do you use digital ocean for?
Well a number of things it's a they have great pipes over digital ocean
So I have a few servers over in Europe. This is my proxy server downloads things stores them in a cache
Good cause great good call has to run sync thing on pretty much all of them, which that's also
My data with me all the time. Yeah sync thing bit torrent sync and own cloud are great uses. I love the proxy idea
That's really slick digital ocean.com use the promo code do unplugged and go build yourself something on a droplet
You'd be surprised how far you can get at just five dollars a month. Okay, so our next segment
I'm really excited. We've got some great stuff
but first I I want to touch on a big conversation we had in Linux action show this Sunday around RFID tracking at
OSCON there was RFID printed in the badges and then some of the major rooms you went through they would track attendees to see
Which rooms are in how long you're in them kind of get heat maps of popular sessions and things like that now
I have to clarify
Josh R. Simmons from O'Reilly tweeted us and said your OSCON show had some inaccuracy
Inaccuracies around RFID people could opt out and employers don't get the data. There's no reports that are sent to employers
So I want to make that clarification for some of you were uncomfortable about the OSCON tracking
They don't send reports to employers, and there was an option to opt out. I thought it was kind of a fascinating thing
They were doing in the first place, but I just thought for those of you who are concerned about that
We should make that clarification now
That's really the only mistake you're gonna run into because you see when Noah and I go down to events like this
We've been doing this for a while now
Professional we are a well oiled machine West like we get down there. We're strutting our stuff
What's up, Linux action show biggest podcast in the Linux world. We're here
We're gonna record some interviews get out of the way
And I tell you it all goes really well until you realize we've showed up an hour early and the Expo Hall hasn't even opened
Yet when you told me you didn't have anything till 1.30. I thought I thought okay. Well, then we'll just go do interviews until 1.30
No, it wasn't what I was thinking it's actually not what I communicated to
You see what he communicated was I don't need to be there until 1.30
I did, but I also I did specifically tell you the inner that the Expo Hall wasn't gonna be open till the afternoon
I think by that time I think here's what I'd work out here's what here's my here's my mistake
My mistake was expecting no it convey more than 15 seconds of information
Important
So I have to condense it down to 15 seconds and spit that out not true
That's not true. That's not true. You find that I have to come up with interesting other things to say to Phil
You do have to sell me. Yeah
Okay, I'll keep that in mind for future
We got that for we got that worked out
But there was a little bit of it's actually kind of nice at OSCON. They have a media room set up
So we were able to kill a little time in there. We got some things sorted out
We got some bad stuff resolved and our first interview of the day was with one of the chairs of OSCON
And I asked her like for people who are listening from a community standpoint
What's the connection between O'Reilly and OSCON and can you give us a little information about how that all connects?
Walking around here at OSCON and I ran into Rachel now Rachel is a very very interesting guest on the unplug show because she runs
This whole thing puts it all together. I'm really excited to talk to her. So Rachel, welcome to Linux unplug happy to be here
Thank you. So Rachel, I know that probably a lot of folks are somewhat familiar with OSCON
But I don't know if they really are familiar with
How O'Reilly is involved with OSCON because I think we all know O'Reilly
So could you touch on just a little bit of O'Reilly and OSCON and how that is all connected?
Absolutely, so O'Reilly has been around for about 38 years and
OSCON has been around for this is the 17th one
and so we've always really been a part of open source before it was even called open source and
I believe we were part of coining that phrase and when we did that was something that we brought to OSCON. OSCON actually started as a
Perl event and then as more and more people came to the open source community
It became more of a developer event. And so O'Reilly has many many events at this point
We have I think we have 18 per year, but we also we have books we have videos
And you know, we distribute ebooks. So yeah
I think you guys are very very well known for the ebooks and the books online and the animals of course are a very iconic
Aspect to it. So I don't know though do people do people when they hear O'Reilly
Do they think of that legacy in open source and how does OSCON help sort of familiarize people with that?
I think they do think of the legacy. Like I said, so OSCON
Has been around for a long time and you see a lot of people if not come back every year come back every couple
Of years to check in with the community
So I think that it's something that people have been looking at for a while
I want to what I want to make sure OSCON is is that we're bringing in constantly bringing in new people
So that they are a part of that legacy because even though open source has quote-unquote won
There's a lot of work left to do because it has to do with how do you bring that into your business?
How do you make that work? How do you make money from it?
Well still being a good open source community member and you know, that's such an interesting aspect there, too
Because it is exploding every year. It feels like the open source world has gotten bigger
There's so many more technologies and you know
We see really fascinating big huge companies like SAP are in here and how they leverage open source
But one of the interesting things about OSCON for people that are
Not here right now that is hard to capture
Because we're on the floor all the time and you get an idea in a sense of the activity
What's really hard to capture is there's some really incredible sessions going on and I know there's been some specific
Retooling around some of that this year. Could you talk a little bit about that? Yeah, absolutely
so we used to be set up by language and I think that was because
Developers identified with a certain language at least more so than others
And what we realized is that there's so many languages frameworks techniques all different open source pieces
That there's now the right tool for the job
So what we wanted to do instead was pick out what are the common problems that developers are having either in?
Securing their software or scaling it or how do you take it mobile and giving them solutions and having those?
solutions be able to be applied to different frameworks languages, so
Absolutely, and there's also been some pretty like intensive sessions this year that really you're like you could come here and get really familiar with something
What's the intent behind that? Well, we wanted to get exactly wanted to get a little bit more intense. We had
Four two-day training courses one was on Swift another was on go
Microservices is a big deal. We really wanted people to be able to come in
Take two days not put it off any longer
Focus focus be able to actually when they go back next week to work to actually solve a problem and give them those materials
To solve that problem, so we had those we had 38 tutorials
Which is like an amazing amount of tutorials and those were like three to six hours
And then like you said the sessions where you're just sort of getting a taste of what something is now if I'm watching from afar
Is there any kind of any kind of resources I can read up and get an idea of?
What's coming up next year, so I know if I want to make it out here is there like a site I can watch or a feed to follow?
That's a good question, so we have oscon.com
And you can go there, and you can check out the the keynotes will be streaming or not streaming live anyway
But they'll be there you can check them out, and then you can check out O'Reilly's radar
And that's some you know I talked a little bit about what we were doing
I'll talk about what I did see and honestly I want to talk to a bunch of people while I'm here to see what they did
Like what they didn't like one of the things I'm thinking about for next year is making a track that's like the mind-blowing track
Which is just like super advanced and like people can go in and be like I don't know what just happened
Get known for being really hardcore in there. Yeah, that's great. I love to see what you guys gonna come up with Rachel
Thank so much for coming on Linux unplugged. No problem is pleasure
And that was interesting you know they did they decided as the conference gets bigger their solution to sort of
Becoming less relevant is to get more hardcore and focus more on content. We'll see how that works as they move to Texas now this next clip
I got here is called matrix
And I don't know if your mess are you familiar with like stack which is like a collaboration tool for teams and stuff like that?
Oh, yeah, yeah, it's really popular these days
It's really tape taking off and there is an open source competitor that you can either use as a hosted service or host yourself called matrix
It's an open source stack killer and it involves IRC chat web RTC
Persistent rooms and project planning calendaring and integration with third-party services
And they're saying stop using stack and try and try out matrix it might just solve your needs
So we spent 12 years building set infrastructure and got quite depressed in the end because set was meant to be like this email
But for open video except in practice nobody has sit your eyes on their business cards and the open Federation the open
Interoperability thing just hasn't really quite taken off so we went and
Wrote an alternative to set based on HTTP just a really simple HTTP API
Or if I want to set up a video call somebody I do one hit
With the offer of what media I want to talk and you do one hit back with the answer and that's it
We're in a call. So none of the complexities of set with all the you know, it's a UDP. Is it TLS?
Is it TCP? Is it this version? Is it that version?
So it's quite old and very fragmented just doing it as an HTTP works a lot better and that's one of the things you can use
With matrix except matrix isn't just about open video. You can also use it for instant messaging
We've got the little drone sitting down there, which we're about to launch as the Internet of Things
Where you can go and get the video off it via matrix, but you can also control it
We went and hooked up people's cars to matrix so the car kind of sends out telemetry as little blobs of JSON into matrix
And you can go and consume it anywhere else
So basically matrix is a big open decentralized object database with PubSub schematics
So that anybody can publish any random data they want and there could be a message or whatever
And over here on the screen, am I seeing like a persistent group chat environment? Kind of looks like a bit like IRC and messaging
Yeah, so this is one of the classic things you can do with matrix. Use it as a persistent group chat thing
This is an angular environment and there are a couple of hundred chats going on there
A lot of these are bridged into FreeNode. FreeNode have been very cool and let us actually bridge matrix into FreeNode or vice versa
Here is another view of the same room, say, but a more Slack-like environment. This one is written in React
So this is kind of like a team collaboration sort of version of it sitting on top of the matrix object database?
And so I assume in this I could have text, image, video, audio, all those things in here?
Yeah, so any JSON you like. You can hear these are just instant messages with people trying to do weird shit with UTF-8, but if we go back to this one
If you double click on stuff like a message like test there, you can see it is just arbitrary JSON
So it could be a M room message or if you were doing a video call here, it could be a bit uglier
It is a M call invite and you have got the description of the media for that call there
But it could be drone control, it could be car telemetry, whatever the hell
And my program, my app just needs to be able to read this and know what to do with it?
Yep, precisely. So we define some standard types like m.call. Anything that begins with m. is matrix and it is part of our spec
But it is like Java namespace, so if you wanted to have a com.google.whateverthehell Google might use it for, then just feel free, go nuts, put data in
So if I wanted to roll this out, what is my back-end structure look like? Is it a Linux server? What is it running on?
So we are providing one reference server at the moment which is written in Python and Twisted and it is about 30,000 lines of code
It is pretty beta but it works well enough to have rooms with like a thousand people in it and a couple of hundred servers participating
And it runs on any OS that can support Python really
Some of that is, it could be Debian, we have got some Dockerfiles, Susie images, Fedora images and even somebody made it run on Windows
Very cool. I like that. Do you have any questions?
So what does a customizability look like? If I wanted to specify, can I specify video parameters like the codecs I want to use or the size of resolution I want to send, that kind of thing?
So what we do for the actual video on one of these calls, if I am going to put this on the right network, I leave them going to create a demo
That is a great question because that is something we run into all the time
We want to be able to specifically say 720p because we know we have the right bandwidth, the right environments, we built it for that
But a lot of hangouts and Skype, a lot of the consumer solutions, they just automatically decide what they are going to give you and you have no say
Right, so what we do is to slightly punt on the issue and we just use WebRTC which is built into the browser already and we use whatever it gives us
We can, I think there is an idea of intents where you can say, or constraints where you can say how I want it 720p
And if you are lucky then the browser and the camera and the planets will align and you will get what you asked for
So the intent says if the system supports it, give me this?
Yes, precisely, so Matrix is just the signaling, we are relying on whatever else is already hanging around like WebRTC to make that work
Now if I go and try to quickly find Evil Matthew, here is my demo self and say hello there
We are going to go and give Evil Matthew a video call I think, I like that
Okay, so that is, sorry, I am Evil Matthew here
Oh, I see, I see
Oh, I like that, wait
Then this is going and pulling open WebRTC
Yeah, and it just puts it right there in line with the chat
And we should have an inbound call, in fact I got it coming in, in fact that is the previous message coming in on my Apple Watch
But if we go and accept it there, then hopefully
Oh, interesting, so there must be an app running on your phone that is also getting the messages from the call, so you are getting push notifications to your phone too?
Yeah, absolutely, so there we go, that is now just a typical WebRTC call, so it is a 640x480 and it is just a default that you get
But as I say you can put constraints on it to try to get 720p and you can see that I am getting push notifications coming in here
Also on the app from various different channels because we have got iOS and Android apps and about ten different clients
Five of them are from the core team and the rest are from the community, so people have done command line clients using WeChat
There is a Java desktop app, there is a Chrome app, all sorts
If I am a company that was looking at something like Slack, could this be a replacement for that? Could I use this maybe in place of Slack?
Potentially, so the big advantage is that you can run your own server
All of the conversation history here gets replicated over the participating servers
So I can run my own one, you can run your own one and if we are in the same room then no single server or entity or vendor like Slack for instance owns that conversation
It is aggressively decentralized, a bit like Git or Blockchain or something like that
So that is quite a compelling thing
We have also got end-to-end encryption in it using an OTR like thing which is actually better than OTR
And that again makes it kind of interesting because with Slack you have no choice but to just hand all your data over today
Whereas here if you wanted to flip the bit and turn on end-to-end encryption you can
And for the encryption implementation, how much of that is done out in the open? How much of that is open source or documented?
It is all open source under the Apache license
What we did was to take the Axolotl ratchet implementation or specification that Open Whisper Systems have written and released
And it is what WhatsApp uses in TechSecure and we wrote our own clean room implementation of that spec
And it is called OM, O-L-M, you can get it from GitHub, Apache licensed along with the rest of the Matrix code base
Awesome, thank you very much for the information, I am definitely going to check that out because we have been looking at something kind of like that
Appreciate it
I like this more than the standard alternative to going with something proprietary like Slack and it is a neat kind of package all put together
SkookieSprite, you seem kind of impressed by it during the playback, what do you think?
Oh, I mean it sounds like a totally integrated free and open source
I am big about that aspect of it, that means it is accessible, you can audit it, you know that like you said it is your own data
Yeah and for the most part you know Slack is a pretty compelling product but when it is my company and it is like
You know one of the things I think about with something like Slack is it seems like it could be a really good solution for 2015, 2016 and maybe even 2017
Now what happens if Jupiter Broadcasting makes it 30 years, 35 years and I want to look back at sort of like the formative years of the company
I would really, really, really regret having that data either A not available because that company is not around or in some sort of proprietary format that I can't get access to
So having something like that, the collaborative details, where our company was at, owning that to me seems like a part of the company's history
Definitely, you know in my office we used to have a custom back end chat client XMPP based
We have been looking at, you know we are using Slack now but I know there are still some shareholders in the company who are concerned about data flowing outside of our company to someone else
Before that we have been stuck using Pidgin and other XMPP clients so if there is something like this that has a new interface, has more abilities that might be big for a lot of enterprises
It is called Matrix and of course that is a, boy as far as SEO goes that is pretty rough, I have even tried to get links for the show and I had a rough time
I can't believe they got the dot org, that is kind of impressive
Yeah exactly, so you can get it right now, matrix.org and go check it out
So this next thing is, this is the last sort of like businessy sysadmy thing and then we are going to get into some really crazy great stuff
This one though I want to talk about because there is this category that gets kicked around and I think a lot of people associate it with being a hipster, maybe the DevOps category
And it is this one guy or gal and they have got to do one thing, they have got to build code and integrate it with servers and they have got to be able to scale
And they have got to get to thousands of servers and the thing is, it sounds like I am making fun of people but this is an actual job that to me sounds like it would keep me up all night long
Being responsible for thousands of servers when I really just want to create software, I don't really want to be a sysadmin, this sounds like the recipe for an ulcer
And so there is an open source project out there called Mesosphere and Mesosphere, have you heard of this at all, Mesosphere is like a cluster management orchestration suite at a high level
I was just looking at a tutorial the other day, it looks very interesting
Really, so this is one of the people working on it, now I have got to warn you, he is not a public relations person
This was a bit of rental space essentially or free space that GitHub gave out to some open source projects
And so Wes I would be really curious to hear your insights after we play this, I get an idea of Mesosphere Apache cluster management
With my chat in the little area where GitHub has given out space to certain open source projects that they like
So my name is Michael Hausenblatt, I am leading DevOps relations at Mesosphere
And what we have here is Apache Mesosphere, just a resource manager, a top level Apache project
Takes a bunch of nodes in your cluster and abstracts that away making you as a developer who wants to develop
So if I am a developer who is in that DevOps role and I have thousands of servers or hundreds of servers or tens of thousands of servers
That is a massive task for one person to manage and this is trying to make it possible for one person to manage all of that
That is right, and for a person like a developer who wants to write distributed applications
It is really the kernel of a kind of distributed operating system and that is what we do
Now I see here you have one of the key bullet points is that it is fault tolerant in battle test
How does something like this not become a single point of failure that just takes somebody down for the day if it has issues
Very good question, number of components like all of them, like the master and everything is fault tolerant
So you always, whatever fails, everything will fail over to something that is on standby here
So there is really no single point of failure
And in the backend server is it Linux based?
It is Linux based, yes
And then what does that look like from a deployment standpoint, is it an appliance, is it a container, is it a software package I install?
Essentially we have two versions, the community edition which is cloud only, so you can only deploy it in one of the public clouds
The enterprise edition which you can also deploy on-prem
And what is the on-premises one look like, is that more of a
The enterprise edition that also comes with support and a bit of secret sauce
So essentially the guys who used to do Mesos at Twitter and Airbnb taking that experience and productize that
Taking infrastructures like that and fascinating, well thanks for the information
Thank you
So what was your impression when you were researching the product, or I guess the project I should say
You know it seems like the Apache Mesos on steroids
Something that even further adds abstractions because the whole big idea here is being able to easily scale
And maybe not even have to think about it
It's like you just drag resources around kind of a thing
Yeah and you can kind of write as if it was all one big resource
Yeah, oh so it gives you tools at a development level
Right, or you can do that
Interesting, well very cool and so where do people, do you have any good recommendations people want to find out more about it
Anything you found very useful
You know it looks like there's even a digital ocean tutorial right here, an introduction to Mesosphere
Look at that, there it is, well there you go, that's actually probably
That's probably the best bet just as a starting point
They have technical writers that go through those
And nice diagrams too
So have you heard, yeah, cool look at that
I don't think I have a shot of your machine there, that's me
No I don't have a shot of your machine but you know what I will for next week
So have you heard of the company Fastmail before
Yeah I was just looking at their services the other day
Are you joking
I think I saw an advertiser for it and it was kind of interesting
Yeah are you kidding me right now
No I'm not, 100%
Yeah I actually, you know I kick around, you know, Jupiter Broadcasting's backend mail is powered by Google Apps
The usual hand wavy, yeah
So there's two ways I look at this, lazy practical Chris goes oh man this is great
I get like all of the stuff I'd want from like a collaboration software without having to run a collaboration software
And it's really great I just click a button, I can create new accounts for people
And the web mail is pretty good right
And the calendaring is great
And so that's practical Chris right
And then tinfoil hat Edward Snowden following Chris goes
Hey man, you know you're getting emails from people in Iran, from China, in Russia
And they're all landing in this Google inbox that anybody could just go we'd like to have access to Mr.
And so like sometimes that's when it's like I have these two competing voices in my head
And they all, you know what they both agree on, they both argue with each other constantly
Except for every now and then they go you know you could check out Fastmail
And then I go oh really
And then I start, so then like Fastmail has been building up momentum
And so I was walking around OSCON and I bumped into the Fastmail folks
And I thought gosh I've really been thinking about this
And I wonder how much of their infrastructure is Linux based
What is their participation in open source because
I was wondering exactly those same things when I was looking at their site
Right exactly and I'm thinking if I maybe make the switch I want to you know I want to vote with my wallet again
I mean I want to make the right choice and so I sat down sort of to vet Fastmail for myself
And vet Fastmail for Jupiter Broadcasting
Fastmail is email done right, really email, calendars and contacts done right these days
We do hosting for all of those for individuals or businesses
And we just do it really well, we have our own interface
Which is much faster and more powerful and more elegant than our competitors
And we also do a lot with open source software which is why we're here at OSCON this week
Very interesting, so somebody like me who's on Google Apps might want to find something maybe a little different
Maybe I'm not as comfortable with Google Apps as I used to be
And I love that you use open source, that would definitely play into my decision just as an open source advocate myself
How does open source play into Fastmail?
So the core IMAP server that we use to host everyone's email is Cyrus
Which is one of the two biggest open source IMAP servers
It was started by Carnegie Mellon University about 20 years ago now I think
And for at least the last 5 years, probably 10 years, Fastmail has been the biggest contributor to that project
My colleague Bron is probably the main developer and leads the project these days
We also have a couple of others now working full time on it
So we make huge contributions to that
We also have a huge number of open source Perl libraries that we've made available
That we built as part of our middleware which is built in Perl
And also more recently we have open sourced a couple of JavaScript libraries that we use to power our web interface
The most popular of which being the Squire rich text editor
Which is now getting quite a lot of attention, 3000 GitHub stars or so
So indulge me if you will on the backend, are we seeing Fastmail run on Linux servers? Is it on Windows boxes?
What's sort of the backend infrastructure look like? Is that open source too?
So yeah most of the backend stuff is open source
We run on Linux, we certainly don't run on Windows
I think there's one or two Windows machines in the office somewhere
Any Linux desktops in the office?
There are quite a few Linux desktops in the office
It's pretty much a split between Mac and Linux or Linux run on a Mac in some cases
And I think there's one guy using Windows because someone has to just to make sure it still works
You've got to blame somebody for the network spam
Well exactly, so the backend is mainly run on Linux
And I believe we publish most of the things we do, certainly anything that's interesting to our GitHub account
That includes our custom patches on Cyrus and various things like that
So check out the GitHub page for that stuff
Great well thank you very much for the information
Thank you
I love that, that was a great chat
It was cool to find out how much of their infrastructure actually uses Linux
Were you impressed now that somebody was looking up their services?
Yeah you know that definitely speaks to the organization where they're going, what they're based on
Also there's other great services out there like Colab and other things to check out as well
So it's a good time out there
And then we have our last interview
This one was a fun one because not only is he a listener of Linux Unplugged and the Linux Action Show
Which I've got to say, the Samsung booth was not going to get any attention by us this year
Except for this guy was here because last year they had a really nice passionate guy from Korea who didn't speak English
And the thing is, it's pretty hard to interview somebody who doesn't speak English
And so what they did this year is they doubled down on the amount of engineers
So they brought in a lot more engineers who are all from Korea
But they also brought in people who were familiar with the products and spoke English
And so what you got to see is people who were insanely passionate about the products
And one of the things that doesn't come across because this is an audio interview
Is we were, once he started talking, all of the engineers huddled around to listen to what he had to say
They all wanted to know, it was really intense
But what was great is because we were doing the audio interview, it was just a very natural
Hey let's walk up and take a look
And it just sort of, the conversation unfolded
And this is one of my favorite kind of, it just happened because I was recording exclusively for Linux Unplugged
Now I'm here at the Samsung booth and I saw a Tizen sign, a big Tizen sign here
And I was like, wow, look at this thing, I've got to take a look
And while I was noticing that, Noah noticed a very slick looking phone
What grabbed your attention about this phone, Noah?
Honestly, it looks like an iPhone but it's made by Samsung
That's the first thing that's coming to my mind
It looks like it's smaller, it's maybe an older one, right?
Right, yeah, yeah, older iPhone maybe
But it has the traditional Samsung things you'd expect
Like a home button on here and all the things
But it doesn't run Android
No, so when I turned it on, it actually, look at this Chris
When you turn this phone on, it actually, it looks almost like the Android unlocker
When I unlock it, it kind of, it resembles Android
A little cleaner UI maybe
Right, and the first thing that caught me were these applications down here
And then obviously the home screen
Oh I like that, I like the way it displays that
So I thought to help put all this together, maybe we could talk to an expert here
So Ben's here at the Samsung booth, hey Ben, welcome to Linux Unplugged
Hi there, it's nice to meet you guys
Hello, so can you tell us, what the heck is Noah holding here and what's different about this phone?
So that phone is the first phone that runs Tizen
Which Tizen is our own open source operating system that
It's basically just a Linux distribution that we've added a few APIs
To give you access to device functionality like sensors and your cell networks and things like that
It's really great because it lets you write applications in just straight C++
Just like a standard Linux application
You can also write apps using web native languages like HTML, CSS and JavaScript
So it kind of gets the best of both worlds
You've got the systems side of things that let you get really efficient C++ apps
But then you've also got the simplicity of your web native languages
So I've wondered, I notice Samsung obviously pretty well known for their Android devices
You might have noticed this too
And when I look at this device, not only does it feel like a pretty well built phone
Because it's a Samsung and they've got some experience with that
But the UI, especially in the notifications tray here
Reminds me a little bit of TouchWiz on my S6
And so where does Samsung see Tizen fitting in with something like the S6 and TouchWiz?
You could almost tell me this was a TouchWiz device
But then I noticed a few differences
Could I maybe see this on a US phone in the future?
Where does Samsung see it all fitting in?
Honestly I can't really answer questions about products like that
Because I'm not really privy to that information
I do know that we're trying to get Tizen on as many different types of devices as possible
I notice it's not just phones
Is this a DSLR here?
And then we've got a watch here too
Tell me about the DSLR widget
It's a pretty full featured camera that runs Tizen
Why Tizen on a camera?
Honestly I can't
You need an OS, a camera needs an OS right?
I mean they're pretty sophisticated I guess
I'll tell you, one of the great benefits of Tizen is it's better for
Since everything runs in C++
It's better for devices that have lower memory, lower CPU power
Which is why we also put it on our TVs
Because if you're trying to put something like Android
It's going to bog it down with all the overhead from Java
Yeah, Tizen's going to get a lot better performance
And so that's probably also why it's on the watches right?
Yeah, that's correct
And so tell me about the process of that
When Samsung goes out there
Didn't they first try these with Android?
And then they decided to switch it to Tizen?
Was it performance?
Can you tell me a little bit why Tizen was there?
Because so many devices these days have Android Wear
As a consumer I almost expect Android Wear
So I would kind of wonder why Tizen
And there must be some advantages
Yeah, well if I'm not mistaken
I think we actually released Tizen watches
Pretty long before Android Wear even came out
But that was actually really where it started for us
And once again it's because on a watch
You're not going to have very much CPU power
You're not going to have a whole lot of memory
So you have to have an operating system that's pretty efficient to run on
And as a community member
Can I contribute to Tizen?
And could those changes eventually show up on a Samsung device?
Yeah, so Tizen 3.0 is a completely collaborative open source project
Anyone can pull it off of
I think we have it on GitHub
Actually no, I think it's a separate Git repo
But anyone can pull it down
And make contributions to it
And send it back upstream
All of these devices are actually based on Tizen 2.3
Which was developed internally by Samsung
And released as open source
So the changes wouldn't show up on these devices
But in the future we're hoping to get some more devices that run Tizen 3.0
Very, very neat
And so if I wanted to take a little look at some of this stuff
Maybe learn more about Tizen
Or learn about creating apps for it
Where do I go?
You can check out developer.tizen.org
And that's got all the information for
It's got an API for learning about
Or API documentation for learning about
All of the functionality that we've provided
Yeah, so that's good
Very good
Well, Ben, thank you very much
I've got to check out this Camera Resin Tizen
Are you playing with that right now?
Yeah, I am
So one of the things I noticed is
I'm not sure if this technically qualifies as a DSLR
Because it looks like there's just an LCD inside of here
But look at that
Yeah, exactly
If I can figure out how to get back to the plate
The picture is super sharp
So I turn the aperture down
Look at how much blur we have
Oh, it's touchscreen
We get all this blur in the background
And look at this right here
You've got a little pull-down menu right there
How slick is that?
Well, the thing I can see that would be advantageous about this is
Chris, is we can take these pictures
And then we can go and just upload them straight to Twitter
So you get all the benefits that you would expect
From a professional camera
So that's Wi-Fi now?
With the advantage of a smartphone
Oh, I would assume so, yeah
Wow, check that out
Boy, welcome to the future
Share with Wi-Fi
That might be my next camera
A Linux running camera?
I've got to have that
It was pretty neat
And you know what?
It was really responsive
You would have thought it was a custom-built operating system
Just for that camera
It was super snappy
So to have all this kind of nice, slick UI and features
On a little camera like that was pretty cool
Has anyone else really embraced Tizen?
Because that seems like where it might be really interesting
Is to have a non-Android platform that other people could take
Yeah, I mean, it made sense on the watches, too
It was interesting
We'll see where it goes
I asked them, of course
They couldn't give me an answer on when we're going to get that stuff in the US
Of course
That would be too fun
That would be the key thing
That would really be the key thing
So that's Scratching the Surface
Of course, we have another two hours of OSCON coverage
In this week's episode of the Linux Action Show
Well, not really two hours
About 45 minutes, 50 minutes
In episode 375 of the Linux Action Show
OSCON 2015
And you can go check that out if you want even more
Also, in the show notes
Because I'm a good guy
I also posted a playlist of just the OSCON interviews from the Linux Action Show
If you don't want to watch the whole episode, you can watch
Tired of Chris
You just want the OSCON business
You got it
There you go
Yeah, because it's all Noah in the interviews
All right, so we've got to talk about this Skunkworks project
In development deep inside the community from Las Vegas
But first, I want to talk about Linux Academy
The third sponsor and final sponsor right here on the Linux Unplugged program
I've been a Linux Academy customer for about a month before they became a sponsor
And when I decided to work with them and have them become sponsors
We said, my conversation started literally like this
I almost don't want you to be sponsors because this was my idea
I wanted to do this
Like if I knew everything I knew now
Almost 10 years into the Linux Action Show looking back
This is so brilliant
Because you have to have the passion for Linux and open source to build a platform like this
And that I've got
But I don't have the connections to the education community and the development community
And that's what Linux Academy had
But it's so genius because it's exactly what we need as a community
It's like all of those big name online education sites you've heard
But specifically around Linux and open source
So instead of just like Linux and open source being a check box
And they're multi-category of things they cover
From everything from Adobe After Effects to replacing the oil in your truck
Like that's just for them it's a feature, right?
But for Linux Academy it's their life
It's their passion
So they came together as Linux enthusiasts and educators and developers
And they built the Linux Academy platform
And that was the missing piece
Is what we really really needed
Is somebody who's truly enthusiastic and creating incredible content
I remember when I was starting in Linux
There was like the Linux documentation project
And there was the Gen 2 Wiki
And all of these things were really good resources
But they were not legitimate resources that I could tell my employer about
That they could go towards my employment
Educational reimbursement
It could show up on my review
There was team account support
Like it didn't meet any of those criterias
The best I had were books
It was horrible
LinuxAcademy.com
Go there and check them out
Go to Linux Academy right now
In fact, if you go to LinuxAcademy.com slash unplug
You can get our 33% discount to really try them out for a little while
Isn't that slick?
Go to LinuxAcademy.com slash unplug
You have step-by-step video courses
Downloadable comprehensive study guides
They have a great system where you can choose from 7 plus Linux distributions
They'll automatically adjust the courseware and the virtual machines
They spin up for you on demand
You want to know about AWS
You want to know about Red Hat certification
Docker, virtualization
Just doing backups on a Linux rig
Building out an entire LAMP stack
Or maybe Android development on the Linux desktop
Linux Academy has courseware on it
You want to learn Ruby, Python, things like that
Anything that's an ecosystem around Linux and open source
Linux Academy has courseware on it because they love it
And they also have just introduced a new feature called Nuggets
Between 2 and 60 minute courses we just deep dive on a topic
Nice things too like IP tables
Or rsync backup or virtualization in VirtualBox
Headless virtualization under VirtualBox
And if you're ready to go get those Red Hat certified engineer certifications
The ones that are basically
What I remember when I was doing interviews
I would look at somebody's resume
And there's a few that would really stand out
The ones that I really respected
And definitely I would count the Red Hat certifications among them
Because you really have to actually earn that certification
It's no joke
It's a hands on kind of testing
Where you really have to work with the technology
And prove you can do it over and over again
And as an interviewer you know that
And it's a big deal that Linux Academy has some of the best courseware on the web on this
And you can go get it right now at a 33% discount
When you go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
And a big thank you to Linux Academy
For sponsoring the unplugged program
Oh man I love the Red Hat certified stuff
They are really working overtime on that
Now I am excited to talk to Mr. Skookiesprite
It's been a while since he's been on the show
And I guess it is downtime he's been working on
I believe it's called the Radio Controller Project
Or something along those lines
Skookiesprite what is it and what's the name?
Radio Control Room Project
Control Room
Yeah RCRproject.com
Yeah okay so what is it?
It enables users to create
From their own local files
Autonomously self generating programmatic streaming radio
So like if I want to be a DJ
Like if I had a whole library of music
And I wanted to be a DJ for a weekend
Can I use this?
Yeah but what's even cooler
Okay so I got the idea because I have 56,000 MP3 files
All of them legitimately ripped from my own CD collection
Which I donated to the VA library
And a bunch of vinyl
So I'm thinking 56,000 MP3 files
How am I ever going to listen to them?
How am I ever going to even create playlists
For what I want to hear at any given time right?
Like are you following me there?
Yeah absolutely
Yeah okay so I thought well what if I had a way for
I like radio a lot
And what makes radio good
The thing that makes radio good is their programs
You just turn it on
You turn it on and you don't have to think about it
It's just the music you love is playing
Exactly or at certain times
There are programs that are playing certain different types of music
So what if I could make a program that would just
Make all of these programs
Like radio programs
And stream them all as like one streaming radio thing
But it sounds like real radio
And this could be like running on my own server in my house
That I could hook up to internet
And it does like an ice cast stream in my phone
Yeah okay so where the rubber meets the road
Is ice cast and liquid soap
But what RCR adds to it
Is like basically the controller that sits on top of it
I've run it off of
Right now it runs off of one of my laptops
Which I use as my daily driver pretty much
And it spits it out to a digital ocean droplet
And anyone can listen to it
And the really exciting thing is tune in radio now
You can sign up with tune in radio for free
That's the other thing
I don't like Pandora and stuff
Where it's like oh well fine
We want to access your preferences
Plus you want to use your own library
Not Pandora's library
Absolutely and the other cool thing is
You can set up every aspect of the shows
You can decide when a show starts
The type of bumpers it has
The intros outros
It has back and outs
Now you're going to put me out of work
You're just automating my job now?
Pretty much that's what I kind of wanted to do
Okay cool
I was cutting straight for you Chris
So I'm gathering this is a closed source project
Released under a Microsoft license?
Absolutely no
No it's totally built on a free and open source stack
Like I said like you said liquid soap
And ice cast
And then this is built on top of it
And we're adding an HTML interface for it
Right now you configure your shows
By actual text files and stuff
Which is not that bad
Because there's a lot of stuff to configure
So could a person say like
In somebody in our chat room for example
Could they string together a few chapters
Of an old time radio series or an audio book
And kind of have like a weekly serial that broadcasts?
Yes absolutely
That's cool
The latest Unstable bill
Because like basically
The coolest thing about RCR
Is that it makes sure
It has several checks in terms of like what gets added
Okay here
So like when you create a show
You select from all of these different directories
Or all of these individual files
That you want to have played
And it actually has checks
That you can turn on or off
Like global freshness factor for instance
So only every six hours
Before any song repeats
Across any show
Et cetera et cetera et cetera
So it's designed to randomize
So that you hear stuff that you wouldn't normally
Hear if you were
That's pretty cool
And so the link to the project
Which you can also just find at rcrproject.com
We'll have a link in the show notes
And eventually
I'll just have this doing Linux Unplugged in the future
You won't even know
It'll just be powered by this thing
Linux Unplugged from a distance from Las Vegas
No that's the coolest thing is you get to be
The puppet master you get to create
Okay so the hardest thing about creating your own
Streaming radio station that doesn't suck
Is actually being there to create your own
Program to DJ in
I mean like hell who has the time
To DJ you know 24 hours of programming
A day well now you can without having
To be there boom boom
There you go now we're going to need a jobs
Program for all those DJs that are getting put out of work by
Scooby Sprite but it's cool in the name of
The source it's cool so check out
We'll have a link in the show notes if you guys
Want to check it out and that'll bring us towards the end
Of this week's episode of Linux Unplugged
Wes I'm glad you could make it out even after the big move
Congrats to the new place
Well thank you sir pleasure to be here
The new digs in Seattle and big thanks to
The folks at OSCON who
Interviewed us and thanks to
Noah of course for making it out there with me
And you know I gotta say I really really
Enjoyed taking this
You know all of the interviews we did for Linux Unplugged
Were just on this little portable recorder
And I think it got some really great chats
Because it's more disarming
Than having a big video camera in your face
And I loved it was a good
It was a good fun opportunity for me to just
Focus on doing interviews for an audio only show
And I think it made for a much more enjoyable
OSCON for me so there's a
Lesson in that for all of us but I want to invite
You to join us next week go over to
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to
Get this show in your local time zone but if you're
Hip to the Pacific it's at 2pm
Over at jblive.tv
Of course you can go to Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash
Calendar to send us an email but even better go to
linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Please linuxactionshow.reddit.com
The feedback thread for this show never gets
Enough attention so give it some attention
Give it some love attention
At linuxactionshow.reddit.com episode 103
Also any stories
Or feedback oh great over there
Wes is there anything you'd like to point people
Throughout the week anywhere twitter account
Anything like that I don't think so no okay
Follow me at Chris Elias and follow the network
At Jupiter Signal and we'll see you back here
Next Tuesday thanks everybody
Jupiterbroadcasting.com
Jupiterbroadcasting.com and then we're going to get out of here
Big show today big show
Jupiterbroadcasting.com
Go pick now it probably should be
Something with the OSCON in there since that was the
Bulk of our
Show a lot of good stuff thank you specifically
To Wimpy for that great update and Scooby Sprite
And Popey great updates and of course
Everybody else in the Mumble Room like Mr. Corpse
Jupiterbroadcasting.com
Oh heck I did a
Search now you see what I'm talking
About there you go
Yeah Wimpy you got a lot of coverage didn't you
Oh boy I didn't
Realize honestly I thought
Like 20 comments
On my G Plus stream were
The size of it I had no idea yeah I was
Surprised when I saw the amount of coverage I got I was like
Wow this is an issue that resonates
With people OSCON
Secret sauce is in what's interesting is that
There's more
People saying
Don't remove it than there are people
Agreeing with removing it so
That's cause crazy people outnumber us
Yeah you know you know Wimpy
My only experience with
That is at a certain point
You gotta go with your gut
And despite oh yeah
I mean you know I'm getting feedback
Right now that would literally
Would literally be suicide for the show
If I followed it and I get it over and over again
And I've got a fresh batch of it today
There's an active thread in our subreddit
And it just
It really shows you how sometimes
The reason why you're the person making
The content is because you are willing
To take these risks
And so you know you can't
You gotta move forward
I think it's a beautiful thing to do because worst case
Is you can always put it back in the next release
So what if
It's already there yeah
If you could wave a magic wand and
Fix software center what would you do
Like you know
Other than removing it what's the
Magic wand fix for software center?
I wouldn't bring it to the ground
Are you asking me or is that a general question?
It's a general question
Yeah
Okay so one the
Developers having access to the
Paid section of the Ubuntu software center
And not having access to do
Anything at all on the
Open source thing that sucks
I don't understand what you're saying
If I create
If I put an app in the Ubuntu software center that is
Completely free
But it's on the paid section
I can control the source of the app and I can
Actually update it myself and I can do
Whatever I want I can change descriptions I can change
The photos and all that good stuff
If I have my app in the open source side of it
And I have absolutely zero
Control and I have to just
Beg and beg and beg for them to do anything
Rod and wasn't that the
Thing like they wouldn't update you went through
Several updates of your own project
And they wouldn't update it?
Yeah it took me a year to get my stuff updated
That's less of a Ubuntu software
I accept that's an issue
That's less of an Ubuntu software center issue
Having that split
Is irritating the fact that I
Can't control that is incredibly
Irritating but also
As an end user
The recommendation
System is pretty much
Useless because it's based on your
Account that you don't have yet
So then you'd have to create the account which the Ubuntu
One thing which then they announced that Ubuntu
One was going away but they really weren't taking
It away it was just the music
I know I just explained
What I meant anyway it created
Confusion it created confusion
Because Ubuntu
One music is called Ubuntu One
And no one called it Ubuntu One music
It confused people so then now
There's actually people who do say that
It's gone and I've had to explain
To them no it's not it's still there
It's just confusing
We just wish that it was gone
No I actually
Explained anyway it doesn't matter
The point is though there is
A situation with
The listings
Of what you have installed
Is
Only available when you're logged into your account
So you can't look to see
What you actually have installed on your
Computer in the software center unless
You have it logged in
That's people that have actually used it
Your complaints Rodden are all from complaints people
That have ever used it I think the first impression
It's also incredibly slow
That's what I'm aiming at
The search is incredibly awful
The search is absolutely terrible
The search is bad but hold on hold on
I'm asking this from the perspective of
Someone who's installing Ubuntu Mate
So someone who's installing Ubuntu Mate
They're going to be affected by the fact that this is missing
So those are people who are doing a clean install
Those are new users these are not people who've already
Got like hundreds of pounds spent
In the Ubuntu store so I'm saying from the perspective
Of someone who's experiencing
Ubuntu software center in
Something like Mate or any other desktop
For that matter what
Other than it being slow I appreciate it is slow
And I hear that quite a lot what
What else is wrong with the software
Center itself I'll tell you what
No I'll tell you the search actually
Moves itself based on different parts of
Where you are in the software center so if you actually
Do a search you go to a
You go to any of the
Items for the results you no longer
Have your search box you have to revert
Back to two previous pages
Before you find your search box again
Yeah that is awful
Here's what it is
And I think why I care is because
It's at a big picture
What the Linux desktop screws up
All the time it's like if we can't
Do it right let's not do it
At all because then it's just
Compared to what Mac and Windows
Is doing and so if we have
A software store it has
To be comparable to what
I understand it existed before the
Mac app store did and before the Windows 10
Software store did but now it also
Exists in a world where those things do exist
And where a lot of people are coming from
Yeah and so I feel like
It sort of personifies that
Poor knockoff
Sort of
Reputation that the commenters on Engadget
Give Ubuntu all the time
Chris let me put you this way
I tried to get my now
Ex-girlfriend and no it was not because
The Ubuntu software store
But it was close
I tried to get her to
Jump onto Ubuntu and
I'm like oh well just look on
Whatever they have because I'm used to all these other
Distributions and she's like no but this doesn't work
She's looking for something that
Could manage her photos better
And there's no
Alternatives to is so much
Better that's where I think
Yeah you do exist in this world where
The software other competing
Things exist and yeah
It should have been fixed two years ago but
I think the web version is better what were you going to say?
They actually have their own
They have a better version that's their website
Appstabuntu.com
I know but that's how much ships with
The OS
Well it doesn't matter you go to it
Regardless and they can put a link in the
Launcher that just opens that website
In a frame kind of thing
How about in a scope?
Yeah put it
Right up there in the dash
I made a video about ten months ago
Explaining why the USC versus
That website
Appstabuntu.com that is
Such a better solution
It was myself and Poppy and you
Rotten that were having a discussion a lot
Like this ten months ago that prompted
You to make that video
Because I had not heard of Appstabuntu.com
When we were
Oh yeah that's true
I like Appstabuntu.com
The problem is that that's not
Maintained either because you'll find that
It's not perfect
I haven't got entries for the current versions
Right it's not perfect but the search
Results work
If it was faster
Had better search results and didn't
Bother doing recommendations based on
Stuff it doesn't know about
You
It's just
I would rather it be able to scan what I
Already have rather than
Require me to create an account
Log into the account
Give them permission to see my install
So if it just looks at your existing
Packages on your machine
Without going off to the cloud or anything like that
Right it just streamlined it and made it simpler
And some people might
Go oh well I don't want them to see
What I have installed it's like well it's local
Anyway it doesn't matter it's only telling
You what it sees
Here's a couple things right here's the really
Depressing thing is this is the same
Commentary that Matt and I have made
On the Linux action show for the last couple of years
You guys had this conversation as recent as 10
Months ago and I think the reason why
Wimpy's story got so much traction is
Because it's now just gotten into the general
Ubuntu community's mind that the software center
Is a total train wreck and that's
Why that story picked up momentum is because
It's just a general shared consensus
Now and Poppy I love you but
Like I gotta say like
Chris is totally right I remember when this show was
Started that was when I started listening to it
We were still talking about it in my opinion
Just so you know whether you love me or hate me
Doesn't take away from the fact that
Software center sucks I can handle
Wimpy you are getting
Such a tiny
Percentage of the people that are following
This story commenting saying you shouldn't get rid
Of it because the amount of momentum
And distribution this story has got
Is so proportionally outweighing
The amount of comments you're getting about why it should
Be removed it's just really hard to see that
Until you've been through this cycle a few
Dozen times it's obvious just by the
By the sheer amount of momentum the story
Got that it is a shared consensus
By a lot of people it doesn't mean by everybody
But I'd say it's a majority
So
Poppy asked the question how
Would we I
Fix the Ubuntu software center
My answer to that is
Primarily I look to my immediate
Family and the close friends
Of mine that run Ubuntu Marte
That are not
Super technical computer users
They use it because it's familiar and they
Know how to get stuff done using it
They can use the Ubuntu
Software center just fine they're
They've been using some of them
Have been using Ubuntu for six
Years or more some have been using it
For a year 18 months
They see that as a perfectly
Usable tool so for them I
Don't need to change it but what you
Said Chris is absolutely right
The undercurrent of
Feeling about the Ubuntu software
Center is that it's not very
Good anymore and
You hear that enough times
And I'm in a position where
I can make a change hopefully for the better
So this change
I'm ushering in by removing Ubuntu
Software center as the default installed
App store is
Because people that
Are familiar with the Ubuntu community
And have been a part of it for a long time
Generally seem to have
This collective feeling that the Ubuntu software
Is not that great and it should
Be replaced with something better and what I'm
Providing is the choice
For those people to make
That decision so they can choose to stay
With the Ubuntu software center or
They can use app grid and potentially
A third way as well and we'll see if
That pans out in the future
It's giving the users the choice
And for those of you that aren't familiar with
Ubuntu mate welcome it
Pops up on
First login you've probably seen these
Welcome screens from other distributions
So the ability
To click the software button and
See this option to install an app
Store is right there in front of
Every new install every
New user on the system
So it's not tucked away or
Hidden it's front and center
I think that's a good compromise
I like it
And it is a compromise
But we'll see whether
It's a good decision or not and maybe
Maybe for beta 1 or beta 2 we have
A change of policy but you know
Ubuntu software centers future
Is maybe you should just keep
Alternating it like each
Release just like rip it out put it back
Hey what could go wrong
I know that Ubuntu mate
Is sort of a throwback to how Ubuntu
Used to be but I'm not going to swap out
Major applications every cycle
Remember you know rhythm box
In f-spot out you remember
How it was I'm not doing that
Oh lord