Breaking news, tweet coming into the show from Richard Brown, Chairman Richard Brown.
OpenSUSE has solved all of ButterFS's issues.
This started on a tweet thread coming at me, a tweet, I'm not going to be using ButterFS
on my system.
I've had some issues with it.
And OpenSUSE has responded with a blog post where Richard writes, ever wondered how to
manually set up ButterFS root file systems the same way we do in OpenSUSE?
For all of you other distributions that are getting ButterFS wrong, you're simply just
setting it up wrong.
Like the words of the deceased Steve Jobs, you're holding your ButterFS wrong.
And one of our listeners tweets back, I'm still concerned about file system issues,
free space issues.
I just don't think ButterFS has a place on production desktops.
Richard Brown responds.
Thank you for your feedback.
But those issues have been long addressed.
There you have it, everybody.
There you have it right now.
This is CNN Breaking News.
Live from OpenSUSE, confirmed all of ButterFS's issues have been resolved.
Format ZFS and install ButterFS.
Have at it, kids.
Can I imagine I jumped from OpenSUSE?
No, really, you are our OpenSUSE guy.
What are you talking about?
Now all we have is Gabriel.
You are our OpenSUSE guy, Eric.
Yeah, well, here's the thing.
It has problems with audio production.
Oh, really?
What kind of problems?
There's just not enough software availability.
Software fails to compile on it that would normally compile, like say on Fedora, which
is why I jumped to the Fedora Jam remix.
Oh, hold on, I think Mr. Payne's at the door.
Continue on.
I thought that the build service was a solution for that, though.
The build service is a solution for that, but the problem is getting the spec files
to go.
It just ended up being a hassle, whereas it was all available on Fedora already.
I don't have to go through that hassle.
I can just set up a system and boom, done.
Really?
All of a sudden, I have a Linux box able to help me with my audio production.
I'm going to check that out.
I got to say, if Fedora is easier, then it must be pretty bad over there.
It follows my old rule of shades of niche, and it goes a little something like this,
my friends.
The closer you are to Windows, the better time you're going to have as far as application
compatibility, support, performance, and reliability.
This is not an argument to run Windows because the platform is trash, but the closer you
are to Windows, the better your chances are going to be.
Now then your next step out, your next niche step out is Mac OS.
Mac OS, you could say the same thing, a little bit more application compatibility, but not
create as good as Windows.
More people writing software for the Mac, but not as much as Windows.
Then you go another step out, and that's Linux.
Really that's Ubuntu.
Ubuntu has the next, the third niche out is Ubuntu.
Now if you want to go a fourth step out, now you're looking at Fedora, you're looking
at Arch, you're looking at general Linux, and then there is yet another step out, and
that is OpenSUSE.
These weird Germans who have a very particular way of building things, they got to have their
own build system, they got to have their own boot splash, oh wait, no they don't, that's
dead.
And then there is yet a fifth dimension, and that is FreeBSD.
And that is really out on the fringes.
The least amount of desktop application compatibility, the least amount of industry desktop support,
and that's where you live on FreeBSD.
And you just got to pick which flavor of niche is right for you.
You know something, I did try Ubuntu Studio, and just raw Ubuntu, and it didn't hold a
candle to Fedora Jam.
Fedora Jam?
Yeah.
It didn't hold a candle.
You got to try it, Wes.
What do you think, Wes?
Fedora Jam.
Tasty jam.
I do like jam.
Yeah, me too.
Mmm, spread it all over.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 233 for January 23rd, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux podcast is downloading distros and preparing
for a canonical invasion.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Glad to have you back.
I hope you're feeling much better.
Much better.
Ready for Linux.
Yeah, well, we have a lot of Linux to get into, sir.
An old friend is back in the news.
The lady tube that is here to save us all, the lady tube that represents freedom, the
original lady tube is back with an update.
Then we'll get into a few, a smattering, a batch, a corner, if you will, of Ubuntu and
Gnome 3 news, as well as Firefox news, which damn, if it's not time to switch to Firefox
is definitely going to be after this week's episode, two, count them one, count them two
different app picks this week, including one that Wes found that's so damn cool, we almost
saved it for an entirely different show.
We'll tell you about that.
And then a critical tool that we use on this network, a lot of streamers use it, it's crushing
the proprietary competition, has gotten a major update this week.
We'll tell you about the new OBS Studio and why it may just wipe your bottom.
Stay tuned for that.
And then later on in the show, rumor has it, the Mate project just got a little bit better
looking and one of the original Linux news sources has been around for 20 years.
We'll celebrate 20 years of LWN at the end of the show and then we'll end it with a question.
Is native Linux app development in decline and why is that?
What caused the state of app development?
And I can tell you as somebody who used to do weekly app picks.
The answer is yes.
So we'll talk about that more.
But first we've got to bring in our virtual lug time appropriate greetings, mumble, rooooooooooooh.
Hello.
Oh, hi there.
Hey guys.
There's a lot of people.
Did you hear all those people?
I sure did.
That's a little weird.
This will be a good episode.
They're all just right there in my ears.
So we've all been wondering, what about Mycroft?
Right?
Haven't we all been kind of like, hey, what about Mycroft?
Yeah.
So obviously the solution is another crowd funder introducing mark two.
Mycroft has announced specs for a new voice assistant.
They've been building towards this.
They recently did a blog post about the lessons they learned from their previous crowd funders.
So they kind of been setting the groundwork for this.
And they've been sort of giving everybody a reminder of why open source is better for
privacy and it's better for these kinds of devices inherently.
And today they're announcing the new Mycroft mark two, which will be more like a speaker
tube, an upright standing tube that has a very large touch screen.
I believe it's touch screen on the front of it.
It's an informational screen.
So who wants to just get a whole jumble of words when you can get a display?
And they're going to be launching this on, I think it's called thunderclap, if I recall
it.
Yeah, thunderclap is where they're going.
And I think it's happening the Thursday of this recording.
So depending on when you're listening, it could be happening right now.
And it's a brand new version of Mycroft that is more competitive.
It's more in the line of the big, large super speaker that you're seeing with Apple's HomePod
and the Google Macs.
And it's also more in line with the Google show, or I'm sorry, the Echo show or the
Echo spot, which all have screens on them.
And then they have what they call hero cards that display information along with the verbal
request.
Mycroft, you're my hero.
What do you think, Wes, is this it?
Is this going to crack that nut?
It's at least further along the way.
It's if they can make it look that good.
I'm intrigued.
You know, really, of course, what it comes down to is like, what's the level of voice
interaction?
How painless is it?
And it can it meet, you know, what the other large vendors are doing that time will have
to tell.
If anybody in the Mumble Room has any thoughts at this stage, you're welcome to jump in.
And I see, JJ, you have something you thought might be worth mentioning.
Go ahead.
Yeah, I guess this sort of interest in me pursuing a little bit of open source, Linux
especially, I'm sort of interested in what Mycroft has to offer in terms of competition
and in terms of an alternative to the data sucking lady tubes that we know, well, thanks
for the term.
Lady tubes that we know such as Google and the credit Amazon word that I'm not supposed
to mention.
She who must not be named.
Don't trigger.
Yeah.
OK.
Beard, talk me down.
What do you think?
Or maybe you think maybe you'll agree with me.
I think desktop Linux, the year of desktop Linux has a better shot than this does as
a as a product.
I think that the Libra five has a better chance of selling five million devices than this
does as a product.
In other words, I think it's a long shot.
Can you walk me back from that position?
No, I agree.
Yeah.
OK.
Another another poignant argument.
What do you think, Wimby?
Can you walk me back from that argument?
Probably not.
What about the slow burn effect of open source?
What about that long, slow and steady approach?
So Microsoft released a video recently of it being adapted for use in a car.
And I imagine that that was some kind of prototype that they were doing as a proof of concept.
But maybe the success of Microsoft isn't consumer sales, but integration into other equipment
and devices.
Right.
That is definitely what I was thinking in the past.
And then this year, CES happened and Amazon's Echo is literally built into everything from
light switches to toilets, literally, microwave ovens, toaster ovens.
You know how we all joke about Linux running on toasters?
The Echo software is literally running on toasters now.
On user error this week, we're going to talk about a flex home that is a prefabbed home
that is everything built in is smart.
Every light, every blind, your heater, your water, everything is like one of these quote
unquote smart devices.
And the home just pre-ships with an Amazon Echo to control it all.
I think that ship sailed too, unfortunately.
Yeah, I think it is hard that they can't even just be as good as the competition.
They really need something to separate out.
And I don't think privacy is enough for a large enough audience.
On-premises support would be a pretty big product differentiator.
So if you could run the Mycroft service on-premises.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm-
Compatibility and patchability.
Yeah.
Part of me is so sort of bummed about it, but then part of me is like this idealistic,
hopeful person.
So the same part of me that really wants the Librem 5 to succeed, wants this to succeed.
All right, well, let's talk about how Didroxx is solely making me fall back in love with
Gnome and is helping bring rational discussion to what otherwise is just a bunch of clickbait.
Yeah, let's please.
So the new version of Gnome is Nye.
And of course, it'll be arriving in all of our favorite distributions soon.
And the big controversial change, which we've given some mention to, is the removal of desktop
icons.
So we're going to do a smattering of Gnome news here.
And we'll start with this, a smattering.
We did some smattering of plasma news last week.
Now it's a smattering of Gnome news this week.
So in 1804, you've probably heard by now that Canonical has made the choice to ship an older
version of Nautilus in their 1804 desktop.
The number one comment I've seen is, and I quote, oh, here we go again.
I can't even believe how many times I've seen.
Oh, here we go again.
Here goes Canonical, crazy ass Canonical, not happy with the upstream Gnome arrogance.
And so they're running off and forking their Gnome desktop all over again.
This has been the common response to the announcement that Canonical would simply be shipping one
version behind of the file manager.
So what's going on here?
Why is Gnome dropping icons?
Is it because they hate users?
Or is there something else more sophisticated and complex happening?
And Didrocks just has this great post that really kind of explains it all.
And Didrocks is a great sort of nonpartisan position to cover this because he's been maintaining
code as part of Unity for years that dealt with this very code path.
So he has hands-on experience with the very feature that's being deprecated.
And he's the guy that for some reason, which we'll get to, is going through all the hassle
of backboarding the old version of files to Ubuntu.
So how did we get here?
And why is Gnome removing icons off of the desktop at the very time when Plasma is switching
to icons on the desktop by default?
How did we get here?
What?
What happened?
Well, you've got to understand the background.
There has been a lot of discussion for years about these icons on the desktop.
So they're not really put there by Gnome 3 Shell.
They're put there by the Nautilus file manager.
And they use this really interesting X layering to be on the bottom layer.
But it's this really weird thing that Didrocks goes into more in his blog post.
But it's making me shiver just right now.
It is one of those moments where you realize this has been kind of this hacky thing that
they've been dragging along for like three years that they've been trying to come up
with a way to kill this feature.
And it has been a controversial discussion for over three years.
And it has been also one of these features that they have been openly discussing.
You can find a recent blog post on Planet Gnome back in December where they sort of
outline their thinking on all of this and why this might be coming.
And on top of that, by reading this post, you discover that the Gnome folks also gave
a heads up to Didrocks and said, hey, we're thinking about making this change.
What do you guys think?
And it did put Canonical in a bit of an awkward position because they kind of were left with
three sort of mediocre choices.
They could stick with Nautilus 3.26, the current version, and keep icon support.
They could ship Nautilus 328 and also ship Nemo desktop to support desktop icons.
But then they're shipping one file manager and part of Nemo, which is a fork of that
file manager.
Or they could ship Nautilus 328 and use a brand new extension that's in the works to
draw the icons on the desktop.
The issue there being that the mechanism that that extension uses isn't even finalized
in GTK yet.
And it hasn't been tested.
Ooh, on an LTS.
And Canonical shipping an LTS.
Exactly.
So they're in a position where we've got to ship an LTS.
We want to do the most rational thing.
And we don't want to remove icons on the desktop that's going to be around for five years.
And so when you stack all the bad choices up, the best choice is to just ship Nautilus
3.26.
And that was also the suggestion of the GNOME project.
Is that right?
Which is an interesting point.
And to that end, didrocks includes sort of like a sub blog from one of the GNOME developers
explaining the rationale on this.
And anytime you can kind of reduce variabilities, then it's easier to test those code paths.
It's easier to ensure reliability.
And whenever you start forking big things, like say they were bringing on Nautilus 328
and also that GNOME Shell extension, those are all new things that they would have to
be testing against, which would probably not be a good idea for the LTS.
But I guess the long term answer, if you want icons, is this extension that they're working
on.
So there's hope yet for you desktop lovers out there.
I guess.
The whole post is a fascinating read because didrocks goes into how he got this working
on Unity over the years and some of the little tricks that he did to position the icons correctly
to sort of sense where they should be.
And you really, reading it between the lines, the message I get is, man, X11 is just a big
cluster.
I hate touching this.
It's really a mess.
And then it's like, oh, yeah, that's why we got to go to Wayland.
Some of the stuff you read, you go, oh, geez, God, that's, yeah, get rid of the icons.
I can't believe they're doing that hack to show my icons on the desktop.
Oh, and by the way, this code path hasn't been maintained for, I mean, it's been maintained,
but it really hasn't been modified for like three years.
It's just time to go.
And you know what?
I got to say this post by didrocks changed my position on this.
I was a little skeptical, like, oh, really guys?
You just, it's like you just constantly are shooting down work.
But then going through this, it's like, oh, they just, why was it implemented via Nautilus
in the first place?
Why isn't just a fundamental function of gnome shell?
And that because Nautilus was the shell, you know, previously in gnome 2, Nautilus was
the shell in the same way that today in Marte, Kaja is the shell.
And Kaja has the option to.
Go ahead Kaja.
It's far more useful where it would be.
So what do you say?
So heavens, your argument is, is yeah, but now Nautilus is less useful and Kaja and Nemo
are more useful.
Well, when you're running a program, what screen space is being used, it kind of overwrites
the desktop.
The dock can only slide out and be visible whenever you want it to be or always visible.
That's more persistent than a desktop icon.
Yeah, fair enough.
Wimpy sitting there with a Mate desktop in front of you right now.
What are your thoughts on this on this fundamental discussion of the code path to maintain desktop
icons is antiquated.
It's not maintained, it's sort of been a hack for a long time, and it's an X11 hack on top
of that.
But yet it's a feature users want who I'd be curious to know what your thinking is on
this.
Yeah, I mean, I'd agree with all of the comments about it being, you know, legacy code and
what have you.
We've, we've really struggled to maintain all of the desktop interaction features that
exist within Mate and Kaja as we've migrated to GTK 3.
And it's hard work, and there are things that could be improved, and that's even harder
to resolve.
I think one of the fallouts of this is that longer term, you know, these APIs to do this
are deprecated now, and they're going to be going away in GTK 4.
So the likes of the Mate desktop and XFCE and the others that are doing the traditional
desktop metaphor, because after all, you can't call it a desktop if it doesn't have any icons
on it anymore, because the metaphor is broken at that point.
So it's just, you know, a shell, you know, you can't claim it a desktop because it isn't.
But one of the things we've been discussing in the Mate project is perhaps we need to
create a library lib desktop, which is a whole cloth implementation in order to broker this
kind of, you know, interaction if that's the route that we decide to go.
Whilst we're on GTK 3, we can stay the course with the improvements that we've made.
But when GTK 4 comes along, we'll have to review, you know, what our plans are.
Wow.
Wow, that is a lot for me to take in.
So the possibility of having to implement your own desktop, something that feels like
it should be a first class baked in citizen of the core desktop experience, if that's
something you want, that's a really, that's a tough road to hoe.
And I have to say, on systems where I have desktop icons, I just make a mess.
I just make a mess.
Yeah, I don't have any systems that have them anymore.
Really?
And then systems where I don't have them, I just make a folder structure that's also
been a mess.
But it's a folder structure within my home directory.
I just, it's weird because I'm working on this project where most of our users are really
interested in keeping that desktop.
You know, if you look at a lot of Marte users desktop, it's just full of icons.
Now I've never done that.
I have a directory I create in my home directory called cruft and anything transient just ends
up in there and periodically I have to go through and sort it out.
A lot of people use their desktop as that space for cruft.
So personally, I wouldn't miss icons on the desktop because that isn't part of my workflow.
The problem is, is we have to be mindful of the workflow of all of our users and a significant
number of them value that feature because it's in their muscle memory.
That's how they've been doing it for years and years.
You know, my mom, who is a graphic artist on the computer, she very much uses the drag
and drop paradigm.
So she'll drag an image from an application to the desktop and from her desktop to another
application.
And the desktop is sort of like this intermediary holding bin where she can then drag it to
another icon on her dock.
I mean, it seems like for some users, the desktop is how they interface with the computer,
right?
That's how they conceptualize it.
Right.
To not have icons that they have on the other platforms.
Yeah.
And then for me, it's like, I'll use it if I have it and it's always a mess.
And then I, if I don't have it, I just make, I make like a cruft folder like Wimpy does.
Although I don't have such a clever name for it.
I'm going to, I'm going to start using that.
I'm going to steal that.
Speaking of stealing, Gnome Photos is stealing a few features from Darktable and I'm all
about it.
I think this is a great idea.
Talk about a nice open source Kumbaya.
This is not a huge story, but Gnome Photos in the next version is getting nice.
And while we're talking about new Gnome stuff, why not?
They're implementing shadows and highlights from Darktable into Gnome Photos.
Oh, that's awesome.
Isn't that great?
Yeah.
It's just a super, super great idea.
New crop features, new scaling features, new easy way to kind of get like a grid on there
when you're trying to get a nice photo.
Basically what I'm telling you is if you just need a nice program to sort photos and make
them a little bit better, maybe increase exposure, contrast, highlights, and crop them a little
bit, you know, that you shot on your phone, this is it.
It's getting there now.
And Gnome Photos is making steady progress.
So I'm excited to see that progress.
It's really kind of getting to that point where I don't need much more than a file manager.
So this is just about it.
Those final touches, you know, before I consider it done.
And then last but not least, while we're in the Gnome news segment, Firefox is, so 58
is next.
Firefox 58 will be out on tomorrow if all goes as planned, I think.
Yeah.
No, today even.
Is it out today?
I can't remember if it's out today or tomorrow.
Looks like they're planning to put it in the release channel today.
Okay.
Yeah.
So it's coming out.
So new version of Firefox is coming out.
Now that's not specifically Gnome, but I guess while we're talking about it, I'll tell you
what's new is a whole new way of handling user profiles, which means it's going to do
a user profile migration and it will, your user profile will not be compatible with older
versions of Firefox.
So heads up if you use portable Firefox or somebody get on the phone with Joe Ressington.
There's also the improvements to the web extensions API and they're making some claims with hard
numbers about performance.
They say they have improved off main thread painting in Firefox and that the rendering
time is improved noticeably, 30% improvement for Firefox 58 when compared to Firefox 57
and JavaScript bytecode cache is reduced by quite a bit from like having to start when
you start navigation to the when the event is fired via JavaScript, there has been on
average a 43 millisecond reduction.
They're actually giving out a hard number there, 43 millisecond reduction in Firefox
58 as well as improvements to the screenshotting tool, which I've actually begun using a bit
more.
Some fixes for audio playback on those windows desktops, not familiar with that, that sounds
like something that's in my house and as well as other nice things.
But that's Firefox 58, which comes out like about now.
That's interesting.
Hit download right now.
58 go get it.
Really?
Yeah.
Go get it guys.
Everybody go.
I'm getting it right now.
But that isn't Gnome related.
What is Gnome related?
It's Firefox 59.
Always looking at the next version, aren't we?
We're always looking.
Oh yeah.
And if you follow the bug tracker, it looks like all of the blocking bugs to convert Firefox
to GTK 3 and GTK 3 only have been cleared.
All of the blocking bugs have been cleared.
And with that marked now as resolved, the migration to move Firefox to GTK 3 has been
marked as completed.
And if all lines up, Firefox 59 will be the first version of Firefox that is solely 100%
GTK 3, which I believe leaves GIMP as the last Gnome application, the major Gnome application,
big Gnome application that has not moved to GTK 3.
Ironic considering that GIMP is the father of the GTK toolkit.
Right?
It is, isn't it?
It is.
But it also strikes me as if you're a Linux user, Firefox is currently catering to you
right now.
Both 58 and 59 have a lot of nice improvements that are specific to Linux users.
It's never been a better time to be a Firefox user.
I'm really looking forward to these new profiles.
I'm hoping that that could be...
It's really difficult to get unwedded from the profiles in Chrome and Chromium, and I'm
hoping that this is gonna be it.
Yeah.
I hope so too.
I am waiting with anticipation.
I'm all in now on Firefox.
The computer I'm sitting at right now is my last computer using Chrome.
And I think it's just mostly because of workflow on air, but that could even get changed soon
too.
That's just so great.
It's so great and it's so nice to have them, at least to me...
Firefox reticules.
Yeah.
It feels like they're back in a way and that they're focusing on Linux users and GTK 3
means we're probably gonna see all kinds of cool stuff.
It's also just nice to have some more, I mean, we're in an era kind of right now with that
and with Brave and other browsers that there's a lot more competition going on and hopefully
that's good for us.
Mm-hmm.
It does seem to be.
Speaking of competition, Ting is bringing the competition to the mobile market in a
huge, huge way.
It's just pay for what you use wireless.
That's...
Oh, man.
That would just totally...
If the wireless industry had to restart today, had to restart right now, say right this moment,
Ting would run the table.
You just pay for what you use, a fair price for how much you talk, text and data you use.
And it's just $6 for your line.
You want one line, it's $6.
You want two lines, it's $12.
You see what I'm saying here?
Uncle Sam takes his tax, you know, in your local area like he do, Wes.
We sure do.
He do.
He takes that cut.
But then you just pay for what you use, nationwide coverage, no contracts, no quote-unquote agreements,
and a dashboard for days.
One of my favorite things about Ting is their GSM and CDMA network.
Why do I like that?
Because when I'm traveling, I pick whichever one works better for me.
And even realistically, in different spots in Washington, there's just sometimes I'm
in a terrain with the trees and the hills where CDMA works better.
And sometimes I'm in a place where GSM just totally rocks.
Like here at the studio, I'm always on the GSM network.
And I love the flexibility because I have a couple of different MiFi devices, and at
just $6 a month, it's no big deal if I don't use Ting that much that month on that particular
MiFi.
That's a really flexible way to work.
Plus, during Linux Fest Northwest, we'll spin up an extra couple of lines, hand out some
cheapo phones, and stay in contact.
It's great for small businesses.
The average Ting bill is just $23 per phone per month.
Linux.ting.com is where you go.
Linux.ting.com.
Go there, take $25 off a phone, or bring a device and get $25 in service credit.
So I'm a big fan of different launchers.
I've tried Synapse throughout the years.
I've tried Noom Do.
I've been using the launcher built into Unity quite a bit.
Wimpy was recently talking to me about some different launchers on Mate with Brisk, got
my interest peaked there.
So I just wanted to give a shout out to an application launcher for Linux that I've come
across recently that's scratching that itch.
It's fast.
It works sort of like all typical launchers do work.
It's pretty quick.
It supports fuzzy search.
It has shortcuts and different extensions that you can load.
It can also browse directories, which is pretty nice for me because I have scripts in a bin
directory, in my home directory, so I can do tilde slash bin in the name of the script
and it just executes it.
It does, you know, like rough math in the launcher.
It's great.
It's called...
It's even got emoji support.
Look at that.
I know.
That's how you know it's modern, right?
It's called uLauncher at uLauncher.io.
And it's wonderful.
It's great.
It's fast.
And it loads pretty easily.
And once you put it on your system, you can use that to start up all the damn applications.
They got an AUR available.
They got a Fedora package available.
They got a SUSE package available.
And they got a PPA for Ubuntu, which is pretty great.
And the project's...
It's kind of new.
It's up on Patreon.
They're taking that as well as Bitcoin, but they also have the extension plugin, which
is great.
So you can, speaking of Bitcoin, have a Bitcoin plugin type BTC in the launcher and it comes
back with the price or can do Bitcoin conversions for you in your launcher.
Welcome to 2018, right?
There's a key pass plugin.
Really?
Mm-hmm.
I'll just say that.
There's a key pass plugin.
There's an open in browser.
So you can say hgoogle.com and it'll launch in the right browser.
It'll support your Chrome bookmarks or your Firefox bookmark.
It supports logging out of the desktop if you want.
So they got some specific extensions for Cinnamon.
And one thing that's actually pretty handy that I think I'm gonna load this on my lady's
computer for is it has a timer built in, which she uses a lot for work.
Like, set a timer for 15 minutes.
That's great.
And it's just built right in the launcher, I mean, once you install the extension.
So anyways, this is one of my favorite finds recently.
I don't think we've talked about it before.
Boy is it great.
uLauncher.io and it's probably in your local repo right there.
Wimpy, did you want to give any mention for the Brisk launcher stuff that you and I were
chatting about recently off air?
Yeah, sure.
So there is a new feature coming in the next version of Brisk menu, which enables you to
change the way that it's displayed to present a dash style launcher rather than the pop
down menu.
So we're running a patched version of that in our dev branch for Ubuntu Mate at the moment.
And when you enable the mutiny layout now on Ubuntu Mate 1804, it tweaks the various
magic settings.
So then when you hit the super key, you get this dash, which is full screen, large icons,
text search, category buttons to touch, and the whole thing is touch capable.
So that will be landing in Ubuntu Mate 1804, which is good because it's one of those little
details that I knew we would get to and I knew everyone would point out was missing
in 17.10 and they did.
Now it's in there for the 1804.
That's great.
Yeah, it's getting there.
Yeah.
Got one bug to fix and then that's good to go.
I love Brisk as it's a great project.
So really cool to see that.
Yeah.
And that was another great collaboration, you know, with the Brisk team.
There's a developer in Solus called Stefan and we offered a bounty for the work and he
did the work and Ubuntu Mate funded it.
So that's really great.
That is.
So there's this next application I wanted to feature today.
Wes found it.
He almost sat on it just to talk about it exclusively in the new TechSnap program because
that's where all our best stuff is now.
I'm kidding.
But I did really enjoy last week's episode.
That was good.
Wes gave us an introduction to configuration management.
And this application is an advanced user interface to manage...
It's like a dashboard really.
To manage...
You know how we love dashboards here in the Linux Unplugged program?
Dashboards for days.
Days!
It's the advanced dashboard for quick managing and inspecting of containers and images for
Docker.
And it's all on the command line.
It's totally Ncurses based, which is the part I love about it.
Because like when you say dashboard, you're probably thinking like a web page.
Sure.
Ha!
Got you.
No, it is an Ncurses application.
It shows you you're running...
It shows you you're running Docker containers, your overall system utilization.
Picture it.
Sicily 1987.
You SSH into your server.
You bring this up and you have a full overview of everything that's going on.
I can't tell you how useful this is going to be for me on my DigitalOcean droplets.
Yeah.
It seems like something that will find its way to Tmux session near me.
Exactly.
It's exactly what I'm going to do with it.
And I have been experimenting with different click and run type setups for Docker.
Just totally like...
I forget what the...
I covered it in Coder Radio months ago, but there is an application...
I think I might've talked about it in this show too, that will search the Docker directory,
pull it down, set it all up, and you just click that one thing.
Oh yeah.
This is sort of more like inspecting the existing Docker stuff that you have set up.
It doesn't quite do that part of it.
But it's...
I don't know.
There's something broken about me about Ncurses user interfaces.
When they're done right, I will take an Ncurses user interface in my terminal over a really
well done graphical interface any day of the week.
Same.
Yeah.
Even if I'm on graphical desktop, I'll just run it in a terminal window.
I just prefer the flexibility.
I can reshape them to the size I want.
There's lots of context switching too.
Even though I have a web browser open, I have to go shift my attention.
And then this last one here for this week is something that the beard slotted in at
the last minute.
It's the new version of OBS Studio, OBS Studios, I like to say.
version 21 is out and it's huge.
It is...
If I was Telestream and I was making the Wirecast product, I would be extremely nervous about
this little ankle biter called OBS Studio.
It's extremely competitive now and they've just introduced Lua and Python scripting support,
which the ramifications of that are going to be huge because you can set up control
devices and you're going to be able to set off entire actions now with this.
And the fact that they're supporting both Lua and Python is pretty great.
They've included some examples like countdowns and all this kind of stuff.
But in the background now, they're getting to the point where they're adding really high
end professional, like I used to pay $2,000 to get access to these kinds of features.
They're adding 7.1 surround sound support.
They're adding higher bit rate support.
They've revamped the audio meters so that way they break out individual sources and
microphones.
They're also supporting microphone multi-sources.
It's really professional grade.
What do you think, Beard?
Is there one feature on this list that we really need to have?
It's almost to be worth the hassle of upgrading the Archbox?
I think that you would mostly like the side chain ducking.
Oh yeah?
Yeah.
That basically allows you to automatically lower the level of one input based on the
level of another input.
Yeah.
And you can see how that would be useful for like audio clips or maybe even the Mumble
Room.
That's how they do it in radio, right?
The caller automatically gets ducked when the host starts speaking.
It's nice.
I had been staring at the OBS interface now for a year because it's how we record all
our shows and how we live stream.
So this is a really critical piece of software for us.
And I've been wondering how they're going to improve the audio meter interface.
I don't know if I love this, but it's better than what I expected.
Here's the feature I'm actually the most interested in.
The preview mode now.
So in the studio, we have a dedicated 1080p monitor that is just a preview output from
OBS.
Wes and I look at it all the time.
All the time.
It shows us whatever's on the live stream on a dedicated monitor.
It's extremely useful.
Yes, absolutely.
And now they're adding the ability to have eight scenes on that screen ahead of time.
So I can have all of the shots, like a director's room, all of the shots on that screen.
And then I know which one to go to.
Well, you and I have some ideas about where to take this show post 250 that involve multi
camera setups and you'd be on camera, I'd have a camera, we'd have a screen camera.
They're adding the very features we might just need to take the show to the next level.
Multi-track recording, multi-camera preview.
This is the kind of thing where this free open source project is coming along and adding
stuff that costs tens of thousands of dollars all told, and they're just doing it for free.
And at the same time, we have these ambitions and goals where we want to go with the network
and with the show specifically, and it's just lining up perfectly.
So it's pretty exciting.
There's other things that I really appreciate in here, and I hope I'm not going too far
off in the weeds, but having managed these systems for like a decade, there's like a
couple-
It's pretty important to day-to-day operations.
There's just like a few little things too that have bugged me for so long.
Per scene transition overrides, which allow you to select a specific transition to use
for a specific scene.
Sometimes I want a slow fade, sometimes I want a hard cut.
That sounds like a small thing, but when I want it, I really want it and I want it how
I want it because it's really important.
If I'm transitioning to like our standby screen, I like a nice slow fade out.
If I'm transitioning from this to our chat room, I want a quicker fade, and it actually
kind of bothers me right now.
I can't quite get what I want.
It's not quite there.
It's driven me crazy, and they're fixing that.
They've also bumped up the developer documentation, made some fixes for those of you that are
stuck on Windows and Mac OS, like now they're using a dark theme.
I didn't realize that Mac and Windows users didn't have a dark theme because if we're
using a GTK, everything's dark and we have everything set to dark on our GNOME desktop,
so it's always been dark.
Oh, no, no.
They already had a dark theme.
They just added a new theme in addition to that one.
And now it's default, right?
And they've also changed the default too, which I just didn't realize that OBS had themes
because it's always just matched whatever my GTK theme is.
There's also one small like little audio bug fix for audio monitoring on Linux and some
fixes for AMD users with AMD GPUs.
Go ahead.
Oh, just one last thing.
They've reduced that.
I was telling you about the preview pane, the 8 preview pane.
They've reduced the CPU usage by about 8% on that, which is pretty significant.
Anyways, Barret, go ahead.
I think you're actually going to love the new audio meters.
This is probably the best implementation of an audio meter I've seen in any program ever.
Yeah, it is nice, and they have different options for like monitoring the peaks and
keeping track of them.
Yes.
And I would say that's an area where they've been particularly weak in the past.
I'm going to talk about it on User Air 43.
So tune into this week's User Air that will come out later in this week.
I have a new podcast studio I'm building, and it's going to be tighter, and it's going
to be more confined than ever.
And so the fact that OBS is doing more might make it a good candidate for that setup, and
I'll talk about that in the near future.
But that's a good batch of open source updates this week.
A really solid launcher, a great update on OBS, the Mate desktop is getting better than
ever.
Wimpy, are you up for talking a little more about some of the things in Mate, some of
the other things we talked about?
Yep.
Can do that.
All right.
Hold on to that.
We'll do that soon.
There's some other really good stuff coming, as well as 20 years of LWN and why I really
believe they're doing journalism right.
And then we got to talk about that application problem.
Everything's Electron.
It's all Electron these days, and we've talked about that before.
But there's another shift.
And darn if Joey over at OMG Ubuntu didn't just put it into perfect terms.
So we'll talk about that as well.
Lots more to come up.
So let's take a moment and thank DigitalOcean for sponsoring this week's episode of the
Unplugged program.
Go to DigitalOcean, create an account, start up, and then use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Deploy entire application stacks or just machines in less than 55 seconds.
Everything is SSD-based.
If you're doing something that's $5 a month all the way up to the systems that have hundreds
of gigs of RAM and lots of CPU and tons of transfer, they're all secure and reliable.
They have built-in, baked-in monitoring and metrics right into the system.
They've got load balancing as a service.
And then you'll also notice, and sometimes it's not even self-evident, but you'll also
notice like firewall features.
Oh, that seems like a good idea, except for their DigitalOcean firewalls, their quote-unquote
cloud firewalls.
What makes it a cloud firewall?
You don't have to touch IP tables.
It's at the network level, too.
Yeah, also that part.
Both of those things.
That's not what I'm excited about.
No kidding, right?
There's two different things there that are really great.
They're both true.
They set it up at the network level so it never even hits the machine.
That's the number one thing I like.
And the number two thing is you don't got to screw around with IP tables.
You can deploy an entire stack or just the base system.
We were just recently playing around with a new way to do VoIP communications where
you have this one central server that sort of proxies the connection.
And once the connections are set up, it's a WebRTC direct point-to-point.
I didn't need a very fast server.
So in about a minute, I spun up the $5 a month droplet, which with their new pricing is better
than ever.
And if you use our promo code, you could try it out two months for free.
I was able to try it out, see if this thing worked right, and then I destroyed the droplet
10 minutes later.
This kind of flexible aspect of DigitalOcean means that sometimes I use a machine for half
a day, and sometimes a machine has been in production for four years.
My oldest box is an Arch machine on DigitalOcean that's over four years old, and I still use
it to this day.
They have great reliability, great performance, and great pricing.
Go to DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, get started, create your account,
and see what's possible.
And then when you're ready to go to the next level, they have fantastic documentation,
a straightforward API, and lots of open source code built around the DigitalOcean infrastructure.
DigitalOcean.com, and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the show, and thanks to you
guys for continuing to use that promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
It keeps this show going, and by goodness, we may just make it to episode 250, and maybe
even 300, because you guys keep supporting our sponsors.
DigitalOcean.com, promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
You know, Wimpy, I was looking back at the Linux Unplugged Archive, and if you fast forward
just a couple of weeks, it was almost a year ago that you and I were talking about you
loading up Ubuntu Mate on your XPS 15 and getting high DPI support.
In fact, I even found the post that I used during the show to show on the live stream
while you and I were talking about this.
So the fact that today you and I were having a conversation where even more is happening
really shows how you've been like a dog with a bone on this particular issue.
Yes, although I have little credit to claim in this story, but the news is today we've
landed the last of the patches to fully implement high DPI support in the Maltay desktop.
And yeah, I've been-
Thank you, God.
I'm sorry to interrupt you, Wimpy, but I have been trying like crazy to get Maltay working
on a Macbook 15 inch from 2013.
It is a high DPI display as well, and I swear I am so thankful for you guys to do that because
I got to tell you, I have been wanting to try out Mate on my Mac, and I got to be honest,
OS X is just killing me to the core.
With the DPI support, yeah.
It's just way better.
I mean, every desktop I've tried, XFC, Stock Gnome, everything, it was just a freaking
nightmare.
Maltay got close, and I tried it on a few, and it definitely was usable, but it felt
like there was a pretty big gap.
Yes, the screen size, yeah, because I tell you, the Mac has a beautiful right now display,
but Mac OS is just going to be a pitter because I hate it, and I have wanted to just dump
this thing for months, but I couldn't find the right desktop to do it for Linux, and
I love Mate, I love Gnome 2's interface, but Maltay being more modern, and I would love
to run Mate on a Mac, but hopefully this will fix that niche.
So what's going on, Moby?
So the changes that have landed are to really smooth those rough edges that you would have
seen.
I put some patches in about four or five months ago that kind of helped make it work a little
bit better, but frankly, it wasn't finished.
But there's a guy in the community, Victor, his name is, we found him through Solus.
He actually did the work on the super key and modify key capabilities in Maltay and
Brisk and a bunch of other places that made all of that super key and HUD stuff work,
you know, that you can use those keys as actions now.
And I approached him a little while ago and said, did he fancy, you know, tackling the
last of the issues with high DPI?
And he dumped a load of patches last night, and I've been testing them this evening, and
we are dangerously, dangerously close now to having a really good implementation of
high DPI.
So now that, so that I fully understand, I mean, what was missing from the high DPI support
as it stands now?
So previously, for example, the panel, you know, the little panels at the top and the
side, I got those so they actually fitted to the screen, but we were having to force
those to use one to one scaling to actually appear on the screen in the right place, which
meant that they appeared in the right place and the things that were in them were rendered
correctly, but if you right clicked on the context menus, they were all absolutely minuscule.
And the same was true for the window manager, and a bunch of other places where things just
weren't right.
And things like when you sized the panels, when you change the size, before that was
literally happening one pixel at a time, and although you're going up in increments that
look like you're adjusting it to 23, 24, 25 pixels behind the scenes, maths is happening,
and it's actually adjusting that scale for the high DPI screen.
So the big changes is that before you used to have to go and configure a bunch of different
things in about seven different places in order to enable this, and it wasn't quite
right.
Now, there's a single option, it's in Marte tweak, it's under high DPI, enable high DPI,
you tick that box, you log out, log in, and everything is then high DPI enabled.
Well shoot, that is a big improvement.
It sure is.
That's no small thing there.
What does it look like from a user standpoint?
What am I going to do now to get this?
Well from Ubuntu Marte's point of view, this is going to be in 1804, and I'm hoping we
may be able to squeeze a preview in for Alpha 2.
There may be a couple of rough edges there, but it's very, very close now, but hopefully
get that in for Alpha 2.
For Marte itself, Marte desktop, we're very close to releasing Marte 1.20, and I'm trying
to work as fast as possible in the evenings to test and figure out where the remaining
issues are on this to try and land this in time for Marte 1.20, so that it's actually
a feature of Marte 1.20.
That would be wonderful.
So I guess the part I'm still not totally clear on is, so if I go into Marte Tweak and
I turn this on, am I at that same time also switching out from Marco?
Is that not an issue as well with high DPI support?
Right, so at the moment that is happening, yes.
So at the moment when you enable high DPI, it also turns on Compiz as the window manager.
So that's where we get the scaling of the window controls from, because we haven't actually
done that work in Marco yet.
But Compiz has.
Compiz has done that work.
But Compiz has done that for a long, long time.
So we can cut some corners in Ubuntu Marte by utilizing Compiz, and that's a fair assumption
because the set of people that have UHD displays and a computer not capable of running Compiz
is zero.
Yeah.
No kidding.
It actually would be something I would almost want to turn on anyways if I was using it.
So this is really, really close.
But I know from our discussion, it seems like the piece that might still be missing is auto
detection of the high DPI display.
That's still a tougher nut to crack.
It's not a tough nut to crack.
It's just like choosing your battles, and we've decided to just get the thing working,
and then we can revisit how that's handled in terms of dynamically detecting that you
are on a high DPI display.
It's halfway there.
The Greta determines if you're on a high DPI display and auto scales.
Then you log in, and you get an unscaled desktop, and you have to go and press a button.
So it's not perfect, but it's way, way better than this.
Can I ask you a crazy question?
Sure.
And this is probably the wrong place to do it, but what about as sort of a front and
center option in the Amate welcome screen, where it says-
Yeah.
Absolutely.
You're already thinking that?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
I think we can do the detection in welcome very quickly, as in implement it very quickly,
and detect that and actually present that as a, we see you've got a high resolution
screen which you'd like to enable high DPI, and then have that flip switched automatically,
and then they can log out, log back in, so it will smooth the edges.
So that could be the route.
That could be the route you end up taking.
Yes, it's an option.
The option to actually do this dynamically is still not off the table.
It's all a matter of time.
We've got to choose what we can do in the time remaining, and at the moment, there are
some other little rough edges that are more important than one fix.
You know, today on Marks PS15, I've been running Ubuntu Marte with scaling.
I opened every shipped by default application widget and window, and everything is scaled,
including things like Qt applications.
So we're passing through all the necessary scaling information from our environment to
the Qt application.
So for example, VLC is all nicely scaled, which is a Qt application that we ship by
default.
And then you install Electron applications, and we push all that information through to
Electron as well.
So they're all scaled appropriately.
Shoot.
This is like full grown, all grown up, real high DPI support here.
And those of you that are familiar with GNOME 2 or Marte will or may remember that in the
appearance control panel, there was a fonts tab.
And one of the things you could do in the fonts tab was change the DPI of the fonts.
And that was like the OG, you know, high DPI option.
You turn that up, yeah.
So that was that was how it used to be in the good old battle days.
Now, originally, I envisaged that we would just lose that feature and that we would do
the font scaling, you know, bound to the integer scaling of the screen.
But Victor has retained that.
And this has a really nice side effect in that we're keeping the font scaling separated
and it automatically adjusts the font scaling.
And when that happens for GTK2 applications, which have no high DPI scaling support whatsoever,
other than the font scaling, they get a font scale that is accurate to the screen.
So while GTK2 applications aren't going to look great, by default, they look the best
they can be on a high DPI display by bumping those fonts out to the right sizes.
Wow.
Is any other desktop doing that?
I don't know.
I haven't looked that carefully because I don't know how many of them had or retained
that feature to adjust the font DPI.
That is great.
It's going to be the premier GIMP workstation.
You can get icon sets for GIMP, which are like oversized.
And when they're on high DPI, it actually makes GIMP usable.
This is so cool, Wimpy, and you know, it has to be mentioned that this was the butt of
so many jokes.
Oh, you're going to take that Gnome 2 thing, that old busted paradigm, which for those
of us who loved it, like myself, was an insult because it was passing judgment on how I like
to use computers.
Somebody was telling me, a lot of somebodies were telling me, that the way I like to use
computers was old, and it was part of a bygone era, and that the future was touch, the future
was mobile, the future was a total redesign of the desktop paradigm.
And then this crazy ass Mate project came along and forked GTK2-based Gnome 2 and was
this total stick in the mud, not going to go anywhere desktop.
Look at this.
This is the butt of all jokes here of desktop Linux.
And fast forward to frickin' 2018, and it sounds like one of the most complete high
DPI implementations that, I mean, it's just, there's few other desktops, really.
There's Gnome 3, the Pantheon desktop, even Plasma, well, yeah, I mean, as somebody who
used the most current Plasma on a high DPI display, it takes two or three or four settings
changes to get it accurate, to get it right.
Oh, right, okay.
Yeah.
I wouldn't know, but that's interesting to hear.
I think you're in the lead there.
I mean, you're not elementary OS and maybe not Gnome 3, but you're pretty damn close
now.
And this is supposed to be the joke desktop, don't you know that?
I had heard, yeah.
I think this is probably something that the other desktop environment developers can learn
from.
Yeah.
Real quick question though.
Go ahead.
So would this lead to any sort of feature toward a window management as in like having
four, like a quadrant style windows in some way, shape or form?
Interesting that you should ask that question.
So one of the other features of Marco, the default window manager for Mate is that we've
fully implemented quadrant and top and bottom panel tiling that has actually been there
for a long, long time, but it was only activateable through key bindings.
But now if you drag to the corners and the tops and the bottoms, it will snap to those
locations and not just do side by side tiling now.
So that's in.
That's nice.
Yeah.
And GLX acceleration for Marco.
And I'm hoping there's another couple of patches for Kaja that make that a bit more interesting
as well.
Oh, how so?
But, well, I'm looking at trying to land tracker support for Mate 120.
For search?
Yeah.
For desktop search.
Because at the moment that's the old, old desktop search and it's slow.
And there are the tracker implementation is much improved in recent years, so that's looking
quite interesting.
Is that what files, is that what files uses?
Yes.
It does.
Okay.
That's all.
And then other changes that we've made in Ubuntu Mate just over the weekend is that
indicators are now enabled by default in all layouts.
So it's indicators all the way.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
And that's, there's another project I'll speak about another day because I don't want to
go on too long, that dovetails with that.
And then the other change we've made in the traditional layout.
So this is the OG GNOME 2 panel layout.
One change we've made is if you remember, it's applications places system.
It now reads menu places system and the menu is brisk menu with super key support, but
retains the places and system piece that people like.
So you still get that traditional UI, but you get the benefit of super key for those
people that like to mash the super key.
Boy, you are making my life so much harder, you bastard right now.
I can't even with this.
The Mate desktop is so appealing.
When I went through this whole rash of switching from Arch to Ubuntu, I went Unity on almost
all of the things.
You were the Unity guy.
Except for two computers, my workstation in my office upstairs and the machines that I,
actually it's three because one's a VPS, that I asked to go into.
That doesn't count.
No.
But out of all of them now, here we are several months into it, they have been my go-to workstations.
They have been so solid wimpy.
I am such a fan of the project having, I'm almost what, five months, four months into
using them.
It's just been so great.
So huge, huge thank you specifically for Ubuntu Mate because that's what I'm using.
But the great thing is, I mean, has there been anything we've discussed that isn't available
upstream to the Mate project itself for all distros?
No, everything's upstream.
It's down to the different distro maintainers as to how they want to implement Mate itself.
The one conversation that we've had today is that we've landed the turn on high DPI
in Mate tweak, which although is cross desktop, but cross distro, it sits in the Ubuntu Mate
hub organization.
So we've been talking about moving that to the Mate project and actually making it a
full Mate thing because that's now got a feature that other distro maintainers will likely
want.
But Mate tweak is used quite widely now anyway.
I'm just struck by the fact that before 1804 has arrived, before the big Ubuntu Mate LTS
has arrived, even with the Ubuntu Mate 1710 release, you've managed to take what was the
butt of a joke and turn it into a desktop that is one of my favorites.
And with these improvements, it just sounds like it's going to be even freaking better.
Yeah, high DPI support, desktop icons.
It's you and a lot of folks.
I mean, I don't want to discount the work, but I know that there's a driving force behind
a lot of this and that driving force is you.
Yeah, there is.
And for a lot of this, I'm a mouthpiece, you know, the Mate team, I play a relatively small
part in.
I turn up and do this sort of thing from time to time and I test bugs and triage bugs and
raise bugs.
I have little coding time for Mate itself because what coding time I have, I put into
Ubuntu Mate and the Ubuntu Mate specific things.
But there is a small group of people who are very dedicated working on Mate and you just
have to look at the GitHub churn, you know, it's quite the commit rate, you know, it moves
every day.
It's not slow moving.
It's a fast, fast moving project.
And Ubuntu Mate, I made it for other people and I was maintaining it for other people
and I was using it because I felt I needed to because that's how I would see what the
rough edges were to improve it for others.
But with Ubuntu Mate 17.10, so after three years of making this thing, I finally had
a desktop environment that I was really proud of and was happy to use, really happy to use
on a day to day basis.
And with 18.04, I feel that even more.
I actually feel like, you know, I've made something here that I'm really proud of and
I'm happy to use.
And those two features we've talked about today, the Dash menu in Brisk and this work
on high DPI, both of those projects were funded through the generous support that we get through
our Patreon.
So you know, big thanks to everyone who's supporting Ubuntu Mate on the Patreon because
you've supported that development that happened in the Solus project on Brisk and this upstream
development in the Mate desktop.
And all of these distros get to benefit from that.
So well done you for supporting the project, everyone.
And it's been fascinating, it's just been it's been a lot of fun, really, to watch the
development of this patreon.com slash Ubuntu underscore Mate if you want to get in on the
action.
Boy, I I don't know how I'm going to contain myself.
It's almost too many good options.
You know, I've got so I've got Unity seven, of course, the did rocks is pulling me back
to gnome three.
Like there's some weird draw I have to going back to gnome.
There's something about gnome.
It pulls me back.
KDE, KDE plasma is doing great stuff.
Yeah, I hear rumors coming out of another flavor in Ubuntu that there's some interesting
stuff going on there as well.
So I think this year is going to be a it's good, a good year for the Linux desktop in
terms of the desktop environments.
Yeah, I've got a 2013 MacBook Pro running arch Linux that has the plasma 512 desktop.
And it was one of those things where I was really putting off the updates.
We talked about this recently.
I brought that whole damn machine.
I mean, it could have been as much as I hate to say it.
I hate to say it four or five months behind, which is a bad move on arch.
That is a bad move.
But I've been on the my fi, you know, and I was just convinced after a couple of months
that plasma desktop would break like a bitch after I tried to update it.
And I sat down, I got through all of my GPG key errors.
I got through all of these little esoteric like package conflicts problems that just
took like a little bit of time to work through.
Command here.
Command there.
Yeah.
And I finally got every damn package on that MacBook that you set up live on the show.
Right.
Updated.
And I was convinced after the reboot plasma wouldn't log in, because that was my experience
in the good old days.
Oh, yeah, I know that feeling.
And sure enough, I rebooted, logged back in and my desktop, the plasma desktop was exactly
exactly where I left it and performing better than ever.
Just snappy as hell.
Just clearly faster than Mac OS on the same hardware.
So it is a good year.
You got you got you got the you got folks that are doing a unity remix.
Gnome three's got more attention than it's ever had in its entire existence.
More hands on the code, more eyes on the code, more companies working with the code than
have ever, ever been.
And and the plasma desktop, the five series is in a super stable position.
They're about to release their next LTS.
They've really matured the project.
So that's in a really good spot.
And then Mahatay is bringing in like these killer features for high DPI and the new launcher
is just got all kinds of options.
It's too damn much.
Yeah, it is.
So we just need a few applications.
That's what that's really what it takes is we just need a few more good apps.
Before we go there, though, I just want to say Happy Birthday to lwn.net 20 years of
of service from lwn.
And and Jonathan Covert writes over here, he says over the following years, we've borne
witness to a long series of events that none of us could really have predicted.
Linux got caught up in the dot com boom and with the VA systems IPO came to epitomize
its success.
But when that went boom, Linux was still there stronger than ever.
The SCO group tried to steal our community and work it and turn it into its own rent
generating machine.
In the process of fending them off, it was made clear that the Linux kernel had one of
the cleanest code bases around companies discovered a little hobbyist system and invested billions
into it, massively accelerating the development at all levels of the system.
We learned how to scale development communities from dozens of developers to many thousands
of developers.
The security environment, which was initially defending against script kiddies playing their
own form of capture the flag became a fight against spammers, organized criminals and nation
states with vast resources.
Google bought an obscure phone operating system called Android and used it to dominate the
phone market.
And as a result, we got mobile devices that are far more open than they would have otherwise
been.
Linux became a base software supporting the bulk of the internet economy.
Some of our biggest contributors do not distribute Linux at all, but they use it internally,
want to help and they want to make it better.
It's been quite a ride.
We in the free software community set out to change the world and we exceeded and succeeded
beyond our wildest expectations.
And that's in the last 20 years and you know, JB has been there for half of that ride and
a lot of that we've seen ourselves.
And so here I am like 11, 12 years into covering this area and I look at Jonathan, I think
20 years.
That's truly impressive.
So congratulations to him.
And I've been a subscriber for many, many years.
In fact, even about two months ago, I ran into a bug on his website and he unsubscribed
me even though I was only a couple of months in and I had to resubscribe.
So I paid him twice this year for my LWN subscription and it was money well spent because it's real
good journalism, you know, without the spin, without the hype.
You look at this whole gnome desktop icons issue and that's the result of advertising
based media where they have to get a certain amount of clicks for those images on their
website in order to justify paying that writer.
And so they run these articles that say gnomes development team is arrogant, removes all
icons.
Really incentivizes the drama that you try to put into your stories even when it's not
really there.
Yeah.
And so it also serves to divide the community as well because you then get tribes building
up on those that are going to defend gnome on this decision and those that are going
to rally behind the, you know, what they feel is a bad decision.
So this kind of journalism is, is self-serving for the publications themselves because it
doesn't do our communities any good whatsoever because it just creates conflict and it's,
it's one of my pet peeves and I hate it.
Wimpy, if you and I had 12 hours for a podcast, we could not get half of why this is bad in
that show.
Yeah.
But in brief, the Linux community isn't like the Mac community or in the Windows community.
It is, we, we are, we are much more exposed and so when the discussions, when the discussion
is set low, when you have, when you have clickbait YouTubers and clickbait bloggers that, that
just want to get clicks and so they start the, they start the discussion at the lowest
common denominator.
They start the discussion in the mud and so that's, so that creates the spectrum of conversation
and then you have people on the other side and you have people in the middle and it just
turns out into a full-on turf war and it's just simply because of the way the advertising
model works and it's one of those things that I think I say maybe 200 times out of 233 episodes,
I think I've maybe mentioned this in 200 episodes.
But if you're not in the business and I, and I'm not like, I mean I'm just barely in the
business but even if you just get a peek, if you just see behind the curtain for 15
seconds, you realize what's going on here and how it directly damages an open community.
When you have a bunch of employees behind a closed door at Apple that are doing what
Phil Schiller tells them to do or they're doing what Craig Federighi comes up with or
they're doing what Johnny Ive tells them to do, it doesn't matter what some jackass on
Hacker News or on Reddit says.
They can say whatever they want all day long, Johnny Ive told them what to do.
But when a person is volunteering their personal time, maybe even at the exclusion of time
with their friends and family to work on an open source project, that stupid thing that
somebody says on Reddit has 10 times the impact on an open source developer.
Or that stupid thing that somebody said on YouTube that they made a video about can completely
derail a project.
And there's people in this community at all of the major companies that you know of.
If I say to you, listen or think of an open source company, I've probably had conversations
with people at that company that are no longer working on projects simply because they can't
take community reaction anymore.
And you name a major open source company, and I've had a conversation with somebody
from there about it.
It really makes a difference.
It's something I hear about all of the time.
And I can't really underscore how much of a difference that outlets like LWN can make
in this.
That's why I am a subscriber because the focus for LWN.net is not pissing off their subscribers.
Not how many clicks can I get so that way I can go get the new HelloFresh advertising
contract.
Can I make the people that are paying me on a monthly basis happy?
There's what I think LWN has been so dependable for me for how many years that it is just
indispensable, included with its built-in comments section below, forum style, even
though it's a new site.
It is beautiful.
Yeah.
And it kind of makes me wish that Patreon didn't get oversaturated because I also think
that the things that make LWN great are the same kind of things that could make an open
source project great.
If an open source project is held responsible to its primary patrons, then it's not going
after the trend of the week.
If a podcast network is held after its primary patrons, then you're not worried about them
trying to just build up enough clickbaity content so that way they can get yet another
sponsor.
And it just is a shame that every Tom, Dick, and Harry that lives in a van or makes a song
or writes a video game has gone to Patreon because it's saturated the market and it's
lowered the value in the audience's mind of sponsoring people on Patreon.
But the reality is it's all about the money.
You've got to follow the money.
It's like why Wes' really good buddy, his long-term friend, Tobey Maguire, always says,
show me the money.
Show me the money.
You follow the money.
And that's why I think LWN, after 20 years, is looked at as one of the most reliable news
sources.
And the only evidence you need of that is look at all of the coverage for Meltdown Inspector,
right?
Absolutely.
You and I know this because we pored through all of it for TechSnap.
There's a lot of the people that really matter in this discussion, the people that really
know what the hell's going on, are constantly referring to LWN as LWN was on top of this
for months.
LWN was following this when it was rumors.
LWN was accurately, technically covering this the entire time.
I hope 20 years from now people will say the same damn thing about Jupiter Broadcasting.
And I say, good job, Jonathan.
Keep at it.
And I'm going to be a subscriber.
I'm going to continue to be a subscriber here.
All right, just one more thing to get to before we're all done this week.
It's exciting.
It's important.
And it's a great piece that was written by Joey.
So let's mention Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
That's where Wes goes, and I go, to learn more about Linux as a full-featured training
library with everything you need to learn new skills and advance your career.
Now, that's easy to say.
But the actual implementation makes all of the difference.
It's not just one of the things they do.
It's all of the things.
All of the things they do is Linux, linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
Go there to support the show and sign up for a free seven-day trial.
Self-paced, in-depth video courses on every Linux, cloud, and DevOps topic, hands-on scenario-based
labs to give you real experience.
And they got human beings that can help you whenever you need actual real help.
Whether you're an experienced sysadmin or new to the world of Linux, Azure, and AWS,
in stack and DevOps, a sharp skillset is an absolute necessity to succeed.
Meet Linux Academy, an online Linux and cloud training platform that uses self-paced video
courses and hands-on labs to give you real-world experience for a wide range of skills.
Train for your certification, learn the latest DevOps tools, and grow your skillset to do
better work.
Linux Academy is not just a video library.
Our scenario-based server labs and quiz system allow you to learn hands-on.
We also have full-time human instructors who answer questions and help you earn that certification
or promotion at work.
We add new training every week, so you'll always be up to date on the latest tech.
Sysadmins of every experience level use Linux Academy to stay on the bleeding edge of the
Linux ecosystem.
You should too.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, I think it's just a combination of their sole focus,
the continual improvements, the full-time human beings, and the community that's stacked
full of Jupyter broadcasting members.
That doesn't hurt.
Yeah, it's a resource like no other, and that's why it's a perfect fit right here on this
show.
Linux is one of those platforms.
If you're coming from Windows and you're getting into Linux, one of the things you quickly
realize is, really, you can do anything with Linux, you just need to know how.
And sometimes you got to bend it in certain ways, sometimes you have to know certain incantations,
and Linux Academy is a library full of all of that.
And now with public profiles, so that way the new job you're trying to get, the new
client or your current employer can see exactly all of the awesome work you've got done.
Yeah, you can show off all that hard work.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
I don't know if everyone in the audience got a chance to see this piece by Joey, but he
nailed it.
I'm a big fan of Joey's work just because I know how hard he hustles.
He really is.
He really does.
He's a hard worker, and he has had the opportunity to sit back and sort of showcase all of the
good stuff that comes to the Ubuntu desktop, which generally, if somebody writes a Linux
app, they tend to write it for Ubuntu.
Yep.
It's over there, and he's talked about it.
Yeah, he's known about it.
And he says, well, what the hell is going on?
You like that?
You hear that?
That's me getting into it.
That's me getting into position here to talk about this.
That's how I can tell you're excited.
And Joey says some stuff here that I just completely agree with.
He says, once upon a time, I was writing about yet another music player, and it was almost
meme-like.
It was such a weekly occurrence.
And just that first sentence right there resonated with me.
When we launched the Linux Action Show Picks, it was a conversation that went something
like this.
There's so many apps that we're not getting to that we need to just stop waiting to review
each one of them and just talk about them.
Because there's too many apps, and we've got to just talk about them.
And so we carved out an app pick segment that we ran every single week at the top of the
show that was yet another application for the Linux desktop.
And we started that segment because there was an abundance of apps.
It was easy pickings, right?
You had a whole bunch to choose from.
By the end of the Linux Action Show, that was one of the most brutal segments.
It was a matter of just scavenging and going to producers and Beard and yourself.
It just meant just digging and digging for something new that wasn't a web application
and that wasn't Electron.
And then it meant installing it and trying it.
It became one of the most tedious parts of the show.
And now here in this show, we just throw them in there.
We had a couple of great ones.
Because they come in spurts now.
But it's not every single damn week anymore.
And I think Joey's noticed that too.
He says, same goes for video players, download managers, instant messengers, torrent apps,
image editors, Twitter apps, image viewers, text editors, photo uploaders, you name it.
I probably wrote about it, and it seemed like for a long while, app developers were out
there in mass creating quality apps to satisfy a full gamut of end user needs.
These days, though, availability of new native Linux apps which cater to users of the most
popular distributions seem few and far between.
We do have a lot of Electron apps.
Go ahead.
There's no winning here.
So when I look at these Electron apps, it's a sensible cost efficiency thing.
Also, the people developing have changed.
I think a lot of people that used to develop for the Linux's used to be people doing it
for a hobby.
That's why so many, yet another video player is usually you want to start with something
you can look at the reference of implementation.
Yeah.
You were doing it because you wanted to.
Yes.
And a lot of people then learned the brutal way that you can't make money if you're not
doing like a business, market research on what you're building, if you're just building
something that you have a lot of competition in.
And nowadays, the people writing apps have two other categories, which I think is the
primary focus.
Right.
So if you're developing an app for Ubuntu, you know that there's some commercial backing.
So the system and the platform that you're building and targeting is not just shifting
out random.
You can reach somebody to know what they're going for and that gives you stability, but
also means that a lot of the apps is not consumer or front user facing, but rather actually
enterprise facing.
And that's the part that is harder to see on the repository, but it exists actually
in higher quantity.
Otherwise, there wouldn't be so many ports of developer tools, even from, you know, proprietary
building software companies.
Okay.
Fair enough.
So I'm picking up what you're putting down, but I think I kind of disagree in some ways.
I can't really fully disagree with you, Daredevil, but I mean, looking at this, I have to point
to our friends over at elementary OS, which have an abundance of native applications right
now.
They just have a smattering, if you will, a buffet.
I think the elementary OS has one thing that is what distinguishes them and makes it appealing
for developers, which is all right.
A lot of people are good at developing, like developing code, but they're not designers
themselves.
Then having these semi-authoritarian view on how things should look like presents a
design.
And if you're a developer and you don't really want to do design stuff, but you want to write
that cool app, well, you go with them because he just does the design for you.
Don't you feel like you're underselling what they're doing?
I mean, aren't they really saying, here's a set of toolkits you can use so you have
consistent design.
Here's a set of really good, easy to read, easy to understand, and oh, by the way, easy
to find documentation.
Oh, and then you want to monetize that son of a bitch.
Well here's an app store with a payment system that's built around Stripe that you already
trust and know.
Sounds like iOS.
I mean, it just seems like, yeah, you could say it's authoritarianism, you could say it's
a design vision, but to me it seems like just a practical path, there's a breadcrumb path
for developers to follow.
That breadcrumb path has been there since day one.
But the thing that catered most of the developers that I've talked to that moved to elementary
to build their app is, hey, there's this guy, he's good in design, I wonder if he has input
on my app and I'll build this thing.
Because they're not designers, right?
They're just one like, I want to spend my time writing this new cool machine learning
technique and I want to implement that in the music store or whatever, right, in the
music player.
How can I do that?
But then I don't have the outreach to users and everybody feels useful if they can help
somebody.
And that's the part that if you know users are going to find your application pretty,
they will use it even if it sucks for the beginning because it's pretty.
And this is, I think, the strategy Apple has figured out.
If you have a pretty app, even if it sucks in the beginning, the user will put up with
it because it's not as unpleasant to be there.
And if it's a productivity app, you probably don't mind using if it's ugly because you
know you'll get your shit done, essentially.
Yeah.
And as long as they show that they eventually add more stuff and make it better, you're
more likely to say, okay, yeah, I'll live with this on the rough edges.
JJ, I know you had a comment about how perhaps Snaps and Flatpak could help even this whole
problem out.
Well, maybe Snaps more or less because a lot more of the mainstream applications are coming
via Snaps, such as Spotify and other apps that seem to be more...
Yeah, Slack.
You know, we should mention Slack is now being distributed as a Snap as of last week's episode.
That's huge.
Yeah.
And so, and this being an ease of entry for bigger app creators to get into Linux, it
sort of makes the jump from going from Windows and OSX to making and also making this less
of a daunting task and having to develop for a lot of out of distributions rather than
and only focus on one form of that app and you don't have to be specific to a specific
subset of apps.
I know most of the time that Linux developers usually initially do Debian application packages,
don't they?
Well, it depends on who they're trying to target.
I actually have a...
Before we go...
Okay, go ahead.
And then I have a question for Wimpy about some technical limitations with Snaps.
Go ahead.
And the only thing I just actually wanted to say is that actually the example of the
apps demonstrated in here are just yet another reinforcing point to the companies being the
primary target nowadays.
See, if you are Spotify and Linux user base is not easy to quantify because of the self-reporting
part of it, and before you decide to invest in making an app for Linux that is going to
be native there, it's going to work there, it is hard for you to justify the price, except
if you can actually know of many other services that are being used by enterprises, and then
you know at least this quantity of people because it's more measurable.
You can say, this company has these many users.
So then they become capable of saying, it's worthwhile to invest in here because we have
these many customers accessing from this platform right now, and if we actually make an app,
they will be better served, and as a consequence, we'll have better customers willing to pay
higher premiums.
And it's better outcomes for normals who want to transition over to Linux because they feel
fed up with OSX, and also they don't have to mess with wine as much.
Well, that's a fair point.
So let's talk about flat packs and snaps, and I have a question for Mr. Wimpress.
Is it possible with snaps to ship like a runtime in the snap?
And what I mean by that is, could I ship a enterprise Java application where the Java
runtime is just all inside the single snap?
Could I ship TeamViewer that uses some sort of wine runtime where that is all packaged
inside the snap?
Is it possible that some of these like these gap covering solutions that we've come up
with, these things that help people transition from Windows to Linux, could those just be
included as one single snap, so I as an end user, I snap install TeamViewer, of course
I recognize TeamViewer 13 as native now, but I as an end user for this example install
TeamViewer via snap, and I just get the wine runtime and all that stuff inside the snap?
Is that technically possible right now, Wimpy?
Yes, and there are snaps that already do precisely those things that you outlined.
Okay, I thought it wasn't for some reason.
I thought that was something that flat pack could do that snaps couldn't.
So in the case of Java, JetBrains have published the vast majority of their product portfolio
and those are all Java based and they have their own custom build of the JVM inside the
snap in order to make those work.
And then our friend Alan Pope has made a snap of ZZT, which is an old DOS based adventure
game and that ships DOSBox inside the snap and then uses DOSBox to launch the game.
One of the Ubuntu podcast listeners, McPhail, has done the same with Blades of Agony, which
is a Doom mod or re-implementation and that uses DOSBox embedded and I happen to know
it's not publicly available but I happen to know one of my colleagues at Canonical created
a snap of Internet Explorer by using wine.
I love it, of course.
Of course, why not, right?
That just makes my day.
So I'm struck with one thing that I take away from this is we are, as Linux users, experiencing
something that the wider market is currently going through.
When you install Slack on Windows 10, I've got news for you, when you use Atom on your
Mac, it's not just a Linux phenomenon.
This is happening to the entire market.
This is the consequence of mobile and the web becoming predominant platforms.
The web and mobile are what people are writing for today that are spending millions of dollars
on developers, for the most part, and the desktop is sort of a second-class to third-class
citizen now in this new world that we see ourselves in 2018.
Many people would rather write a LadyTube skill than a Linux desktop application.
Simply put, it would be more valuable.
You know, I'll give you an example.
There's a lot of different podcast networks that are writing LadyTube apps right now so
you can listen to podcasts on your LadyTube, and they're not really all that interested
and don't really give any shits about the Linux desktop.
It's just not on their radar.
It's a simple market dynamics, market force that we are also at the whim of, just like
Mac users are.
I've got some thoughts about this that put this into context.
Currently there are 46 GNOME applications that make up the core GNOME applications,
right?
Okay.
More or less.
Elementary have been doing a fine job with their developer outreach and their developer
program and their app store, and they now have 70 apps in their store, which is a fantastic
achievement considering the size of their team.
I think they're punching above their weight in that respect.
Absolutely.
There are 30,000 to 40,000 packages in the Debian and Ubuntu archives.
That includes libfu and devthis and all the rest of it, right?
There are approximately 50,000 electron applications on GitHub.
Oh boy.
Well put.
Right there.
That's it, isn't it?
That puts it all in context.
It sure does.
Thank you, Mr. Wimpress.
Go find out more about what Wimpy's up to and his whole crew, the Ubuntu podcast.
There's plenty of fine episodes ready for you to listen to.
The season hasn't started yet, the new season, although rumor has it it may come around.
Is that right?
Possibly.
So go get more of that Ubuntu podcast.
Go get more Westpane at Westpane and also TechSnap.Systems.
Brand new episode just went out this morning where Wes breaks down configuration management
for thousands of systems to your personal Linux workstation.
I'm at Chris Hellyes, Networks at Jupyter Signal.
See you right back here, next week.
All right, guys.
That was a lot of fun.
I really enjoyed this week's episode.
That was kick ass.
Thank you.
And that's really wimpy.
That really puts it all into perspective, too, doesn't it?
You're trying to hit an hour and a half for episode blank.
Well, you know, we got to make room now for the Ask Noah show.
This is a bit of a longer show, but we got to make room for Noah.
He's coming.
And there's no avoiding it.
He can't stop him.
No.
He can't stop Noah.
Don't even try.
Chris.
Yeah.
I got a quick question about Wi-Fi adapters.
So my dad's looking to get me a USB Wi-Fi adapter for my machine.
Oh, that's nice of him.
Yeah.
You see, I'm upstairs in my room right now talking to you guys on my phone, but my desktop,
it has a D-Link DWA 125 Wi-Fi adapter.
It's USB-N only, and I need an AC adapter, and I was wondering if you had any suggestions
for me.
Oh, I don't.
I don't.
I mean, I have so many things.
There's a lot going on with what you just said, and boy.
You know, what's your budget?
So let's start there.
My dad said he's willing to go at least 60, but he'd prefer to keep it a little bit lower.
Okay.
All right.
And what kind of machine you're plugging in?
It's got to be USB?
It's got to be a tower.
It's a custom-built machine, and it does have USB 3 capabilities.
Maybe you should ask Noah.
Hey, Citizen, by the way, I got to say, Oh Hi DPI is really funny.
That's really good.
That's a good title, by the way.
Well, I'll ask Noah, I guess, when he comes on, because he may be the better person to
ask that kind of person.
Does anybody have any hardware?
Does anybody have any hardware recommendations for that?
Asus Dongle, they have one that is pretty good.
I'm trying to find it.
And is that Asus one, is it like an Intel chipset on the inside, or what is that?
I just posted it in the chat.
Oh yeah?
Okay.
Very good.
Okay, Rekai.
There you go.
And Best Buy's got it, too.
So it's an Asus dual-band wireless AC USB network adapter.
And I'm fairly close to St. Matthew's portion of Louisville, Kentucky.
So hopefully I might just have him go down and pick it up.
Just one thing.
That's nice.
That's just basically the size of like a mouse wireless adapter.
Yeah.
Just one small thing, though.
Because you're using in tower, and the tower itself can interfere with wireless, make sure
that you have an adapter in case you need like a cable, an extension cable.
Yes.
You can actually-
Get a USB extender cable.
He's absolutely right.
So get a USB extender cable, and then put this at the end of it.
I have had that same exact problem.
That is good advice right there.
Yeah.
My current one is sitting up on the wall right now.
Oh yeah.
There you go.
So you're hip to it.
Okay.
I'll definitely look into that.
Even not in the wall.
That's what I usually do.
What do you think, Wes?
Oh, just in the same situation in the past, I've ended up, if you have like some of the
cheaper and like older Wi-Fi hardware just sitting around, you can flash a lot of those
routers, add them as just a Wi-Fi adapter plug and plug it into your-
A bridge.
Yeah.
It's funny you say that.
That's what I was actually going to say until he said this Asus thing.
I was actually going to just recommend just bridge it.
I got to tell you, at the end of the day, all my devices that are Wi-Fi bridged, I just
like better.
I just plug them into the ethernet port.
The machine is none the wiser.
It doesn't have to futz with the Wi-Fi stuff.
It has no idea.
And the bridge is always connected to the Wi-Fi network.
And that is my-
Provided your Wi-Fi doesn't change a lot.
It works pretty well.
Yeah.
Yes.
Thank you.