Someone here at the barbecue though, he asked like, so do you guys submit bug reports during
your reviews?
Like if you come across a problem, do you submit a bug report?
And I said, you know, often no, that's not always the case.
We sometimes do submit bug reports, but most of the time when we review it, we're reviewing
something that's been officially released and so we review it as if it's a finished
product and then give our thoughts.
But we do submit a ton of bugs and work with the communities that build a lot of the projects
that we use internally to make the shows.
So what's happened with this video, so it's a Python, if you search for Python audio visualizer
in Google, you'll come across the project.
It is amazing what's happened in the last couple of months because of the Jupiter broadcasting
community.
They have taken this thing from a pretty decent application that sits on top of FFmpeg.
And I mean it, it almost chokes me up looking at it because they have taken this into something
that is more competitive than anything that's available commercially, including some products
I have looked at that require a monthly charge.
And this thing is more competitive.
That's crazy.
And just because the community just got involved and it's going to make our shows better and
it's going to make late night Linux better.
It's one of those great examples, right, where clearly this was a need.
People wanted this.
Maybe not everyone had that clear conception yet, but once it was there, once it was started,
there's just this natural momentum that's fascinating to watch.
Yeah, I love open source.
You could see how media production on Linux can be more successful in this paradigm.
I don't know if it's going to be the truth.
Maybe it's not the same for video editing.
But this is something you can't do on a Mac or Windows.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 203 for July 4th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's feeling the patriotic spirit
or the bourbon.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Quite a show for us today.
That's amazing.
Obviously we have the big barbecue going on right now as we record this, but we have some
breaking news applicable to us Linux users, and apparently it is the season of stupid.
We'll be talking about some developments in the community that really have your host quite
ponderous.
Then we'll give you a few updates on some stories we've talked about, discuss something
big and bold the XDA developer forums is doing that us Linux users are going to like quite
a bit, and then package kit.
You know it.
You love it.
We'll give you the platform package management possible.
Turns out a little crashy, a little crashy, a little unstable on Fedora.
We'll give you the reasons why you might want to avoid package kit on Fedora, at least for
this release, and something might change in the future, and then we'll discuss System
76's new operating system as well as a way for you to hide your Steam... Well, I won't
call... I won't quote RMS.
We'll just say it's semi-negative in the Freedom Dimension games.
We'll tell you how you can hide those and isolate them from your system.
You found that one.
Oh yeah, I did.
You found a good one.
Plus, it seems that Rust is taking over as the language of choice for the Linux desktop.
I think we're officially Rust fanboys on this show.
I don't even know how that happened.
I agree.
Well, I think because we both listen to Koda Radio.
It's because you like Firefox so much and you're excited about Servo.
That's totally what it is, dude.
No, you know, it's like Apple's got their Swift and we've got Rust.
You know what I mean?
The branding is traditionally an open source.
We're not quite on their game with that, but it is fun to say.
And Rust looks like a really, really serious, really good technology.
And we'll tell you about how it's making... Potentially.
I guess it hasn't actually come yet.
How it could potentially make GNOME much better, a little more crash-proof, thanks to a Google
Summer of Code project.
But Mr. West, I hope that the audience out in the living room... We have a small group
out in the audience in the living room, as I just said.
You say small, but those are some heavy hitters out there.
Geez.
And boy, was it some good food.
So we're doing the barbecue right now, the 4th of July episode 200 barbecue.
And all-star, Wes Payne right here.
Thank you.
I mean, knocked it out of the park with the bratwurst.
Unbelievably good.
And rumor has it you are up till 2 AM working on those Sons of Guns.
Oh, maybe.
Just a little bit.
Soaked in butter, beer, and onions.
Mmm.
Nature's finest.
Super good, Wes.
Super good.
And everybody ate those things up.
The food here has been amazing today.
We're cooking rib-eyes, we're cooking burgers, we're cooking the bratwurst, and we've also
got some great veggie skewers, and...
Don't forget that... Oh, you got it.
What?
No, go ahead.
I was going to say that avocado.
The fried avocado.
Just really a game changer.
But I'm hoping that those people out in the living room... I'm talking directly to them.
I hope right now that they will keep an ear out for a knock, knock, knock at the door,
because UPS is supposed to deliver my brewery today, which is a Linux-powered, one-touch
Linux brewing machine of the beer.
No way.
Of the beer, Wes.
And that should be delivered as we do this show today.
It was something that Blaster and I went into.
So buddy, I think it's almost here.
If you hit me up on Telegram, we should definitely do a vlog or two about this thing.
You put all the ingredients in there, you push a button, and then you come back in a
couple of weeks and you've got beer.
So you're saying in a couple weeks, I can come back.
I don't think so.
You can drink beer.
You'll have beer.
I think that could be the case.
In the meantime, I've got something better for you, though.
You ready for this?
Surprise me.
It's our virtual log.
Time appropriate.
Greetings, Mumble Room.
Greetings.
Hello.
Hello, gentlemen.
It is good to see you.
I hope everyone is well in there.
We have a really good show for you this week, so I'm glad you're here.
Thank you very much.
Now, Wes, before we go any further, we've got to stop and just mention something really
quickly, because I know not everyone listening to this show listens to user air, although
they should be.
I know they're not.
They should be.
I understand.
And I just want to give them a heads up that we have a bit of a giveaway going on, a sweepstakes,
if you will.
Don't call it a giveaway, Wes.
It's a sweepstakes.
It is a sweepstakes.
100% sweep.
That's right.
User Air is doing a sweepstakes for the Dell XPS 13.
13.
Yeah, that's right.
You have one of those, buddy.
Oh, yeah, I do.
Yeah, you do.
You have the original.
And we're going to give one away.
We're going to give a brand new one away.
Give it to me.
It's for me, guys.
Sorry.
You already have one.
Yeah.
It's for me.
It's a sweepstakes.
Don't call it a giveaway, Dylan.
It is for me.
Sweepstakes.
Now, here's the thing.
It's for U.S. residents.
It's a sweepstakes, by the way.
Yeah.
And it's for U.S. residents only.
You have to be 18 years or older.
I'm 19.
No, you are not.
You go to jupiterbroadcasting.com, click on shows, and go to User Air.
It's in the User Air description, right at the top of the User Air show.
We're going to be giving away the laptop... Oh, I'm sorry.
It's not a giveaway.
It's a... Sweepstakes.
Yeah, we'll be doing the sweepstakes in User Air to give away... I'm sorry.
To stake an XPS 13 to a listener of the User Air show, and we want you to have a chance
to get in there.
Just go to jupiterbroadcasting.
So we sweep the stakes?
Yeah.
Yeah, we're going to sweep them.
So go to jupiterbroadcasting.com, click on shows, and then go down to User Air.
Right there in the description where we have what the show's about and our contact information,
we have a temporary link for the sweepstakes.
I want you to get an XPS 13.
If you're over in the EU, just come over and live in the U.S. for just a little while.
It's worth it.
These XPSs are great.
Get the Dell XPS 13.
We hear that the ear needs a roommate.
That's true.
Yeah, you could just crash here in the garage for a little bit.
Yeah.
There you go.
Sorry, you have to be 18 years.
Sorry about the 18 years or older, Dylan.
Sorry about that.
Let's start with that rust thing I was just talking about, because this is neat, and it's
summertime.
The Googles has the summer of codes, and I don't really need to explain this, do I?
Because everybody knows what this is at this point.
People throw some money around during the summer to employ some students to build things,
and often they build open-source things that we all use and love, and sometimes have actually
turned into long-term projects that we use today.
Philip is one of these blokes who is going to be working on the – I think it's the
GNOME JavaScript server.
I think it's – it's GJS, so I'm kind of guessing at the acronym, and he's worked
on it for quite a long time.
He's going to be mentoring someone that's paid by Google to essentially rewrite this
JavaScript binding for GNOME and rewrite it using Rust to make it stable, essentially
more craft-proof.
It's not just GNOME Shell that uses this.
GNOME Documents, GNOME Maps, Polari, Sushi, GNOME Photos, a lot of things that are modern
GTK applications use this backend, this GJS backend.
JavaScript really is everywhere, even not the hip places.
I think right now – I think right now the current version uses Mozilla's SpiderMonkey
for the engine, and so this is going to be a rewrite of that in Rust.
And the reason why I mention this, so this was actually a highly-submitted story to the
show this week because a lot on JB, we've been talking about some of the GNOME crashing
issues we've had recently, and so somebody submitted this as a possible, like, hey, look,
things are improving.
I've also heard some – it's not rumors because they're blog posts, but I have heard
some implication that there has been some work at Canonical on Mudder, and I'm not
clear on what that work has been, but you combine different people working on this stuff,
and it could start shoring up some of these problems that we've experienced with GNOME
pretty quick.
And this is just the kind of thing that you need.
It won't be the be-all, end-all.
It's not going to be the next thing maybe that you run on your system even, but this
can lower that barrier to entry suddenly if Rust becomes a thing that, like, oh, yeah,
you already have build support.
If you want to add a module that's in Rust and not in C or C++, you can.
I think that really opens the door.
So if this works out, hey, that would be great.
And you can find out more in the link in the show notes.
Let's talk about the new kernel that came out.
So I just want to do a couple of pieces of breaking news right now.
Let's talk about the new kernel release, and let's talk about the WikiLeaks document
dump that shows the CIA was targeting Linux users because this is probably the one that's
getting the most attention as we record the show right now.
It's named Outlaw Country.
You may have heard that name floating around, and it's a Linux kernel module that gets
loaded into the system and creates a new entry in IP tables, and then once it does that,
it forwards all the traffic to whoever they want it forwarded to, and the attacker, in
this case the CIA or whoever has this code, could then reroute to whatever mining system
they have or whatever.
Now, what I'm not clear about from this exploit is it seems like you could just do
an IP tables list and you would see this entry, so not only would it be pretty easy to detect
if you were looking for it, but you also would have to have executed this exploit with root
privileges.
I think some of the issues there are that, one, it adds a new table, and so unless you
actually specify that table, by default you won't know, right?
You'll be like, oh, well, it's not in my NAT rules and it's not in the default
table.
Right, so it's not like you're going to look at your config and see it.
Plus, it's most likely on, you know, here we're relying on admins in the middle because
it's not like they're going to be infecting you most likely with this kind of thing.
It's going to be at some router or some NAT or some web server that wants to know who's
visiting that website and it's been running on a VPS for six months and you're not checking
the logs.
What's interesting, though, is this doesn't give itself access to the system, so you have
to take advantage of another existing vulnerability in the Linux system to get access to run this.
So this doesn't give you the access.
You know, it does also say to me maybe that, hey, this is one of those things people who
are pushing UEFI maybe were thinking about, right?
Otherwise, if this module has to be signed, hey, that'd be nice.
Can I tell you the honest truth, though?
After the Snowden leaks, I was feeling pretty cocky because they had stuff on there about
exploiting Macs through Thunderbolt and they had stuff in there about going after Windows
and Windows servers, but Linux desktop users, if you go by the Snowden leaks, were just
totally off the radar.
Like, they weren't even worried about Linux users and I'm like, hey, hey, hey, look at
me.
I'm like James Bond just by running Linux.
And then I see this WikiLeaks dump here from the CIA and they're going after Linux users.
And here I thought Linux users were upstanding moral citizens.
Yeah, yeah.
I guess I was wrong.
Yeah, of course they're going after the servers.
That's the problem.
So yeah, if you hear the story going around and you hear them talking about outlaw country,
just keep in mind that it's just, all it is, it's a kernel module that maybe it does some
other nefarious things, but mostly just injects rules into IP tables, which is just, the reason
why it's a kernel module is because like Wes just said, it doesn't check your config and
so it has to be able to apply it to your config after it's been loaded.
And that's why it's a module.
And really the worst part is that it makes you have to go look at IP tables.
So sorry, everyone.
You know how you bring down the entire spying industrial complex?
You sue them for GPL violations, right?
I bet you that's not GPL compliant.
You follow up on that.
Mm-hmm.
And then just before we get into the good stuff, I mean the stuff I really – I got
a couple of more things I want to talk about with you guys.
kernel 4.12 came out today, that's the other big breaking news.
That might have been yesterday.
But it just came out.
And the big thing in here is BFQ, the BFQ scheduler and USB type C manager that I talked
about in a recent episode has been integrated into the kernel.
Also actually I should say Vegas support too, which is going to matter to a lot of you.
Vegas support has been added as well.
And the thing that I'm very excited about, although I've gotten mixed feedback on this
and I would like to get more, and maybe if anybody in the Mumble Room knows, please feel
free to interrupt me, BFQ, which is the better, faster, quicker scheduler, the scheduler that
sets the priority for like all the things going on and access to IO.
If you've ever had a Linux box, I can replicate this on Linux every Wednesday night.
I replicate – I have this scenario.
I open up Chrome and then I go to pinboard and I load up all of the links I have for
that night's unfilter and I go boom, boom, boom, boom, boom and I'm using my middle
click and I click, click, click, click, click along my pinboard list and I open tab after
tab after tab after tab after tab and some of them have flash.
Most of them actually have flash because I'm linking to news sites and the whole system,
the entire system locks up for about 10 seconds, 15 seconds.
Just long enough you can't do anything else.
You can't get up.
No.
And BFQ promises to solve that problem.
Now a lot of people say there's ways that you can fix this without BFQ but in a nutshell
it's an IO scheduler that balances how the system accesses data on a drive and supposedly
it has improvements for SSDs.
BFQ targets desktop users by ensuring that at no point a single application is using
all of the bandwidth.
Sometimes when copying large files in Linux a user sees systems slow down or freeze completely.
This will now be a thing of the past.
I like the way the Arch Wiki as always describes it.
Budget fair queuing is a disk scheduler which allows each process slash thread to be assigned
a portion of the disk throughput.
So that kind of explains how you're – again, this may be the case where you wouldn't want
it on a server but you might minimize your maximum throughput but it should give better
latencies for desktop users or at least that's what people say.
Yeah.
And by the way the USB type C stuff is like the stuff that figures out charging based
on what has –
Oh my God.
The future is here now.
Yeah.
If you're living the USB lifestyle that's a good kernel for you to get.
You're not mandatory USB – your USB-C devices will still work fine.
But if you upgrade to that kernel you'll get the smart intelligence where it decides
oh, that's a phone, I should charge it and not charge from the phone which could happen
right now under Linux.
We'll see.
It's kind of adorable.
We had the first USB-C support so I'll give us credit for that.
We were there first.
We just do it our own way.
Yeah.
Okay.
And then the last kind of newsy thing before we get into the nuts and bolts of the community
stuff this week, Wes found this and I just found it awesome because when you stopped
by UserAir a few weeks ago you were talking about playing around with SystemD's Nspawn
and container support.
Yeah.
That's right.
And so here's somebody who self-admittedly is not a Linux expert – his name is Drew
I guess.
I'm not sure.
I don't know what his name is.
And he's been messing around with confining Steam into a SystemD Nspawn container.
And I don't – I've never set one of these up yet but if I'm understanding correctly
– well, he did it to play around with too but it was a great way to sort of solve the
32-bit library problem because instead of spewing 32-bit libraries all over your system,
you contain it all to this container and you don't have to like – if none of your other
applications need it, you don't have to bother with it.
Yeah, exactly.
It's this crossover now.
Finally like containers are big on that in the development side of things because exactly
that.
You don't want all of these – I have six different projects.
I don't want the dependencies or the libraries from all of these different things on my
system.
I don't want to mess in this.
I don't want to cause dependency hell or have some weird app thing go on.
Containers are perfect for that.
And now it's like yeah, I don't want 32-bit libraries.
I don't want to have to deal with that.
And yeah, he points out some of the things like FireJail or other alternatives which
can work for some of the – getting more control over the process.
But he's using SystemD Nspawn it seems like – mostly just because it's built in.
Yeah, it's built in.
It's right there.
It's really easy to go.
And it makes it super simple to be – you can pretend maybe you don't want to use a
cloud provider or something that you would need something local like for Steam, boom,
perfect.
Throw away Linux distribution.
Yeah, exactly.
And the thing that would have tripped me up, and this is why I like his post and we'll
have it linked in the show notes, is he talks about getting the X applications out of that
container.
And actually at first this was a bit major hurdle.
But these days between Docker and SystemD Nspawn there's like a thousand guides out
there for how to do that.
It's really pretty easy.
X needs some stuff that's under slash temp.
You can also do other things like you can share special devices.
You can mount stuff.
SystemD Nspawn makes it super simple to just bind mount stuff.
Networking is really easy.
If you use SystemD NetworkD they have a lot of primitive setup to just, boom, NAT's already
there.
Your containers automatically get set up behind the NAT.
They've got their own private IP address.
Super simple.
And SystemD Nspawn can run Docker containers.
So you can use all the Docker build stuff.
You can use – yeah, exactly.
Oh, I did not know that.
But it makes sense.
Because it's just a file system that you start a process on.
Right.
I'm going to chew on that.
So I don't know.
In the background you might be able to hear some of the barbecue going on.
The barbecue continues while we do the show which is awesome.
And not only do we have a crowd out there but we have a big crowd in the Mumble Room
which is pretty exciting.
And Mr. Popey is back after a little bit of a stay.
Mr. Popey, did you happen to go to the recent Snap Sprint held by Canonical?
I did.
I was there Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday and then I had a conference to get you on Thursday,
Friday to go and give a talk about Snaps.
So yeah, it was great.
It was nice to see a bunch of people from different projects, people from KDE, from
elementary, from Nome, from Flora.
It was really nice to have everyone in the Canonical office and all working together
to make Snaps better.
It was good fun.
Yeah.
And I've seen some recent news about Nome software.
Is that as a result of some of the work that came out of that Sprint?
Yeah, definitely.
Robert Ansell who maintains software from the Ubuntu side was there.
But also Richard Hughes who works on, who's the upstream maintainer for Nome software
was there as well.
And so there are lots of conversations they can have about improving the experience for
installing Snaps on any distro, not just on Ubuntu and improving things like how options
are presented to users and there was lots of discussion about how to improve that kind
of stuff.
So it was really, really nice to see all these working together in the office.
Yeah.
That is really cool.
All the different walks of Linux.
You know, I was listening to the Ubuntu podcast today and I noticed that you sort of built
a better, improved Mycroft and I was wondering are you going to launch an Indiegogo for that
anytime soon because I might be willing to back that.
You mean launch an Indiegogo and then not deliver for two years?
Yeah.
I think I can do that.
That's what Chris prefers actually.
Yeah.
You got a long time.
That's what I'm used to at least.
You could have a stretch goal for Palmer Violets included.
Yeah.
Okay.
Hello Mr. Wimpy.
How are you?
I'm very well.
We've had a great, I mean we've had unbelievable food here at the studio.
It turned out it was so, so, so good.
Were you at the Sprint yourself?
I was.
Yes.
Well, welcome.
Welcome.
Now I'm jealous.
It's nice both of you guys here.
Now if rumor has it, are you going to be AFK soon?
Are you going to be traveling?
Are you going to be on staycation?
Like what's happening soon?
Because I think if I'm not mistaken, I didn't expect you to be here today.
Yeah.
So our schedule is a little bit off by one at the moment on the Ubuntu podcast.
We just recorded one episode of Ubuntu podcast this evening.
So we were let out of school early.
Very good one.
I'm glad you made it here.
Now we have some good stuff to get into today including, I'm really excited.
I know Pharaonix gets a lot of crap.
Some of it from you.
Yeah.
Okay.
Fair enough.
It does.
I mean what?
No, you're right.
I mean I will own that.
I have.
But at the same time, I do respect Michael Arboul's hustle to put it in sort of …
Whatever you think of the output, there is a lot of output.
There is a lot of output.
There is a lot of hustle.
But actually where a lot of my respect comes from for Michael is what he has done with
OpenBenchmark.
It's just the Pharaonix test suit, if I were him, I would rename it and I know that's
really a hard thing to hear.
But if I were him, I would honestly rename it to the OpenBenchmark test suite because
it uploads to OpenBenchmark.org and I have found it to be such a useful tool not because
I'm all into benchmarks and numbers but because it gives me baselines to see how machines
compare to each other that I'm testing up against each other.
Some heuristics you can use later when you're trying to evaluate them really quickly.
Yeah, absolutely.
And then as a reviewer, I can publish links to that and say now run it against your own
system and just see the delta.
It's not about what – it's about the gap in the numbers, not what the numbers are.
Right.
There's no absolute measure here.
It doesn't matter.
It's an amazing resource and that database is growing and growing and growing.
So Pharaonix has been – I think actually in total, a pretty good resource and when
anybody is working that hard and publishing that often, you're going to get a couple
of things wrong here or there, especially if you don't have an editor, if it's a
one-person team.
So I can understand some of the mistakes that people have criticized in the past.
They're somewhat unfortunate and I think it's been a good resource but I think what
we could really use in this space is some competition.
This week, XDA, the ones that have traditionally exceedingly well-covered, ROMs and that whole
development community, announced that they were going to cover PC hardware with a specific
focus on Linux and open source and they've got some really good things that they're
thinking about and they capture and cover some of the feedback from their readers and
I've been talking to the author.
I don't think he's going to make it.
He was going to meet us up today in the show but you know, mumble, hashtag mumble problems.
Wow, did you hear that?
That's America.
Did you guys hear that in the mumble room?
Did you hear that in the background?
Yup.
Yeah, that's fireworks that are going off already right there.
We're having a small war with the neighbors.
I think we're going to win though.
The charge is happening as we speak.
We do have a larger group here.
We do have a larger group.
So I want to talk about what they're all doing and why I think it's a big deal and how they're
doing it differently and honestly, the brilliant point they made about why they're starting
it.
So we're going to talk about that next but first I want to talk about Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com.
That supports the show but it also gives you $25 in service credit if you bring a device
or $25 off your first device.
Mobile plans used to drive me crazy.
It's obviously a scam.
You can sense it.
You can suss that out.
You're smart enough.
You know that they're scamming you.
They're really only capable of doing this because they have a duopoly.
It's AT&T and Verizon and they have a duopoly and so they're able to do all these kinds
of crazy things and then the competitors have to wear crazy leather jackets and pink shirts
and make all kinds of crazy claims and completely destroy net neutrality to sell phones.
It's a horrible competitive environment.
If you go to linux.ting.com, you can make a difference.
Linux.ting.com is mobile the way it would have been done.
If you hit the reset button on wireless, this is how you would do mobile, right?
It's pay for what you use.
It's $6 a month for your line.
Think about that for a second.
So you want a cell phone line?
It's $6 a month.
Okay, now your kid gets a little bit older, you want to get them a cell phone, $6 a month.
You got a small business, you're growing, you want to give a couple employees some phones,
$6 a month.
$6 a month for a phone and then your usage on top of that.
Ting just takes your minutes, your messages, your megabytes, you add them up and that's
what you pay.
It's simple.
It's straightforward.
There's no contract.
It's easy.
And the best part?
CDMA and GSM networks to work with.
So whatever you got, you're likely going to bring over to Ting.
Just check their BYOD page.
It'll give you all the details you need.
You bring it over to Ting, you get a $25 service credit.
The reason why that's great, average Ting line, $23 a month once you include the line
cost and the minutes.
So if you get a $25 service credit, it pays for more than the first month.
Maybe you don't have a phone that you're going to bring, like you need a new phone.
What?
Then you get $25 off your first device, Wes.
Whoa.
That's right.
Linux.Ting.com.
Big thank you to Ting for not only making wireless not suck so bad, but also for supporting
the show for so damn long.
Yeah.
But really the first thing is even more important, honestly, because wireless is the worst.
Also happy America birthday up to our friends in Canada.
Linux.Ting.com.
You hear that party out there?
Oh, yeah.
They're having a party out there.
Well, we left, so they're now kicking it.
Well, and there's booze and there's food.
I mean, there is a party.
Yeah.
Let's hurry up and finish.
XDA has announced they're beginning regular PC hardware coverage, designed for quote-unquote
their audience, which I think means the Jupiter Broadcasting audience, and they go through
some recent comments they've had about some of their articles that they were kind of preemptively
planning this, and they're like, let's test out this material and see how it works here.
And so they published a few articles, and the comments are like, do more of this.
Yes, please get more into computer hardware.
And they say at the time, we didn't mention that we were kind of considering this, and
we were monitoring the feedback.
And I love what they say they're going to cover, because they're so brilliant about
it, because they say XDA has traditionally covered mobile devices, but how do you make
all these apps and OSes for these mobile devices?
You have to use great PC hardware.
Exactly.
And there's that link, right, between – I mean, I think there's a lot of people who
get into Linux because they want to mess with Android ROMs whenever it turns out, hey, Linux
and open source is the best way to get started with that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, and so they say like – so here's the logic.
They say after two months of working behind the scenes, we're ready to say it, XDA will
start covering PC hardware on a regular basis.
And if you dig down a little bit, they talk about the type of hardware they're going
to be covering.
They say reviews will largely focus on the Linux operating system and continue to have
a developer focus in them.
We decided to keep our reviews on Linux for two primary reasons.
Oh, I love it.
Okay, number one.
First up was the lack of dedicated Linux coverage for new PC hardware in the global market.
We hope that this will help introduce – what's that word right there, Wes?
Cooperation?
I don't know that.
I don't know what that is.
What's that?
I don't think that's something we do down here in the States.
Is that – no.
No, I'm not familiar with that.
Is that something where you fight other people and then whoever wins –
It's just another word for argument.
Okay, okay.
Okay.
They're going to – anyways, they're going to take that and they're going to work with
other people and do Linux reviews.
I don't understand that part of it.
But what they go on to say is there's not really many competitors and they address this
directly beyond Ferronix.
That caught my attention there.
The other half, by the way, is one that we have had – here's what they say.
A lack of information on how to get most PC hardware working on the day of release.
As part of our reviews, we'll be including notes on any issues using hardware with Linux
as well as any solutions and workarounds available.
You know, I hadn't really thought of it until this article but you're right, there kind
of is that gap.
We talk a lot about software, releases, those kind of things, but you're on – by and
large, I mean, yeah, you might have some Ferronix articles, maybe there's an ArchWiki entry
for your laptop, but hardware is kind of neglected.
It's like, well, just go to the regular PC hardware news.
You'll be fine for that.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I've been talking with Daniel Moran and he'll – I think that's how you say
his last name.
He'll be doing the writing over there and he's available on Twitter.
I have him linked in the show notes and he's pretty excited about it.
I think he's got a good vision about what he wants to do with it and it's not going
to be exactly what Ferronix does.
It will be somewhat competition in that space but I think it's going to be also more like
here's first day release of this new piece of hardware that everybody is talking about
and here's how it actually works today on Linux and if you really got to use it, here's
the couple of things you have to modify or tweak to make it work.
Awesome.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's the kind of stuff that Windows users typically get to enjoy and they talk
about that too.
They say, well, look, there's tons of other people that are doing Windows coverage.
Right.
And like before, we've been kind of left waiting like, OK, well, I hope someone buys
that laptop and writes a blog post sometime in the next six months because otherwise how
will I know?
Yeah.
I hope that somebody who's on like Planet Gnome or something, the blogs, writes about
buying this thing and they fix it.
Yeah, that's exactly it.
So I'm actually super glad that Wimpy is here because I hadn't even planned on having the
expertise of Mr. Martin Wimpers for this next story.
But Joey over at OMG Ubuntu has an article on the new software boutique app that's going
to ship in Ubuntu Mate 17.10.
Couple of things I noticed that jump out at me, Wimpy, is it looks like some of the Mate
branding has been stripped from this.
More theming support has been added and snap support.
It kind of feels like this is starting to be positioned as any distro could use this
thing.
Hopefully.
Yeah.
We're using all the right technologies for that to become a thing.
We're obviously going to be developing it to hit the 17.10 release deadlines and it
will be squarely aimed at doing what Ubuntu Mate needs.
But because we're going to be using a snapdglib, which is the library to do all of the snap
stuff and then package kit now for the traditional repository installs, it could potentially
work anywhere.
So decoupling software boutique has several advantages.
It can be installed and used in other distros.
Software boutique and Ubuntu Mate welcome use and use fewer system resources and software
boutique will dynamically adapt to the currently selected theme to better fit in with your
preferred look and feel.
So I didn't realize this before, Wimpy, because I've always used it after immediate
installation but did the software boutique not follow my desktop theme in the past?
Well, it did in the usual places but then within the application itself, it has its
own CSS to style it and it didn't take any cues from, or it didn't take many cues from
the theme that you actually had running to, you know, blend in and it will do that now.
Oh, I see.
So can you give me a little peek behind the curtain?
Like are you doing the work on this?
Are you paying somebody to do the work on this?
How are they getting paid and that kind of stuff?
So most of this work is – well, all the front-end work is being done by Luke Corwell
who is a contributor to Ubuntu Mate.
Yeah.
We've talked about him before.
Definitely.
Yeah.
He's responsible for all the cool stuff you see in Ubuntu Mate welcome and the software
boutique and if you use Razer peripherals, you are probably using his other project which
is called Polychromatic which is the tool to do all of the RGB configuration.
Cool.
Okay.
Well, what a gentleman because this is one of my favorite, favorite experiences on Ubuntu
Mate.
Like I honestly would – for internal uses, it has tipped the scale in the past to know
that I could – you log in after your first log in.
You run this thing and now with the cued installations, you just go through and all of the great applications
for Linux are in here.
It's one of those things that makes me actually think, okay, I could install this on someone.
I was setting them up on Linux for the first time and I wouldn't have to be there and
walk them through.
I could just give them this and be like, call me when you have problems.
Yeah.
Even on systems where I've run the Unity desktop, I've still got out of my way to
install it.
Yeah, right?
Why not?
Boom.
We hear that a lot from people.
We hear a lot that people install welcome on other Ubuntu flavors just to get the boutique.
So there are other advantages for us.
It's easier to maintain the boutique when it's decoupled from welcome.
So I don't know how much you can say but I – if a great software –
Well, it's open source.
I can tell you whatever you want to know.
Well, so if a great software project like this comes along that happens to hit things
like snap packages, happens to have an apt, get back in, happens to use PPAs, what could
I as a user do to let Canonical know that I would be interested in actually having that
ship in mainline Ubuntu GNOME like the standard Ubuntu desktop starting with 1710 and beyond?
What could I do as a user to voice that opinion?
That's a very good question and I don't know the answer to that.
It seems like – I mean I know maybe 1710, that's too soon.
But in the LTS, what a piece of software.
You give folks an entirely new desktop environment but you give them this guide to get their
whereabouts, to get their bearings and get to the applications that they use and know.
It seems like it's that perfect kind of – I know this is new but this will help
and even just ironing out – I mean GNOME software is great and actually that is getting
pretty good.
It is getting better, yeah.
But just ironing out that extra little bit of friction would be really nice and a totally
new desktop environment.
I'd like to see we set the same person down in front of clean Windows laptop, clean Linux
laptop.
You got this.
You got the Windows Store.
Have at it.
Where are you going to be in a day?
We should bring Will on.
I'm going to try to get Will Cook.
I'm going to ask him because I really want this.
It's so great that I install it even on mainline Ubuntu desktop.
Oh, yeah.
Why not?
Yeah.
So we did a lot of this work at the Snap Sprint last week and Will Cook was there as were
as Popey said earlier people from KDE and Fedora and elementary and there were a couple
of breakout sessions in the week where we have coffee and we all sat around and showed
each other our wares.
The KDE guys have added – well, they had Snap support in their store but they had written
their own interface for Snaps and they've now used Snap DGLib and it's cute wrappers
and they were showing us all of the new stuff that they'd added as a result of making
that transition.
So we're all doing a little bit of show and tell and everyone was looking at what
the new stuff in GNOME software is, what's new in KDE and they were all looking over
our shoulder at what is a very embryonic software boutique to see what we were up to.
It's kind of fun comparing notes and seeing how we're going about stuff.
I love it.
I didn't realize – has Canonical always ran this many sprints or is this something
that's picked up in the last year?
Well you might remember about this time last year, I was at a Snappy Sprint in Germany
and that was quite a big – and this was like the continuation of that effort but it
was a much smaller focus group.
I think there was about 30 people in total at this one and this one was more about doing
rather than making decisions and drawing up plans.
So these were – not that we've already decided we're going to do these things,
now how do we go about doing it?
And for some of us we spent the week kicking out a lot of code.
The great unblocking festival.
Yeah, right?
Doesn't it just sort of kick everything through and you make serious progress?
It's fascinating.
Yeah.
I mean for Luke and I, this was something that we wanted to work on for ages and it
gave us a week to actually – and it's the first time we've met in person.
So it actually gave us a week to like work on this stuff and actually make the progress
we needed to do to sort of kick this in a new direction because Luke has decoupled
Boutique months ago.
We just haven't had the time to work on it.
Oh, I didn't realize that.
I did not – I thought that was a recent thing.
Well, we announced it recently but Luke started this work maybe six months ago.
Sure.
Wow.
So this is something you've been thinking about for a while.
Yeah.
Smart.
I hope it takes off because it's such a great user experience and I really – I don't
know how much emphasis and underscore and exclamation marks I can put on this.
But as somebody who is feeling back through his years of trying to use Linux in the corporate
space and trying to use Linux as a creator and trying to use Linux as a small business
owner and trying to use Linux as a father with photos, like all of these things, I come
with the weight of saying this makes a difference.
And it seems – it's like one of those things that's so obvious but I want to – so
I want to go to the rooftops and I want to shout it around and say make everything better
with this.
Yeah.
Well, and it's like we – it seems like the time is ripe in many ways with the Windows
Store and everything that Apple has been doing.
Right?
Like consumers are now expecting this sort of model but the traditional workflows we
have for – we have the package management and those systems and all of that.
But something that says this is really the best of the best that you can hit one button
and have it installed at links and icons are here and it's just great.
And it does all the PPA math for you.
It does all of the snap math for you.
It just handles all of that and gives it to you in a cute interface where you can go check,
check, check, check, check, check, check, boom, go, make my system usable.
And one new feature is we're going to retain that curated list of the hundred or so applications
and we've had a search facility in the boutique for a while but it's only ever searched its
contents.
Now when you run a search it will query the entire archive and the Snap Store.
So what you see in the boutique is just the stuff we're recommending but when you search
for stuff it will interrogate everything it's got access to.
Smart.
So any Snap package that's been submitted since that thing's been released will be
available in the search.
Yep.
Wow.
So that's like the critical momentum pieces for Snaps and the whole ecosystem it feels
like that suddenly it's cohesive now, it's thought out, it's well rounded.
So let's talk about kind of related to this is package kit.
Now if I say package kit, you probably think that thing I think Fedora uses, well it turns
out a lot more than just Fedora uses it.
Pretty much all Linux that I use it, it is – think of it as an API that sits on top
of your package manager.
So at some point in time people came together and said, I want to write something like Gnome
Software or Neon Discover or whatever and I don't want to – or KD Discover.
And I don't want to have to write a version for DNF – I'm sorry YUM then DNF for Pacman,
for APT.
You want one API that you can write to.
Yeah.
And so that was the idea of package kit.
You can actually use it as a command line tool as well which is kind of nice because
you can bounce around distros and use the same package kit commands to install software.
Hey oh.
Yeah.
So there is some real like worthwhile investment here in package kit.
However, right now – and these things always change but right now package kit on Fedora
is not in a great space.
And so – and I think this isn't a big deal.
DNF is great and Fedora users aren't like married to Gnome Software.
But it relies right now on a library libdnf, pretty sexy name really, that is pretty new.
And they've just recently ported it from Python to C. So like when I say it's new,
it's like not only is it kind of new but they've also just ported it to C kind of
new.
So it's all kinds of new.
And they actually say in the read me they say libdnf is not currently – I'm sorry
is currently being reworked and is considered unstable.
Once major users like package kit and DNF are fully ported, a new stable release will
be considered.
In other words, Gnome Software and Plasma Discover, two front end center applications
for end users of Fedora workstations, especially Gnome Software, rely on unfinished work in
progress in Fedora.
It's worth noting that both Pacman and the app backends like the one for Ubuntu are in
a much better shape.
I think that highlights the whole thing here, right?
Like the value proposition is that you're pushing this off to some middle layer and
you – what you can do is only as good as the binding between you and what the end system
is.
Well, and you know what?
DNF is newer than app or Pacman.
And so they just – that middleman layer hasn't been finished yet and that's really
the problem.
And you wonder like, OK, well, how bad is it?
Because that was my consideration.
Like how bad is it?
Well, actually it's pretty shit actually to tell you the truth.
I was pretty surprised.
Like I wasn't going to cover it on the show but then I realized how shit it was.
I was about to say, is there a story here?
No, yeah.
Yeah, there is.
So libdnf doesn't support delta RPMs.
So if you're on a mobile connection, go screw yourself.
So libdnf just totally ignores etcdnf.conf – etcdnf slash dnf slash –
That's where I put the conf I don't want to use, Chris.
Right.
So like where you maybe turn on automatic fast mirror selection, package exclusions,
controlling network utilization.
Nope, sorry.
Libdnf ignores all of that.
Also, it doesn't uninstall things properly and it can leave orphan packages behind.
When you uninstall software, it won't necessarily clean things up.
Oh, that's less than desirable.
Yeah, it also lacks safeguards to prevent users from uninstalling crucial software such
as glibc, dnf itself, also libdnf itself can be uninstalled via package kit, and other
things that can cause complete devastation on your system.
Now these are not total likely scenarios but it's a bit of a shit show right now.
It's kind of amateur hour and, you know, full disclosure, they say that in the readme
for libdnf.
They say it's not ready yet.
So it's not like this is a surprise here.
But if you're using gnome software or other graphical managers, you may like you might
just not have any expectation, right?
If it works so well, works just fine on apt or sure.
Well, here's what I Yeah, especially if you're coming from Ubuntu and you're trying out fedora,
you don't even consider the fact that it might be talking a totally different language.
Here's Chris's recommendation, and this is really gonna, this is gonna be fine.
If you want to discover software via gnome software, if you want to discover something
new and install it, you're gonna you're gonna be fine.
Maybe just do your updates from the command line or using the fedora.
That's not available anymore.
Just use your just use just do dnf update and upgrade.
Just do that because dnf will do on the command line, it will do delta packages, it'll also
under and when you uninstall software, just use dnf from the command line.
The command line syntax for dnf is exceptionally simple.
So I normally wouldn't say like, go to the terminal, but dnf is like simple human readable
commands.
Here's the problem with dnf though, when you tell someone to use it, they're gonna ask
you what it stands for.
What does I don't remember anymore.
What does it stand for?
Do you remember?
Does anybody in the mumble room remember what dnf stands for?
I thought it was something kind of womp womp.
Kind of meh.
Like does not stand for much.
Dandified yum.
Oh, it's down.
Oh, okay.
That's what Yeah, of course.
Yum.
Right.
Of course.
Were you gonna say that w w?
It's usually do did not finish in other Oh, yeah, that's no dude.
That's lib dnf.
Yeah, which is back Yeah, yeah, you know, it's just something to know about.
I don't think anybody listening to this shows using package kit in the command line.
If you're just adding new applications from either goo either plasma discover like an
API type, you know, yeah.
And probably by fedora 28.
This isn't going to be an issue anymore.
This blog post over at control dot blog, wow, what a great frickin domain name, control
dot blog, which I have linked in the show notes.
It talks about how 26 and 27 are gonna have a problem, but by 28, this should be this
should not really be a problem anymore.
But it is interesting.
Like you said, it is interesting because we kind of think we talk a lot about there's
a common there's a common conception and this is gonna actually come into what we're about
to talk about that Linux is all kind of the same.
You know, you can use different distros, you can use pop OS, you can use Ubuntu, no, but
it's all kind of the same thing.
You can use Ubuntu Mate, you can use Ubuntu XFCE, you could use Ubuntu Studio, all kind
of the same.
And then when you switch over to something else, you know, you get the gnome desktop
on fedora, you're like, Oh, this is kind of the same.
And there actually can be huge, really, really like screw your disrupt differences in things
like package kit and what and other things.
And I actually think that's a that's an interesting topic to consider as we're about to go into
our next thing.
Yeah, you're absolutely right about that.
So this week, I don't know, I almost feel like I almost feel like a sec if you need
do you think?
Yeah, that's fine.
Do you think so?
Because I almost feel like I almost feel like I can start to see if I can, my heart rate
just jumped up.
Like I'm starting to get a little upset.
Could you see that?
Scoot back?
Because there's no video but you like the Westpane like theater of the mind.
Do you see me starting to get a little better right now?
Yeah, I'll get a little upset.
All right.
Okay.
Let's take a second here.
Let's take a deep breath.
Let's talk about digital ocean.
That's that's a good idea.
You're right, Wes.
Thank you.
You're right.
Because this is gonna help me.
This is just something that makes us all happy.
Focus on something that makes us happy.
Digital Ocean is so great.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go over there, create an account and then apply our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
One word after you create the account.
That's all you got to do.
And then you get a $10 credit.
You can spin up a rig.
They have my favorite.
It's not even the most expensive or the cheapest.
But they have a three cents an hour rig.
It's kind of like right there in the middle.
And the things you can do for three cents an hour, it's crazy.
DigitalOcean is the simple, easiest way to spin up some great Linux machines on their
amazing infrastructure.
They have data centers all over the world.
New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London, Toronto, Germany, India.
And I do prefer San Francisco, but if I'm going to spin up another droplet, I like to
get close to Allen Jude as close as possible.
Oh yeah.
Yeah, so I go to Toronto.
That Toronto data center.
Plus.
Speak and span.
You know what else turns out?
No NSA in Toronto.
No.
Turns out.
DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, create a machine on their great infrastructure
in seconds.
It's simple, easy to spin up infrastructure.
FreeBSD is also available, tons of great Linux distributions, and a dashboard that makes
it easy to use.
It's like butter on top of corn on the cob at a barbecue.
DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
And they have a new feature too.
Block, or I'm sorry, they have block storage, but object storage is a new feature.
Oh my gosh, I'm really excited.
And I'm just waiting.
I signed up for the beta.
I haven't heard back yet.
Yeah.
Literally every day I check my email.
See, when you switch over to using something like object storage, it means that you're
even a small application, you're building it in a way that you're going to be able to
use that code base for 10 years.
And the storage aspect of it too is the biggest bet when you're writing something that could
have images or media or anything with rich content.
Object storage is such a game changer.
And it feels like one of the last things to drop here in like, they made a ton of improvements
this year, last year.
Lots, yeah.
One of the last ones that seems to me like they're suddenly, not only is it simple, intuitive,
super easy to use, but they now have basically all the features you could get from any of
the major cloud providers whatsoever.
I mean, they've done the same thing.
With an interface and an API that none of them can even touch.
And it makes such a difference.
Clear upfront prices.
And it's fast and easy to use.
It means that in a moment before a show, before we go live, if we need a little additional
infrastructure.
No problem.
How many times have we done that?
A lot.
We've even done on the live stream is like a bit.
Like how long?
How many seconds can we get up new infrastructure?
We spun up like a game server one time.
Yeah.
Whatever you need.
It's so awesome.
So digitalocean.com, go there, create something, and use our promo code DOUNPLUG to get the
credit.
Thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged Program.
I love it.
I love that they're in the background because there's no other show where we've ever had
that.
We could do this more and go, like we've talked about going to a bar.
Yes, a bar would be awesome.
This is fun.
You know, we have a ton of viewers in Utah.
I'll go to Utah.
I know.
No problem.
I'm like, well, if we're going to, we should go to Utah, we're going to do it.
So okay, so there's a lot, there's a lot to cover here.
Let's start with, let's start with Tuxedo.
Tuxedo is a manufacturer of Linux notebooks in, I believe they're based in Germany.
I've never had an opportunity to be a customer.
I've never had an opportunity to interview because there's a bit of a language barrier
and they have a different market.
And today they have announced Tuxedo XFCE, which is their own version of Linux, a distro
respin, if you will.
And they've worked on something like this in the past, but now they're getting really,
really serious about it.
And they say it makes a big difference.
Tuxedo Computers has announced the release of their own highly customized version of
Linux.
Tuxedo's Ubuntu will be its own distribution based on Linux kernel 4.1.1, even though it
is based on Ubuntu 16.04, which does not ship with that kernel.
The kernel is expected to significantly increase battery life compared to Linux Mint, while
the Infinity Book 13 will go from six and a half hours of battery life with their new
magic sauce, special sauce distribution to 12 hours, 12 and a half hours of battery life.
Say that again for me.
12 and a half hours of battery life just by installing their distribution.
You install their distribution of Linux, not that piece of shit Ubuntu, but you install
their special curated spin of XFCE's Ubuntu, and you'll go from a measly, pathetic six
hours to 12 and a half hours of battery life.
Now that's something to brag about.
Yeah.
Also, by the way, XFCE, they say, uses less memory than Unity.
And the most important advantage for Linux beginners, all the necessary drivers and the
latest firmware are already installed, and adjustments have been implemented, quote-unquote.
Tuxedo's Ubuntu now available when you buy a Tuxedo notebook.
Well, I'm looking at them right now.
Are you?
Yeah.
How do they look to you, Wes?
Hey, I mean, not too bad.
Here's one that looks kind of...
I've never tried the Infinity Book, but Wimpy, you had a chance to review it on the Ubuntu
podcast, didn't you?
Yeah, we did.
We reviewed the Infinity Book Pro 13 a few weeks ago, and Marius, who's in the mumble
room from Ubuntu Fun podcast, has also recently reviewed the same unit.
Oh, really?
Oh, great.
This is awesome.
Awesome.
So what were your thoughts?
If you don't mind just sort of the elevator pitch.
And I remember that episode, but I wouldn't mind just a quick recap.
Well, I'm going to skip anything to do with the hardware, because obviously this announcement
is about them making their own distro.
Sure.
And I think this is probably where Marius and I have most opinion.
This is a brave move that they're making, creating their own distribution based on Ubuntu,
because when you receive an Infinity Book or any one of their computers pre-installed
with Ubuntu or one of the Ubuntu flavors, it comes already with the customizations that
they allude to in this announcement.
Okay.
That was my impression, like they've been kind of doing this.
Yeah.
And the problem is, is that, well, one, I can't stand by their claims for the battery
improvements because I didn't see anywhere near that kind of battery endurance.
And my understanding is talking to them, the modifications that they make, specifically
the kernel changes, are to try and improve battery endurance, but that comes at a cost
in that it's effectively a mainline kernel.
So Docker doesn't run properly, LexD doesn't run properly, there's no live kernel patch
for you, and snaps don't work, and a whole lot of other stuff.
So it's kind of, you know, not a very useful Ubuntu experience at that point.
That's something I really hadn't thought of before, but that totally makes sense, is
that, hey, suddenly you've disconnected this kernel.
Normally I think of having a kernel with more features that I'm adding onto from the base,
you know, config profile for a kernel, but here you have something where you have this
user land that expects things in the kernel that you just won't have all of a sudden.
Right.
Yeah.
Like ZFS modules, for example.
User namespaces, probably.
Oh, geez.
So Marius, does my summary sound familiar?
Pretty much, yeah.
I've been using the Infinity Book Pro for a review for like two months, and even back
then when I was in the show to talk about Magic Device, I was actually using the Infinity
Book Pro, and halfway through the show, the screen went off and I couldn't get it to turn
back on.
I basically did the whole show blind, and I didn't know what to do, and it's basically
one of the aforementioned kernel problems, or problem because they were using the mainline
kernel.
Okay.
So this is not encouraging, then.
Kernel 4.1.1, that must be a typo, right?
Is that a typo?
It's 4.11.
It's what it's referring to.
Okay.
Thank you.
So are we just talking about some mindshare here that doesn't really matter?
Is this the market that we're going to?
Would a developer be comfortable enough adding in a different kernel or making some of these
changes?
I mean, okay.
So what if we take a second here and we use the announcement of Pop OS as a lens to look
in this, because so Tuxedo has been doing this now for a little while, as Wimpy just
implied there.
So Tuxedo has been doing – this isn't their first time.
But now they're like serious about it and they're calling it a name and all that.
But does it change your opinion, Wes, when you – specifically because I've talked
about it on UserAir, I've talked about it on Linux Action News, but I have not heard
your thoughts about Pop OS.
Does it change your opinion of their announcement if you think of Pop OS or are we talking about
sort of one and the same here?
You know, there are a lot of similarities there.
Everything – it just makes me think about what the – what's the maintenance burden
going to be and how much is this really the special sauce?
And that's what I've been trying to think about for Pop OS as well.
Is this really – is this the kind of investments that I want to see?
I think System76 has a kind of clear idea as to what they're doing.
I'm not sure yet.
I haven't seen – I haven't really played with it or anything like that.
And so I don't know that much here about Tuxedo comparably.
I can see why a consumer vendor would want that level of control.
But from the Linux advocate side, the Linux power user side, it does – there's a lot
of compromises and there's a lot of this isn't what I want you to focus on for me.
I just want the hardware and that part of the experience to be the priority.
I'll tell you what I see similar here.
And I don't think they are the same thing.
But what I do see similar here is we want to provide something for our customers that
is competitive.
And I believe that is what this is rooted in.
Battery life being an example of that.
I kind of want to run through the Mumble Room really quick and see what everybody thinks.
I have definitely had my opportunity to share my thoughts.
Benton, would you mind sharing what do you think about things like Tuxedo, Zubuntu or
Pop OS?
Are they one and the same and do you – do you have any strong feelings about their announcements?
I haven't really tested them at all.
No, not tested.
But what is your impression just aside from that?
Just new distros coming in.
So here's an idea that I've heard floated around is maybe every OEM should be making
their own distribution.
Perhaps every OEM should be focused on the end user experience and Benton, they think
– here's the theory, Benton.
If every OEM wants to satisfy their customer, they should focus on the experience and ship
their own distribution that enables their hardware.
What do you think of that?
Well, it sounds good if it doesn't break any stuff.
I haven't read about the German distro thing but I heard some stuff about the Pop OS and
for now it's only been to GNOME, it's another teams and stuff.
Yeah.
Yeah, I agree.
From what I've heard.
Yeah.
What about you, Mariusz?
What do you think?
I think it's a great thing if more of companies like Tuxedo or System76 focus on getting their
hardware out of the box, working with the drivers and all this stuff.
But if the experience is like it was for Martin and me with the Tuxedo and Fintech Pro, when
the experience is actually worse than if you put a vanilla Ubuntu on it, then I don't
think you see the point.
Right.
So what you – I mean, I think to boil down what you said is you just – if that's what
they have to do to make sure that out of the box, when the customer opens the machine,
the Wi-Fi works, the sleep works, the resume works, the video works, that's probably
understandable.
Yeah, definitely.
Yeah.
Well, I can see that they want to ship it out of the box with their logo on the wallpaper
and that's totally fine.
Sure.
But that's not worth a whole OS.
Yeah.
Okay.
So it's not worth like a whole OS.
Yeah.
Okay.
So JM, did you want to chime in?
Did you have a thought on this?
Yeah.
I had an interview with Ryan Sipes from System76 and he talked a lot about making those last
mile improvements.
Sure.
Which they had a hard time doing while waiting for Canonical to ship new versions of Unity.
I believe his words were, we waited three years for features for our operating system,
right?
Yeah.
And it makes sense for them to do the software and the hardware.
So what do you think, so if I said to you that people were not buying System76 hardware
to get their OS, but they were buying System76 hardware to get the Ubuntu OS, then I think
Ryan's comment in that context doesn't reflect the motivations of their customers and far
be it for me to say what their customers prefer.
But if I was buying a System76 machine, I mean, the point I always made sure to emphasize
for 10 years in the Linux Action Show was System76 machines were born to run Linux or
I'm sorry, born to run Ubuntu.
They run Linux, but they're born to run Ubuntu, i.e. this company has made it their
mission to make sure this thing runs Ubuntu.
And that is why I thought they were a great vendor to sponsor because if you want an out-of-the-box
great Ubuntu experience, then wouldn't it be wonderful if there's this one company
and their sole purpose is making sure that these systems run Ubuntu really well.
They're born to run Ubuntu.
I'm not waiting for System76's features.
I'm not buying a Bonobo.
I'm not buying two Bonobos and a Retel.
I don't buy Oryx because I want System76's features to Ubuntu.
I buy them because I want them to run Ubuntu and mostly, actually, if I'm being honest,
I want them to run the Linux kernel very well.
That's what I want from them and that's why I'm buying them and I really couldn't, to
be honest with you, could not give two shits what features they want to add to the desktop
if they want to put a great theme on it, God bless.
And you know what?
Papa Bless have at it.
I really, I think that's a great idea, but myself, I'm going to format that shit and
I'm going to put Solace or Anagros on it and then I'm going to make it work for me
as a workstation that gets actual work done and I'm not going to care about any pop theme.
I'm not going to care about anything that's a special distribution.
I just want to make sure that this thing runs Linux really well and if I know it runs mainline
good old fashioned Ubuntu, then I know I can get my Arch Kakamani or Fedora shenanigans
working on this thing.
What does it mean to go from changes, maybe even a large amount of changes on top of an
OS or distribution, whatever verbiage you want, to do that, to make it your own?
You know what I mean?
It seems like we're okay.
We want, we recognize that the mainline won't be enough.
What is it?
A distro versus a fork versus an OS?
Right.
Clearly there needs to be some customization.
There needs to be driver customization or whatever, but what does it mean to change that
branding?
What does it mean?
What is that line?
I had a really interesting realization when I visited Dell because I hadn't really ever
gotten inside a company that was selling Linux at a massive scale.
What I realized is at a certain scale, and it's actually less than you would expect,
but at a certain scale, what was explained to me was you are working with Canonical on
a contractual level.
You get a partnership at some level where there's an agreement to work together.
This is official.
It's between two companies and there's money exchanged.
In that process, get ready for this one.
Because I think if you watched our Dell coverage, I think you would have the opinion and the
impression that Dell did all of the modifications to Linux.
Dell made the changes to make high DPI work on Linux.
Dell made the changes to standardize the Ubuntu installer.
Dell made the changes to do an after first boot splash screen.
You might walk away with the impression that Dell contributed all of that code upstream
and Canonical just fell backwards into adopting it.
While Dell did write some of that code, the reality is, and this is explained to me, and
if anyone from our friends at Canonical wants to correct me, please, because this is just
third hand that I got from Dell.
My understanding is if you sell a certain amount of computers, you become an OEM partner.
By doing so, Canonical does all the heavy lifting for you.
If you want to have high DPI support, if you want to have special branding, or if you want
to have a special theme, or if you want to have something that works with your wireless
chip that isn't upstream yet, Canonical actually does all of the grunt work to make that code
actually work.
Then they turn it over to you and say, here's your repo, here's your repos, here's your
image, deploy this on the systems.
What Dell has to do is they just have to figure out what hardware they want to ship.
Then they go to a company that their entire job is to make sure that their operating system
works on your hardware.
Their entire staff is intimately familiar with Ubuntu, and then they make all of the
modifications necessary, and they deliver that end result to their business partner.
In this case, in my experience, it was Dell, and then Dell ships that.
What's beautiful about that is instead of having Dell write software like they used
to for Windows, you actually have the manufacturer of the operating system writing the modifications
necessary to make it work on the OEM hardware.
The concept that every OEM, every Dick and Harry OEM that gets the idea of shipping an
ISO on an x86 box needs to write their own distribution is completely negated when you
realize that if you work at a certain scale and you create a business opportunity with
Canonical, they'll do the work for you, and you can call it Ubuntu legally.
Problem solved.
Then your customers that want Ubuntu can buy Ubuntu, it's called Ubuntu, and the software
is developed by Canonical.
And it is much more straightforward than Tuxedo as Ubuntu, or whatever it's going to be called.
What is that?
What are the small scale people do?
So I'll just chip in and say, yes, there is an OEM team, and you know, that's how that
arrangement works.
My understanding is Ubuntu are not the only distro manufacturer that offers services like
that.
And, you know, I would suggest that the likes of Tuxedo and maybe System76 as well, consider
what they're going to spend on engineering resources in terms of dollars to actually
pull this off, and whether they do better to actually partner with insert name of distribution
here who can offer those professional services.
So I've not spoken, I think Chris needs to take a breather for a moment.
I do, I appreciate you guys filling in because yeah, I will calm down because this is really
upsetting me.
I'm not kidding.
I've, I've not spoken to System76, anyone from System76 since the announcement of BobOS.
I don't doubt that I will at some point soon.
It feels to me like they, when Canonical made the announcement back in April that we were
downsizing slightly, and refocusing our attention on different things.
And as a result, the desktop was changing.
I think perhaps from an outsider's point of view, it looked like System76 utterly freaked
out and did what they thought was best for them and their customers.
Now, to be fair, System76 know better what their customers need than anyone else, right?
Because they talk to them every day and their customers give them dollars to make this stuff
work.
And they're super connected too.
Like they are, they're not like a company that just sort of sells a piece of hardware
and then they just, like they really are good faith.
Like they have employees who talk to their customers all day every day and they get good
feedback from their customers about what they like and what they don't like.
And they're getting support calls and they're telling, you know, they're working with these
people and okay, yeah, this is always something we get a call about.
Yeah, here's all you have to do to fix that.
I cannot totally understand that.
Right.
But this is reminding me of something in the IT world that's been happening for years.
Have we learned nothing from Android where every single manufacturer has their own strange
quirky version of Android that's bastardized from the original and is slightly different
and not well maintained, doesn't get updates and isn't as consistent as all the others.
It's a perfect thing.
It sells iPhones.
It's a road that sells iPhones.
It's a road that leads to the damn Apple store.
What I see is that I just don't want like, are these upstream chains?
Are these going to go upstream?
Any of these gestures?
Are they going to be updating us?
I suppose.
But you know, so upstream is something that gets tossed around a lot.
But let's take a second and talk seriously.
Let's like, let's be real about it.
So if you're going to make a modification that works with your limited range of hardware
and then you submit it upstream, there is not a guaranteed chance that's going to
be accepted.
There's no – no one knows what the quality of that code is going to be.
There's no saying how the impact on the overall ecosystem is.
Saying you're going to create something and toss it upstream is not the same as actually
having upstream stuff you send upstream getting accepted and integrated into the wider ecosystem.
Right.
And it raises the question too, right?
It's upstream's job to guard against modifications or changes that are only, you know, make sense
for your base but may not make sense for the broader community.
Right.
So say Tuxedo decides to, in a year from now, let's say that after 1804 ships, Tuxedo,
they're going to – let's just – I'm just theory here.
Tuxedo launches Unity 7 Legacy Edition because their customers have heard – they've heard
from their customers.
They got support tickets.
They got phone calls.
They got emails and they have tweets that all of these customers miss Unity 7.
So Tuxedo launches the Unity 7 Tuxedo Linux and it's great, Wes, because you log right
in and you just get the great traditional Unity 7 desktop.
My favorite.
It just knocks it out of the park.
It's really nice and standard and it's easy.
And so they, you know, but a couple of users have noticed that the online accounts don't
really support any of the modern services anymore because it's been a couple of years
and, you know, it'd be nice to sort of maybe get those updated.
So Tuxedo writes a patch to add support to the online accounts to make sure that you
can log into you name it service, Mastodon, so you can get your fucking Mastodon account
logged into Unity 7 and they submit that upstream and then guess what?
The canonical team looks at that and goes, yeah, well, that's great.
That's code for a desktop we don't maintain anymore for a social platform that's dominated
by social justice warriors that we don't support anymore.
So thanks, but no thanks.
We're not going to integrate that upstream, but thank you for writing the code.
And then Tuxedo writes a blog post about how they've written upstream code and they
submitted it, but nobody accepted it.
You see, there's no winning here.
No, there's not.
I suppose there's not.
That's the world of distributions.
I guess that's what's been frustrating here and what I was trying to get at earlier is
I just don't see the kind of tenants or axioms or clear thoughts behind what does it mean
for this to be a distribution?
What does it mean for it to be an OS?
Why are we doing this?
What are our changes actually be?
Because when it was just like modifications that include drivers or new firmware or some
customizations that are the boot screen or whatever, okay, those all make sense.
Those seem like a reasonable level of customization to be applied to a base operating system.
But when I compared things, like when we've talked so much about Solace recently, et cetera,
that feels much more like something that has goals, it has process, it has a philosophy
behind it.
I don't see these in that same light and it doesn't feel like an organic space for a Linux
distribution to really thrive.
I think the other thing that I find slightly irritating is seeing a company who's in a
difficult position like System76 or Tuxedo who clearly have customer demand or their
own internal brainstorming that's decided they need to do this and then tell us that
they've waited for us to do something for three years.
They could have contributed to Unity over those last three years.
It's the same argument that I keep seeing when a project gets shut down, a lot of people
pop up out of the woodwork and then fork it.
It's like, well, the reason this died is because for the last three years you didn't contribute
but suddenly you want to contribute after the death of the thing has already been announced.
If you wanted the thing to be better three years ago, you should have contributed three
years ago, not now.
Okay.
I want to play devil's advocate because I watched Ryan's interview on the Lunduke Hour
and at the end of it, I felt like he didn't mention anything new.
There was nothing that hasn't been in a blog post or replies to comments that we didn't
already know.
I was a little disappointed.
I was hoping to hear something new because what he did toss out there was something about
flat packs and snaps that didn't make any sense to me.
I actually did kind of understand a bit where they're coming from because he said something
that really resonated with me.
He said, we just want to make great things.
We just want to do great work and fuck if I don't understand that, man.
I really understood – like when he said that, I was like, yeah, okay.
I can see where they're coming from to some degree and I can almost actually understand
why they had no other choice.
I feel like they legitimately had no other choice than to do this and so I'm sitting
here like really super skeptical and at the same time, like I'm going like, yeah, I
kind of understand guys, why you had to do this.
So I kind of want to share some of that with you.
So let's talk first about Linux Academy, our last sponsor this week and we got to give
this in before I forget.
There's a lot of barbecue stuff going on and the summer is here and Linux Academy is
a great use of your time.
You're sitting around wasting time right now.
Use Linux Academy.
If you're sitting around in your car driving to work right now and you're thinking, man,
I wish I had a lifestyle that enabled me to live a little bit differently, Linux Academy,
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
I say this because before they ever became a sponsor, I had a lot of conversations.
In fact, I had conversations about producing content for them.
I had conversations about running shows on the JB network from them.
We really kind of came eye to eye on one thing and that was spreading the adoption of Linux.
Now this was several years ago now, which almost sounds like a stupid thing to say because
it's like so crazy.
How do you say it?
I'm not sure.
I can't say it post-Berman.
You are not that.
That's not your name.
Please, just talk about Linux Academy.
Oh, okay.
Linux Academy.
Please, I need to know.
Okay.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
And when we were first talking and then later on a couple months later we were talking about
how they were building out their virtualization system so that you could do these labs where
Where you SSH into a server and you're working on a real server.
It's such a difference because that's exactly how I learn.
It means when I go to – not only does it mean I'm going to test better, which is
obviously a benefit, but I think the thing that matters a lot more than that is when
I actually go to do the work, I have the confidence that I've done this before because I actually
did it in one of their hands-on labs and they have instructor mentoring too, like real human
beings to help you.
They have CERTs – if you want to go for CERTs, they have courses for that, like just
HyperCard.
Are you familiar with that?
They don't have courses on that.
No.
They also don't have courses on barbecue because they're focused.
They don't have courses on Windows Command Line Essentials or working with the IPX protocol.
They don't have courses on that.
But they do have flashcards that are forked by the community and made better and better
to help you study.
They have nuggets when you have just a little bit of time you want to do a deep dive.
They have a course scheduler when you've got a time frame and you need to just stick
to it, kind of like an exercise for your mind – linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
So I was looking at both Pop!
OS.
I kind of ironically – I have it installed on a Dell Precision laptop.
I have Pop!
OS right now out there.
Yes, you do.
I've invited everybody here to the barbecue, which is – how many people do you think
we have here?
I couldn't even –
That's a great question.
Yeah.
We have a lot of people here.
We have a good amount.
They're the best people.
And more than a dozen, not including us.
And I've asked them all to kind of take a look at it, like, hey, here is the Dell Precision
running Pop!
OS.
And I always snicker.
And one of the things I was really impressed with – and I'm showing the Tuxedo Zubuntu
screencast right here.
That's the – let me just mute that because that music is distracting me.
I think I would like XFCE more if it came with that music.
Yeah, right?
And looking at both Pop! OS and Tuxedo Zubuntu, I get it.
I do get it.
They – and I'll talk more about System76 because I get it more than Tuxedo.
Tuxedo is a joke because it looks like a house of cards.
In fact, if I'm not mistaken, their previous attempts have been pretty, pretty bad.
I'm sure you must have had some experience from their Ubuntu Mate attempt in the past.
So the review unit that I received had an Ubuntu Mate image on it, but they made a number
of customizations beyond the kernel stuff I referenced earlier.
So they'd replaced the Greeter – they replaced the GTK Greeter with the Unity Greeter, which
as a distro maintainer, as soon as I saw that when the thing booted up, I knew it was going
to be bad because I know full well that that breaks things in Mate because it pulls in
different input managers, so IBUS for example, and it means that the keyboard layout is completely
un-configurable.
So that was one example, but also because of that change and the way that Ubuntu Mate
16.04 is put together, they have this – this is something that they've created.
They have a script that runs on first login.
Now it's in German language, so I didn't know what it said, but I had it translated
since.
So it basically says welcome, and you click okay, but behind the scenes that does an apt-get
auto – apt-get minus y auto remove, and that actually removed most of the Ubuntu Mate
meta packages and software.
No.
Yeah, so that was the out-of-box experience.
Now these are considerations, so you know when – you can hear the full gruesome story
on Ubuntu podcast.
There's a full review of the laptop.
Yeah, it was good too.
You were actually pretty polite, if I'm going to say.
You were actually fairly polite.
Yeah.
I mean it's disappointing from my point of view because I obviously make Ubuntu Mate
and I've put a lot of effort into it over the years for it to work hopefully the right
way when people install it for the first time, so to think that people might be buying computers
and this is what they expect, that reflects badly on my work, and it also reflects badly
on Tuxedo.
But it's an illustration of the kind of naivety that someone who isn't a distro maintainer
has about how easy it is to maintain a distro.
You know, all I'm doing is changing the greeter and changing the theme with not a full appreciation
of what the knock-on effects of doing that might be.
A cynical person, Martin, might think that the negative feedback that you gave to the
people at Tux, whatever they call Tuxedo, that negative feedback might reflect badly
on the recent blog post where they talk about how their XFCE edition is better memory footprint
even Ubuntu Mate.
Yeah.
I don't care what they write.
They also took a couple of shots at System76 in that post, it's in German so it's a little
hard to translate, but yeah they did.
Yeah, you know, that's fine.
I mean they're welcome to make the comparisons that they want to make, that's fine by me.
So here's where I could kind of see no other choice than doing this and I have to make
some assumptions and I'm not saying these assumptions are correct, but I'm going to
make some assumptions to just try to share what I perceive to be their side based on
what I've read, talking in years of conversations with Carl and recently with Ryan.
I know every person in the System76 office except for the couple of new people they've
hired since I've been there last, but I actually met one of them at Linux Fest, two of them.
So actually I think I know everybody there.
And that third one, he's coming for you, watch out.
So I'm not saying this is not officially their position and I'm not saying this is the position,
I'm saying this is my insight, maybe it's an 11 year customer too.
I think that they have reached a point where they have maximized the leverage that they
can apply against the ODMs and the ODMs being Clevo perhaps and others.
And so they are trying to be competitive, they want to create a workstation, mobile
and desktops, that address creators, developers, engineers, specifically people who are most
likely to buy Linux machines.
People we've talked about on this very show and said, let's be real, new users aren't
coming to Linux automatically.
You have to introduce them to Linux.
Otherwise the people that are seeking out Linux are Windows and Mac OS refugees that
just want to get their damn job done.
And a lot of times they're writing software, they're in the engineering, scientific or
creative field.
And on top of that, System76 makes machines that are exceedingly more powerful than most
other hardware manufacturers.
Like we have Doug out there in the living room right now who has the Bonobo workstation
and he pulls that thing out of his bag man and it is the size of a skyscraper.
But sure enough, if it's not a powerhouse with ports for days and power for centuries.
And the Oryx Pro is the same, right?
It's nothing like Apple makes, it's nothing like HP makes.
It's similar to stuff Dell makes but it's still in its own category and its own league
with certain things plus it's Ubuntu.
Now if you're making this hardware and you've got these customers that are coming to you
looking for something other than a laptop that has four USB-C ports, you want to be
able to provide an experience that's similar to the competition, a complete hardware and
software experience.
And …
Matthew Feeney Dare I say, synergy?
Jason Kuznicki There gets to be a point when you start considering
things like super high resolution screens, LTE modems, dual batteries, other things we
haven't even considered that you might just …
You're just going to have to start making more and more fricking modifications to Ubuntu
that it's almost a joke to call it Ubuntu anymore because you've got a PPA in there
that makes kernel module stuff, it puts stuff all over the file system, it changes the way
things operate and now you're maybe preloading software like a blender, maybe you're going
to preload a text editor that people really like.
You're going to make this thing more readily available and just out of the box great workstation
for developers.
So you're going to maybe put something crazy on there like visual studio code or maybe
for strategic reasons you want to just totally integrate flat packs throughout the entire
operating system.
So there are these things that you're considering and then there are these back in the mind
problems you've had with support over the years.
Like a lot of times we've had to fix problems by just shipping people newer drivers that
aren't in mainline Ubuntu so that's often the fix.
So it'd be kind of better if we could just release maybe every three months, if we could
just push out a release every three months with the latest drivers that fix microcode
issues that make hyper-threading unstable and fix problems with your Thunderbolt controller
and enable the webcam or the fingerprint reader and we're just going to push this stuff every
single month and including that we'd like to update the theme and make it look good
and keep polishing the brand because we've got a person over here working on it all the
time and they're always making modifications.
Jesus, you really can't call this Ubuntu anymore.
And now all of a sudden you're at a position where what do you do?
Do you keep calling it Ubuntu because that starts pretty much getting you in, I would
think, in the sights of trademark issues or did you say, you know what, fuck it.
We can maintain this, we can do the Q&A before we ship these machines, if it's not ready
we won't ship it, we're going to base it on Ubuntu anyways, we'll be able to take advantage
of their repos and we won't have to host all that stuff so we'll save a ton of money and
we'll ship it on our machines and we'll put it out there and you know when people complain
we'll say it's Ubuntu but it's our own spin and honestly how could you not do that, seriously,
how could you not do that?
How could you not do that?
I mean it's pretty tempting right now, yeah.
I kind of want to do it myself.
I actually started an Ubuntu spin while you were talking.
Yeah, I mean if I didn't have the scale to participate in the OEM program where I could
just make Canonical do the work for me, this is the route I would go.
And that's why you see Tuxedo doing it, Purism actually did it early on, we didn't realize
it, but these guys are really copying what Purism did months ago.
Purism did this initially and I have talked to several sources inside Purism that have
told me that one of the reasons that they shipped their own desktop instead of Ubuntu
Vanilla and I've heard this from multiple sources that System76 was already shipping
Vanilla Ubuntu so they had to differentiate so that's why they didn't ship Vanilla Ubuntu
with the Librems.
Interesting.
So it's almost like System76 is going to open themselves up to more market competition
because there is a market for people that really want real Ubuntu because this is what
they need for their job and they want their machine, their laptop, their dev environment
to mere production.
So as I understand it System76 have said that although they're going to debut Pop!
OS for 17.10, they will continue to offer Ubuntu as an install option at the point of
purchase.
Oh very good, I think that's smart.
I don't think it's going away at all but it isn't clear to me what customer Pop OS is
looking to serve.
I've not seen anything in the discussions to fully understand that.
Well what if it is just somebody who wants a really great GNOME desktop on Ubuntu?
Like if Ubuntu is going to go all in on GNOME and Ubuntu is my jive, then why not run something
that's like the Mint of Ubuntu for GNOME?
I don't think you want to start labelling Pop OS as the Mint of Ubuntu.
I think that would be an unfortunate.
But you follow my drift though right?
There has been a market demand there.
Yeah so I mean the thing about Linux Mint, and this is another concern I have about these
OEMs going their own way as opposed to working with distros, is that there are all manner
of considerations that get made.
So you were talking earlier about the GNOME JavaScript backend, GJS.
That was recently added to the main repository for Ubuntu 17.10 as part of the migration
to the GNOME desktop.
But that came under quite a lot of security scrutiny by the security team at Canonical
because that has a short maintenance window.
So their questions were how do we maintain this thing that is fundamental to the desktop
that has such a short lifespan and is able to pull down code from arbitrary online sources?
So that was something that was thought about long and hard at Canonical.
Now I'm not saying that System76 are about to do this or Tuxedo are about to do this,
but somewhere along the line Linux Mint started making decisions about the governance and
the direction of their projects and they ended up with a decision which is you will never
get critical security updates by default.
It's those kinds of decisions that you can work with a wider group of people with security
teams with people with experience of putting distros together to help overcome those tough
decisions and present some insight that you may not have on your own.
So it also strikes me as a position of comfort.
So these are decisions that are being made both by Tuxedo and System76 that strike me
as short term decisions that don't reflect what we have coming over the horizon.
Linux has got a lot of really big things and because we're talking about System76 and
Tuxedo I want to keep it focused on the desktop here for a second but there's so many things
I could go into that are server related.
But just specifically on the desktop you've got Wayland coming down the pipe but it's
not I mean it won't be that many more episodes until we're talking about GTK4 and wouldn't
it if we were talking about the transition to Wayland and GTK4 right now imagine System76
and Tuxedo now having to take and Mint and Mint who just got to GTK3 with like a dozen
episodes ago now imagine witnessing them make the painful transition to GTK4.
It's a position of luxury in which there has been some refinement and stagnation for the
last few years and it is with that mindset that it seems like well this shit's going
to be easy.
You know what I just do this I just do that and I just put it up here on this and I got
the GitHub community and what's the problem?
And it's not until you have to really start doing some significantly heavy lifting where
these things are going to change and then all of a sudden we're right just like the
point was made earlier we're right back in the Android system where Samsung's delaying
their latest OS by six months because they got to make sure that the new Samsung UI works
with the latest version of Android.
Now as far as I know the transition to GTK4 isn't going to introduce the kind of theming
complexities that the not so distant past with GTK3 did but like you say just adding
a theme is easy but then maintaining that theme through new releases of the toolkit
can be a massive undertaking and we've seen this in the Linux community.
Just look at how many independent theme creators there were six years ago and now look at how
many are actively making new themes today because they have drifted away because they
got screwed over every six months every time they had to rework their themes and it just
became too much effort for a lot of people.
Yeah that is actually really true that is something I've watched personally some of
my favorite themes have died off.
Wow but at the same time I don't deviate from the from the position like I totally understand
why they've done it and I almost don't think they had any other option.
Even when you feel maybe that they're you know that a bunch of you is less focused on
the desktop or on what they're doing.
Well I if I could have if I could have like gotten a Doctor Who time machine or a Bill
Sh- It's in the garage.
Oh yeah?
Uh-huh.
Oh what about the Bill- I think Dylan's playing with it.
What about the Bill Shatner Bird of Prey that I can fly around the sun can I because that's
my preferred method of transportation.
It's cloaked I'm sorry.
If I could go back just six months and I could if I could have a if I can have a little closed
room conversation with Carl I go into his office where he's got his he's got his system
set up there and I would sit down and I'd say Carl I would say stay tuned three to five
months after this Unity 7 announcement that's coming and he'd say what Unity 7 announcement?
I'd say don't worry about it but there's gonna be something important it's gonna in fact
it's gonna also impact Unity 8 and that phone you've been working on for three years and
you're gonna be super upset about it but if I could just give you one piece of advice
and I'm like I'm like biff right now I'm giving biff like the sportsbook you know I'm saying
just give it six months and see where they go because I'll tell you I have subscribed
to the mailing list for the Ubuntu desktop because Will Cook is submitting stuff every
single week about what they are working on and sure enough if not every single week it
has it hasn't made something useful for the Linux action news about what they're doing
to make the transition to Unity from Unity I should say to Gnome easier and the things
that they're tweaking to make it a they're adding features that I wish the Unity 7 desktop
had then they're adding to the Gnome desktop so it just you know if you just hang tight
for a few months and see where things go hang tight till the LTS you know hang tight ship
it ship it and just wait till the LTS and see what happens and then by the LTS if you
don't like what you're seeing rebase off of that 1804 would be the thing to base off
if you're gonna create a distribution at that point I'm sorry don't call it distribution
if you're gonna create an operating system this is an OS man base it off the LTS and
give yourself a buffer to figure this shit out to figure out transitions to Wayland to
figure out transitions to GTK 4 to wonder if maybe you should have gone with the plasma
desktop to really differentiate yourself give yourself that buffer with the LTS but to go
with 1710 to go with 1710 they know better than that I mean I know they want to ship
the latest hardwares and they want to ship the latest kernels and they want to ship the
latest enablements but my god go with the 8 go with the 1804 you have watched Ubuntu
for 11 years you know that they roll this shit out in the in between releases and they
bang things around to see how it works and then they nail it down for the LTS you know
that you know that you know that you know that so why would you base your OS off of
a 1710 which is mid transition mid effing transition mid transition it is the most awkward
stage of what Ubuntu is going to be for the last 11 years that you have been shipping
Ubuntu quite literally not even the transition to unity was this awkward because you nailed
that you got it but this is it this is the most awkward moment in the last 11 years of
the Ubuntu desktop it's 1710 and it looks good I mean I'm really impressed but you based
it off 1710 I know right now I know right now it's 1704 I understand that I have it
installed I'm running it but you're going for 1710 and that's crazy that's crazy why
wouldn't you wait for the LTS why wouldn't you give them a few months to figure out what
they're doing because you know what it looks pretty good they're working with upstream
they're getting snap support built in to gnome software so it's not some weird canonical
patch set to the gnome desktop they're making sensible choices with extensions they're asking
the community for their feedback it's it is a clear transition already in its early beta
state it is a clear transition from the unity 7 desktop to the gnome desktop it's exactly
what I would think the system 76 customers would want would be stable simple transition
to know and what's pop OS shipping no it should be no it should be known three pop OS is shipping
known three what is Ubuntu 1710 shipping no no three it's the same thing so all of the
heavy lifting of a transition all of the awkward stuff all of the stuff that's weird and different
it's it's happening regardless and they're making it an easy transition pop OS is not
bad I mean the theme is not bad I kind of like it you did the whole show notes and everything
on it today right not bad not bad however it is nothing like unity and the thing is
the gnome 3 implementation that Ubuntu 1710 is going to ship with is a lot like unity
it looks like unity it's familiar it is an obvious transition path what pop OS is is
more like XP to Windows 8 I see what you're saying I mean it does kind of feel like unfortunate
timing you know when they when they previously talked about like the pop theme etc that felt
a little more natural like an immediate reaction something like okay well we don't know what's
coming coming now I think I think you're entirely right that there is going to be a
lot of changes and while system 76 does need to keep abreast of those what they have right
now I think is stable enough they're not in a huge rush to present this whole new operating
system that they suddenly have to support that they have it's like an entirely change
of lifestyle and supports cycle and all of that I I guess I guess it really doesn't it
doesn't matter as long as they offer the Ubuntu 1710 vanilla like if you have that as an option
install and that's what makes your corporate purchaser happy then have at it and then if
enthusiasts they like think it's a good idea can use pop OS and choose that it by by time
or build time that's true that seems like that's actually a pretty good way to go about
it and then system 76 will have the numbers they'll have that and they can see what's
successful but myself if I was going to launch Jupiter broadcasting OS don't call it a distro
if I was going to launch Jupiter broadcasting OS no way in hell would I base it on 1710
I might go 1604 to be honest with you but I would probably wait for 1804 really so I
if so what I here's where I feel like I'm at is I would probably wait a couple of years
to see how this thing plays out and I would probably buy it with Ubuntu for now and then
I would just you know see where pop OS goes see if they get a good community you know
and see if they start shipping some stuff I'm like damn that's a good idea and you
know like you'll know because like some of their modifications will start showing
up in the AUR right and you'll see Fedora users that are posting guides on how to get
that and Ubuntu users will have guides on how to convert their existing Ubuntu install
into more pop like if you start seeing that kind of stuff that'll be a sign that they
have a they have some they have some good momentum they have some success here and I'm
all for that like go for it and and then I'll just kind of sit back and wait and look at
and go okay all right I'll wait for it and I'll wait till 1804 version ships and then
that might be when I try it I mean I have a running now but I don't think I would run
on anything in production until 1804 right I was gonna say that you know this in the
same way it feels very much right it's like they're just like it's 1710 it's their 1710
except even more so right it's like the the beta beta where they're they're kind of playing
with this now it's just hard to have that kind of announcement and to have you know
the interpretation is is always going to be like this is the future no matter what this
is what you'll see when really there's a lot to come on both sides yeah to actually find
out what we're gonna see long term you know what gets me fired up about it and like like
a reason why I'm like so passionate still this is like the third show I've recorded
about it I'm still like super fired up about it is it seems like they are they are just
like they're just saying here Dell here's all the customers that just want a really
good Ubuntu integrated machine you want an Ubuntu desktop that has firmware updates that
come through gnome software and they just ship Ubuntu yeah and then you just want something
that has Ubuntu proper with a couple of modifications to make high DPI look right or to make wireless
work and canonicals done that development work like it's like the most proper Ubuntu
you could possibly get on your workstation that's now Dell yeah and if you would have
asked me I would have a year ago I would have said it's system 76 but it's not full stop
end of sentence that's a huge game changer right there that's a huge game changer right
now and that is a massive conscious decision that system 76 is made and if the pop OS is
successful then it was a wise choice and if they can really provide something valuable
there it's going to pay off but if people are buying their hardware because they want
a really good machine that runs Ubuntu they've really marginalized themselves a bit and that's
why it gets me fired up because I've been a customer for 11 years and I am I'm so passionate
about that and I'm so passionate about an idea about a hardware vendor that's pushing
this forward and it's oh man it seems like the riskiest time of because also at the same
time they're launching manufacturing that's everything right that's the whole thing who
man I guess we'll see yeah yeah I think if unless he changes his mind now Ryan's going
to be joining Joe soon on Linux action news oh is that yeah because I'm going to go to
Montana with Noah soon and I think the beard is going to fill in for me here on this show
how about that yeah is that good with you yeah he offered I'm like yeah man although
you might have to sit here and you might have to sit there yeah because I don't want to
mess with we'll be staring into each other so yeah yeah you'll be staring into his beard
don't kid yourself yeah that's true yeah and look away and then we've asked Ryan to fill
in for me on Linux action news for one episode you know and I don't think they're gonna talk
a lot about it but it probably come up so that could be that could be in Linux action
news is like I think we just we're close to 10 episodes yeah you are if you haven't heard
it yet it's like it is like a direct dose to your brain of Linux news and what I'm really
proud of and I wouldn't have I wouldn't have it's funny because I wouldn't have thought
of this ahead of time but there's a couple of things secret sauce wise that Joe and I
are doing for the show that I think are really paying dividends right now and you if you
listen to the episode half ketchup that's what it actually no it's not Mayo can you
guess what else it is miracle web dude no there's just some secret sauce in there that
we're doing that I think is is paying dividends and I think we do it I think we do an exceptionally
good job of busting through the news and and taking hours and hours and hours of research
and giving it to you in five minutes so it's like we do hours and like talking to people
behind the projects emailing people to get follow-ups running the system running it on
our systems and then we consolidate it down and and sometimes we even nail it under 30
minutes and it's Linux action news calm and hell of hell of a show I'm really proud of
the way it's coming together and so Ryan will be joining on that soon it's like those you
know like the you know like NPR or other things it's like the five-minute news update it's
like that acceptance instead of depressing world news it's like 30 minutes of awesome
Linux right so it's better in every sense yeah eight episodes mr. bitten that verifies
and if you haven't heard it yet it's I think the show is turning out really good and you
can get all the feeds and everything at Linux action news calm also you can find mr. Wes
tech snap the text napping over there check out the show it should be out probably right
about now as we're recording the show this one episode and then poppy and mr. wimpy just
wrapped up their live episode from FOSTOC live and that was a really fun episode so
go check out the Ubuntu podcast gentlemen anything else you want to plug before we run
not for me thanks no well okay very good of course I'm waiting for poppies IndieGoGo
project for the Minecraft all be jumping on yeah yeah and if you want to know what I'm
talking about go check out a book what you didn't what you didn't hear from FOSTOC live
is that we had a a vinyl record made of the no bonus tracks of poppy mycroft scenes that's
my favorite that somebody won well first of all I have no idea what you're talking about
and second of all that's one of my favorite things so that's amazing very good very good
I have vinyl records huh dang do you have a vinyl record player Wes I do I do it I do
it you and Michael Dominic you and Michael Dominic Joe Rissington won that yeah oh did
he no kidding speak of the Linux action news go figure yeah good does Joe have a vinyl
player though everyone but you does oh I gotta give him a hard time we gotta get one here
for the studio yeah yeah yeah all right well thank you for tuning it should have been 204
for the barbecue but it just landed on 203 oh three America's birthday we're gonna get
out of here we got more meat more meat to eat more cooking it's been it's been a lot
of fun thank you for joining us this week if you'd like to join us live next week over
to jblive.tv on a Tuesday you can go to jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar get that converted to your
local time jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact for the contact page and also linuxunplugged.reddit.com
go there now got that subreddit yeah yeah and we'd love if you join us live in the mumble room that's the best yeah that really
is if you can go over jblive.tv do bang mumble all right everybody thanks so much for joining
us and we'll see you right back here for episode 204 next week all right JBtitles.com oh we
gotta go boom oh yes that's right that's right so JBtitles.com