Is anyone using LibreOffice 6.1?
I haven't installed, but I haven't used it that much.
Hmm, have you noticed the native GTK message dialogs?
Yep.
And what do you think, does it enhance your experience to have that?
Not really, I haven't used it that much.
It's the kind of stuff that I, you know, there's a couple of blog posts and there's some people talking about it,
but honestly it's like, how many dialog boxes do you get in LibreOffice?
And why is that such a concern?
Even on this article, there's people commenting, even on the article itself, and I'm just, is that a thing?
Is that what we're worried about these days in the Linux community, is the pop-ups of GTK dialogs?
The things that ask me to save or not save?
We're really glad that those use the native GTK theming, is that a thing that we care about now?
I'm just asking.
Well, at least enough people did, or at least one person did, to make it happen.
Yeah, apparently.
I suppose that's always one of those things, right, it's not quite a fallacy, but it's always one of those things in open source,
where you can argue, like, well, is that the best use of time?
Does anyone really care?
Would this have been voted on for something to actually try, you know, putting energy to fix?
But at the end of the day, people are going to fix whatever they do,
and if we have nominally even better software at the end, that's probably a win.
Yeah, I guess that's a good point, Wes.
So I guess that is what keeps Linux kind of on the cutting edge, right?
When we go to lay out a file system, we have the guy that knows more about file systems than anyone under the sun,
and that's the guy who makes our file system.
And Apple doesn't put a lot of money or stock into file systems because it's not a sexy product that they can put a bullet point before, right?
So to a certain degree, I guess that's our competitive advantage, I guess.
Yeah, it definitely can be.
And I agree, like, I hardly use LibreOffice, not that it's not great, just thankfully don't have to use Office software that much,
but I could see a future, perhaps, Chris review where we're lamenting the state of consistency on the Linux desktop,
and that this little change would maybe prevent a future rant.
Right.
Yeah.
Definitely, in the case of protecting user data, dialogues like this are super important as well,
because users aren't typically very good at interacting with dialogues, and so removing any inconsistencies,
giving them a clear path, things they can expect, helps them get through the information.
Okay, so elaborate on that a little bit.
So you mean like, are you saying if yes is always on the right, and all of a sudden once it's on the left, then all of a sudden they inadvertently click?
What exactly do you mean?
Well, like in elementary we have some rules about dialogues, as far as never ever use yes and no labels,
because then there can be really bad logic conflicts between the messaging in your dialogue and what your action buttons do.
You should have an affirmative action that describes exactly what it does, and it should always be in the same position,
and then directly to the left of that should always be cancel, which is your do nothing,
so that users always have a safe way to back out of this and go, oh no, I don't know what this dialogue even means, I don't want to do anything.
Okay, interesting. So you're saying if I say erase disk, if that's all I'm asking, and I have a yes and a no,
yes, I want to erase the disk, or yes, I want to leave the disk alone, and no, I don't want to touch the disk, or no, I want to erase the disk.
Am I picking up what you're saying?
Right, depending on the messaging in your dialogue, you could unintentionally be unclear to the user about what you're actually asking them to take a decision on.
And then we even go further with using style classes that are available in GTK dialogues for where a destructive action button is going to be styles red.
Oh, yeah.
Right?
Okay, yeah, that makes sense.
So I like that, and you've laid all of this out in some sort of a specification format, so anyone that is working on the elementary project knows, hey, this is the way we do it.
Right, and I believe GNOME has the same human interface guidelines set up for how they expect alerts to work as well.
Well, it's interesting you say that, because I suppose to a certain degree that is what this whole GTK dialogue thing wraps around, I guess.
The fact that GNOME has set out, here are the dialogues, and this is the way we want to present it to the users, and then LibreOffice, up until now, I guess, is not calling those.
And so the user is presented with a different experience.
Yeah, and this is a big problem, I think, for cross-platform applications in general, because they have to cater to the different platform conventions of all the different platforms they're trying to ship on.
And it makes it difficult for the end users to have a clear and consistent experience.
So in your opinion, do you think that we should always let the operating system deal with the window decorations?
Yeah, absolutely. I'm a huge proponent of totally native apps.
Oh, okay, cool. So are you not on the Electron boat then?
Oh, no.
Really?
No, not at all. Not for a second. I think Electron's like the worst thing to happen to desktop development.
It's like the antithesis of good design on the desktop.
Now, if the only way to get more users on Linux was to offer them the software they want, and the only way that those manufacturers are going to bring them the software they want is through a common, I guess, application frameworks like Electron, does that change your perspective at all?
I don't know. I think that's kind of like a fallacious assumption because we hear from people that, oh, users will only switch if we have the same apps as Windows, but that's not a compelling reason to switch.
Like, why would anybody switch if they can just get the exact same stuff they already had?
What makes Linux a killer superior thing than just like an alternative is the things you can do on desktop Linux, the apps you can get, the tools you can get that you can't get on Windows.
So the experience is actually, in your opinion, is better on Linux than it is on Windows because the applications we have are better than they are on Windows or Mac OS?
Not in all cases, but in a lot of cases, yeah, and it's getting closer there. And in order to switch Windows and Mac OS users, we need to get to the point where our consumer and productivity applications are much better and not just the same as.
So what if we attacked what Wendell Wilson calls the Lotus 1-2-3 problem and the Lotus 1-2-3 problem was back in the late 80s and early 90s, Microsoft wanted to get more people on Microsoft Office and using Microsoft Excel.
But in order to do that, everyone was at the moment using Lotus 1-2-3.
And so what they decided to do was it wasn't just good enough that they could open those files because they had to be able to save them back out and send them back to the original user.
So Microsoft Office made a calculated decision to be able to actually not only read, but also write to Lotus 1-2-3 format.
And in doing that, they almost overnight switched users from Lotus 1-2-3 over to Excel.
So using that model where Electron, maybe it's not that maybe maybe Electron isn't the end all be all goal. Maybe Electron is the transition layer, the necessary compromise that we make long enough to get our users over to our infrastructure.
And then we say, if the application is great, go ahead, let's make native development. If the application isn't great, here is the better open source alternative.
Yeah, I think to push the Lotus 1-2-3 analogy further, it's a big problem that users data is caught up in these single companies that control how that data is stored in these silos.
It's a huge problem for us to switch people because we can't really build a client that's compatible with such and such service.
I think Spotify is a bad example. I think they do actually have an API so we could potentially build a Spotify app as long as you have their pro version or whatever.
But then you still have to keep up with it and you're responsible for it.
Yeah, and I don't know if you could build a Slack client. I don't know if that API is there for you to even be able to do that.
So there's some problems we have like that, or like YouTube that has these certain restrictions and things with the way that you can't really interact with their API on the same level that Google does.
So it's really difficult, I think, for us when we live in a world where now things are so siloed that you really can't technically be compatible with these other applications.
Right, users just have this expectation that they're using these proprietary services, they expect that they'll provide everything they need, they'll tie it in, and yeah, the operating system integration levels are in some cases non-existent.
Yeah, so it's kind of a big mess.
Yeah, I do think Daniel makes some great points. I sort of see it as like, yeah, Electron may be able to bridge the gap, it may be able to solve some of those just like, I need this to be able to work, I would like to use Linux, this lets me do it.
But that's not a reason that we shouldn't continue pursuing and making desktop development on Linux as good as it can be.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 240 for March 13, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's tracking its usual host as he heads back from scale. My name is Noah.
My name is Wes.
Hey, Wes, happy to be hosting with you again.
Oh, yeah.
We have an exciting show lined up. We're going to talk to you and give you some audio from what happened at scale.
And of course, we have the latest in Linux news, and we're going to start with a great story about how you can access your desktop remotely, even if you're on Plasma. Before we get to any of that though, Wes, you know what we have to do.
I sure do.
We have to welcome our Mumbo room.
We got to say hello.
Hello.
Good day to you.
Welcome. Welcome. Welcome. How y'all doing?
I'm doing good.
Crazy.
Very good.
That's awesome. So this first story is about screen sharing in Plasma in a Wayland session.
And basically, what the article says is that Plasma using a Wayland session now has the ability to share your screen or record your screen.
However, as most of you, everyone in this room is probably aware, in order to do that under Wayland, you have to have some help with the compositor.
The thing that like draws all of the pictures.
And then you have to deliver all of that information to the client application.
So, in a perfect world, we would do that in such a way that all desktops talk in the same manner, which lessons.
That would make sense.
Well, it just lessens the work for the developers, right?
And luckily, Gnome is on the precipice of this with Pipewire and basically Pipewire together with the support from Flatpak means that they have it.
They've created this API that applications can use to access screen content on Wayland sessions or in case they're running inside of a sandbox.
And with the various implementation like xdg-desktop-portal-kde or xdg-desktop-portal.gtk, they just need to support one API and they can target both of those desktops, all desktops, really.
Wow.
Yeah, so the client needs to create between them this portal backend and then the user will get a dialogue on which screen they would like to share.
Now, I did some more research on this aside from this article.
And one of the revolutionary things that people are really, really excited about is at the moment, OBS screen capture does not work under Wayland.
I've been bitten by that myself.
Have you?
Yeah, absolutely.
Especially, we were doing the Gen 2 challenge right here on the show.
I don't know how I was going to use that, but we had to come up with some alternative setups.
Okay, well, no more, Wes, no more.
It's going to be solved because now, yeah, it's going to allow you to actually screen scrape and use OBS.
Secondly, it is going to support multiple monitors.
So that was my next question is, okay, fine.
They have this this pipeware thing going.
It's going to talk to all this backend stuff, but is it robust enough?
Because I have six monitors in my computer downstairs and I'm running Wayland and I run into some issues.
So is it going to support?
Yes, it supports multi monitors.
I don't have any of those issues.
Is anyone in the mumble room using multi monitor support under Wayland?
Is anyone using Wayland and tried to do any sort of screen capturing or run into problems?
Hmm.
No, huh?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine of nine Linux users in this room and no one is using Wayland.
Come on, guys.
Well, I don't have a second monitor to go multi monitor on, so there's that.
Okay, single monitor though?
Yeah, single monitor on a laptop.
Okay, cool.
Anybody using zero monitors?
Hmm.
At work I am in several places.
Strictly yes, at work.
Well, so interestingly enough, I have machines that I actually do have zero monitors on.
In fact, the machine that I use for this very program is using zero monitors and I remote into it.
But guess what?
If that machine was running Wayland, it would actually cost me another hundred and some dollars
because I'd actually have to physically plug a monitor in because I wouldn't be able to remote into it.
At least the machines I use at work have no monitors.
You can hook a monitor to them, but really it's made to be used within a web interface anyway, so there's that.
Sure.
I like this idea of, and I'm interested to get your take on this, Wes.
I like this idea of using a common API for them to access the screen content.
Oh, yeah, definitely.
I mean, that just seems like a big win for everyone.
I'm also really impressed that I feel like the first time we even talked about PipeWire wasn't that long ago.
Right.
Looking at the commit history, it's making great progress and it's to the point where, you know,
a diverse set of projects are looking at integrating with it and using it to provide these features.
Yeah.
It seems like that's, you know, none of this is quite there yet, but this is like a huge one of the like,
can Wayland really even work in practice?
Right.
It's one of those roadblocks that seems like it's going to get knocked down pretty soon.
Yeah, I think that the development of Wayland alone has easily surpassed my expectations of how fast I thought it would gain adoption.
And, you know, they rolled it out in, I guess it would be 1710 and ran into some issues.
And so they're going to fall back to Xorg by default in 1804.
But having used 1710, it was way more pleasurable than I thought it was going to be.
I mean, I really hit a lot less roadblocks than I thought.
And so now to see them start to stack some of these newer, cooler things on top is really cool.
And when we were at the Ubuntu Sprint in New York, I had a chance to interview one of the gentlemen that works on the Wayland project.
And one of the things that he was saying was how they are repivoting Mir to be that interconnection part where you have a common thing for developers to target.
And then that does all the heavy lifting and talking to Wayland.
And I think that's a really interesting way to not throw a bunch of work away, right?
I think that's a really interesting way for Canonical to take a lot of the work that they're doing and saying, OK, the community doesn't accept this as a whole, so let's pivot on it and let's make this available.
Because when you actually have the technical discussions between Mir and Wayland, Mir was a better choice from a technical perspective because it was less work for people to speak to it because it was end to end.
Whereas in Wayland, you have this middle compositor thing that's sitting there that you have to like Kwin or Mudder that has to sit in the middle in between.
So when I start to see things like this and it supports Flatpak, I'd be interested.
Does anyone know if this could be done with snaps instead of Flatpaks?
Nobody knows.
I'm just wondering because it seems like that would be, you know, if you're trying to find these common things for everyone to talk to, it seems like in a large way, snaps have much more market penetration than Flatpaks do.
At least that's my perception of it.
I see Canonical knocking doors down right and left saying, hey Skype, would you package for snaps?
Hey this, would you package for snaps?
And when I take all of those and I try to use them on distros that snaps were never necessarily designed to be used on like Fedora, like Arch, they work fine.
And not to say that Flatpaks don't work, but I find them to be much more cumbersome.
Wes have you played with both of them and where do you fall down on this?
I don't think I've ever asked.
You know, I'm still trying to watch a little bit.
I definitely have used snaps quite a bit more and it seems like so far there's been more momentum on the third party side, the vendor software side on snaps of, oh yeah, here's your application, doesn't really fit into the distro model, snap it up, we'll ship it out, it'll just by and large work.
And it seems like the Flatpak project has been a lot more involved in a lot of the underpinnings of some of the OS essentials or components or at least the scaffolding right above that.
Sure.
And it kind of seems like that's where this fits in.
I don't know, I can't comment as much on the story of, you know, will that be used in the same way as snaps?
And I know snaps have some features that could be similar or could be mapped to these, but that doesn't seem like it's really been as much the focus.
Okay.
You know, and I think part of it, obviously I think a part, a large part of it comes into the fact that Red Hat GNOME team are really heavy into Flatpaks and so if they're going to, if they're, you know, leading the development or working heavily with the folks that are developing Pipewire,
then obviously, you know, the natural choice of a quote unquote universal package manager that is now getting segmented into multiple, you know, if you're a universal installer is Flatpak. I think there's an obvious reason that we have landed on that.
But as long, I suppose, as long as, you know, both systems can be supported on a large number of operating systems, then it may be good enough to work. It's certainly not ideal, but we rarely get to ideal here in the open source world.
Yeah. You know, the other thing, Wes, I'd be interested in digging in a little bit is why certain things work and certain things don't. So I'll give you an example.
X2GO obviously doesn't work and I think that's pretty obvious. X2GO is, requires some sort of implementation of X. So if you don't have X2GO, X2GO doesn't work.
But there are other things that don't work. I have had trouble with VNC in Wayland Sessions. I have had trouble with TeamViewer in Wayland Sessions.
I haven't tried the latest version of TeamViewer, but last version of TeamViewer, when I tried it on a Wayland Session, it would just show a black screen. I could see the mouse moving around, but I couldn't actually see anything.
Oh, well, that's almost what you want.
Almost. Very close. I couldn't click on anything either, which was even further away.
You just get to watch the mouse.
Right. But the nice thing is, at least so far at the moment, every distribution that has Wayland, you can pretty easily fall back to X and then that allows me to fix it, which is how I know that those specific issues were related to Wayland.
So though, and then like we spoke about OBS has a problem. You know what doesn't have that problem?
Simple help.
Really?
And I don't know exactly what they're doing. I know it's a Java thing, but it works on both Xorg and it works on Wayland.
I wonder if they've updated it for Wayland explicitly?
I'm not sure, but either they have and they're one of the most forward thinking companies ever or the way that they have implemented it, the way that they're grabbing the screen doesn't rely on the traditional display model because it's worked longer than things have been making noise about Wayland shipping by default.
I want to say it was even working before Fedora shipped Wayland by default, but I can't quite remember back that far, so I'm not sure which one came first.
All I know is I've never had a box that I couldn't connect to.
That's awesome. I mean, that's probably all you care about from your perspective.
Yeah, well, for the most part. Anyway, Mumble Room, we all think this is a pretty cool thing.
I think it is.
I think the API thing is my favorite part of all because I think the API thing sends a message to everyone that we as a Linux community are working together for once and working towards a common goal.
Because if there's one thing I get frustrated with Linux users about, it seems like every time there is a way for us to fragment on something or there's a way for us to take different camps, we do that.
And so the fact that we're targeting this common API and we have XTG Desktop Portal KDE and XTG Desktop Portal GTK, I think that's really cool.
Yeah, right. If we can do this right. And there's been so much promise. We have this new technology.
We're finally at a point where it's almost ready to be in our hands. And maybe it works for the like of all you do is just, you know, you sit on your laptop, you browse the web, you use a terminal.
Wayland's pretty much already there. And so now we're like reaching the points of, you know, you have a little more complicated use cases.
You're trying to do content creation. So as that bubble grows and grows, it's great to see this actually being picked up everywhere.
So it's interesting you bring up content creation because last week, obviously, we're at scale.
Yeah. And so we're sitting there and I was doing the Ask Noah show live from the show floor.
And the process to actually put us on the air requires me to be simultaneously twenty seven hundred miles apart.
I have to first I have to be in the J.B. one studio outside of Seattle and I need to be able to stop the streaming there.
And then I have to magically teleport myself over to Grand Forks and start my streaming there.
On top of all that, after I've actually streamed out, then I have to establish a connection to myself from the show floor back to my studio.
And so to do that, I was using a remote, a remote software so simple to connect back to and turn these off and on.
And one of the things that was absolutely invaluable was the fact that I had my Ting hotspot.
And if you go to Ting.com and use the promo code Linux, you too could have a Ting hotspot.
And what's great about the Ting hotspot, it's a dedicated device for using the Internet.
Now, why is that important? Because there's there's people out there and they'll say, well, no, I have my cell phone.
I just toggle the cell phone Wi-Fi or toggle the hotspot on. There we go. I have right.
There were numerous times where I had to get up and I was running to the bathroom or I had to run grab a piece of equipment or had to run grab a bag.
And I couldn't afford to not be with without my communication device, particularly because that particular dad forgot my badge.
And so I was using Chris. I was saying, hey, Chris, you know, can you come let me in? Can you come get me in? Whatever. Right.
So I wanted to have two separate devices. Well, if I had gone to, you know, whatever big box carrier and said, I want two devices, they're going to say, well, it's a twenty five dollar plan or to add on.
And then you got to pay the device fee and then we don't sell you the device. We like rent it to you at some insane cost.
And so, you know, it's probably by the time you get done with a thing, it's probably fifty five bucks. With Ting, you only pay for what you use.
So it's just six bucks a month and you pay for your usage on top of that.
What gets better is once you buy the once you buy that particular bucket and I start filling up minutes and I've used fifty one minutes.
If I have four phones, I'm only paying that six dollars per line for those four phones.
And if all four phones stand or one hundred minutes, we're great. And if we go over one hundred and one, that's fine.
We can share that next bucket with everyone. But I'm never paying for more than what I use.
And that meant that days like scale. Yeah, yeah, I did. I use a little bit more data.
I needed a little bit more data because I needed to be able to stream. But you know what?
Months like this month where I'm going to be in Grand Forks the majority of the month, I'll barely use any.
And next month when we do Linux Fest Northwest, which is the last weekend in April.
So if any of you can make it, you should. You'll see me there with my Ting hotspot with my Ting phone.
And I carry spare Ting cards inside of my briefcase. So if anyone wants to try Ting, I'll even give you a Ting Sim.
So you don't have to buy the Ting Sim. You can just put it in your phone. No, no.
How can you afford to do that? Because it doesn't cost that much. The Ting Sims, you can buy them on sale.
I think they're like four or five bucks. I activate Ting Sims and give them to people.
I said use it for a month. I don't even care. That's how cheap it is.
In fact, I was redoing my password manager and I didn't have my Ting account.
And I'm like, I'll just wait till the end of the month and then I'll then I'll turn it off. Why?
Because it doesn't matter. Because it's cheap. It's cheap, great service that works really, really well.
And we can use it to do broadcast level recording and production right off of your T-Mobile network or the CDMA Sprint Network.
They're MVNOs of both. So head over to Ting.com and use the promo code Linux and get $25 off your first month of service.
Or your first device. And a huge thanks to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
All right, guys, I want to talk about Ubuntu Mate. Ubuntu Mate 1804 Beta 1 has been released.
What do you say? Oh, boy, I haven't even gotten to the story yet. Ubuntu Mate 1804 Beta 1 has been released.
They are preparing for the distribution on April 26th. I'm sorry, it hasn't been released. April 26th.
With this beta pre-release, you can see what they're trying out in preparation for the next stable release.
Now they have some they have the website gives a little bit of details on the kind of user that might want to try the beta release.
And they give some examples of the kind of people who might not want to try the beta release.
But some of the things that stand out right off the bat. DPI, auto detection and auto scaling.
Oh, that is huge. And let me tell you, as a person who had to sit next to another guy that was setting up his laptop on a 4K display that did not have that particular feature.
It's real frustrating because what happens is you can't read anything and the windows take up some annoyingly weird proportion amount of the screen.
So you get this window that takes up like 15 pixels by 15 pixels and it's like, I have 4000 pixels for you to choose from.
And you're cornering yourself to the fact that I can see three of my available 15 options.
So the fact that it auto detects high DPI is great. And every display that we are buying here at AltaSpeed for in office use is high DPI.
We're not buying 1080p displays anymore. And I think those are going to stick around for a while in the production world.
But as far as like day to day people, I think more and more laptops are going to become high DPI.
Certainly more and more desktops are going to be going with high DPI.
And I'll tell you another little secret, Wes. I didn't tell you about my new toy. I got a new toy.
I got a Dell ultra wide monitor. I don't remember exactly how big it is, like 32 inches or something. It's absurd.
Awesome. Yeah. And I put it on a stand up desk and plug my laptop into it and it's fantastic.
But guess what? High DPI. You know what my laptop isn't? High DPI. So you know what's really great?
When you have a distro that automatically recognizes the difference between a high DPI monitor and a non high DPI monitor.
It's really fantastic. It seems like a great win too for like new inexperienced users because you know, you turn it up, you plug it in.
You can't read anything. You have to go try to find maybe where the setting is if you even have a setting for it.
So if it can just work, it goes so far to getting us to like Apple level polish.
It definitely eliminates the need to use binoculars while using your computer.
Exactly. Yeah. And you guys aren't just Whistle and Dixie. I had the Chromebook Pixel and that's not even a 4K display.
That's just a 2K display. And that sucker, when I would install Ubuntu proper, I think the last version I had on was like 14.04, maybe 16.04.
And it didn't automatically scale. Trying to read the numbers was so miserable that I actually resorted to changing the resolution down.
Then scaling up, then setting my resolution back because otherwise I just couldn't read what I was doing. It was that bad.
So it can be a showstopping problem for new years, especially if you're not expecting it and all of a sudden things are teeny tiny all over the screen.
But that's not all that the next beta of Ubuntu Mate has.
It also supports hardware acceleration for compositing that dramatically improves 3D rendering, particularly in games.
If you have the support for DRI in your hardware and in your drivers and they have improved global menus.
So I think Ubuntu, Wimpy, is he here? Wimpy is not here.
But Wimpy and his team continue to do a really fantastic job at making a really fundamentally useful desktop.
And I talk to people all the time. A good friend of the program, Chris DeLuca, swears by Ubuntu Mate, puts it on everything.
And he uses it as his daily driver. And I know that Chris has toyed around with using it as his daily driver.
My wife played with it for a while using her daily driver.
It's such a great operating system if you just want your computer to work.
And I think these new features, the fact that they are looking at hardware acceleration, the fact that they are looking at global menus, the fact that they are looking at high DPI.
I think all of these things lend itself to being really, really comforting and welcoming to new users.
So the person I go to, Wes, I don't know how closely you follow Chris's fiance, Hadia.
Oh, yeah. So she owns a like she works so hard. That's that's one of the things I really like about her.
She works really, really hard and she has a really deep passion for what you're for what she does.
So if you happen to be in the Seattle, Pacific Northwest area and you're looking for somebody who does acupuncture and really, she can help you with like a variety of things.
I never thought of myself as a person who would need acupuncture for anything.
And I don't really like needles, but she's got all sorts of other little remedies for things.
And so I had I think I had a stuffy nose or something like that. And she gave me this little this stuff in this bottle that I don't even leave home without it anymore.
It's always in my travel bag because it works so well. That's I mean, that's neither here nor there.
But the great thing about her office is if you go to her and use our services, you are supporting a Linux running business because all of her machines are running Linux.
Now, one of them I know is running Ubuntu Mate. The other one is running Ubuntu proper and that machine is getting a little long in the tooth.
And so they are looking at updating it. And so Chris and I were going back and forth.
We're like, well, maybe KDE, maybe this, maybe that. And one of the things I think is really worth considering is Ubuntu Mate.
Because Wimpy has designed this operating system from the ground up to be the kind of operating system that you're that anyone can use, regardless of their experience with Linux.
And the fact that he is concentrating on what where the next hardware is going to be, if she walks into Best Buy and buys a very nice computer, the chances of that thing having a 2K monitor or 4K monitor are high.
So the fact that Ubuntu Mate is going to work out of the box, I think is great.
Yeah. And it's such a neat combination to see the you know, you have this combination of a somewhat traditional desktop model, but with all this, like it's not only is it built on good foundations, but it has all this shininess they're able to add on top.
So whether you're coming from Unity, you're coming from Windows, it doesn't really matter. You can craft it into a desktop that works for you and still enjoy the benefits of all these features.
Yeah, I completely agree, especially with that panel layout, being able to switch between Mac OS and Windows or traditional Linux or Unity, all of those things, you know, it brings it all home.
And it's funny when you go to some of these Ubuntu sprints and you look and you're like, how did that guy get Mac OS to run it? Oh, it's not Mac OS.
Yeah, that's it's really something fantastic to see. What do you think Mumpleroom? You guys are being awfully quiet. Am I totally off here?
No, I think you're right on Noah.
I mean, you know, you can make it look like whatever you want. And, you know, I'm installing it right now on my MacBook, actually, and I love the way the stock looks.
Actually, I have no complaints at all.
Yeah, I think he does a really good job. I think that if you try to go away from green, that's been my one.
I mean, I do admit it looks a little too greenish, but I'm going to change that once I get it set up.
And actually, I'm half tempted to try out the stock NVIDIA driver versus Nouveau and see, because last time I did that, it broke the high DPI support.
Given this is a little bit more time to get proper and everything, I'm actually going to see if that works. If not, I'll go back to Nouveau.
But either way, you know, I'm half tempted to see how much their high DPI has improved.
And, you know, because I do have dual screens upstairs in my room and I've got a Thunderbolt display and I've got a Thunderbolt to display and a Thunderbolt to HDMI and a Thunderbolt to an HDMI connection on the computer.
I have tended to see how well the dual displays work under that and all that. But like I said, I'm going to change the stock theme because I have to tell you that is way too much green on top of one of those.
Yeah, I guess I don't necessarily agree that it's too much green. I think he actually does a fantastic job making it look great right out of the box.
I guess my point was when you change one thing from green, everything is kind of designed around the green background.
But I tell you what, if you have an inclination, Ben, to give it a shot, I would suggest you head over to Ubuntu-mate.org and download the Bionic Beta 1.
I actually already did.
Oh, you did? Okay, great. Because I'm sure they would really appreciate feedback for that April 26th launch where they actually sent it out.
And that's going to be a big one for them because it's the next LTS, right? So anyone that has an inclination to help, especially if you're the kind of person that can spot problems and are willing to fill out bug reports, willing to file tickets and then follow up and give the developers the information they need to fix it, I'm sure they would really appreciate it.
Oh, I definitely love Ubuntu-mate and how they're doing with the high DPI support and all those different things. Well, I'll definitely let them know about my findings and what I've done with it. So yeah.
Outstanding.
And also I wanted to tell you that it just booted in and it looks freaking amazing, my friend.
That's good to hear. Yeah, I always think it looks really great, especially with that software welcome boutique. I've even used that on other machines that aren't Ubuntu-mate.
I think that definitely helps newbie users unlike a pro user like me, but it definitely helps a new user to Linux or whatever to have that.
Yeah, absolutely. I still, I guess where I always see Ubuntu-mate fitting in the best for me is like where really nothing else works as well as Ubuntu-mate, inside of the cloud. So if you have, Wes, do you have a cloud workstation yet?
You know, I don't.
I've gotten Chris on this bus. He has, he turned one of his workstations, one of his really powerful ones into his cloud workstation. And in fact, he was, he was extra going into it remotely from while we were on the road over a tank connection, I might add.
Awesome.
Yeah, but that's where I think Ubuntu-mate really shines is in stuff like that because it is so low resource because it works so well with older hardware.
It means you can really drag out the life in some of your older systems. So we have a machine that sits out right by our back door as our technicians come in and leave and they check in and out and check tickets and whatnot.
That's running on a P4, on a Pentium 4.
Really?
Yeah, Lenovo on a P4. I'll send anyone a picture that doesn't believe me. And you put an SSD in that sucker and guess what? For logging into OS ticket and closing out a ticket or opening one, that works great.
There is no reason other than maybe some power consumption why we would ever change that out.
Right.
And I have a Raspberry Pi here that runs the studio clock and the on-air lights and all of that. And that's running Ubuntu-mate as well. I really like it.
You know, overall, the one place that I still will take Ubuntu-mate over every other desktop every single time is on cloud workstations.
When I need a desktop environment that has to run in the cloud and I have to connect to it remotely over X2Go or whatever it is, I use Ubuntu-mate.
And there's no place I'd rather store my cloud infrastructure than on DigitalOcean.
And if you go to DigitalOcean and use the code DOUNPLUG, they're going to give you $10 credit, which you can use to get one $10 rig or you can do what I do and get two $5 rigs for free for one month.
That'll give you a chance to try it. Or I suppose you could even use the $10 credit and get one $5 rig and run it for two months.
And the $5 rigs are enough to run a cloud-based workstation.
So visit DigitalOcean.com and use the code DOUNPLUG and get $10 credit towards your first Linux server.
Or if you're like me, use two of the $5 servers and you can actually drag that promo code out.
You can actually get more bang for your buck.
And there's a number of HA droplets up in the cloud and they have a ton of nice features like monitoring and stuff to make that even better.
They do. And you know what the other thing they have, Wes, that I really like is their API.
The ability to tie those servers and the control of those servers into a number of other things.
Now, we talk a lot on this show, you and Chris do, and on the rest of the network, talk a lot about being able to tie that into the IRC.
What we don't talk a lot about is the mobile apps.
And again, this is where DigitalOcean sets itself apart from the competition.
If you take, for example, Amazon or any of the competitors, there is an inherent advantage of being able to pull my phone out and restart my server right from my phone.
And there's an inherent advantage of being able to deploy and destroy those servers right from my phone.
And if you listen to the Asanoa show and you check out an interview that is coming up later, actually later today, with Yubico,
we can show you how you can actually tie this hardware-based device into your DigitalOcean account.
That is so exciting.
So that when you install a new server, Wes, you never have to worry about getting these passwords emailed to you.
You never have to worry about uploading your key. All of that stuff happens automagically.
And you can do that and you can try it for free. If you're like, yeah, I'm not sure if that's for me, try it.
Duo Unplugged, use that code, digitalocean.com, and a huge thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
All right, so one of the things that seems to be getting a lot of discussion this week is the Ubuntu 1804 GTK theme.
Now, Ubuntu has looked roughly the same for years, I think, since probably right around 1204.
And they've had this traditional orange theme that when you sit down to this Ubuntu box, you know it's an Ubuntu box,
over a Windows box or Windows box, right?
And I've always kind of said, like, if it looks blue, it might be Windows. If it looks orange, it might be Ubuntu.
And if it looks ugly, it's probably a Mac.
You see, you know, in a window in some building, someone you're like, that's probably Ubuntu.
Right. So this is from OMG Ubuntu.
And basically, the article says, as many of you know, the community theme, as it's currently known, is shaping up to do something pretty special.
A canny crop of community creators have carefully adapted the ditch designs of the Unity 8 desktop into an attractive, real and pretty reliable working theme.
But alas, their work will not be part of the 1804 LTS due to release on April 26th, 2018.
Now, the article goes on to say that they believe that this is a sad decision,
that it means that the Ambience GTK theme will continue to live on until 2023, even though that theme was, oh, here it is.
So that theme was first introduced in 2010.
Now, I guess my question, my first question to you, Wes, is, do you care?
I mean, I can see how it's disappointing, but I also have a strong appreciation for, you know, limiting the amount of changes or really getting that polished layer on an LTS.
And while this new theme, you know, might make sense, I don't know if it makes sense to go through all those cycles when it can be something that will be able to be bolted on later for interested users.
And, you know, in the future, if it works out really well, then it will show up in later LTS.
Oh, yeah, no, that makes sense. Mumble Room, what do you think?
You guys, that's my first question is, does anyone care? Does anyone care what theme, default theme Ubuntu ships with?
I care about stability.
Okay, what about stability?
Well, lots of, I mean, lots of the time I want, I just want to chuck the OS up and running on some client's machines and I just want it to work.
Especially if they are not Linux savvy, if something slightly weird goes wrong, I don't want a headache of, well, thing doesn't work again.
Okay, so if it works, it's better.
So for you, it's not an aesthetic thing, it's a functional thing.
Pretty much, yeah. I mean, I would like to see a new theme and it does, the new one does look really nice.
But at the end of the day, less calls for me is better.
There's a reason I'm pushing you on that.
And the reason is I agree with you implicitly.
I agree with you that the priority should be in the user experience, not necessarily in what we subjectively think is pretty.
And we have to remember us Linux users are going to have a predisposition to think that the current Unity theme isn't pretty because we've seen it for so long.
Right. And so we're probably a little bit sick of it.
But I would challenge you because the Internet, I went to, I think I was in three or four different telegram groups and this particular article came up.
And people are saying, why aren't we taking the reboot of Linux as an opportunity to say this new GTK theme could be really great.
We could come up with a new GTK theme that really shines, that really shows what GNOME is capable of.
You know, maybe something that's a really nice dark theme, something like that. Right.
And I agree with all of that. I think that eventually we should get there.
However, I want to play a piece of audio that we captured while we were at scale.
If I turn my volume slider up.
Are you getting a lot of questions? Are you getting a lot of concern?
Are you getting a lot of excitement for Canonical's decision to switch to the GNOME desktop?
People are looking saying, oh, that doesn't look so different at all.
I said, no, we've worked really hard to make, we haven't implemented Unity on top of GNOME Shell.
We want it to be a GNOME Shell experience.
But we want to provide an easy transition.
So when people, when someone has 6.0.4 and they do their upgrade in July, they're not surprised new interface.
Okay, so what he's saying there is that they have had concerns from users that they're going to have the rug pulled out from under them.
And he's saying that user after user is walking up to this demo machine with GNOME installed.
And they're looking at GNOME with the current Ubuntu theme that people are used to and saying, yeah, actually, you know what?
That really doesn't look too bad.
That actually looks a lot like to what I'm used to.
I mean, I can see a couple little changes here and there, but roughly things are how I would expect them to be.
What do you think, Wes? Is that a logical reason?
Yeah, I mean, I think there is.
I think it ended up being kind of disparate communities, too.
And here we talk a lot about news and exciting stuff of what's coming up.
So it's really easy to get super excited and want all that latest shiny stuff.
And of course, we want Ubuntu's awesome.
They've done a bunch of great work here.
We want it to look really good and appetizing to users.
We want to try to bring to our favorite platform.
But I do think there is a lot to be said about limiting that change.
And there's even some consternation here about, well, couldn't you have shipped this theme just as an extra or somewhere as an option in the menu?
And yeah, sure.
But even that feels like there's a certain amount of blessing, official blessing from the distribution maker.
And if you really can't stand by it versus having that stability for users new or old, knowing that it just works, it's what you've been trained on.
And that from there, once we get this, you know, it's a big transition going to GNOME.
It's a big transition building this new infrastructure.
So if we can do that in a way where change happens, but at a pace that is enough to keep it going, but not enough to drive people away, like maybe that first Unity transition, I think that's a good thing.
I completely agree.
I completely agree with basically everything you just said.
And that is kind of where I think Nathan was going. That is where I think the Ubuntu design team was going.
And that's what I would suggest if somebody were to ask me for my opinion.
Let's make GNOME all it can be. Let's make GNOME shine. Let's show off all of the shiny bells.
Let's just do all of that after we have made this absolute hurdle of a transition where we are changing the desktop experience.
Because I think as geeky Linux users, we underestimate this.
And I have some unique insight because my company deals directly with this very issue where we are taking desktop Linux and putting it in front of users who they don't care what the desktop environment is.
They don't care what the operating system is. They just want to get to work.
And I think you start to lose perspective.
For us, we don't care because we've tried KDE, we've tried GNOME, we've tried Unity.
It doesn't matter to us.
We know how to switch if we need to. Not a big deal.
I can't count the number of times, Wes, that I have heard a Linux user say to me, I don't really care what desktop is on top.
What I really care about is what's underneath.
Now that can either be I want the bleeding edge of Arch or that can be I want the stable security mountain of the Ubuntu LTS.
But I don't care what desktop is on top of it so much as I care is what's underneath.
And I will tell you, as a person who puts food on the table by catering to users, the vast majority of computer users that aren't geeks look at their computer working environment the exact opposite way.
They couldn't care less if Arch is underneath or Ubuntu is underneath or Fedora is underneath.
What they care about is that the close button is in the same part of the screen every single time.
What they care about is that the file menu is easily findable.
What they care about is that the doc that was over on the left and that's how they launched their applications for the last five years.
That doc is still there.
What they care about is when the computer boots up that it has roughly the same look.
So they feel like they are at the same computer.
That's what the average Linux user is thinking.
And at least the average Linux user that was not necessarily put there by choice because most of us choose our desktop.
Now, I'm sorry, Mimic, you had a comment about people just changing the wallpaper?
Yeah, it is interesting.
I switched a lot of people to Linux and everything.
But what they do is they change their wallpaper and nothing else after years because they like to use their desktop.
As you said before, as always, as they used it before, they don't want to change.
But the only thing they change is the wallpaper. The rest has to stay as it was before.
That's a good point.
And so they can work like that, yeah.
No, that's an excellent point.
I really agree.
And I'm sorry, Wes, I cut you off.
What were you going to say?
Oh, no, I think you covered it.
Yeah.
I was just going to say, Noah, that, sorry, I meant to say that, you know, I have to say the Ubuntu stock theme is fine.
But in my experience, it doesn't really play that well with, what should we call it, other apps.
And I've noticed this very well, a lot.
And I think that maybe if they shipped something like Numix or something like that, like a different theme,
then maybe some normal users, like non-average Linux users would probably be happy.
That's my opinion, but I don't know.
Yeah, I guess I can kind of see that.
I just keep coming back to it.
It seems to be I don't see a lot of dissenting opinion on the Internet.
I'm not seeing a lot of people saying, oh, this isn't really a bad thing.
This is fine.
And I'm not seeing a lot of people saying it's a theme.
I don't really care if I didn't like it.
I'd change it.
I am seeing a lot of disappointment.
I guess that's the word I see keep coming up.
But we're disappointed.
We're disappointed about this theme.
We're disappointed in Canonical's decision.
We're disappointed that they're not making GNOME look like GNOME.
They're trying to make it look like Unity.
And you heard it in the clip.
Nathan said himself, we are not trying to reinvent Unity on top of GNOME.
We want GNOME to be GNOME.
We just want people that have been using Unity for the last 10 years to not feel totally lost on their computer when they click an update button and everything moves.
Literally, the entire interface that the user talks to is going to get ripped out from under them and replaced with a different one.
We need to make that transition as smooth as possible.
So I think Canonical's absolutely on point.
I think it's a great way to go.
And it's also it seems to me it also speaks a little bit like it's you know, Canonical's doing a lot, especially if you're going to compare it with something like, you know, with Mac OS X.
1804 is not just, you know, there is this this workstation desktop environment, but they're, you know, they're working on the back end and a lot of the core that still gets on the server as well.
And their cloud distributions.
There's a lot going on here.
So, you know, if they can't commit, if there's not enough resources to polish this theme, especially with, you know, it's really like a community thing that does into it, too.
And we're really, you know, we want to shine on every platform that we're going to do it on.
Sometimes that means things just take a little longer.
And I don't want to get too sidetracked, you know, and I'd rather concentrate on what we're doing right instead of what they're doing wrong kind of a thing.
However, I will say this since you bring up Mac OS, you know, Apple users are perfectly OK with their desktop staying basically the same for 45 years.
I mean, Apple has not really significantly changed the desktop layout.
I mean, I've still got the little Apple. I still have the file menu up top.
I still have the you know, I mean, little things have changed.
There's less brushed metal now, but OK.
Yeah, right, right.
But but yeah, no, I just I feel like there is something to be said about familiarity and stability.
And you see this in all sorts of places, right?
Like one of the reasons that I always stay at a particular hotel brand is because I know where the beds are.
I'm used to the paintings on the wall. I know where the bathrooms are.
Everything's kind of laid out in the same way.
And anybody that travels a lot for a living and I became particularly aware of this because we were I was just in L.A.
And one of the things I enjoyed was we went to Target and I kind of had a rough idea of the layout of the store.
We were able to find the things except for a towel that we needed because they're roughly laid out the same way that they're laid out in Grand Forks or Seattle or New York.
And I think that kind of familiarity is sometimes taken for granted.
So for those all of those reasons and everything we just discussed, that's I think canonical is making a great decision.
Dan brought up a pretty good point in Discord and I guess we could let him chime in on that if he's there.
Sure. Hey, Dan.
Yeah, I think something a lot of people don't realize is that like back in the old days when we had like GTK2, we had themes.
And the thing was that themes were super limited.
You could change some colors. You could change a little bit of styles.
You could change like some very surface things, but it was super constrained.
And nowadays we don't really have thieves anymore. We have style sheets and the difference is huge.
And style sheets are incredibly powerful and they can also be incredibly dangerous.
And if you went to any random website and you copied their CSS style sheet and tried to apply it to a different website, it just wouldn't work.
You would think that was insane. Like you would never expect that to be a thing.
But for some reason like Linux users still think that we have themes and it's easy, you know, but style sheets are really hard to get right.
And it's absolutely a good thing that they said, hey, we need to test this. We need to look for corner cases.
We don't know if this is actually going to physically work. It could really break things.
So to that point, have you looked at some of the CSS style sheets in GNOME?
Yeah, we reference Adwaita all the time just to see what they're doing, because in a lot of cases we kind of have to chase GTK when there's API changes.
Okay. If you were to rate it on a scale of one to ten, ten being everything is perfectly documented all the way through.
And I never have any questions of how what this style sheet does or what this thing references or if I change this color, this is what's going to happen.
And one is I basically change it, save, reload the desktop and see what it looks like.
How would you rate the documentation?
Somewhere between one and I really use Inspector a lot.
Yeah. And so anyone that has dug in, I'm serious. Anyone can check this.
I've heard this from a number of developers that the style sheets inside of GNOME are horrendously documented.
And so one of the issues that we are going to run into if we start willy nilly changing all of this stuff, what are we down to?
The date is the let's see, are we are less than OK, we have a little over a month.
We have like a month and a week before the LTS ships.
Yeah, we have a month and a week before the LTS ships and LTS that follows a somewhat less than perfect LTS that came out last time.
Right. We had wireless issues. We had a couple issues that came out.
But this is the opportunity for canonical to get the desktop right. And they have restructured the company.
They're going back to this old desktop. They have pared down to just the eight players.
This is an opportunity for canonical to shine.
And the worst possible thing they could do at the 11th hour is go in and say, well, we don't really know what these hex codes do.
So we change them and we reload and then hopefully we run into all of the places that it didn't change so that we can go and fix those two.
That is a ridiculous model, I think.
Yeah. It's like someone asking you to write the entirety of Bootstrap in a couple of months.
Right. Yeah. Right. Exactly. Yeah. It's really it's a month and a week.
So let's get through the transition. Let's go with the thing that works, the thing that we know.
And then from there, let's move on to making it a totally different theme.
That's that's kind of where I want to leave it.
If you want to learn more about how to change things, because there's going to be somebody out there and they're going to say, how does how does how does Noah learn that stuff?
Because I'm an I.T. admin, right? I don't have time to be I don't develop. That's not what I do. That's not what you do, Wes.
Right. Neither one of us develop desktops for a living.
But what I do do what I do is I go to Linux Academy dot com slash unplug.
That's what I do. And when I do that, a promo code is applied and I am able to get a discount on my Linux education.
Now, this is you have to understand something. You have to understand that I have I approach Linux education from the old school model.
I have O'Reilly books. I don't use them anymore other than to set them up behind my desk so that clients are impressed.
They're like, oh, you have O'Reilly books. You are well, that's essential. Yeah, right. Exactly.
There's some people that still judge me on that. But I was the guy that spent five, six thousand dollars in tuition to go to a Red Hat training course.
And then plus hotel expense, plus I'm away from work, plus I'm paying for, you know, eating out every night, which is really a lot of people don't understand.
That is probably one of the most expensive things about traveling. Not anymore.
Now I go to Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged my route, my Red Hats. I let my Red Hat certification expire.
I'm not proud of that because I liked being read.
But the truth is, I am a small business owner and I don't have to certify myself for myself to understand that myself understands what to do.
I just need to know the technology. And with Linux Academy, I'm able to do that.
I was able to learn everything I needed to know to get my clients up to speed on rail seven.
And again, this is coming from somebody who paid for the course in rail six.
And I don't feel like I got anything more out of the actual Red Hat course for the thousands and thousands of dollars I spent than the discount than the discounted course that I got from Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged.
And here's why the people that work at Linux Academy and I met them at scale.
These are true dedicated Linux users. These are people that have passion for Linux passion about the projects that they are presenting on.
And one of the fantastic things, one of the fantastic benefits that you get when you're working with a true dedicated professional that understands and cares and has a passion about what they're doing is they are excited to answer your questions.
They are excited to watch that light bulb go off when you learn something.
And that two way communication, that two way learning, that ability to say, yes, I get this and no, I don't get that.
That's what leads ultimately to success.
Right before I got on the air, I was having a discussion with another gentleman I met at scale and he was asking me, no, I want I'm working at this particular job.
No technical relation whatsoever. I don't have any sort of technical skills that I'm using at this job, but I like Linux and I want to move into a Linux job.
How do I do that? My first answer was Linux Academy Linux Academy dot com slash unplug and start your new career.
They're going to take care of all the hard stuff, spinning up the lab, spinning up the AWS instances, spinning up the servers, setting up the you know, the you know, the minutiae on top of it.
You need again, go back to a lamb stack. You need to set up a lamb stack. They're going to set all of that up for you.
And even if you don't want even if you don't want to change career, maybe you're very happy.
Maybe you're like me and you just want to learn something about something because knowledge is the one thing nobody can take away from you.
So go to Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged and make sure to check out their Linux courses and find your passion and get started today.
And a huge thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program.
So this I have two things that I want to get to this one, I don't want to spend a lot of time on it, but I just want to talk about it briefly.
Are any of you familiar with Simon from the KTE project? Yes. Sorry.
No. OK. Whoever said yes. Tell me. Yeah. OK. Talk to me about Simon.
So are you referring to Simon Quigley? No. OK. No. OK. Then I don't have any idea where he is.
Almost as cool as Simon. It's not quite as cool as Simon Quigley, but it's very close.
Simon is an open source speech recognition program that replaces your mouse and keyboard.
And the system is designed to work with any language or dialect. Now, here's why I was so excited when I first saw this.
I get people all the time that write into the Ask Noah show and they'll say, I have a hearing impairment.
I have a visual impairment. I have a speech impairment. I know for a fact I have one listener that has all three.
And accessibility on Linux is usually not is something that I would have not thought a lot of developers had a lot of time for.
I would have thought we had bigger fish to fry, bigger fires to put out.
But it turns out there's some really passionate people that are working on these accessibility options.
And what this does is it legitimately enables us to switch people to Linux.
So I'm over at KDE.org and you can it's Simon.KDE.org and you can you can click on for a short demo.
I don't have any way to show that to you, but the screenshots look absolutely fantastic.
And I have reached out to one of the viewers of our shows, a listener of our shows that I know for a fact would really benefit from this.
And I'm hoping that he can get back to us with a more in-depth review from somebody who actually relies on tools like this to use his computer.
Because I would feel a little weird trying to give you my opinion about an accessibility tool that I don't really have a use for.
I don't really have a need for it. And I wouldn't really notice if it was I mean, he can't if these tools don't work for him, he can't use his computer.
If they don't work for me, I just go, well, I didn't quite get it, but I just typed it anyway, you know.
So Simon.KDE.org, I'd check that out and see what you think.
And yeah, I'm not bringing on Simon Quigley. He's a great guy.
But as far as I know, as far as I know, having a Simon Quigley in your computer will not will not aid you in your...
It just doesn't scale the same way. He might be able to type some things for you for just you, but he can't help everyone.
Yeah, he's not replicatable. That's what it is. You can't r-sync him.
It does seem really important for us to have this sort of technology, though, especially if we want to be, you know, the open source operating system for the masses.
You know, we talk a lot about that with things like LibreOffice and others, but if we can't reach, you know, all kinds of people, it's just not as good.
It goes back to what we were talking about in the pre-show, really.
The we have to have not only we can't just have the same apps that exist on Windows and Mac OS.
We have to have better apps. We have to have more accessibility.
We need to be able to say to the person who's struggling with accessibility features, this is why you should use Linux, because it's so more flexible.
It's so much more accommodating of your disability.
Exactly.
That's great. So we'll...
Go ahead.
I actually met the lead developer once in Berlin at the Desktop Summit three years ago.
Oh, no kidding.
It's from Austria. It's a project from an Austrian university.
The problem is at the time it was very difficult to install because you have a lot of underlying technologies, open source technologies, so you have a lot of dependencies and everything.
So I guess by now the installation process is better, but at the time it was very difficult.
Yeah, it looks like it's pretty straightforward.
Again, I haven't played with it myself, mostly because I don't think I could do this justice as a review.
But that's interesting that you spoke to the developer.
So does he have a passion for helping people with disabilities, or does he have a passion for making Linux more accessible, I would assume?
Well, it started as a university project for him, and then they had a group around with a professor that was interested in that kind of technologies.
And so they developed, they started, and they're also successful, it seems.
Excellent.
That is so encouraging to hear.
And I'm really happy that there are people out there that are working on projects like that, and I think that it really goes to speak to the Linux community as a whole and how we come together and work together.
I think that's a really cool message.
So we'll keep an eye on that.
And again, if the gentleman is willing to share his experience, we'll have him participate in Linux Unplugged.
Otherwise, we'll play with it a little bit and let you know.
So I don't want to spend a lot of time on it, but just take a look at it and see what you think and be thankful that there are people that are working on things, even if they don't affect a large, proportionally speaking, a large number of users.
Wes, you sent me one of the coolest articles I've read today, and this comes to us from Hackaday, and it is about ThinkPad culture.
Now let me explain, I have to go in a little bit to ThinkPad culture before we can talk about this article.
Yes, there's some background and context.
A little bit of background.
So ThinkPad back in the day, back when it was owned by IBM, was largely regarded as the best business laptop out there.
And then they sold to Lenovo, and most would argue that the quality of the laptop didn't go down, but the quality of customer service would go down.
I worked with a gentleman who literally had a semi truck come pick up a entire office load of ThinkPads, this is back when they were owned by IBM, because they were having some small minute little issue, and that's just not how IBM operated back in the day.
They wanted to make sure that you had a class A computer you were paying for, and they were going to make sure you got it.
My first computer was a ThinkPad, and I've used them, you know, really ever since.
But basically a couple of years ago, they retooled the ThinkPad and they made a number of changes.
Prior to the changes, the ThinkPad had everything was built around functionality.
So the keyboard was built around somebody who bangs on it, you know, for 15, 16 hours a day, all of the function buttons that you would need.
When I say function buttons, I'm talking about, you know, insert, home, delete, all of those things were laid out in a way that basically resembled a regular desktop keyboard.
And around three, four years ago, maybe five, Lenovo decided that they needed to imitate Apple.
And so they went away from the functional great keyboard that worked perfectly and went to this chiclet style keyboard.
And they took away, they remapped the home, insert and end keys.
So that end and insert is a single key that you have to use function a lot, which is frustrating because you know what I use?
You know what I use a lot? I use end to get to the end of something. Exactly.
You know what the key I've never once used on a keyboard for anything intentionally? Insert. I've never I've never wanted the insert.
No one no one no one uses that. It's like scroll lock back in the day.
But yet they have they have that's that's the kind of idiotic things they've done.
There used to be a way I could seek tracks by hitting function and the arrow keys.
They've taken all of that away. And because of that, ThinkPad users were understandably very upset because they made these changes.
They there's no improvement. The laptops haven't gotten smaller. There's not any more space.
There's absolutely no reason that we couldn't have left the old keyboard.
And in response to that, Lenovo created a retro ThinkPad that went back to the old keyboard, that went back to the old, you know, layout.
Basically, everything was kind of the same as it was in the in the quote unquote good old days, except it had newer specs.
But they weren't new enough. They weren't fast enough.
They didn't put enough into it. And consequently, a lot of people didn't buy the retro ThinkPad.
So this article from Hackaday talks about the ThinkPad culture that is literally taking these older ThinkPads that are designed basically perfectly.
And they are replacing the motherboards, the processors and expanding these laptops and making them into laptops that can be used in 2018.
So tell me about this, Wes.
Oh, yeah. I mean, it seems like they've got a lot of they have some of the modernization stuff, right?
The biggest one for me is just there's there's like way more USB 3.0 and 3.1 and Thunderbolt 3.
And it seems like they're embracing that in a first class way.
Right. So they added the USB 3.0, they added Thunderbolt, they updated the RAM to DDR4.
Now, if you're interested in doing this, the motherboard that they are, the model that they recommend that makes it easy to swap these motherboards out, I believe is the X60, X61, X62, X200, X201, X210 and T60.
Now, if you're not familiar with Lenovo's lineup, product lineup, the X series is kind of the ultra portable and light.
The T series is kind of the hybrid in between portable desktop and super, you know, super light laptop.
And the P series is the I don't know what you want to call a mobile workstation, I guess.
And so they have a couple different options for you to choose from.
It's interesting that they have they have been able to get these newer motherboards into these older chassis.
And with the heat sinks and getting them to fit and getting the ports to stick out without looking terrible.
Because if you look at some of these pictures on the Hackaday site and we'll have it linked in the show notes for you, this laptop looks really good.
This looks like it was actually produced at Lenovo, and yet it is produced by a community of hackers, a community of hardware tinkerers, right?
Yeah, it really it really does, and I think there is a strong contingent of Linux enthusiasts out there or even just ThinkPad enthusiasts who have that love of the classic ThinkPad shape.
But we're really getting, you know, for a long time we talked about, especially if you're fans of not using proprietary firmware or other things, you're probably already checking out some older ThinkPad models for that reason.
But that hardware has really been showing its age, especially if you do stuff that isn't just, you know, a terminal and a web browser. But you want you want more high DPI stuff.
You want modern USB, you want PCI Express, all those good things that, you know, a lot of people these days depend on, especially if you're trying to give presentations, you're trying to create media.
Having that in this little being able to have that in a classic package, it seems like maybe the best of both worlds. Is that possible?
No, absolutely. You're absolutely right. Mumbo Room, is anyone else in here using the is using a ThinkPad?
Oh, I wish.
Mimic?
I have a 230.
You have a 230. OK, so the 230.
I love that guy.
So the 230, if I'm not mistaken, is the last ThinkPad that was that was produced from the X series before they switched to the new layout. Is that correct?
Nope. And it was a 220 was the last 230 is the first that has a new layout.
OK, all right. So you have that.
I love the keyboard is not bad as I didn't know the layout before. For me, it was no problem.
Did you? Well, yeah, that does explain a lot. So you never use the old ThinkPad layout?
Nope. Nope. I have I bought one X220 for my sister afterwards, and she's loving it. But I never used the page down page up keys that you have on the old IBM layout.
Yeah. And, you know, it's not so much that I use the you know, the page up page down.
It's really not even one particular key that I used a lot. I guess what bothered me was we didn't gain.
We didn't have any meaningful gains by getting rid of that stuff.
Well, as I said, as I didn't use the thing before, I cannot really see the difference.
Yeah, sure. But as far as your 230, though, you're happy with it. It's worked very well. I assume you have Linux on it.
This is a solid horse. I use it every day.
And you have Linux on it?
Oh, certainly. Yeah, yeah. I have a dual boot and I you have these slots. You have an M2 slot in it so you can add a different an SSD in it and still have a normal slot for another hard disk.
So you can do whatever you want. And if you don't want it, you take out the M2 SSD and you make a SIM card in it and you can use it even with GSM.
Yeah, I had that on my X250, I want to say, or X260, whatever the one I had before this.
Now I have the X270 and I'm actually in the process of perhaps upgrading to the X1 carbon.
And Lenovo has made some design decisions that I'm a little frustrated with.
You can hear more about that in in user and ask Noah.
But suffice to say, this is a really neat article and I'm glad to see that there is a community popping up around ThinkPads.
If you go to any of the grassroots Linux conferences like Self, you'll see a lot of ThinkPads.
You'll see a lot of ThinkPads. In fact, at Self, for example, they actually require you to present on ThinkPads.
And so for a long time, ThinkPads have kind of been known as the, I guess, the computer that Linux enthusiasts kind of rally around.
And that is where Red Hat has chosen to purchase all of their computers. And now Google, I understand, is actually purchasing X1 carbons for their employees and putting Linux on them.
So it's a really good choice. And that's not to demean Dell. Of course, Dell makes really excellent computers.
If you want the XPS, it's a fantastic developer's machine. In fact, I think that's going to be my wife's next computer.
My dad purchased one. He's been very happy with it. That's not to demean System76. They make great machines, too.
It's just that Lenovo just, because of my roots, I guess, Lenovo has a special place in my heart.
So to see a kind of community pop up around it, I think that's really cool.
And the fact that we are, I have a passion for older hardware, too. So the ability, the thought of being able to use a really old T60, that appeals to me.
It does look like maybe there's a few complications here. Some people who've reviewed them have not had the best battery life in the world and some issues with firmware updates and that sort of thing.
But for what you're getting, it seems like a great deal.
Yeah. In fact, I would argue, I think I still have a T60 around here. Maybe that'll be a project for Linux Fest. Wouldn't that be cool if we rehabbed a T60?
I'd love to see that.
Would you?
Hell yes, Noah. I got to tell you, I mean, I loved my T60 when I had it, but unfortunately it died on me and I'm like, oh my God.
So, you know, I've been craving to get my ass another thing, Pat. I just, I just can't, you know, afford one right now because I'm a broke college guy.
Yeah, I hear you.
I'm just like, ah, you gotta be kidding me. So, you know, I would love to see this thing in action at some point.
Actually, when I finish my classes, I'm thinking of coming up to Linux Fest Northwest if my dad permits and I might bring him along with me.
And, you know, I got to tell you, IBM, the company he works for is big supporters of Linux.
And I was thinking of, you know, bringing him and I up there and checking this thing out.
And, you know, he actually uses a ThinkPad T420, which is unfortunately still running Win 7.
But, you know, I'm actually thinking of bringing my Mac, which is running Ubuntu Mate on it and having that with me, actually.
Yeah, well, I'll tell you what I have. I tell you what I'm planning on doing.
I'm going to pick up my excellent carbon. I'm going to get Linux loaded on that.
Then I'm going to talk Chris into using my old X270 and then we're going to rebuild.
Maybe we'll build a T60. And Wes, are you up for doing that with me?
Heck, yes.
Well, that'd be great. So maybe that's what you can look forward to. I don't know. We'll see what happens.
But anyway, thanks so much, Mumble Room, for being here. We really appreciate having you. Wes, it's always fun to host with you.
Heck, yes.
Absolutely. If you want to check out more of this great content, go to JupiterBroadcasting.com.
Follow Jupiter Broadcasting on Twitter at JBSignal.
If you want to support the show, Patreon.com slash JBSignal.
Chris on Twitter at ChrisLES. At Wes Payne for you, Wes. I'm at ColonelLinux.
Anything else, Wes?
Go check out the TechSnap program. We should have some exciting new episodes coming real soon.
And of course, stay tuned for Ask Noah.
And we'll see you next Tuesday.
I promise you, wherever Chris is, whether he's in his RV, wherever he is, he's sitting there and he's like,
Noah just mazed multiple times over the weekend. He was making a point about coming in right at the right spot in the music.
And then this is the problem with guest hosting is I don't know the music well enough to know right where that spot is.
Perfect spot.
Yeah, I didn't quite milk the sweet spot.
Whereas I see Chris, you just hit play and he'll start jumping into it.
He was talking about when he's in the RV, he's like, there are times when somebody will be playing something and I'm like, show mode.
And then he's got to call me. He's like, no, no, no, it's not show mode. It's just if he hears Ronald Janky somewhere.
That's amazing.
Yeah, I know. I would do it too, actually. I just I don't ever have my theme music anywhere.
Right.
I meant to tell you, there is actually now in the Ubuntu Mate installer a minimal installation option where it only does like the minimal GUI and then with a browser and a bunch of utilities.
That's all it includes for you.
It's awesome.
Yes, I'm actually half tempted to check that box and see what it gives me.
And I will say that, like I said in the show just a few minutes ago, that this actually scaled my Mac screen right down to the proper setting.
And I am really amazed at this. And it didn't pick up my Wi-Fi, but it did pick up my Thunderbolt to Ethernet jack almost instantly.
I was really impressed with that. And all I did was plug it in right from the router.
Boom. Done.
Nice.
It worked just fine.
Yes.
Yeah, the wired stuff tends to work, you know, actually pretty well.
Yes, and I am unfortunately going to have to install the proprietary Broadcom driver after the install.
Maybe it'll pick up during the updates, but I don't know.
But I always download updates while installing Ubuntu because that way I'll have my Wi-Fi and all that other stuff working.
And I'm actually planning to stick around for the Ask Noah show because there are certain things that I need to talk to you about during the show and maybe afterwards.
Awesome.
Yeah.
Well, I'm planning to stick around for that.
And like I said, I wish to God that I could afford a ThinkPad right now.
But unfortunately, I just can't.
You know, and it really sucks.
Yeah, I hear you.
Hey, guys.
Hey, guys, can we go to JBLive.
Can we go to JBtitles.com?
Do we pick titles from JBtitles or do we pick them from Discord now?
I have both up.
I think normally we do both.
We'll do a search in Discord to see what people throw there and then also look at what's up.
I did put Discord on my laptop just to do this show today.
Oh, look at you.
But Noah, another thing I meant to talk to you about was the thing that I'm on Sprint right now with my family and there's such a pain in the neck.
So I've been thinking about maybe getting a Tim Sim card and just throwing it in there.
And I don't even have five bucks to throw towards that.
And I'm like, you gotta be shitting me.
So I'm thinking about, you know, waiting till Friday this week and chucking out five bucks and getting one.
Yeah, for sure.
Now, Ben, you're more than welcome to call into the Ask Noah show.
But just make sure you make sure to keep a family friendly.
I will. And I forgot to do that during during which we call it on love.
Love doesn't matter. Love.
Well, I mean, I suppose I suppose I suppose they should have.
We should probably always try to be family friendly, but it doesn't.
The thing is, the only thing you have to worry about is you just have to not offend Chris or the audience to the point that Chris gets upset.
That's really all you have to do.
My show, you say a bad word, I get a ten thousand dollar fine.
So don't do that.