This is Linux Unplugged, episode 22, for January 7th, 2014.
Hi, everyone, and welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's still airing
out the studio after a power supply failure.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
And when I say failure, I mean of the most dramatic kind.
Last night, I was repurposing an old studio Hackintosh, which is a pretty nice rig, Core
7, has about 16 gigabytes of RAM, SSDs, and I swapped out an ATI, like 590, something,
and I put in a GTX 780, and I was going to wipe it, pave it, and make it a dedicated
Linux workstation for trying out a bunch of stuff with the Nvidia card and whatnot.
And I get it all hooked up, and it's running pretty good, and I go to reboot it, because
I'm going to go Integro, so I figured, I've got the Integro ISO burnt to my DVD, I put
it in the drive, it boots up, and I notice the lights in my room start to flicker a little
bit, I'm like, geez, this thing doesn't have that much power, so I shut off some gear,
lights are still kind of flickering, I'm like, gosh, that's really strange.
And then, all of a sudden, I start hearing this kzzzzzzzzzzzzzz.
And it almost sounded like water, and I look over the back of the PC, and because of where
the fan was positioned in the power supply, the smoke is just billowing out, and it immediately
starts stinking in here just horribly, right?
So thankfully and this isn't my first time I've seen a power supply fire before so I I don't I don't panic or anything
But I I try stupidly tried turning off the PC by hitting the power button
That ship sailed already. Yeah, so oh yeah dummy
so then I just reach over and I kill the power at the at the
Search protector, but the problem is the smoke is just going now right the components have melted
They're going like crazy, and so I sit there from I have a moment of hesitation
I'm like well do I just let this I know it's not on fire anymore
but there's gonna be a lot more smoking do I leave it in my office and close up all the doors and then just say
goodbye to my office for a couple of days or
Do I rush this thing through the house smoke and tail and put it out on the front porch?
And I opted to go that route because this because I was just like I gotta have my office back to do the show
I and I rushed it out and put it on the front porch
And then I like had to abandon the office for the rest of the evening cuz it was just so strong
And it's funny cuz my son's coming down the stairs and the first thing he says and it cuz I'm talking to Angela about what?
Just happened it all happened so fast, and he's coming down the stairs, and he goes oh it smells really good in here
I like that. What are you cooking dad?
And then by the time he gets to the bottom of series like oh that smells horrible
It was kind of a crazy and so now I'm out my I was gonna build this awesome Linux workstation
Because as we're as we move to the new studio in March
We're gonna be redoing all the computer layouts, and I thought okay well
I'm gonna get myself set up with a nice Linux workstation at the new studio
I'll get it all loaded up with arch and steam and all that kind of stuff
And I'll have an HDMI feed to the live stream so I can do some you know
Let's plays just on the stream when I want so I'm getting this thing all configured like with all these hopes and dreams and then boom
Fire happens and now all of the components of the computer just reek in the brand new
GTX 780 I got
Totally smells to high hell and and this was like one of these purchases I get where I'm like well
You know what it's it's 2013 if I buy this right now. I'm gonna use it in the new studio
This is gonna be a tax write-off right you would think yeah, yeah, so now
I'm now I'm worried like when I fire up that graphics card if it still works after a power supply freak out like that
You know the components could be damaged, and that's a really high voltage piece of equipment
So that's if anything's gonna get damaged. It's gonna be that and so it could be totally fried now
I don't know, but I don't want to plug it in anything
So I'm worried it's gonna fire it up and make the whole room stink all over again
So well, that's when you take it to a Starbucks. You know and you just set yourself up on a table
I'm a real jerk you can tell yeah, you go to somewhere
You don't really have anything invested into it. You know this is whatever and then just act all surprised when it catches on fire
Yeah, no a chair and think there's integros is fault
No what it was it was probably switching a tea out in video. It was putting the
Yeah, you know probably the video cards pulling more power
Although this is a high-end
Thousand watt power supply because I got a really good one because it was the wire cast machine and it ran
24-7 and it was our production machine
So I put like I went high-end components in all of it and wonder if it's still under warranty because that sounds
Maybe but you know how we were having problems with that hackintosh. Oh, yeah
Yeah, this might mean this power supply might have been failing for a while now that I think about it. Oh that one
Yes, okay. Yeah, that could be why yeah, so I'm wondering and and so I think what happened was is when I put the blank
D or when I put that was gonna burn a DVD and I put it in the drive and I think just spinning up the optical
Media was just the straw that broke the power supplies back and there you had it. Jeez. Jeez. Well, I'm glad no one was hurt
And yeah, just a stinkiness nothing a good call on taking it outside opening up windows a fast track to getting the fire department called
I know
I've been there myself. I actually had that happen once all the all the smoke detectors here are connected
So I was a little worried. Yeah
The whole house would start buzzing like crazy and didn't want that either
Yeah, usually there's like a thr- I think it's like a three second delay and then it's like I've wasted ours
Anyway, it's the same thing and then it's like after three seconds. It's all over. They're all going off. Yeah, I wanted to play Steam
All right. Well, I got some feedback to get to Noah wrote in
So with some follow-up to our predictions episode that we had a ways back now before I get to this
I want to just mention for people who maybe have just started listening to Linux unplugged
One of the things that we do here on this show is we do follow up to the big show Linux action show which gets so
Much email that we just simply cannot get to it all
So a lot of times in this follow-up section will cover
We'll pick up on threads that were started in the last and this here from Noah's is one of those exact threads
So Noah writes in he says in the predictions episode you talked about the death of Microsoft
Let me start out and say I do not believe this will be happening anytime soon
I think Alan Mulally will become the CEO of Microsoft and will think the open source closed argument is similar to the two nerds is
Similar to two nerds sitting in a room debating Batman versus Superman
I think Mulally will make a new structure for Windows
The basic version of Windows will be based on an open operating system that relies on a central server to operate the machine similar to how
Chromebooks rely on Google for services, then
I think Microsoft will release a pro version of Windows that really will be closed and have all the goodness badness Windows currently has
Here's the twist in an enterprise environment basic workers will have the basic version of Windows
Why IT admins will have top and top level execs will have the pro version this pro version will give them tools to control and monitor
the basic versions of
Windows everything from version various levels of access to automatically generated reports on productivity based on time spent on certain apps
This will give Microsoft a competitive advantage over their newest business enemy Google
this is all this also allows Microsoft to further push office into the subscription service because basic users will have to pay to have an
Advanced feature not offered in web apps. Don't get me wrong. I'm far from a Microsoft lover
I deep down which LibreOffice and openSUSE could make this happen
And ultimately the Linux user space is more concerned with defining what is good and what isn't good for the Linux community
Who knows maybe I've just had one too many bottles of New Year's cheer anyway
Thanks to you and Angela the rest of the JB team for bringing the highest quality content any nerd could hope for just remember every
Week you make a nervous Windows user a little less scared of switching to Linux happy 2014 nice nice
Yeah, I actually agree with them for two reasons one. They they are basically pushing my argument for
Microsoft's remaining an enterprise
Situation that's true. They're excellent for that and I would say that they will continue to own the American
Enterprise situation they will not under any circumstances be doing wondrous things overseas
I I just don't I can see that I could see that yeah, but American yeah
I think that's true
So one thing that is really prevalent right now not talked a lot about is a lot of our apps that we use on mobile
Devices have in some cases literally Google Analytics, but in a lot of cases
There's a lot of different analytics companies that are really actually tracking all your activity in these apps to a great extent now it varies
Of course depending on the app and the developer
But they can get down to how much time you spend in a particular function of the app what other apps you switched from
The location the geolocation you ran it from the Wi-Fi network all these things the time you spent doing different things in the app
Wouldn't it be interesting like like he's saying here wouldn't it be interesting for Microsoft to say well
You know what we're gonna. Do we're gonna
We're gonna take those kinds of analytics and because we're appifying the desktop
We're gonna apply that kind of analytics at the enterprise space
And just like where you go into group policy
And you set enterprise wide policies for Windows machines and active director where you set enterprise level access controls and the event log
Where you can have well not really centralized logging like you get with this log
But you can have a logging an event log this could be one more thing that sits on top of that
Microsoft active directory stack is these in these analytic tools pointed back in at the user and provided to the company
Instead of provided to some sort of third party
And I think that would be compelling for places that are horrible draconian places to work for yeah
You know this would be great for the office space type corporation however
I don't first of all believe it's gonna be Malaly he's currently working at Ford
And he's definitely at retirement age and second of all I think that would require
Such a level of insight and vision into the computer industry it would that I just can't I mean
I just can't see it happening unless there was somebody that
Brought this forward from within Microsoft to Malaly and he then gave it the okay
But well I think and if you look at something like Yahoo
Here's an example if they took a superstar from Google dropped her in very very talented amazing talent amazingly talented person who?
Despite having all this amazing talent has really done
Not been able to do squat to really turn Yahoo around that Yahoo still doesn't know if it's a search engine or directory or what?
The hell they are there's still a media company or a media company or an AOL yeah
I think I thought well thing going I mean they're all over the map so I think Microsoft suffers from the same thing
I think their stuff is so deeply rooted down to the core that bringing in a new talking head isn't gonna solve any problems for
Them at all yeah, yeah, and they just don't unfortunately
They're a company that has been ran by us by a sales team for a very long time now
And they would do good to get some engineers behind the reins
And I don't I mean Malaly is an old-school engineer
I'll give them that but I just I don't see it
I think the big problem they've suffered from is somebody who doesn't have great insights into the industry as a whole right
That's it. So I have I have some more feedback to get to let's see here
Well, we had a lot of stuff on the gnome on the on the gnome in the home thing
Yeah, I think what I want to do is I want to cover a bit of late breaking news
We don't normally cover breaking news on the Linux unplugged show
but this just happened about an hour ago, and I it's it's huge so I want to talk about that because
We'll definitely cover it more and last but since it just happened
I just want to let I want to get people aware of it, but before we get to that
I want to thank ting.com sponsor of Linux unplugged ting is mobile that makes sense and
Ting also offers you some great devices with some amazing rates
You only pay for what you use with ting at six dollars a month for a phone
And then it's whatever usage your minutes your megabytes and your messages on top of that
Ting is my mobile service fighter ting is Matt's mobile service right and you know
I don't know if you were called Matt, but a few weeks back. I think was December
They were doing a survey where if you're on AT&T or Verizon, and you took a survey and did their savings calculator
It wasn't even a survey. It was just their savings calculator
You would be entered to win a free cup of coffee
Oh, I remember that that was that was actually really popular so ting is a very transparent company
and this is one of the things I like a lot about them as I'm
I really pride myself on trying to research and understand the companies that I I spend my money with and so I
Really like this aspect of ting and one so they're sharing some of the data they got from those
Savings calculator from the from the coffee survey and here's here's what some of the results are
92% of participants would see some savings in their monthly bill
87 would save more than three hundred and fifty dollars over two years
Enough to basically pay for a Nexus 5
82% would save more than six hundred dollars over two years
now here's what's really crazy is when you are a small business say like around ten devices a
Hundred percent of the small businesses with ten devices saved money on their monthly bill with ting
That's crazy. So it literally now ting is validated from two different companies that
that 98% of the people who switched to ting save money and this is something as we move forward with computing devices that are in our
Pockets, I we are really going to enter an age where companies are going to try to take advantage of us
We already are seeing this with the existing incumbent carriers who are big maybe you know duopoly cut type situations here in the u.s.
And it's really not in their interest to be customer focused where it is
Specifically by the way ting is structured as an MVNO that is in their core business DNA to focus on customer service
And as an end result it really shows from the dashboard from the fact that if you call them at one eight five five
eight four six four three eight nine anytime between 8 a.m.. And 8 p.m.. A real person answers the phone
Usually like on the first ring
Resolves your problem is empowered to solve the issue gives you their numb their name their number right then and there and this is also
Why ting makes their savings calculator available to you?
They're just gonna put it right up front plug in your minutes use your text message your megabytes your total bill before taxes and they'll
Calculate what your savings could be with ting and to help you switch over to ting they have an early termination relief program over
At ting comm slash ETF check this out you pick your ting phone you port your number over
And then you submit your ETF claim to ting and they'll give you up to seventy five dollars per line that you have to cancel
That eases that transition over to buying a device that you own outright. It's not something you're financing from the carrier
It's your phone you own it when you're only paying for what you use. This is why I literally I literally went from about
$120 a month on my phone bill to I average around twenty five thirty dollars now
It's it's amazing and that is enough money that it actually makes a difference for me every single month
So here's how you get started go to Linux dot ting comm that'll take
$25 off your first device or if you already have a sprint compatible device and you want to bring it just check their compatibility page
And if you've got that device they're gonna take
$25 off your first month that might just pay for your first month of service over at ting so Linux dot ting comm to get started
And a huge thank you to ting for sponsoring Linux
Unplugged all right before we get to any more of the feedback. I want to cover this big story that just broke
CentOS is joining forces with Red Hat. It's it's through acquisition of talent
It's it's gonna be core members of the CentOS team joining Red Hat now
They're not gonna be working for the Red Hat Enterprise Linux division interestingly enough and as they put it
The new initiative is going to be overseen
by a new CentOS governing board the initial board will comprise of the existing CentOS core team members and
Also, they're gonna add new members one nominated from the community and three members that were nominated by Red Hat directly
Which I thought is kind of interesting they said further further down the road
The CentOS Linux platform won't be changing the process and methods built around the platform
However are going to become more open and more inclusive because now that they're working directly with Red Hat legal. They're gonna be able to
Clear some hurdles like doing Q&A out in the public and things like that
so there's a lot of good interesting things there are some things that are gonna be changing, but I
Think I think this could be a real stepping stone for him
I think this could definitely be kind of that someone said legitimizes them
I think it's more it adds to their credibility, but and just expands on what they're already doing. That's awesome
You know I don't know if legitimate legitimize might be a little strong, but yeah, I agree
I watch CentOS from the beginning and
Scientific Linux and other ones too
And I know early on when I had a customer who had Red Hat Enterprise Linux there was
Selling on my part to convince them that it was even okay to try CentOS on the testing machines
Then let alone a whole nother round of selling I had to do to get them to try it on production
Where now everyone who made a bet on CentOS and for some of them there might have been just a little
Wiggle of doubt in the back of their mind. Oh, this isn't a legitimate copy of Red Hat Enterprise Linux or whatever
Which even though it's you know?
Technically exactly the same
That doubt now is completely washed away
Everybody who had made an investment in CentOS on their server farms right now all of the hosting companies all of the small businesses and large
Businesses that have CentOS deployed. This is a huge validation for that deployment and that just gave them a huge peace of mind
I would think if I was still running a bunch of CentOS servers. I would be very pleased with this news. I
Would think so. Don't be curious to see where it goes. We'll follow follow this story throughout the week
And if there's further developments, we'll cover it on Sunday on the on the Linux. Yeah, I think it's still pretty early
Yeah, we'll definitely kind of have to see where it all yeah translates into literally just happened. Yeah, so it is very early
Okay, so we talked about Gnome 3 on Linux action show on Sunday and oh jeez reddit isn't working right now
Lots of feedback lots of feedback in the reddit thread that we do every episode of Linux action show gets tossed in Linux action
Show.reddit.com where people can comment and give us feedback on it. There are so many good ones in there
But you know what reddit is totally down right now like a clown. Oh, there it goes
I should say I got it running
I was getting that I was getting the pile that dude gets piled on you know I'm saying
No, it's like too many upvotes reddit alien had a fit reddit get your crap together. Gosh. I'm sure he's cloud stuff
I I'm sure yeah
All right, so there's so many in here
I'll link to the whole thread in the show notes
But I did pull out a couple a weem wham wrote in he says my main problem with gnome 3
Which it's always which has always been is removing core functionality and then expecting it to be implemented as a user developed extension
This is bad. I'm sorry. It just is this is a point
We heard a lot
I don't know if I agree with it, but a lot of people made this point
And he just summed it up really good, so I highlighted his
So for example like the minimize button right or certain things that have been taken out that you then have to go back through
Some other third-party method to get that functionality back. What's your take on that Matt boy?
You know I don't know I'm
Gonna really kind of have to wait and see where everything ends up in the long on the long haul
But right now. I just feel like it still needs a little more time in the oven
I like I like the overall aesthetic direction
They're going but I feel like there's just certain little bits of functionality that
While extensions do address them and so did a great tools like the configuration tools they offer
I just feel like that
You know I don't want to rush to judgment, but I definitely feel like I'm not ready to make that permanent
I think that's fair. I think it's kind of early days and for me. I like riding that that that early wave of these desktop stuff
It's always kind of been one of the one of the most entertaining aspects of using Linux for me is being right there on that
Edge and so I see it where it's at now, and I saw I've kept using it
I thought maybe I might go back to KD, but I kept using it after the Linux action show and
gosh, I'm
See I can really like it
I can use no over Katie because I mean there's other desktops out there of course you know that I that I enjoy
But so I would say at this point. I could see myself using gnome over Katie, but at the same time
You know yeah on an older machine. It's still bloated. I'm sorry it is
I mean just factually speaking if you run it on an older machine. It definitely feels bloated
Here's a new machine. It's fine, but what do you think of this one?
so
Obermeiser was writing says working working dual displays across four virtual desktops and then apps remembering size and position for me is a serious
requirement for integrations and productivity I find it annoying that opening up six to twelve apps across virtual desktops
It's it's annoying and unproductive
I'm surprised by it being a non-issue with the user base out there what he's talking about is like under
Kwin or Kde it will remember the position of a window whereas
I know I'm in GTK take the point that well this is up to the application to store the position and then restore itself to
That position well and see for myself
It's like okay, so you have your virtual desktops
And then of course you often times a lot of people have dual monitors or maybe even more than that
I run everything full screen
And so you know I'm doing side by side with whatever I'm working on one in one
Workspace and then if I need to switch to another virtual desktop
I do no big deal you know I've and so I just full desktop
I just it's just never been a thing for me one of the one of the bits of feedback
We got on the gnome 3 stuff is if you want a tip for working with gnome 3 is every time you decide to start
A new task or open a new window put move it to its own virtual desktop
So don't think of virtual desktops is just a spot to store a new window
But every time you begin a new activity you you you instead of opening a new window you move it
You open it to it in a new virtual space
And so I've been trying this even like with with like multiple web browsers
So I had I have the email up and when but one web browser, and I have the dyslexia pastebin
and
Site up in another browser
And so I I highlight the email in one and I just I slide down and I paste it and it actually has been working
Quite well for me
So I'm gonna continue to try that out instead of having a bunch of windows on one virtual desks
What I've always done before is this is my web browsing virtual desktop. This is my email and I am virtual desktop
This is my terminal virtual desktop, and it's always been very structured in my mind
And now I'm gonna do it more just based on hey
I need a task so I'm just gonna create a creative virtual desktop because he pointed out in gnome 3 you can you can create and
Destroy virtual desktops at whim just like you can open and close windows, so there's no real disadvantage to doing it
Yeah, exactly. That's that's really it and I mean a lot of people think well
Why the hell would you run everything fullscreen? I mean for myself personally just comes down to usability
I don't I'm very very easily distracted, so I don't want a lot of crap on the same on the same
Notice I can't deal with that. It is easier to focus
Especially for videos and chat rooms like that
All right, well one little bit of news that just broke too, and we're gonna be covering it way more in Linux action show on Sunday
We'll be covering all the best of Linux. It's already first day of CES. It's already been a blowout for Linux there
Web OS made a made a comeback
Intel has an amazing SD sized x86 PC that runs Linux and
Valve has demonstrated showed off some of their new steam boxes and Matt we're seeing steam boxes from Alienware
Alternet I buy power cyber power PC, and they are looking amazing
Well if you think about it, especially with Falcon Northwest and Alienware those are probably my two favorite examples
These are people that are being told over and over all the desktops gonna die, and it's all about mobile
This is their bread and butter
So they're they're not only embracing this right as an opportunity to show folks that it's not dead that they can in fact
Adapt adapt and evolve, but in the fact that it can actually be really awesome
And I think I think it's gonna be really exciting to see how some of these machines perform
Gigabyte is showing one that does use iris graphics, so that might be a limiting factor
But it's like sure I think they're talking four hundred dollars or something. Yeah, I mean
But great yeah, I think a little bit high
But I mean they got the lower end machines to the crazy what one was like between 17 and 6,000 yeah
Yeah, you can go real hardcore. Yeah, and I love that one. Yeah, oh, man
I'll tell you what I have seen so one that I thought was really compelling is one that actually mounts behind the TV
And it has it has a rack and it slides out
There's there's been some really interesting steam boxes showing off so pretty
Is that video card right there in the picture is the one I installed in the computer last night to cut on fire someone needs
To Photoshop fire on that yeah, no kidding
so
Really so far. It's been a great CES for Linux, so I'm looking forward to I see yes chat
I want I like the variety
I think that's like my number one thing that I'm really most excited about it even if you're not a gamer you have to appreciate
The fact that they are bringing back the desktop at some level yeah
You know various forms
And it's it's so cool to see these different takes on it like
Falcon Northwest is doing like a very cool paint job on the side of the case and there's so many different
Approaches to this problem. I I think this is gonna be awesome. I think it's gonna be really cool to watch great opportunity
Yeah, no, I just want one valve yeah, right trying to remind valve that Matt and Chris are within a couple hours at Matt
And not even that of driving distance. Just we will drive to you guys. Let me put that out there
We will literally we will bring you lunch. Yeah, whatever you want
We will dress up like butlers and serve you I mean whatever you need just let us hook up with one of these and you're always
Throwing the dress-up stuff. I know yeah, it's like I got like valve cosplay, right?
I don't know how that works don't dress it like a PC one more bit of feedback or follow-up
I want to get to is we talked about the AC or you see you see
Pi the turnkey Raspberry Pi based internet search engine that q5 systems started a Kickstarter for he's got 44 backers as
We record this episode and he joins us right now in the mumble room mr.. Q5
How would you say the Kickstarter is going? Are you pleased? I am very pleased I at no point
Expected to be at almost 25% within three days the response has been fantastic
So I think you know that reason is because I would guess the reason for the same reason you started doing this
Why did you want to make?
You see more accessible to people. What's your motivation there?
As you've talked about on on Linux action show and with an analytics unplugged about bringing
These services that we've kind of allowed other people to take care of for us to bring them back into house
That's been something that's you know been of a lot of interest to me and also just the privacy aspect that it gives a user
To be able to do searches locally and not have you know Big Brother or Google or Bing?
Sitting there cataloguing everything your every single thing that you're searching sure sure and now so why make it turnkey
Just so that it's the simplest possible
Implementation for someone who's not extremely technical oriented
To set up Yasi it takes some configuration. You've got to work find what the best settings are going to be and
There's a lot of people that I know would like to use software like this
But don't have the technical prowess to be able to set it up themselves this way everything's done
They get the item they plug it in they're good to go now
They may have to set they may have to set a port on their local router
So that the actual unit can talk out to the rest of the network, but that they can do just in their basic router settings
I guess my first question when I saw this is is the pie powerful enough to pull this off. Is it got enough juice?
To do searches. Yes, it has enough juice to do searches and also crawl and index the web. No it doesn't
The raspberry an image, which is what most people have been using for running Yasi on pies in the past
Respirant is a great release. It's a great distribution
But it has a lot of overhead because it's intended to be a full-fledged OS for everything
So you can get it and you can run an entire full-built
Linux distribution on your Raspberry Pi what I am doing is I've built a custom puppy Linux ARM release
Specifically for the task of running Yasi so it does not have any of the extra overhead or anything else that it doesn't need
It's as trim and as slim down as possible so that it can achieve the goal and nothing more very nice
And so I've got this picture up on the stream of your little Raspberry Pi cluster that you're testing different images on
And what are you kind of doing to to test the performance of it here?
I've got several different builds of the ARM release of puppy Linux itself
I'm testing different variants of you know compiling busy box and seeing okay
Well, can I get better performance if I use if I compile it with certain options and not other options?
using the Debian RML
binaries just kind of picking through which ones are going to be the best for what I need and then once that's set up
Testing, you know just basic one job implementation and seeing okay, which of these, you know
OS setups works the best and then the next deck I'm going to go to is to figure out what's the best Java choice
To use because there are several that we can do
And then once that's chosen then take the next step of okay
What's the best way to configure the actual settings within Yasi?
So that the performance is the most stable wow, and so do you I mean are you hoping to sort of raise awareness of the?
Yasi project with this too, because I think a lot of people are seeing this and they're going well
Maybe I'll just roll this myself. Are you okay with that outcome?
Actually, I am perfectly fine if the campaign because of failure it does not bother me
This gets word out about the Yasi network and it gets people interested in it and it gets people actually deploying
It whether it's on laptops their home, whether they get like a digital ocean VPS, you know a little five dollar a month instance and throw it up
As long as it brings higher visibility to the project. I will be happy. This is probably a great
Digital ocean VPS wouldn't it? Yeah, I think it is. I know have you have you considered
Reaching out to the you see project and saying hey you guys cool with this or have they talked to you?
I've actually was contacted by a mic guy
I've actually was contacted by a Michael Christian who is the maintainer of the I see project
We got a message from him today had a couple emails back and forth. He is totally on board with it
You know, he said, you know, I hold on let me see if I can actually pull it up real quick
Hold on a second. So that's actually in the middle of emailing back
I wonder if you must have you know, maybe he was watching the last maybe he's a viewer then you never know
Hey, possibly you never know. Well, hello fees. All right
So we got 44 backers. There's 42 days left to go folks if you want to to pledge
We'll have a link in the show notes to this and or you could go over to a Kickstarter and search for why a CY pie
And I have the email up right now
Um, it goes on and in part of any was there's already been discussion if you know
Yasi pie my project is good or bad for the asses, you know network
And if a production of commercial Yasi type products are liked or disliked by me or the other developers
He said let me clear this out right now
I like the Yasi pie project and I am happy to support you awesome
And I responded back to him. I said look my goal is not to actually start producing these commercially and selling them
The Kickstarter campaign is to help defer the development costs of actually being able to do this once that's done
The SD card image will be completely released freely
Um, they will have a copy of it. It'll be on source forage. I'll have it on the actual website
So anyone can then at that point go get the SD card image burn it onto their own SD card if they have a raspberry
Pie and go that's awesome. My goal is not to make money off of this
It's to raise awareness and to get the tools into people's hands so that can actually be used. Well, you are a gentleman, sir
I I have been I've been borrowing quote-unquote. I keep a really nice not just the raspberry pie
But also an HP doc that was made for the atrix
I think it was like way back in the day
And so I've I've been experimenting with different uses for the raspberry pie
And I think if you know if you get that performance spot in there that is perfect for a device like this
It's essentially a search appliance for your house. Yeah
Awesome. All right. Well, mr
Q5 sister anything else you want to share with us before we go back on to other business?
Not really just I hope that you know anybody who is listening to this or is you know?
Considering it if you don't have the money to donate that's okay. Just instead help spread the word
Well good work, and I think it's awesome
You'll be releasing the image if we if we reach that goal too because then other folks who already have the pie can take advantage
Of it so and there are there are also if you don't have a pie yet
He's got backing levels which will get you like a complete solution and you just take it and go so well good work, sir
And stay stick around if you'd like and join us for the rest of the discussion here in a moment
Yeah, congratulations on the progress so far. That's really awesome. Yeah. Yeah, that is really great
So I want to take a moment and thank our second sponsor this week and that speaking of digital ocean
We were just talking about them is
Digital ocean digital ocean is simple cloud hosting dedicated offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up a cloud server
You can create a server in 55 seconds and pricing plans started only five dollars per month
512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer for that five dollars a month
digital ocean has data center locations in New York San Francisco and
Amsterdam the interface is simple and it has an intuitive control panel which power users can replicate on a large scale with an API and
Digital ocean also offers a vast collection of tutorials in their community section and the users can submit articles and if digital ocean publishes that piece
50 bones folks you get $50 from digital ocean
You can get the link to it more info about that in our show notes now. Here's the thing
You guys get to be part of the hip club. We got a special thing
We still we're still using the special promo code from last month now. I know you're gonna think but Chris
This is January trust me dear viewer listener
I know that but I like every now and then to get you guys in on the club
You know we like to sometimes stick it to the man right well guess what you can still use Linux unplug
December when you're over digital ocean, and you'll get a $10 credit you can try out that $5 machine for two months for free
When you use the promo code Linux unplugged December, I want to recommend you do it, and you know
Q5 sis kind of inspired me
I kind of want to go throw you see on my digital ocean droplet, or maybe spin up another one
Hey, I'd pay five dollars a month for my own totally private
Completely self-controlled search. I think that's totally worth it. Oh definitely
Uh geez I think I'm gonna do this. I mean, I think that's a great idea so digital ocean has all kinds of great
Technologies KVM for the virtualization SSD hard drives for the speed
amazing hardware
Flexible API great bandwidth and of course they also offer incredible pricing you can get a
$5 a month machine 512 makes about RAM a cool one core processor 20 gig SSD one terabyte of transfer you go up to
$10 then you get a gig of RAM you get 30 gigs of storage and two terabytes of transfer you go up to
$20 is two gigabytes of memory two cores of CPU 40 gigabyte SSD and three terabytes of transfer and on and on and on
They also offer hourly pricing if you just need to do a little testing if you're working on a web app and you want
To have your client take a look at it
You want to have a few folks just to do some Q&A or maybe some critiquing for you you could toss it up on
A digital ocean droplet turn it on and then just pay by hour and the rates are absolutely I mean nobody beats these rates
It's awesome. So go over to digital ocean
Dot-com and use our special limited time promo code Linux unplugged December to get that $10 credit and a big
Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplug. Oh, definitely. Those guys are so awesome
I love the fact that you can just basically run it any way you want
You know, they don't treat you like you don't know what you're doing. You just get a blank box and you have to go for it
Absolutely. I love I love the droplet and I love having root access on my machine. I mean, that's a huge deal for me
All right, so I want to open this up to discussion here with the mumble room last week
I asked the question does does open source governance by
Consensus of the community
Inhibit innovations and where I'll point this I'll point out a couple of things what we're watching happening right now
For me seems to be a great example of this with Debian
They are down the path now of choosing something besides systemd primarily because they are concerned about
Portability to the BSD's even though according to the voluntary
Survey hardware software survey for Debian users only
0.8% of Debian users would be affected or it might even be less than that
It is it is an infinitesimal small portion of the Debian community
It would be impacted by the switch to systemd but the switching of to systemd would be I would see the positives of that would be
Much more interoperability with Linux at a large at a larger scope
So I look at this and I think if this was for example if they had a Mark Shuttleworth or they had a Steve Jobs
Or they had a who uh, you know a Larry Page whoever sitting at Debian who was responsible for making these decisions
He would look at this and he would say hey, you know what portability is great
It's something to aspire to but let's be practical and let's get real here
We have to make a competitive product that a lot of people can use that'll you know, it'll stay relevant
It 2015 2016 and beyond let's go this direction
And I feel like that would be I actually feel like that's the most it is so blatantly obvious
that's the way to go the only reason we're not going that way is because
the way community works is a small minority if they push the right buttons and if they're vocal enough can influence the herd into
A certain direction where all of a sudden it it becomes a sacred cow to sacrifice portability
You that's that's Debian's core vision. You can't sacrifice portability
you can't do that and if really if you took a rational look at it and if somebody who was a leader a
Dictator if you want if you will or a benevolent overload looked at and said come on, this is just not practical
It's not tenable. Let's get real here. I feel like I feel like that's what would happen. Yeah, go ahead. I
Beg to disagree there do it because first
It might seem a bit weird that Debian has such a strong feeling about its principles
but that's just it principles openness diversity and
Nobody knows what the future will hold. Is it principles or is it almost like a well?
We don't want to we want to tell ourselves ego crap
To me it feels like we don't we don't want to we don't want to say even though it's not true
I feel like a little bit as well
We don't want to bet the whole farm on Linux because maybe ten years down the road
Linux is gonna die and we want to be able to we want to be at this portable system that will move to whatever becomes the
New king like it's almost like enough a fear to commit to Linux in a sense, even though it sounds ridiculous
That's almost what it sounds like to me when I look at it. I
Don't know what this printing is
I feel like principles is a way to cover up that fear unless they can cite something concrete concrete besides ego stroking
I'm just not buying
Stuff is already coming through on yeah and testing. So I mean we all know that they're gonna go system
Well, I don't actually know it's not looking like they are gonna go with system D
I think they're gonna do up starter. Well, I'm not
Yeah, I mean I don't know what they're gonna go with but now it's looking like according to what I read on the Linux WN
Over the weekend. It looks like they're not going the system D direction. I think it's interesting that when you introduce this you said
You know, maybe if Debian had a Mark Shuffleworth type person or a benevolent dictator that this might not happen
But then the fact is that even the Ubuntu project has a technical board and they have discussions like this and mark doesn't swoop in
And you know kick everyone to one side and say nope
This will be the way it happens take for example and a discussion happening just this week about whether we should re-enable
Suspend to disk on Ubuntu and the whole technical board are weighing in on the pros and cons of re-enabling that thing
So and I so I think all Debian are doing is the same kind of thing that the Ubuntu technical board would do which is
Evaluate all the options given their principles and make a decision based on technical and other merits. That is true
However, what mark has a very public thing
Public mark and they don't have timescales like like, you know, they don't have a release date like we do
I think but see mark can set the tone right mark and say
Convergence is the future and then that frames the conversation that everybody has from that point and just that ability is
huge because it you you
fundamentally alter the state of the conversation that the group has when you set the cadence like that and Debbie doesn't have that
Some degree but they they have their free software guidelines. They have their principles
They they have a long history of you know doing the right thing
And I think they want to continue doing the right thing whether that means it system D or upstart
Yeah, they want to do the right thing
and I I think their influence is just not one guy or a set of contracts that canonical may have with OEMs its
principles I have I could agree it see
at what point do you reevaluate the principles because it almost seems like
Insanity to me to make this level of sacrifice just to maintain compatibility with BSD when in reality
You know anybody that runs Debbie and BSD in large-scale production. No, it doesn't happen
It is it's a it's a it's it's it's a dream
It's it's a hope that the Debian project could get utilized for something that the BSD guys have already got covered
They're pretty happy with their package management. They're going off doing their own thing
Anyways, it seems like Debbie ins principles drive them to aspire to something that is ludicrous
Well, you know, I don't know it's gonna be interesting to see how it turns out
I at this point unless I can actually see a working table citing exactly what the hell they're dragging their feet with and why
Because for just the average guy looking into this it's it's just it's mind-boggling. It's just like oh my god make a decision already
You know, I mean seriously, I feel like this isn't this isn't the first time that the Debbie
But it does kind of get old after a while though
Well, the problem is they are not just five guys
They are several hundred guys and they just have different opinions and they need to talk about it
By the way, it's absolutely fine by the way
It is good because I I don't mean to keep cutting you off
But I want to you I want to respond to each point you're making it that is true it to an extent
but it also allows for stagnation and it allows for a
Washing down to the lowest common denominator and instead of making something amazing and streamlined
You can make something that makes everybody happy and I talked about this with gnome
on the Linux action show is when you have
Designed by community you really get something that's not that great. And when you have designed
I didn't say it. So you but you are making my point for me is exactly that
I feel like you could apply that that scenario to Debian is
They would as the larger the community gets the more discussions that happen
It actually turns out that the more arbitrary aspects of the community are able to wield a larger
Influence and you I think if if this could be streamlined the pace of innovation would be a lot higher
It slows us down a lot. It really weighs things down
Well, Chris, wait, wait, wait, wait, the first thing you need to remember is either way it really does not matter
How the outcome is in this?
discussion
System D is already in Debian as is upstart and open I see
I don't know if open RC is in it
But it doesn't really matter how the outcome is because both in its systems are already in Debian true
So you can choose whether you want it or not
But we do know the discussion is just a yes. The discussion is just about the default, right?
And I but I think that's as good as that is just as good as only having one. Yes
so and also don't forget the the
what you're what we're all navel-gazing and
Bike-shedding about
This same thing will have will have been happening on that mailing list over the years and nobody would have been looking at it
There would have been no Twitter. There would have been minimal podcasts
There wouldn't have been you know
Everyone sharing on Twitter links to oh so-and-so said this on the Debian project mailing list because nobody cares
Or the people who do care are the people who are already on that list and having those discussions, right?
It's the sharp focus of you know, the 24-hour news the the Twitter generation of people who are
You know having an opinion and want to express that opinion rapidly and in 140 characters
When in fact, that's not how Debian works and I don't think Debian should work
I think what it what it is is we are reaching an influx point in Linux where I was just talking about this in Coda
Radio where the the the core between the distributions with systemd and a lot of other things
You know big changes in the kernel too is becoming less and less chaotic
It's actually becoming we could see a future where developers don't look at Linux as this crazy wild west of all of these different
Fractured I mean you talk about Android fragmentation. Let's talk about distro fragmentation for a minute
But that is kind of coming together
it's kind of cajoling a little bit and
Debian is now at a crossroads where they could choose to go down that path or they could choose to be fragmented and different and
The the hope is because Debian is so important to all the people built off of it and because Debian is such a critical
distro to Linux itself. I
Want to see more great development come into Linux and I feel like the more consistency we have there in in the middle of these
Distros the better the better time and we're gonna have from our dev, you know, the better applications
We're gonna get the more applications
We're gonna get the more people that will target Linux and the more fractured we are the less likely that's gonna happen
You're gonna continue to see software that only works on Red Hat or software that only works on Ubuntu
Laundry list of reasons why it's a benefit right? It's great. It's awesome and all go all this choice
Yeah, sure. We can't get any two things to run. It's the same way and same
That's such a critical thing, you know if we have if we have a future in which we can start to
Smooth some of those differences out. I am I I I don't want to I don't want to you know
Sacrifice something important to get there
But I also want to make sure that if we don't go that direction we have some damn really good reasons like I mean really good
Good
I think people are just making this out to be way more of a big deal than it is
Is remember when our to switch the system be everybody just went insane?
Two months later. It was like, oh, yeah that happened
Remember when we move the buttons over to the left hand side
Yeah, yeah or remember when skies opened up when we switch to pulse audio
Well, that was kind of crappy first so but I think this the stakes are a little bit different in this one because it's more
about what future Linux is gonna look like and how
compatible each distro is gonna be with each other and you know if skills learned in one distro like how to stop and start services are
applicable to another distro and those small little things like all to us
Those of us who use Linux on a regular basis
They seem trivial but people who are maybe like a Windows admin for their whole career and now they just got Linux boxes
These are the little details that make night and day difference for them and anytime, you know
We can reduce the differentiation between the different distros the better
it's going to be for all Linux adoption as a whole and and I just I
Appreciate that there they have a lot of technical requirements and principles to follow and that's what makes Debbie and as good as it is
But I guess I have to wonder again if you took out the community element of the decision-making process and you just put a CEO
In there, I think he would come down pretty handedly on the system D side of the discussion
Dictatorship and to import this corporate Borg into Debian really? No. No, I mean I wouldn't want that. No
thing is not a problem like people look at group thing as horrible and it's it's great and also it's it's it's it's got a
Massive flaws, but if you had like say a board of three people that were
In control of the group thing and saying this is the direction we're looking at and then they have like a mediation situation
Then you could get input from everyone
but at the same time and and you get any you give input but you also get like
Do you give everybody who's putting their input as a valid, you know?
They have the same amount of input or the same
Their their merit is the same
They don't have any kind of skewed if you have a CEO
Then everybody's just gonna listen to the CEO and then they're the opinions are gonna just dwindle. Yeah
I mean the technical board is I think probably the right answer I guess I
Just look at this. We actually got a really good email in on this that really kind of I thought did a good job
it came from Kyle and
You guys can you can feel free if you think Kyle is off the rails to interrupt
But he wrote I'm writing in regarding your question in this week's a Linux unplugged about whether Linux has too much endless
Squabbling and consensus decision-making that inhibits innovation versus a top-down organization like Apple or canonical that can follow a singular vision
Oh, don't get poppy started again
Essentially your question comes down to an argument of the merits of democracy versus dictatorship
While I appreciate you raising the question
I have to say the implication the implications of your argument seem to distinctly be negative in the freedom dimension. Oh, hold on
There we go dimension he says I got it I got it busted out
I think your question doesn't just have to do with innovation
But also the common argument that Linux is bad because debates within the community are too heated
I'm sure many others will write in with technical or practical opinions on this question
But I thought I'd bring it a little bit of political theory since I have a liberal arts background that others might not I would
Argue the Linux community is like a Roman is like the Roman Republic
It has its own sorts of dictators consuls tribunes and any number of other competing powers
It has an armed citizenry just like Rome did where users are largely free to contribute code and start projects and it is driven
by a chaotic political structure that leads to competition and
expansion
Like the Spartans Apple is careful in its expansion plans choosing to occupy
particular upscale segments of the market and it certainly has a lot of success with that like the leonians or
leonians the
300 Apple elite has elite Apple's elite of workers could be said to punch above their weight in terms of innovation
But when you look at the big picture in terms of install base and not just the direct market value
Apple is dwarfed by the chaotic Hydra like
Expansion of Linux and open source our Liberty is the condition for our success
We are positive in the size dimension because we are positive in the freedom dimension
So just as Romans occasionally found the need to elect dictators to lead them
We may occasionally find the need for executive powers to get things done
But let our envy of Apple not lead us to expand these islands of tyranny to the point that they crushed the Liberty that makes
Linux so great. I
Agree with a lot of what they said. I really cringed when he used Romans an example because I for one enjoy myself my Roman citizenship
Oh wait, that's right. We're not because it collapsed, you know
I like some of the I like some of the things he said but man
I was just cringing the whole time with the whole Rome thing because it's like bad example
Maybe this is why Debbie wants to keep that BSP competitive
Oh, horrible, horrible
Rome was moved to Byzantium
to
Over to Byzantium the capital Rome was moved to Constantinople by Constantine and it's just proper
basically propaganda
By Roman Catholics or whatever that it's been collapsed, but it lasted for a long time before
It lasted for a long time and it had
It brought forth amazing successes as did Greece and a lot of other other things but empires fall
I mean at the end of the day, that's
The parallel Kyle was drawing there is that the the essentially chaotic and sometimes competitive nature of the political structure of Linux sort of
Leads to it's always growing expansion in new areas and new territories agree with that. Yeah. No, I agree with the points
I just the whole realm thing just really rubbing the wrong way
I think you're missing a bigger point here to is Linux is not bigger than any one dish show. It's
Colonel so it doesn't matter what one dish show back. There's always another
Places. Yeah, and I'll tell you the other thing
I've really noticed over the years of doing these shows is the things that seem like the biggest
Biggest technical upsets or the you know, the thing we really got to be concerned about
Have yet to ever actually be that
You know, like I look back you remember the amount of upset around Novell signing that deal with Microsoft
We did like three weeks of coverage on the Linux action show back to back to back discussing that issue because it was so red
hot right or you know a lot of other things that
Has happened in the past always seem like these X
Lend. Yeah, everything right and then like so so say say Debian doesn't choose system D
Hey, somebody will just figure out a way to still make things compatible and work
I mean we all that's what happens right every time but it is interesting to sort of look at this and think that
Every now and then I wonder how much further would we be if we had a few more?
benevolent dictators in these communities because I think where you do see real progress made in open source is
These little fiefdoms we have of like, you know, here's Camp Apache over here. You know, here's Camp Ubuntu. There's Camp fedora
There's can't you know or even more even more granular that there's camp system D
And they have their they have their sort of appointed
Chiefs that sort of push them forward and then as a collective whole we all benefit
But it's kind of like in a way the body all works together
It's sort of this weird organic creature that has some
Some ugly spots that we all get to just look at and watch because it's all happening out in the open
I've awesome
I've often made the point that if these these types of discussions happen at the Microsoft's and at the Apple's and the Oracle's of the world
But they're all done behind closed doors. So we have no idea where the way those conversations went
This is true. This is true. I also think that the
Open way of doing things is more holistic. Sure
It may not be as fast, but it's definitely more holistic and the way it grows. Hey
Yeah, I wanted to shift gears why we got the mumble room here
What do you guys think about the cent OS team joining Red Hat? What do you think that means?
Nobody
I
It's it's also the way they say they talk about it
It sounds like it's going to be a front a backing of the center was not necessarily an overtake on
gonna make it for
sale and
Kill the cent OS team in the process
It's a good thing yeah, it's a complete redo of their initiatives
It's it's gonna turn the project something else. They made it sound like it's gonna keep going as is
but the part I'm wondering is what what we kind of what I talked about during the fedora 20 review is the fedora project is
Redoing, you know
They got fedora next and they're talking in that proposal about potentially having a server spin of fedora
And I at the time I looked at and go that sounds like a cent OS competitor and I wonder if maybe there's some
Some sort of collaboration that might happen there, but I just don't know is it more of a
Ubuntu server competitor in the cloud space not so much the service base with the cloud space
That's what they like this is this red hat buying themselves into that space
That's what I'm wondering right because cent OS has huge deployments in a lot of the cloud services and cloud hosting
It's like I use into us
So I don't think fedora will ever directly compete with cent OS in the server market just because they target different
Different areas, I mean, I guess fedora could work well as
as
in the cloud space
But sent to us is a much more concerned distribution than fedora is right
And so it will act more like an abutu LTS or rail itself because I've been in companies where we're still using
rail 5 and it's still support or sena was 5 and it's all supported and
You're not going to upgrade versions because it's such a huge effort to do so
And if you're on fedora if they have the current release cycle and they're releasing every I guess they release six months, right?
It would be impossible to support that
Yeah, I think so the way they're working this in fedora next is they're gonna have like rings where the first ring will be
Like the cloud version fedora that sees more conservative changes and then there'll be the set of stuff on top of that
That's the next ring. Maybe it's like more network services and there's a third ring
which is like the desktop services that sit on top of that and the idea is is you could pull out just that middle ring and
You would have just a very minimal core
Literally gonna call it fedora core again
And then that could be their hope I think is to have that be
server ready to make that make that core not change that much and
That would be what people deploy like on digital ocean VPS's and and other places
and it it is kind of like
You got a figure
Red has been sitting back and watching Ubuntu eat its lunch on like a lot on EC2 and a lot of racks based
deployments, I mean
Red Hat is has a presence there, but they're not staying competitive with the LTS is with the LTS Ubuntu releases
So I think the big picture is is it's probably to compete there, but I don't see exactly how it's good news for the CentOS
team, I think
It's gonna be interesting and it's one of these things where I'm not quite sure if the audience is that interested because it's all server
stuff so it yanks my chain because I used to be a server guy and I don't know if it really if
CentOS becomes a
you know a really
popular option in the cloud space then
Red Hat have an upsell there
Pretty easily to go in the same way that Oracle upsell from my SQL to Oracle database
You can upsell from CentOS to rail licenses. Yeah, totally. It seems a no-brainer for them
Yeah, I really that that aspect of it totally makes sense. That's exactly what it is
And yeah, that's probably gonna work. Red Hat's gonna make more money surprise surprise everybody
Yeah, right
Red Hat doing this is actually interesting for CentOS too because the Red Hat was making it harder for CentOS to make their
using the Red Hat source code to make it they modularized everything and
They made it like piece by piece that CentOS had to get best the legal issues. They had to kind of
Put a lot of effort into making each release
So now maybe CentOS could actually improve like how fast they do things so they can make it make it easier
Thanks to Red Hat funding it then so CentOS could actually improve a lot of and a lot of ways very quickly
I wonder so in a post NSA
revelations world where we know there's distributions out there like isn't red Linux that Chinese Linux distribution that's based off CentOS and
They wanted a distro that wasn't attached to a US company. That's why they spun that I wonder how that impacts stuff like that now
Work, maybe yeah, maybe yeah, maybe a fork. Yeah, they could just fork it and maintain it
Maybe the maybe it's not a big deal. Yeah, but CentOS was just a hack
Well
It was it it didn't it wasn't compatible with Red Hat and anybody I know that was running it in production
I told them absolutely not
What are you talking about? It's not compatible. Yeah, it's entirely binary compatible
But what way have you found on that? It's not compatible
mostly upgrades and packages that were
critical to
Red Hat EL
and trying to run some
applications that were
Suggested for Red Hat EL
Trying to run in CentOS. It was just a nightmare. I haven't experienced something
I know I've actually had been pretty fortunate. I have I've even gone as far as taking like I can't I'm gonna get the numbers
Wrong, but I took like a CentOS 5 installation
Or I'm sorry
I took a Red Hat 5 installation and repointed the repos over to CentOS 6 and I actually upgraded
The release of that installation of CentOS 5 to Red Hat
I'm sorry from Red Hat 5 to CentOS 6 like I went to a whole new version and switched from Red Hat to CentOS
It's not recommended, but I there was the server where there was just absolutely no option other than that
And I did it and it I was like amazed to me
I was stunned because I went from Red Hat 5 to CentOS 6 and I changed repos and all that kind of stuff
So there I was been quite successful
But I suppose you could always have an application that would maybe double-check to make sure it's on Red Hat Enterprise Linux
And then just kick you up a refusal to operate. Is that what you ran into Don?
I don't think it was anything in the app itself. It definitely had something to do with libraries that were
renamed and you know we
Real kind of thing. Yeah, maybe to take out the branding or whatever in like a file name or something
Huh? Plus I had a major problem trying to go from five eight or whatever up to six something
There just wasn't an easy way to upgrade. There you go. There you go
I that's a little good a good little piece of feedback and thanks to the jack-in-the-box to for voicing
Yeah, a good descent there because you know
I mean you were I brought good points in defending Debian and and my only I guess my closing my closing army would be is
Debbie's got to do what's good for Debbie and whatever the end of the day
I don't know enough about what they do to make any broad judgments
I just I just would like to see them kind of pick their direction and embrace it and then continue to
Crawl along at a snail's pace as usual. I would love to see them choose something that makes Debian work better with Linux
Yeah, and I would love to see them not make a bad decision just because they're not questioning principles from time to time
But as long as those things aren't happening, I'm happy. Hey, they're happy. I'm whatever they go with right sure
I yeah, I had something to say about that too because I come from the Unix side. Mm-hmm
You know, I'm all for system D. I use it in arch and everything. It's something new
I don't see why Debian should be
You know holding back
My problem is that now
Linux is sort of getting away from the init RC world, right and
You know now I'm I'm in the Unix side doing RC and now I got to come up with a whole different. Yeah
There is that there is a big change and it's a lot different but all right guys
Well good show and thank you very much for all the inputs. That was a good discussion and we'll have links to the stuff
We talked about like a q5 sys a yasi pie. Yeah, or you see pie turnkey solution
Maybe go back him if you like the idea and we also have a link to that CentOS news
We'll have further discussion about all the stuff that happened at CES Matt coming up on Sunday
I think box stuff steam box stuff will just be part of our overall coverage. So should be a great show assuming
Chase's flight isn't delayed. He'll be joining us to cover what he saw. He's on the floor right now at CES
So we'll have a great wrap of that following all that if you see some good CES stories that are Linux related
Please link them up in the Linux action show subreddit. I'd love to go through that as we're preparing our coverage
So Matt have a great weekend. I'll see you on Sunday. Okay. All right. See you then. All right, everyone
Thank you for joining us this week
Don't forget you can email us just go to Jupiter broadcasting comm and pop that contact link and join us live on a Tuesday at
2 p.m
Pacific over jblive.tv and jblive.info for the audio edition. I don't have a great week
We'll see you on Sunday. And if not, we'll see you right back here next Tuesday. You