Happy end of life for Windows 7 day, Wes.
Microsoft sent us a whole bunch of new Linux users
for our return show.
You don't think they'll upgrade to Windows 10?
I don't know.
I was looking this up.
How many people are actually still using Windows 7?
And over at Computer World, they have an article that says,
they ran an estimation, and they say on January 1, 2021,
so a year from now, there will still
be 18.7 of all Windows users running Windows 7, which
is approximately 281 million machines.
Something tells me they're not going to Windows 10.
Pretty sure those folks are all going to openBSD.
Yeah.
Hello, friends, and welcome into the Unplugged program.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
If I sound a little different out there, dear audience,
today, it's because I am a little different today.
I'm on a remote snow setup using my emergency podcasting
pack that I carry with me like every good podcaster should.
So if I sound a little different, that's why.
But nevertheless, we still have a great episode today.
Jim Salter from TechSnap and Ars Technica
and other places online, like anywhere you want to find them,
is joining us.
Hello, Jim.
What's up?
Hey, Jim.
Now, you must be here because we're talking about a ZFS topic
today.
You can't keep me away.
Well, thank you for joining us.
We'll be getting to, in our estimation,
why Linus has gotten a few things wrong about ZFS
recently.
We'll explain it to you and also what he's gotten right.
We've gotten some community news that we're
going to get to, something that's
a little more straight from the headlines type inspired.
But before all of that, we've got
to say holler to our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
What's up?
I can hear that we have a really good showing today,
but I'm flying blind in my remote setup.
So I know it's like around a dozen people,
so it's good to see everybody.
I think you're just going to have
to find out as they make their erudite comments.
Yeah, tag me in the chat room with the old mumskies
and let me know if you want to jump in since I can't really
monitor the room today.
But yeah, I am snowed in.
And I say that kind of like with a kind of laugh about it
because it's not like there's a lot of snow.
I posted a quick like 20 second video
on my YouTube channel, which I have linked in the show notes
if you want to see what I'm talking about.
I mean, I'm not trying to overstate what's going on here.
It's not like it's horrible, but for the Seattle area,
it's snowpocalypse 2020.
And it's combined with a couple of days
of staying below freezing.
And so the roads are just trash and my water's frozen,
which happens from time to time.
But more importantly, people do not
know how to drive around here.
And an area of the freeway that I transit through,
it's the exit right before the studio exit,
has just seen nothing but accidents today.
There was a car fire around 5 AM.
There was a pile up that caused.
And then spooky enough, around the time
I would have been heading into the studio
had I decided to brave the snow, there
was a five car pile up and a semi collision
in that exact spot.
And so I thought, you know what?
I'll just podcast from the snow in the RV today.
Sounds much safer.
Yeah, it's much safer.
And it means it's kind of an interesting slow ramp
back because the show has been on break for the last three
weeks when we've been running our holiday specials.
So this is our first episode back since before Christmas.
And it's like a slow ramp up.
It's kind of nice in a way.
It's a little different.
It's great to be back.
Meanwhile, while we're dealing with the snow,
the rest of the tech industry has
been dealing with CES, the Consumer Electronics
Show that happens every single year in Vegas.
And we don't talk about it a lot because there's not
a lot of pure Linux and open source stuff going on there.
But as you would expect, there's a lot of gadgets running Linux.
But some of them have been a little more upfront,
a little more obvious about the fact that they're using Linux.
They're sort of proudly using Linux.
And surprisingly enough, Wes, it's
the devices that seem to be using the automotive grade
Linux project from the Linux Foundation.
Subaru made a big announcement this week
that they're going to do all of their infotainment systems
using Linux.
So they'll be rolling it out initially
in the Subaru Outback and Legacy booth vehicles.
But there's a bunch of others that already have announced
support as well.
Yeah, including the 2020 Toyota RAV4 and Mazda CX-30,
both powered by automotive grade Linux software.
Apparently, there were 20 plus open source demos at the Linux
Foundation booth this year.
Yeah, I did a little digging.
And there's almost a dozen different manufacturers now
that are on board with automotive grade Linux.
And it's like legitimate companies that are in on this.
We're going to actually start seeing real cars
that people buy running automotive grade Linux.
And they had over 20 different open source software demos
running on this thing.
Yeah, that's pretty neat.
And maybe that's where some of the advantages.
I mean, it's neat to see Linux being used.
But this definitely feels Linux Foundation-y,
if you get my drift here, in that these probably won't still
be user modifiable or Linux like we
would recognize it in any way.
Yeah, it's kind of like that Android.
It's the Android effect.
But it does still speak to the capability and usefulness
of the kernel we all love.
Well said.
And it's pretty neat to, it's like when
you get on the airplane, how many times have you
seen when people get on the Delta airplane
and Delta will do a reboot of the infotainment
systems during the passenger offloading and unloading.
And so if you get on the plane kind of early,
or they just are slow at the reboot, I guess,
you can get a little shot of picture
of Linux booting in the seat cushion of the Delta airline
plane seats.
Makes me feel better to have tux right there
as I'm getting ready to fly.
Doesn't look like it's a super great system,
but I probably see one of those once a week either sent
into the show or somebody posts it online.
And I remember, I mean, we did it as a runs Linux forever
ago.
So yeah, it's out there.
And it's just an implementation detail, really,
for the most part, except for us.
Right.
That's assuming you can see the seat back
screen between your knees when you're in that Delta seat.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's true.
And honestly, I prefer Alaska.
But I don't want to start a fight.
I have so much to say about the snow.
But I know we need to get into housekeeping this week
already, because there's a lot to update people
on since we've been gone and tons of really good stuff.
So nominally today, we're going to talk about Linus's take
on ZFS and maybe where he got it wrong.
But before we do that, let's do a little housekeeping.
There's a lot to tell you about, so I
wanted to kind of get right into this sort
of near the top of the show.
First of all, thank you to everybody who's joined us
at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Telegram.
That's our official Telegram channel
where the conversation goes on after the show.
And you can keep it going over at jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash Telegram.
It's doing great.
And I think a big part of that is the spam bots and stuff.
It's really kind of changed the game over there.
So it's been really nice.
Also, this Friday, assuming I'm not snowed in,
Cheez and I and whoever else wants to join us
are doing a live stream on living in the terminal,
essentially creating a desktop-like environment
but in the terminal, something you could SSH to on a VPS
or back home.
And it's really slick.
It's something Cheez used to do on the DL at an old gig.
So he really dialed it in.
And he'll walk us through it on Friday.
So that'll be live, assuming I can make it.
I'm excited to see what his secrets are.
Yeah.
He's got a few great ideas in there.
And then I've got a couple of points of interest
that we need to get out there for everybody.
Number one, two fests are closing their calls for paper
very soon.
This Saturday, January 18, Texas Linux Fest
closes their call for papers.
Now, Texas Linux Fest is one of my favorite Linux fests
because it's the perfect size to actually build friendships,
relationships, and connections.
Some of the most fruitful things that
have happened in my career and others I know
are the result of Texas Linux Fest.
So it's a great conference to get involved in if you can.
And their call for papers wrap up very soon.
So we have a link to their papercall.io site.
If you want to give a shot, there's
worse places to go than Texas in the winter.
Is there anything else that we want to add to that, Carl?
I know you're involved very closely with Texas Linux Fest.
So if there's something you want to mention,
I want to give you a chance here in the show.
Yeah, just one thing somebody asked me about today.
The call for papers, you don't actually
have to have your talk done.
Just get the idea and the basic elevator pitch submitted.
So that way, we can select between them
and schedule them in categories and all that.
Yeah, yeah, get your pitch ready, get an idea,
get an angle, get a concept, and then flush it out.
You use the time between now and the fest.
That's probably something people don't think about
because it feels like you're cheating.
But really, that's the expectation.
Besides, you want to polish it right up to the time
to get time to go.
I don't know any other way.
Also, Linux Fest, our favorite Linux Fest,
Linux Fest Northwest, it's call for papers, wraps up Wednesday.
That's tomorrow as we record.
So if you're listening, it may have just closed
or you may have a tiny bit of time left, better go check.
And it's a good time to think about your plans
to come join us at Linux Fest.
Definitely.
We are starting to do our planning.
And we've had so much fun over the years
that if you can make it, it's another one of those
where you can really hear it's made connections and change
things for people.
So I really recommend, if you can make it,
please join us at Linux Fest Northwest.
You can get the details at their website.
It's in April, towards the end, like last weekend.
And then last but not least, our buddy Alex,
my co-host on Self-Hosted, sat down
with the Home Assistant podcast that comes out this week.
And the Home Assistant podcast is definitely
for those of you who want to learn a lot more about Home
Assistant.
We go into it on Self-Hosted, but it's
part of our overall solution, whereas this podcast focuses
in on what I think is one of the most remarkable open source
projects and in the top 10 active open source
projects on GitHub.
And great podcast that really zeros in on that.
And they had Alex sit and join them.
Alex has a beautiful Home Assistant setup, too.
So that was a good call on their part.
Yeah, that's for sure.
That'll be episode 61, if you want to find it.
There you go.
And we'll also put a link to the general podcast page,
since it's not out as we record yet, in the show notes.
But you can find it there.
A lot going on.
It's just about Linux Fest season,
because something we didn't mention,
but I will get it out there right now,
since we're covering this, we're also going to be at scale.
So if you're going to be at scale this year,
come say hi to us.
I'm sure coming up soon, we'll start
setting up the actual meetups and all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, this year we're planning to do Linux Fest Northwest, Texas
Linux Fest, and scale.
Now, everything's always subject to change, especially
these days.
But that's our intention as we record right now.
So if you're thinking about it, and we
could push you over the line a little bit,
I hope that encourages you to come say hi to us.
Come hang out.
And that's the housekeeping.
I thought that was going to be a lot to get through.
But really, for being off the air for three weeks,
that wasn't so bad.
No, it actually looks pretty good in here.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm pretty proud of us, Wes.
A computer kid in the chat room asks if you're going to Self.
I don't know.
It always conflicts, but we'll see.
I've always wanted to make it down there,
but it's a really long travel.
I'm going to Self.
Are you?
Yeah, OK.
Great, Jim will be there.
Jim goes every year.
Not quite as far for Jim as it is for me.
No.
So that's good.
And you often go to all things open, too, don't you?
Every year.
There you go.
I want to try to make it this year if I can.
I don't quite have it nailed down yet, but I would like to.
It is a monster of a show.
Is it?
We had 5,000 people last year.
Whoa.
OK.
Sounds like we shouldn't miss it.
Yeah.
You really should not.
All right.
OK, I'm getting hyped.
I mean, it's on my plan, so I'll start taking it seriously.
All right, well, let's talk about Linus Torvalds' recent
claims not to use.
He says, quote, don't use ZFS.
But unfortunately, he doesn't seem to fully understand it.
For me, it was kind of hard to read this,
because it's sort of like when I have a family member who I
realize isn't going to figure something out.
It's not kind of within them, and they sort of
hit their limit, and it's sort of a little, well.
Turns out Linus has faults, too, Chris.
Yeah.
I mean, we're all human.
I think we knew that.
It's just when Linus says something,
it comes with a certain level of authority.
It immediately, immediately generates headlines.
It creates blog posts.
It creates discussion.
It's as it should after its contribution.
But there was a series of questions
about Linux performance in a thread,
and eventually in there, ZFS came up.
And it was in here where Linus went
on to make some inaccurate and damaging potential claims
about ZFS.
And Jim kind of makes this case in an article we're
going to link that he wrote over at Ars Technica that really kind
of goes into some of the history here,
because that's, I think, something that's really key
to understand about this, is this really kind of goes back
to January of 2019, when Greg KH decided he was done exporting
certain types of kernel symbols to non-GPL loadable kernel
modules.
Yeah, back then, that particular symbol
was keeping track of the state of the processor's floating
point unit.
And without access to that symbol,
external kernel modules, think ZFS,
which access the FPU directly, as ZFS does, well,
they've got to implement some of the code, the state
preservation logic, all on their own.
So once that symbol was no longer available to them,
that had to be done.
Right, and I remember when that change was made,
Greg was quoted as saying, quote,
my tolerance for ZFS is pretty non-existent.
And it kind of created a lot of drama.
It spawned a lot of chatter.
And it did create a breaking change
that the ZFS folks had to respond to.
So there's been some obvious kind of, not hostility,
but not really a will.
There's a hard line.
Maybe a reminder that these are not well-meshed systems,
that it certainly works very well.
But these two development communities
are not necessarily working together.
Right, and the hard lines, I think,
really form because of the licensing.
And that's where I think Linus got this thing right.
His concerns over licensing, I think, are reasonable.
He writes, honestly, there is no way
I can merge any of the ZFS efforts
until I get an official letter from Oracle.
Other people think it can be done,
or think it's OK to merge ZFS code into the kernel,
and that the module interface makes it OK.
That's their decision.
But considering Oracle's litigious nature
and the questions over licensing,
there's no way I can ever feel safe doing so.
And he goes on to discuss the flimsy nature of the shim.
But where it kind of goes off the rails
is when he says, don't use ZFS.
It's always more of a buzzword than anything else.
And the benchmarks I've seen don't make ZFS look
all that great.
And as far as I can tell, there's
no real maintenance behind it anymore.
Well, my jaw dropped when I saw that.
How about you, Jim?
Yeah, in a big way.
I do want to back things up a little bit, though.
Things were kind of already off the rails
when Linus started talking about how he couldn't integrate ZFS
into the kernel.
Because while I don't doubt that he has seen people ask that,
maybe even some people have asked him that directly,
he was responding to somebody.
And I'm sorry if I mispronounce your name
if you're listening, Jonathan Danti.
Jonathan had replied to Linus saying
that the number one priority for Linux
has been don't break existing users.
And he goes on to some degree about that, which is great.
And that has been a longstanding policy.
And it's an important one and a good one.
Jonathan says, I really appreciate
this pragmatic policy targeting user space application.
However, I have a question about a recent kernel change.
That was the one that Greg KH made his infamous snark about
that broke an important third party module, ZFS.
I don't want to flame and feel free not
to reply if you think I am.
But recently, the kernel FPU symbol was declared GPL only
and caused a significant issue for the ZFS on Linux project.
How do you feel about that?
Can you speak about the motivation?
Now, it's worth noting that at no point
does Jonathan say, hey, Linus, why won't you
pull ZFS into the kernel?
He just wants to know about why do we
stop exporting that symbol when that breaks a project
and we say we don't break users.
And how Linus opens up his response, he says,
note that we don't break users is literally
about user space applications.
And I'm alighting a couple of his words
here for brevity and clarity.
We don't break users about user space applications.
If somebody adds a kernel module like ZFS,
they're on their own.
I can't maintain it, and I can't be bound by other people's
kernel changes.
Yeah, his argument is that's not user space.
That's a module.
That's kernel space, and we can break that as much as we want.
Exactly.
And now, at this point, right there at this point,
he has answered Jonathan's entire question.
He has done so informatively and very usefully.
He's also, if he stopped right there,
done a lot to put a productive positive cap
on the controversy from Greg KH's change.
He says, hey, don't break user space is about user space.
A kernel module is not user space.
If you want to play in kernel space,
you've got to play with the big boys,
and that means that ABIs will break and you have to keep up.
And that's perfectly fair.
We were so close to not having to talk about this at all.
Exactly.
So he should have just clicked send right there.
When he starts saying, and honestly, there's
no way I can merge ZFS, blah, blah, blah, well,
nobody's asking you to right now.
And he's already gone off the rail there,
because I got to tell you, like you opened up,
I wrote a long, detailed article about this at Ars Technica.
We're up to 10 pages of comments now,
and I can't tell you how many people, because they've
read Linus' comment, they think now
that stopping the export of the kernel FPU begin symbol,
now they think that that's about license compliance.
And it never was.
It was just a maintenance thing.
It was tidying up.
Right.
And I think importantly here, where
it gets into comments about performance
and the state of maintenance, it really goes off the rails.
Because first of all, the performance
is an extremely complicated story,
but I'm not sure where he got the maintenance thing
from at all.
He may have maybe found an old repo or something,
but it seems like the ZFS on Linux project
is firing at all cylinders these days.
Well, so since then, he's kind of, and I got to be honest,
I mean, I don't know somebody the stature of Linus Torvalds
really cares what I think, but he really
disappointed me because he replied to that,
to where are you getting this unmaintained thing from.
And he kind of retconned it and said, oh, well,
if I say ZFS, obviously I'm talking about Oracle ZFS,
and maybe it's being maintained.
I don't know.
It's proprietary.
How can I tell?
Do you know if it's maintained?
And it's like, come on, dude.
I mean, how could you have been talking about Oracle ZFS
when you know perfectly well they don't need a Linux kernel
symbol export, and nobody using Linux and asking about ZFS
is asking about Oracle.
They're asking about ZFS on Linux, which is open ZFS,
and the GitHub repo is right there.
There were 5,000 code additions in the last month
at the time I wrote the article.
Yeah, and a great things, if you just look at over 2019,
landed in ZFS on Linux that really brought up
a parity with the BSDs and brought fantastic features,
some of which can lead to pretty decent performance,
like some great compression features.
When you look at ZFS itself, there
is this tendency to just write it off as a buzzword.
There's things I can build around it,
things like Red Hat Project Stratus, which
looks like a pretty nice collection of tools
with an API that could eventually
lead to some real serious alternatives.
Or we have our setup in the studio where our OS
and our boot drives and things of that type of nature
are ButterFS, and then our data storage is ZFS.
And we didn't have to pick a camp.
We use both for what they're great for.
But when it comes specifically to this kind of writing ZFS
and reducing it down to one variable, oh, it's a buzzword,
where is that coming from?
Because it's clearly used in production quite successfully.
But the only thing I can tell, I don't
know what kind of private conversations
senior developers like Greg KH and Linus might have,
but Greg has been pretty voluble about his disdain for ZFS
and what appears to be some anger about Sun having
released it under the cuddle, at the very least
with the knowledge that it probably would not
be license compatible with the GPL.
And he's made some pretty salty comments
about if they didn't want to work with me,
then why should I work with them?
The thing about that is, I mean, now we're
not talking about Oracle.
We're talking about Sun.
But to the best of my knowledge, we're
not talking about the actual developers.
Now, we do have some original Sun developers
that are very senior and very active in OpenZFS.
They basically, when Oracle bought Sun to begin with,
ZFS developers pretty much all quit and immediately
began the OpenZFS project, Matthew Ahrens
being one of those.
I haven't asked Matt about this, but I
find it hard to believe that the actual developers, some of whom
I know, were really all that keen on, hey,
let's make Linux not be able to use our crap.
That just reeks to me of Scott McNeely, who
he was the CEO of Sun.
And he absolutely on the record hated the crap out of Linux
and didn't want any of his stuff ever working on it.
Well, it competed with Solaris.
Yeah, well, I had the great displeasure
of attending a Scott McNeely keynote at an open source
conference a couple of years after Sun was bought by Oracle.
And he went on for nearly twice as a lot of time,
would not get off the stage, and would not
shut up about how the entire open source world was screwed
now if they didn't have their hero Scott
McNeely to protect them.
And all they had was crappy old Linux.
Right, and around that time, SCO was going to come and get us,
too.
So they were really feeling empowered at that time.
But I mean, that's the guy that didn't
want to cooperate with the Linux kernel maintainers
or anybody using the GPL who had the giant partisan agenda,
not the Open ZFS project, who is neither Sun's
corporate leadership nor has anything to do with Oracle.
That's a great point.
Yeah, I feel like it's pretty crappy to still be holding
that grudge and snarling about they
don't want to work with us.
Yes, times have changed.
The crew has changed.
The project location has changed.
And it's a really great project.
I wonder, too, though, can we just from,
because you address this, and I think it's worth touching on.
Can we talk about performance for a second?
Because there is some truth to the fact
that if you put ZFS up against an extended 4 disk
or a single XFS SSD, ZFS might be a little bit slower.
And so that performance thing is a bit of a touchy subject.
It is, but it's also an unusually complex subject.
If you just set up ZFS default and you run benchmarks
and compare it against EXT4 defaults or XFS defaults,
it will probably be slightly slower.
It's usually not going to be slow enough
to really notice unless you get yourself
wedged into a particularly pathological corner case involving
really, really heavily loaded SQL binaries stored on it
or something.
Sure.
But it will probably be slightly slower.
But here's the thing about that.
One, we're just talking about the defaults.
And I think it's reasonable to say
that most of the people that are using ZFS,
they want to dig a little deeper than that.
Even if they don't on day one, they eventually
get into looking at data sets and record sizes and all
this tuning stuff that can make an enormous difference.
And the other thing about that is there
is a very, very long history of benchmarking storage.
And one of the first rules of benchmarking storage
is you do absolutely everything possible to eliminate
any impact from file system cache.
So in the real world, you're doing everything
you possibly can to make sure as few reads as possible ever
hit the metal because you want to conserve those IOPS.
And you want to service those requests literally
like two, three orders of magnitude faster from RAM
in your cache, right?
So you want to eliminate that when you're benchmarking disks
or even usually when you're benchmarking file systems
because the assumption is cache will just completely wreck
the actual numbers that you care about because it makes
such an enormous impact.
And also, the assumption here is that all file systems
will cache the same way and to the same degree
of effectiveness.
Right, using the same probably kernel level algorithm for it.
Well, so one, up until very recently,
they've all used the same algorithm, which
is least recently used.
It's just slightly smarter than FIFO first in, first out.
An LRU cache, the way that works is as you read in a block,
it goes into cache.
If the cache is full, then the block
that has been sitting in the cache for the longest
without being read gets evicted to make room for the new one.
Now, every time you read a block from cache,
it gets jumped up to the top of the list
again like it's brand new.
So it is at least that smart.
But an LRU cache will very happily
evict every single block in it if you just
read a stream of data off the disk larger
than the size of the cache.
Now, every file system on every operating system I'm aware of,
other than ZFS, they share an operating system kernel level
cache facility.
On Linux, ext4, XFS, Butter, whatever you're using,
it's not just, they're not just all using the LRU cache.
They're all specifically using the Linux kernel page cache,
which is an LRU.
Now, over on the Windows side, NTFS, what have you,
it's using a page cache, which is LRU,
which is built into the Windows kernel.
But now when you look at ZFS, ZFS not only
doesn't use the operating system cache facility,
it also doesn't use an LRU cache.
It uses something called the ARC.
ARC stands for adaptive replacement cache.
And I like to explain it in simplistic terms
as you can think of it as a weighted cache.
So basically, every time you read a block,
it not only stays in cache, it gets a little heavier,
and it's harder to push it out.
So if you've got a block that has been in cache
and has been read from cache like 500 times,
but maybe it's been five minutes
since the last time it was read,
it's gonna be more difficult to evict that block
just because you read in some random thing off of disk,
because even if it hasn't been active for a few minutes,
the cache knows this block gets hit a lot.
It's really hot.
And it's even slightly smarter than that.
Let's say that a block never quite gets all the way
to the top of the cache, which are really hard to push out,
but it keeps getting read in and keeps getting evicted
and keeps getting read back in again.
Well, the ARC also tracks blocks
that have been recently evicted from cache.
So if you have a frequent flyer like that
that keeps getting evicted and bouncing back in,
the ARC notices that and starts being more reluctant
to evict it, because it's like,
I'm just gonna see this thing again pretty soon.
So the data impact here is that you have
a much higher hit rate in most real world workloads
from the ARC than you would from the LRU cache.
And as we discussed before,
the impact of cache is enormous.
Every time you serve a read request from cache,
you can serve IOPS and you also service
that individual request much, much, much faster.
Well, let me ask you this, am I right in saying then
it's also even a little trickier with the ZFS ARC
because it sounds like the adaptiveness of it
takes it a little bit to figure out,
oh, that is something they actually are using frequently.
I will add it.
Would that might not show up in a benchmark immediately?
I'm not sure.
You're correct.
It's very difficult to trigger in a synthetic benchmark.
Usually the gold standard for storage benchmarking
is a tool called FIO.
You can use FIO to model workloads.
You can say, I want read, I want write, I want random,
I want sequential, I want this block size,
I want this many processes.
You can mix it all together however you want.
And if you're bypassing cache,
it's a really, really amazing tool
for modeling your exact type of workload
and getting really realistic answers.
But once you start looking at something
that is as smart and adaptive as the ARC,
it gets really difficult to synthetically benchmark it
because the very synthesis tends to be way more random
than an actual workload.
So it doesn't really do a great job
of modeling the actual impact the ARC has
on you really doing real things
that really do read the same data over and over again.
Right.
Okay, and then there's sort of the big picture question.
Do you think there was some harm done by these statements?
I, you know, you notice it in the comments for sure.
Certain people will feel empowered now.
Is there long-term harm done here
because of just the scope of Linus's reach?
That's kind of a complicated question to answer.
The first answer is absolutely,
there's no question about it.
When you speak from a pulpit as tall with a mic
as heavily amplified as, you know, Linus Torvalds does,
when you take a crap on something, people notice.
Positive comments from Linus, for example,
got me, you know, that's what finally tipped me over
to actually look at WireGuard,
which was already on my radar
as a potentially cool VPN thing.
But I can't tell you how many potentially cool VPN things
that I've been like, I should look at that, and never did.
But Linus says, let me just say I love this code,
and that day when I see him say that, I'm installing it.
Yeah, that caught Wes and my attention the same.
Yeah, now with that said,
I mean, Linus taking a dump on something
is kind of less newsworthy
than him actually praising something.
So I don't know that it has quite the same impact,
but people absolutely do notice.
Also, honestly, you know, I feel like podcasts like this one
and, you know, articles like the one I wrote
immediately responding in a thoughtful, detailed way,
I do think they nerf a lot of that damage.
So it was a negative impact.
I don't think it's gonna be the end of the world
because the community responded and responded pretty well.
And it sends a pretty clear signal
that there is demand here.
You know, Wes and I were talking about this,
and it could be, in part,
if you look at Linux in production today in enterprises,
true, some of them, and some very well-known ones
are indeed using ZFS,
but probably at scale, most traditional shops
that have invested for, you know, maybe a few years ago,
they have a NAS or a SAN.
It's probably doing some sort of vendor magic hardware raid.
Could be that they've iSCSI'd out the disks
and they're just connecting them directly
to the different machines and handling them that way.
It could be they're using who knows what file system
on the backend, but it's likely not ZFS,
at least not if you bought something in the last five years.
So I wonder if part of this is just simply
at a practical user base level,
there's a lot of enthusiastic people
that are rolling custom solutions around ZFS
that work really well, but it's not at a scale
that like your SANs and your NASs are.
I don't know that I would necessarily
entirely agree with that.
I think there's a kernel of truth to it,
but I think you're probably discounting the popularity
of, you know, like the IX systems, you know,
that makes storage appliance.
I don't want to use the word storage appliance
because that's what Oracle calls their ZFS box,
but they make free NAS mini and they make true NAS
as their, you know, true enterprise product.
And there are a lot of those things, you know,
in the wild in businesses.
And there are a lot of, you know, just like free NAS
installations, you know, on individual boxes.
It's a pretty popular backend with like an iSCSI
or NFS transport, you know, to people's VMware
or KVM or whatever, you know, virtualization systems.
And then you've also got some people going hyper virtualized
like I do with the ZFS storage part
and the virtualization part all inside the same chassis.
Now I think that's considerably less common
because people are just so used to that idea
to separate the storage silo from the vert silo.
Right, it's essentially how we have it set up
in the studio those we have with Docker
instead of virtualization, but it's a similar setup for us.
And it, I think, you know, when you look at things
like ZFS send and compression that works really fast
and really well and just the overall like functionality,
it's a good option.
There's a lot of good options, but it's certainly a good one.
And I don't know if it's ever going to be possible.
And maybe this is my last question
because I'm curious to know your opinion on this
because obviously it's just opinion,
but I don't know if it's ever going to be possible
for it to be officially mainlined.
I think it's possible.
I certainly wouldn't bet anything
that you can't afford to lose on it.
You know, the current situation is that
there's just not really anybody with a good reason
to try to bring an enforcement suit, you know,
against mixing the GPL in the cuddle.
That was my opinion before Canonical went all, you know,
yellow swag in 2016 and just started shipping ZFS headers,
you know, in their mainline kernels.
I don't know if you knew that by the way,
but Canonical doesn't just have ZFS in the repos.
If you're using an Ubuntu machine
with a kernel from Canonical,
there are a cuddle licensed headers built into that kernel,
whether you installed ZFS or not.
But yeah, even before Canonical just went all yellow
and decided to do it, my position was, you know,
I don't see where anybody would want
to bring a suit like that
because there's literally no good outcome out of it.
It feels like the most likely honestly
would be a GPL partisan, you know,
folks who are really, really invested in the GPL
get really, really pissed about this particular topic,
but they don't want to bring that suit
because it's a risky ass suit.
And if you bring a GPL enforcement lawsuit
against somebody bundling cuddle
and it doesn't go your way in court,
well now you've weakened the GPL
and you've weakened enforcement efforts.
And that's certainly not anything
that somebody who's big into the GPL wants.
I don't want that.
On the other hand, if you win,
you've also set a precedent
that's really going to put Linux very far back
because if you win a cuddle enforcement lawsuit
that says you can't have a cuddle kernel module,
well you can't have Nvidia drivers either.
Those are freaking proprietary.
Now you can't have Nvidia drivers.
You can't have, you know, hardware drivers
for industrial stuff that requires dongles or whatever.
You can't do any of all that proprietary.
You have just made Linux unusable
for an enormous portion of industry that it's in right now.
And now you're just hoping everybody goes BSD
instead of going to freaking Windows or something.
Nobody wants that.
This has got to be the calculation that Canonical's made
is that it's just too destructive of a fight
for either side.
What if they won?
What if they took it to court,
the GPL folks take it to court and they won,
the ZFS user base would get drained too.
I mean, it would be so damaging
to not just things like dongles,
but anything else like that to your point.
But transversely, if they didn't win,
it would be so damaging because you would just see,
you would see folks no longer have the motivation
to mainline their code.
They would just come up with these shim solutions
and call it good.
And the knock-on effects would be felt for years.
Yeah, absolutely.
I don't think that Canonical only had my thoughts there
about, you know, nobody is going to be,
nobody with any sense is going to be motivated
to bring this suit.
I do believe that their lawyers also told them,
you know, look, we think this is fine.
We're totally willing to take this to court.
We think we'll come out on the other side of it.
I know many years before Canonical did that,
I want to say it was like 2012, 2013.
I was very interested in the same question.
I was about a year or two deep into, you know,
my ZFS on Linux journey.
I was several more years deep with ZFS,
you know, on FreeBSD initially.
And I convinced a local intellectual property lawyer
to co-author a presentation with me
for an open source conference.
And basically, you know, I kind of brought him up to speed
on the technical details.
And, you know, he took a look at it from a legal perspective.
And to my surprise, his conclusion was not only, you know,
yes, you can get away with installing ZFS on Linux
and then like selling somebody a system with that installed.
He was like, you know, I'd be perfectly willing
to take a course case defending,
just putting ZFS directly in the kernel.
I think it'd be good to go.
And he had a lot of reasons for that.
Some of which I have seen repeated elsewhere,
some of which were mostly, you know, his take.
But basically what I'm seeing is, you know,
every time somebody who is an actual law professor
or an actual practicing IP lawyer
comments publicly on this,
they seem to all be commenting, nah,
I think we can work this out in court.
That has been my observation as well.
Kernel has a question, aptly named, in the mumble room
about maybe Oracle playing a long game here.
Letting everybody get all ZFSed up
and then coming in with a big old lawsuit.
Yeah, Kernel, is that your thought that that's their scheme?
Yeah, I was thinking, you know,
if they hold the intellectual property rights
and they let everybody integrate it
and then they go after people,
it'd be a lot harder for us to switch over
to, you know, BcashFS or something else.
It would, but again,
that's not really in Oracle's best interests either
because Oracle is a significant Linux player
and it's gonna be really damaging for them
if all of a sudden unbreakable Linux
becomes completely freaking useless
because of a court case that they instigated
that set the precedent
that you can't have proprietary loadable Kernel modules.
And that actually seems like a big deal
to Oracle's customer base too, in particular.
Exactly, I just, I don't see that happening
because again, I think that it would damage them badly
if they won such a suit.
Now, what I used to worry about,
I worried about a poison pill effect
where Oracle, you know, might take a long time
to let interest in open ZFS build up,
wait for it to reach a critical mass,
then say, oh, hey, Oracle ZFS is now GPLed
and can be integrated in the Kernel.
Open ZFS can't, you know, ha ha, LOL.
And now everybody's, you know, scrambling to, you know,
get on board the Oracle thing and yada, yada, yada.
I'm less worried about that now
because what I hadn't understood at the time,
and this is the thing that most people
who get vocal about this topic
seem not to quite understand,
the terms of the cuddle that Solaris ZFS
was first licensed under,
they include the ability for the licensed steward
who is defined as the initial developer of a project.
In this case, that would be Sun Microsystems,
which has now been purchased by Oracle.
So the initial developer is the licensed steward
and the licensed steward may issue
a new version of the license.
If that happens, the covered code can now be used
under the terms of either cuddle 1.0
or the new license version introduced by the licensed steward.
So it's completely possible for Oracle to fix this
should enough, you know, grassroots irritation,
you know, get them motivated.
If they were to make, you know,
the last Solaris ZFS before they turned it proprietary,
if they were to add, you know,
cuddle version 3.0 monkey blue or whatever,
that just happened to be exactly, you know,
the MIT license or the simplified BSD license,
you know, which was weak permissive,
but also, you know, GPL compatible.
If they did that, that would automatically cover open ZFS
as well as, you know,
well, it wouldn't have to cover Oracle ZFS
because again, you know, they own that code
and it doesn't have to apply to what they did
because as the owner, they can say,
well, we're no longer offering that.
But if they did that,
that would immediately fix everything for the open ZFS folks.
It would not require everybody
who's ever contributed open ZFS code or Solaris ZFS code,
it doesn't require them to okay it
because again, if you contributed to the project
to begin with, you had to contribute under cuddle one
and if there wasn't an exclusion
for the future license version clause,
which there was not for Solaris ZFS,
then that's just, you know,
you agreed to that when you contributed to begin with.
So it's good to go.
You've essentially just laid out a potential path
to eventual mainlining.
And I wonder if we talked about the damage
this could have potentially done these statements by Linus,
but I wonder if there isn't potentially
a longer term greater good
if the top kernel developers play hardball,
they sort of force Oracle's hand maybe long-term
to do just what you laid out.
I don't know that anybody can really force
Oracle's hand on this.
I think the potential path to success,
and this is something I've discussed at some length
with Brad Kuhn of the Software Freedom Conservancy.
He and I don't completely see eye to eye on this topic.
He's a lot more of a traditional hardline GPL partisan
than I am, whereas I'm a definite GPL fan on my own code.
I licensed GPL v3, but I'm a little,
maybe a little bit more pragmatic about it.
But at any rate, what Brad said,
and it makes a lot of sense to me,
is that the way that you maybe potentially
get Oracle to resolve this,
it amounts to a grassroots campaign.
You get enough pressure, enough complaining,
enough why won't you fix this?
This is a thing of great good
you could do at no cost to yourself.
Maybe eventually you convince them that,
yeah, all right, we'll do that.
Sure, it'll make us look like good guys.
We could use some good PR.
It's not like we get a lot.
That's my hope.
I mean, maybe it's, I think, you know,
of course there's gonna be people
that completely disagree if that's even possible,
but gosh, I sure like to think it could be one day.
It is possible.
Like I said, I'm not betting anything
I can't afford to lose against it,
but it's absolutely possible.
To one degree, it's already been done.
Brad hounded, and other people,
hounded Oracle relentlessly
about being the biggest GPL violator on the planet
by shipping a detrace with Unbreakable Linux's kernel
for years and years and years.
Yes, right.
And they got him to fix it.
And they fixed it the exact same way
that we're discussing right now.
They added, you know, weak permissive license to it,
and problem solved, you can now ship it with the kernel.
That's true.
So this is not theoretical.
This could be done.
We know exactly how to do it.
It's just a question of, you know,
do we have the collective will to make a great big,
you know, public stink in the right way
to convince Oracle that, you know, yes, we should do this.
I think it's building.
And the kernel developers not being willing to bend
also sort of, I think, does hold a line.
Yeah, and again, I'm not mad at them about that.
I do not think Linus is wrong for his opinion
that, you know, we should never integrate Cuddle code,
you know, into the kernel, which is GPLv2.
Right.
And although, again, he shouldn't have brought it up
the way he did and the context he did.
And the other thing is, you know,
his whole thing about I get an official letter from Oracle,
no, that's stupid.
You either resolve the license conflict
because Oracle has, you know, added weak permissive to it,
or it's resolved, you know, in a court,
somebody brings in an enforcement lawsuit and loses,
and now you have a court precedent that states,
no, it's totally kosher, you know, to mix CDDL and GPL.
At that point, that's when it becomes okay.
Yeah.
But until then, no, Linus is totally right for saying,
you know, we're not gonna mix Cuddle and GPL code.
That's fine.
Right.
Linus is also completely fine to say,
we don't break users is about users,
but we can't extend that guarantee to kernel space.
You wanna play in kernel space,
you gotta play like a kernel developer,
you gotta keep up.
That's fine.
Yeah, reasonable.
And what the expectation has been
for a long time in that regard.
I agree.
Yeah, it was just some of the other comments about it.
Well, all right.
I feel like we've got our head around it.
So thank you.
Thank you, Jim.
I appreciate you joining us to break that down.
And we'll link to the Ars Technica post that Jim wrote
that goes into even more detail
and some of the history in the show notes.
And Wes, before we go, we should probably do some picks.
We've got a good batch, one that I've already been using
since I'm on a remote connection
with a very limited bandwidth.
So it's time for some picks.
Ooh, yeah, something you can play with
while you're stuck at home.
Yeah.
Now, who found Bandwich,
the terminal bandwidth utilization tool
that was, I think it used to be known as what?
Yeah, you know, I've seen this floating around.
It looks to be a somewhat recent,
it is written in Rust, so I knew you would like it.
And that means they've got simple single binary releases.
You can go download from GitHub
if you just want to give it a casual try
without installing it.
Now, can you spell that for me?
It's band, B-A-N-D-W-H-I-C-H.
And it's up on GitHub.
We'll put a link in the show notes.
It's in the Arch repo.
And it's in, apparently, it's in void Linux.
And it's also, if you've got a Mac, it's a brewable.
Not doing anything unique here,
but it is a really handy, simple display
of what connections are going on from which programs.
Yeah, well, and I was surprised when I ran it
that a couple of applications I had paused syncing on,
and those apps were still communicating,
just like doing heartbeat check-ins or whatnot.
But right now, every single bit
when you're broadcasting from the snow counts.
So I went and closed a browser that was checking in,
probably bookmark sync or something,
and I closed those applications.
And I think it's, I think it's been kind of helpful,
specifically for today, so it was sort of perfect.
But a follow-up pick, previously, on Linux Unplugged,
we reviewed, or picked, STUI,
a terminal-based CPU stress and monitoring utility.
Well, it actually worked out pretty great
because Joe was running it last night on his machine
and discovered that he had a clogged fan with this thing.
So just a replug for STUI,
the terminal-based CPU stress and monitoring utility.
It's got real pretty graphs right there in the terminal
and an optional stress feature if you want to actually
put some load on your system.
Put it under stress.
But we're not done yet.
There's more picks, Wes.
Oh, yeah, okay.
So we've talked a little bit about Firefox Send,
Mozilla's offering to be able to quickly, securely,
and easily send files.
That works great in a browser,
but you know me, I'm mostly in the terminal, Chris.
So FFSend is also Rust-based,
but it's a terminal CLI interface to Firefox Send.
That's awesome.
Firefox Send from the command line.
And then last but not least, Age.
Yes, it's called Age.
It's a simple and modern secure encryption tool
with small, explicit keys,
no configuration you got to worry about,
and it goes together like a regular old UNIX command.
You'll grok it immediately.
We have a link in the show notes for that as well.
Sometimes you just want to encrypt a single file, right?
Maybe you've got some archive or you just have
a single backup or you just want to, you know,
have something safe and secure for transit.
But we've all tried to use BGP or GPG,
and it's just a horrible mess every time.
This tool uses some nice modern cryptography,
and it's a lot simpler to interface with.
You know, I was thinking about doing
my Docker compose files with this
and then throw them on a cloud storage provider
just to have some easy accessible backup that's offsite.
So there you go.
There you go.
A simple, modern encryption tool for the command line, Age.
And we have more picks than that,
but we realized we're going to have other podcasts.
So we should probably save them,
but we got pick-plorific on our holiday break, Wes.
Yes, we did.
Although that doesn't mean we're not still soliciting
some good picks or any other feedback from the audience.
Well, I got some feedback for you right now.
Real time.
I took a look at Bandwitch.
It looks pretty cool.
It's got a really nice looking interface.
I like that.
But if you want something that's already in repos
and it's just an app getaway on Ubuntu or Debian,
the most direct old school, you know,
tool that serves the same basic function is called NetHogs.
Oh, yes.
NetHogs does the same thing.
It'll show you all your connections.
It shows you process ID as well as, you know,
the termination points on both source and destination.
And there's also IFTOP.
IFTOP does not show you process ID.
So you can't tell if, you know,
if it's Apache or NGINX or, you know, Firefox
or what have you on your end that's using the bandwidth,
but it does show you the source and destination terminations.
And it's very useful if that's all you're looking for.
Both of those are in the main repos
on pretty much everything.
Good ones.
Yes, I love NetHogs.
Thank you.
Yeah, and like Wes was saying,
if you have something that's a really handy desktop app,
command line app, or even a web app
that makes using Linux a little easier,
do let us know.
We've got a year of podcasts.
We have now taken our totality of breaks for the entire year
and the Linux Unplugged show never misses a beat.
So we would love to hear your feedback,
your picks, all of that.
LinuxUnplugged.com slash contact.
Jim, thank you for joining us.
Really appreciate it and the real time feedback.
Go catch more of Jim over at TechSnap.Systems.
He and Wes are cracking over there these days.
Been absolutely loving it.
And there's a whole back catalog
if you haven't been listening, so go grab that.
Also, join us live next week.
JBLive.tv on an old Tuesday.
We do it now at noon Pacific.
You can get converted to your local time skis
over at JupiterBroadcasting.com slash calendar.
And you can find me on Twitter.
I'm at ChrisLAS.
What about you, Wes?
I'm at Wes Payne.
And what about you, Jim?
JRSSnet.
Magic, there you have it.
That's it.
That's the podcast from the snowpocalypse.
Don't forget about that live stream on Friday,
assuming I can survive and get out there.
Hopefully my water will unfreeze
and my vehicles will become unburied.
You'll be a little leaner by then, but that's okay.
It's really not that bad.
I put the video on the YouTube channel.
I mean, it's really not that bad,
but it's kind of fun for us.
And people in Western Washington
have no idea what to do with it.
So it kind of, it makes it a whole nother bit.
It makes it an event.
I'm really grateful I was just able to get back
for our first show of the year
and we're still able to make it work
via the remote connection.
You never know.
And there's always more when you join us live.
So do that.
Thanks so much for joining us here on this week.
And we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
If you analyzed this video or found it interesting,
see what you find in YouTube ICO in the description under.
Also being good to know,
you come across many VIINAL manicurists
and other anonymous people using VR for their smallrtr supply.
These are primarily non-descript or non- limite.
Okay, thank you everybody, JBtitles.com.
Let's go vote on our title, take care of our final business, and then get this shipped
over to Joe so he can edit it up.
Yeah, we really need some voting here to prune through all the great suggestions.
It's funny how we're running out of sounds for music.
We're at the point that we're starting to run out of, you know, simple like chord structures
for music.
Like you just, I don't think you can really invent one of those anymore.
That's what people say about movies too, you know, we're running out of new stuff, except
for podcasts.
There's always a new podcast out there.
There's always new podcasts.
I will say I am very happy that movies are finally starting to get the message that cell
phones are a thing though.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's an entire plot point.
I mean, when I watch like Die Hard and Cliffhanger and stuff, it's an entire point of the plot
that they can't communicate because they can't, or they got to make it to a payphone in time
and in Die Hard 3, they're all about running from phone to phone.
Yeah.
What a different world.
And yet so similar.
There was a real like run of movies in the 90s where the bad guy was over the phone.
The bad guy is always over the phone and it's a whole dramatic bit of it.
It's really funny.
Sometimes they just fix it by releasing an EMP.
It's a dark outlook, but yeah.
You've got the phone.
Not anymore.
I think I might maybe just jam the frequency instead, but you do you, buddy.