So we've been on the road for a couple of weeks and this is normally the time when I come on the air and tell
You how something broke in the rv or maybe I broke myself trying to fix whatever's broken in the rv
But I gotta say
Jupes is doing great. Those investments are paying off right? You got those shocks
You've been I mean fixing slides since the day I met you
Must be working now, huh?
Yeah, yeah
Yeah, the rv's working great
But the home server that runs pretty much everything like home assistant my sync thing my media server
My documentation my scheduling system all
of that
It died while we were down at jpl
Came back to a dead server
It only it's always something that breaks in the space where we aren't I know right?
I thought it might have been down because I couldn't connect a home assistant. I thought okay
Well could be home assistants hung up could be a networking issue or it could be something much worse
It turns out it was much worse
so now
no, I think you'll hear us do an episode on home servers soon because
Uh, you know, who knows what i'm gonna do. I gotta figure that out in the meantime
I guess the show must go on another episode of what not to do with chris
So
Hello friends and welcome back to your weekly linux talk show. My name is chris. My name is les and my name is brent
Hello gentlemen coming up on the show today. We all get a front row seat to linux history in the making
We'll take you behind the scenes of our tour of nasa's jet propulsion laboratory and our thoughts on a famous linux platform
Getting shut down and then we'll round out the show some boosts and picks and a lot more
So before we go any further, I want to say a big good morning to our friends over at tail scale
Tail scale is a mesh vpn protected by wire guard. We use it. It's what connects all of our machines
It's what's making the show possible right now and it'll change your game
Go to tailscale.com and try it out for free for up to 20 devices at tailscale.com
So we are on the road
We are at listener jeff's right now
in sacramento, california
Just got done with the big pasadena meetup and the jpl tour which we will tell you about in a little bit
I feel like i'm still buzzing from that experience of so much great stuff there and that might be the hangover. Oh
Or some of those chemicals they use, you know for the
What for the science experiments and all is it the chem chem trails? Is that what you said?
Yeah, he did. He did break into that one room that he wasn't supposed to go into
It was like I like the color red and everything was red in there
Yeah, but that thing said chem trails don't go in. What'd you do?
You went in
But before we get into all of that, I wanted to talk about something that's been sent into the show quite a bit
We've been asked over and over again about our thoughts on stadia getting shut down google stadia
You remember it was launched as google's big entrance into game streaming and it was going to bring so many game developers
Over to linux to get things compatible with stadia
Stadia is only the newest most logic defined mind-bending absurd gaming platform on earth
Forget boxes forget consoles just your games your screens and electric air and this electric air is
stadia
Well absurd might be right 412 linux on twitter wrote sadly at chris last is the first person
I thought of after reading the stadia update. He really did believe in it. Can't wait to hear his thoughts on at linux unplugged
And if you missed the news
While we were on the road google wrote
That they are shutting down stadia changing strategies
And they will be refunding all stadia hardware purchases and game purchases to players. I didn't expect that part
I mean it does I think somewhat ease my frustration because
I mean i've been predicting stadia's downfall for what a couple of years now
Yeah, we all have
Everybody knew this day was coming
And I think that's actually maybe what sort of prevented it from being a success
In the first place
Is this like the moment where when your predictions comes true for the year or wes is wes usually makes this prediction
I can't remember. We'll have to review. I don't know if I did this year. Well, yeah, we'll find out
Unfortunately soon, you know the verge blamed linux
How come the verge writes google spent millions convincing publishers like ubisoft and take two to bring their biggest games to stadia
They go on to say
Google had to pay such large sums because of the work to port their games over wasn't particularly easy given stadia
Runs on linux a platform game developers haven't paid enough attention to I mean they're not wrong in the sense that yeah
That probably made this more difficult than if you were trying to set up some sort of you know
windows game streaming environment, but
at least by google's read they expected more user adoption and I don't know if the
One of those two were directly connected. I kind of liked a take I saw over at tech crunch which which said
Stadia died because no one trusts google. I agree with that take
I think that's that's why I never got into it as much as I wanted it to be a hit
And I really wanted it to create a network effect where developers begin porting more and more games over to linux
I think you could argue it was good for vulcan adoption. Yeah, it does seem like the
The bare bones of the like the technical side of this actually actually worked pretty darn well, you know
Like linux between all the work that valve is put in between the work that obviously google and then the stadia folks have put in
Between all the regular good linux stuff
Linux is ready for games. I just don't know if the world is ready for games on linux
Especially on google. Is there a connection between
Sort of steam doing its work and stadia coming out at the same time because it seems like those two were overlapping and I wonder
Which one made which possible?
Is it is it that google brought more attention to gaming on linux and that steam was able to take that?
Sort of energy and make it really run
No, I think you know, the linux side was kind of hidden over at stadia to me
it just seems that I don't know if anyone believes google can have a
Exciting new independent division that exists beyond their like core ad tech or youtube platform
And also the need for me personally with stadia was reduced when proton got good and I could run most games that I didn't
Have access to before on my machine again, right stadia was a little bit better of a solution
when I didn't have a local option for that stuff, but when
Proton came along and proton was pretty pretty good. Then I could just play that stuff on my computer again
So I think in some ways valve's entrance maybe harmed stadia's overall momentum, but I don't think it really could
Probably be accused of anything more than that. The other side of this too is you know
Even as a stadia sometimes stadia user feels like a lot of technologies these days
Like some apple products or sometimes tesla products or other things where I really like the technology
But the way it ends up being presented to the consumer and all the all the top layers of it
Just doesn't work for me
And I don't know like I was never going to get that excited about stadia because even at the in the best use case
How much was I going to really invest in it? It was never going to be fully under my control
I was just going to be depending on internet pipes and uh, you know google to keep running it
yeah, it's even worse than the compromise you make with the steam store where
You know when you buy games through valve, I guess they could technically take them away
but you when you install them you're at least downloading them and installing them locally and you've paid for them and you can put them on
other computers and other devices like the deck when those come out but with stadia
You are always tied to google in a very direct way in a way that made a better experience honestly because i've tried g force
I even tried on live back in the day and none of them were quite as good as google because they chopped off some of that
Uh user interface stuff and just got you right into the game
But classically like microsoft before them and and now how google seems to emulate what they once so much hated they don't
They don't fully embrace a technology like this
I should have been able to look up a game on youtube, you know, destiny 2 or star trek online
Look up that game on youtube watch a gamer and then one click
Inside the youtube ui I should have been able to transform that into a gaming experience
Launch the game in my browser and start playing within seconds. Google has the technology
They even they even talked about doing that at one point
They just never pulled the trigger because you could tell even internally at google. They just didn't have the support
They didn't even believe it themselves. It would stick around and I don't know if that's true
Stick around and I guess the upshot is is the only way they can save face and prevent a controversy is by refunding everybody
Which is probably going to cost them a pretty little penny
Yeah, people are also concerned that all those controllers out there unless google enables bluetooth on them
Which they have the hardware for i'm led to believe but just wasn't ever turned on
Well, that could also be a bunch of e-waste
I guess we should probably make it clear that this isn't actually going into effect until
Until january, I think it is so you still have a few months. Yeah, january 2023
Uh, they they said you have you got some time for quote unquote final play sessions
Yeah, yeah, you know go get your gameplay out now, I guess
But I imagine that if you've spent like I don't know 80 000 hours or so on playing a game
You can't even transfer it out. So what the heck it's so dumb. Yeah that part. I just don't get I don't understand why
Uh, they didn't like give you the option to maybe get a steam key or something. Maybe it's the competitive angle
I don't know what it is
But uh, not good enough chief not good enough
This is disappointing to see and the refund helps but it's not going to make me
Stop thinking everything google launches. They eventually are going to kill now. That's just like they just confirmed it
We are on the road again
On the road again
Just can't wait to get on the road again. This one has been a busy blur
There has been multiple phases of this road trip
I think we're like on the fifth phase right now because we got down to grant's pass like two weeks ago
We had a meet up down there. Then we got down to sacramento
We had another meet up there and we got to park here at listener jeff's house where we've got power and ethernet like
Kings, you know
It's nice over here. Then we uh, we switched from the rv and we switched to the car and we took the car down to pasadena
Which is like another seven hours from sacramento. Yeah, in case you've never been to california. It's obscenely giant. It's huge
It's way too huge. This is definitely it should be two states. There's no doubt about it in my mind
And then you get to pasadena where we had an airbnb as a team
So we flew in some of the team and we hung out there and uh, we did the jpl tour
Which we'll tell you about here in a little bit and then we did the pass
Adena meetup, which was our largest meetup yet and just an absolute blast
And along each of these major five phases of this road trip
We have been dropping geo caches all along the way as little treats for you guys
That could be listening today that could be listening a year down the road
Maybe you couldn't make it to a meetup. Maybe you're not even in that area today
But one day you will be we have little treasures for you that we have stashed throughout the west coast
And brent you did one of the first ones in southern oregon just north of grants pass at that little rest stop that the seven
Feathers casino has yeah hadia and I uh figured we actually talked a long time about like how hard do we make this?
Because we want people to find it. That's definitely true, but we don't want just random people finding it
We want jb listeners to be the ones finding it. So that was a bit of a tricky go
But we did find at this rest stop
A giant wall of boulders that seemed like just the perfect place. So we stashed this little geocache
It's got a bunch of really great stuff in it. It's got some swag t-shirts. It even has a freaking computer in there
So I feel like it's a wonderful to find if you do find it
Well, please work hard to find it because there's some great stuff in there
And if you do find it take some audio and uh, take some video as well send that our way
We would love to hear about how you find it
And um, also feel free to take the stuff and put new stuff in there and even I don't know
Start a journal of all the people that have found it just get creative like that
I like that but but no bsd stuff, right? Right? No kidding. Jeez gross. We like the idea of something that people could
Uh go look for when they're visiting the area. So look in the canyonville, oregon cow creek rest stop area
And hopefully you'll find something that you like
And then the lady and I we stashed the second
Geocache in sacramento in fulsome california
There is a hydro plant that has been retired that's open to the public worth going just for that
I think johnny cash played a really famous concert near there. Okay, nice good little hint, too
And uh at this retired hydro dam
There is a little nice space down by the water a little park area just to hang out and there is some burnt trees
That's your hint. It's in that general facility. We will have gps coordinates for all of these but they only get you within so close
So you're gonna need these hints too and that one so that one's in uh, sacramento in fulsome california area
And uh, also some good stuff in there again a little mini-carousel
In fulsome california area and uh, also some good stuff in there again a little mini computer in there some t-shirts
Some stickers feel free to leave a note and take the note that we've put in there for you and leave something else
Uh, because that's just too much fun. And then wes you got to hide one in pasadena
Yes, I did
Well here I am in beautiful downtown pasadena
The meetup's over the jpl trip is done and it's time to go home but
Before that i've got one last task
I've got a geocache to hide
Ah here we are this looks like a nice little spot
Good luck pasadena wes, I would love to know like give us more hints
I I feel like I need to know kind of what's out there. Was it on a beach?
Was it in a forest? Was it kind of in the middle of the city?
Oh, it's in the middle of the city. All right, and let me just say downtown pasadena
Absolutely, lovely. I hadn't been back there, uh since we went to scale a few years ago
So it was it was nice to get to see the city. It was nice to get to see the city
It was nice to get to see the city
Hopefully I hadn't been back there since we went to scale a few years ago. So it was it was nice to get to
Spend a little bit of time there on my last day
Let's see a hint. Okay
Well, there's a nice little park in downtown pasadena with some beautiful trees
Those trees
They seem they seem to have more than a few nooks and crannies. So maybe start there
All right, that's a good hint. I can I can I can almost kind of picture it already
The sacramento one I think is only hard because there's so many nooks and crannies it could be in
So we'll see the pasadena one. I imagine it's a little tricky too because there's probably a lot of area
There um, you know, well, can you trim it down? Is it in a nook or is it in a crane?
I'm not gonna classify that come on. That's above my pay grade
Okay, fine. This road trip has been a
Blur it feels like it's been one long monday. In fact, do check out office hours 13
We recorded that down at the airbnb and we recounted a lot of the story behind the scene stuff getting down here
So if you're curious about what the trip has been like some of the stories some of the meetup stuff
Do check out office hours 13 office hours dot hair
but I want to get more into some of the history we got to see being made at jpl and some of just
The real world uses of linux, you know, we talk about it here on the show
But to go somewhere and see them using it in these mission critical situations
It's always so educational
So I want to talk about all that seriousness
But before we get there, I want to have a little fun
And there was a moment where listener jeff who's been hosting us here at his house
Took us out to one of his favorite local diners a great staff there
They seemed like a lot of fun and I got myself a nice stack of pancakes
And after I got done eating these pancakes
I wanted to know what our local maple syrup experts opinion was on what I had just eaten
Okay, brent reviews the local syrup
Okay, this is actually a very small mug of syrup presentation is top notch
Fragrance is nice
It's it's it's it seems a little more on the golden side than the that darn kirkland brand we had the other day
ready
Oh my god, okay, so
It's definitely not maple syrup and uh
What do I just eat
It's like corn syrup or something
With a tiny bit of maple in it perhaps but the texture is all wrong
So that's my review with brent. I'm still trying to get that mouth feel out of here
Like I just it was such a bad experience. I I kind of loathe that you put me through that
I thought when I handed it over to him saying I'm not going to do that
So you got to picture it. It's in a mini. Um, what are those mugs called brent like those, uh,
Hmm, it's kind of like one of those mason jars with the handles on it. Yeah, it's a mason jar mug
But it's a smaller one and it's filled with syrup. So they give you a ludicrous amount of syrup. It was just right
Okay. All right canadian. So, uh, I put on the pancakes and I you know, I was hungry and I ate them all up
And i'm like this syrup
It's not so good. And it's not so good. It's not so good
It's not so good. And I wanted to see what his take was
And then you just kind of like tore into it you troll
That was one of my highlights of the trip. So as you can imagine
Um, i've had some fun with brent. We tell it all in office hours 13. So do check that out
Lino dot com slash unplugged go there to get a hundred dollars in 60 day credit on a new account
And it is a great way to support the show while checking out something awesome because linode is fast reliable cloud hosting with the best
Support in the biz i'm talking about like real humans all day everyday humans that are right there fixing your problems on the first call
Not like this multi-tiered weird support system where you got to start a chat with somebody and then like they can escalate you to a
Phone call but then that person can't no
No
Linode has built their business differently
So that way they can provide you great support while also continually investing in their infrastructure
Linode
Is gonna go crazy crazy. Linode is blowing out the doors and they're adding
I think it's 11 more data centers or something like that
So they got 11 data centers now and I think they're going to like 12 more additional data centers
It's it's wild you guys linode is just really moving these days
They invest back into their infrastructure and just make it better and better since i've been a customer
I have seen mvme hard drives. I have seen new amd epic processors roll out
I've seen upgrades to their infrastructure. I've seen new services come along like managed database services
I've seen improvements to their physical servers that you can deploy and of course
I have begun to just use the absolute heck out of their s3 compatible object storage
And they're 30 to 50 cheaper than the hyperscalers that just want to lock you into their crazy esoteric platforms
30 to 50 cheaper is no joke
That adds up immediately
And on top of that they got the best performance. That's not chris saying that's not brent sitting over there quietly saying that
You go google it. It's been tested right right see brent's nodding. He knows
He knows he knows and it's just got great features as well easy backups and so much more
So go build something go learn something
And try it for yourself and thank them for supporting us on this road trip, too
Head over to linode.com
Get that hunny dollars and 60 day credit on a new account, you know treat yourself. You deserve it and support the show
linode.com
We have a few things I want to tidy up around here before we get into the rest of the show
We have one more meetup. I want to let you know about friday, october 7th in portland
It's the last meetup of 2022's west coast tour. Come hang with us. We're we're at the brewery
Um, which I cannot remember the name of at the moment
But the details are at meetup.com slash jupiter broadcasting we'd love to see you there
These meetups have been absolutely fantastic and it's the last one
Then we're done talking about it. And if you're in that west coast crew
Stick around you'll hear about future meetups there first bit.ly slash west coast crew for our matrix room migration brewing
Thank you. Look at that west coming in with the hot facts right there migration brewing
Very nice. Thank you west pain
So check it out meetup.com slash jupiter broadcasting for all those details. We'd love to see you there
And we got a baller boost into the show this week so we love getting to your boosts
They're a great way to communicate with the show and the way to exchange a little value for value
And we want to highlight the big boosts that come into the show every single week
And ladies and gentlemen prepare yourselves because he's done it
for a fifth week in a row
John a is our big baller for linux unplugged this week
Unbelievable sir unbelievable. He says, uh, yes, I uh, he because we pre-recorded so he got in on a technicality last week
And he says yes, in fact
That was an accident on my case, but I am more than fine with that. You guys have been on fire lately
He sent in
And one sats into the show this week. So we really appreciate that john. Thank you so much the big ballers
Those are the moments when those come in you're like, okay, this gives me this gives me a little energy
It's like a little hit of like dopamine. Yes. All right. Let's go. Let's keep working and boy. Did we need that?
Today so john a thank you very very much. We appreciate that. Unfortunately, we were not able to stream live this week. So, um,
We uh, we did have some tech issues. We weren't really I actually thought we weren't gonna have an episode
I thought we weren't gonna have an episode then you see boosts like that come in. You're like no we got to keep going
We got to do it. We got to do it for john out there
So thank you very much john
We appreciate it and we have more boosts that we'll get to later in the show
If you'd like to send one and get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com
So let's talk about how we ended up at the jet propulsion laboratory because I think not everyone is familiar with the story
And it starts with a mutual love for linux, doesn't it with listeners?
And brothers that listen to the show and work at jpl
And we started talking with tim who was at the time like the mars helicopter operations leader
I think he's I think he's had a title upgrade since then and we knew tim was a kindred spirit when we started talking
Linux and solaris with him on the show
So jpl for many years was a solaris house, right? You know when I came out of school
Everybody wanted a big solaris workstation. Yep, you know the old spark workstations. They were pretty cool. They were cool
And so I got you know, I kind of came up the you can call it the unix curve learning how to
work on solaris and you know the
the flight project side used solaris a lot
and
Prior to getting on curiosity, which is the the big rover that's still on mars and operating
um, I had been on a project where we were doing a lot of
software technology development and
We could kind of see the writing on the wall that solaris was
starting to decline in the marketplace, so we in our own project we went and started looking at alternatives and
I just bought a pc made out of random parts
You know just commodity parts at the time
and
loaded linux on it
And took the software that we had on that project and compiled all that software on linux
and it was kind of a somewhat comical moment because one of the senior engineers in the project had had gotten his
$15,000 son solaris workstation
That he you know, he wanted as a senior guy
And we had the software compiling on both
And I took my my little commodity level pc and compiled the software
And and it compiled twice as fast
And he just had this look of what do they waste all my money on?
Yes, he just just just look came over his face like I can't believe that
And he ended up pawning off the whole system to an intern and then went out
It was kind of funny
you know when we were talking with tim at the meetup the fat theme kind of came up over and over again about how
things have flipped where jpl and nasa used to be seeding the technology that would then create the
The consumer tech that we all used now things have flipped around and the consumer tech like snapdragon processors
and lithium ion batteries
And blades for drones and whatnot have become so good that they buy the consumer stuff and they can buy it cheaper
And they can tinker with it easier and quicker. Yeah, I think on the on the tour
We heard that back in the old days. They even made their own physical nuts and bolts. Yeah
And it's like a 10x savings when they can buy it just from the market. It's a massive savings
They said but also means they can prototype quicker
And then the other thing that tim mentions later is that you know, it also means that they can find people who already know this stuff
So just having that relationship with tim was great because of what they're working on and that linux copter that they've built
That has just been so incredible and really become
Probably a real future part of all mars exploration that has a rover. I mean just incredible to watch that history and so tim
Tim started chatting with us. He said, you know, I think I could probably arrange
A little bit of a tour for you and some of the listeners if you're interested like well, yeah. Okay. We're interested
Are we not interested? Come on? Yeah, of course we are and so then it was just a matter
Well, how do we get down there?
And so that's when I started talking to linode and I said, hey, what do you think about doing another road trip this year?
We could do a series of meetups and then we get down to jpl and we could do a tour of jpl
And they don't said well, how are we gonna make money on that?
No, they didn't say that they said of course. They said that'd be great. We'd love to support you in the community doing that
and so they worked with us to make it possible to get down here and do this and
I'm telling you guys even as we were walking up to the entrance of the jet propulsion laboratory
It just wasn't feeling
Real until we came around the corner
And we saw everybody there
Hello, sir, good to see you again. Hello. Hello. Hello
Hello
Hello. Hello. Hello everybody. Hello. Welcome to jpl
It's real it's actually happening
And you're all early good job
now we'll just uh
Take over the place because I think we got the numbers. So I see a bsd shirt. Yeah
You're gonna be our frontline guy
How about everybody showing up on time? How great is that? I mean we were on time and I felt late
Right
So, what'd you guys think of the tour wes I didn't capture your thoughts much afterwards
So i'm curious to know your overall take on the tour and if anything surprised you
I was really quite impressed with our tour guide, you know, he he um
Not only related a crazy amount of information
but I think I think did a pretty good job of bridging the gap because you know, you gotta have
You know much like doing podcasts sometimes you gotta be able to accommodate all kinds of different knowledge levels and backgrounds
And even as a science and space nerd myself
I felt like I was getting lots of little tidbits to hang on but it also seemed like like he did a good job
You know engaging some other folks. I'm thinking partially here of of your wife adia here chris in you know
Being interested in the crazy stuff going on in space, even if it feels very far away sometimes I appreciated too that
Especially with our crew that was there
You could throw a few of the technical questions at the tour guide and he had answers for like 99 of them
And which was really really impressive because we do have the best nerds in our audience and they geek out on this stuff
Oh jpl was awesome. Uh, I I really enjoyed seeing the cassini space probe and all the other space probe models in the auditorium
uh, but uh
since I I mentioned galileo before
I I was really happy. They built the entire museum around the galileo ground model
And that they left the high gain antenna deployed in its undeployed arrangement just like in real life
Nice, and then uh, how was it to see the control room because we weren't sure we were going to see that
Oh getting into where the magic happens
It was incredible and i'm glad I was able to sneak a couple peanuts out of one of those tubes, too
Sneaking the peanuts the control room was great. Hey, did either of you get any peanuts? No, I didn't even think of that
Oh, oh, well, I did I was oh really? Yeah. Oh, man. I was so focused on not touching any buttons
Yeah, I sat next to you and it was I mean you did touch a few that you just touched them really lightly
Yeah, and I actually caught my hand once reaching out on its own. But seriously that was that was amazing
I mean i've i've watched so many streams, you know and seen images on the internet of that control room
I reckon, you know, you recognize the little details and to be to be set physically there and watching the little animations
But they're not for show right? Like sure
I mean they're a little for show because they're on big tv screens, but that it's real data
We could see in real time. Like what's the transmission bit bit rate across the deep space network to these probes out in the universe?
i'm, just pausing for a moment because
You're right wes like I I the whole time felt surreal for me
and I
at a few moments
Tried to ground myself and be like wait, but wait, this is actually happening for us. We're in these places that we've
only seen on tv or dreamt of and
uh
That's what stood out for me was
You know everybody who was on the tour with us was super invested in the experience
Super respectful of everyone who was there trying to work really hard. You know, we got into some places that
People were actually working and we were trying to like just shimmy around them while they're working and take photos quietly
and so that we weren't disturbing them and
I I think that's what stood out for me is like
We got an amazing audience who really took everything in and appreciated every bit of it
Yeah, and the other thing that was a lot of fun from a technologist standpoint is just watching the eras of technology
When you go in there you see like oh that was clearly state-of-the-art in the late 70s
And this is the mid 80s and here's the 90s and here's the early aughts and you can see that with everything from like the storage
medium to the operating systems and how the operating systems could get more complex and
That all is extremely fascinating and hearing too about how they're now they're struggling with
Well, we deployed this up into space with an ubuntu 1604 base
And now we can't get modern software to build on an ubuntu 1604 base
but we still need to reproduce production and so they're like discovering kind of
linux specific challenges in a way and hearing a little bit about that was
Um enlightening, you know, these are the real problems that they face out there in the world
It was such a great tour. Unfortunately, they weren't very cool with us recording the tour
They were not okay with any kind of press or professional gear or anything like that
So we did our tour and then we had to say our goodbyes and do the swag giveaway thing
Well, thank you guys for all making it. This is a lot of fun
Okay, so we do have some great swag provided by linode got to tell the lady your t-shirt size
They run a tad small
Not atrociously
But yeah, just a tad nothing too bad. We got updated shirts this year and you know brand's going on right now
Yeah, it's actually really comfortable. I like this
We wanted to get alex's thoughts too from self-hosted because he was able to join us and is also a big space nerd
I think i'm just struck by the fact
of how amazing
This whole experience has been the audience that turned up were fantastic. You know, all interesting people all had stories
Some had driven 25 hours to come and see us
Uh and take the tour too
And I couldn't believe some of the cool stuff. We got to see like the clean room. We actually got to see
The next europa satellite or the next europa mission that's about to happen
uh, we got to see
There was this really cool picture paint by numbers
Picture of a the first image from mars and I used to have that in a textbook from when I was a child
And I got to see it in person. My mind is still processing that
So huge. Thanks to tim
Chris hadia
Everybody at jb that made this happen
But from personal perspective, it was super cool, but I know from talking to several of the audience members as well
That they had a blast as well
Alex probably would have joined us on the show today, but he's flying back home. So he captured that in the airport for us
So we had the jpl tour. It was absolutely fantastic. And then a lot of that crew plus a whole bunch more people
Joined us the next day
For a big meetup at the congregation brewing ale house right here in pasadena. Hi, we're here at the meetup
Uh just after our jpl tour yesterday and uh, there's a bunch of ton of great people here. So, um, hello
How are you both? I'm doing great, man. And uh, tell me your names. Uh, i'm zack. I'm alex
Hello. Hello, and I uh gleaned from our conversation that you've come a long way
Yes, we came from central arkansas in little rock area
That's amazing. And how long did that take?
Uh, so we did it over two days. It's a 24-hour drive. Uh, we left saturday morning. We finally got to la monday
Isn't that something?
You know chris i'm realizing that you and I are not the only ones on a crazy road trip, right?
The audience is definitely making their own road trip to feel like they're here with us
I believe listener optimus gray did about a 24 25 hour one-way drive himself and uh,
Listener steve came from wyoming just to hear people talk about linux. My name is stephen ing
And i'm from lander wyoming and I yeah, I first went to the salt lake city meetup
I happened to be in southern california
So I thought I'd join you guys here and it's really cool, you know, it's a lot of fun to be among
I consider you all to be friends and colleagues because
I don't have friends outside this world who are into things like linux
They kind of look at me with that kind of
Scared stare, you know what I mean?
Well, thanks for coming all this way. Um, tell me something you hate about linux and what you love the most about linux
It's a vibrant bypass
The one thing I hate about linux is that it is so complex and it's so many pieces all over the place
And that's also the thing I like about it because there's just so much there
It's funny how often we got that answer. We asked people that a lot
complexity, uh number of choice
Uh too many options
It was the thing that was the number one thing they hated and the number one thing
They loved people really like a lot of different packaging formats. It turns out
Yeah
Everybody had thoughts on that too
And you know when you're doing a trip like this and you're doing the meetups and you're you're doing these tours and all that
Kind of stuff. There's so many logistics so many and just to give you a taste
one of the many things that has to be solved is somebody has to watch levi the podcast dog like
You can't go to jpl. And while he could go to the meetup, it's probably not ideal
Yeah, my wife and I watched uh, levi during the jpl tour yesterday. This is listener tim
my wife is watching levi right now during the uh,
the meetup
Well, thank you for that. I mean I heard he had a really great time
So he was talking all about it when he got home yesterday
Yeah, it was fun. We enjoyed levi as a wonderful dog
very very chill
And made made himself right at home. That sounds like levi. Yeah. Well, it must mean they don't have any squirrels over there
Right, and they're probably not podcasting
Long-time listener eric who made it to the meetup also attended the jpl tour and we wanted to get his thoughts
It was epic. Um, it was really good like as someone that doesn't follow
nasa or jpl too closely
Um, I was a little bit, you know, like oh, this is gonna be too much
But I knew it was going to be an opportunity of a lifetime and I really I loved it
I loved every minute and as we talked to him
It's like stuff really stuck like stuff. He never knew it really registered with him
And I I think listener eric is slowly turning into a big space nerd now
I don't think he knew too much about it beforehand and it really stuck with him
And I think he's going to be geeking out a whole bunch. This was a pretty fun meetup
We were there for at least five and a half hours
We had so many people come and go we had food we had drink and tim who helped set all this up at jpl
And has you know just been like our tour guide to linux in space
He made it to the meetup as well and he sat down with brent
It's been a great time. It's been great to meet everybody and the hosts and all the other people that come along because
we're all engineers and and uh
Computer geeks and we love space. So it's been a great time to meet everybody great
I saw uh, you brought a little something that you've been showing people. Are you allowed to talk about that?
Yeah, sure. I brought an example of the processor or one of the processors that's on the ingenuity mars helicopter
And it's a tiny little helicopter
Computer it's about the size of a match book box
And it's great to show everybody the kind of computer that we're flying and how small it is something
They could just take a look at yeah previously on linux unplug
We've talked about these things but seeing the scale of it and some of the stories you've been telling about batteries and stuff is
kind of incredible actually
It's incredible, but it's also concepts people can understand right there were people here who did drone development
And they looked at the board and they said hey, that's almost identical to the board
I use and yeah, I understand you're using these sony batteries that i've used before and
Using these sensors and things and you're managing, you know software so I get it
So it's it's the same time. It's exotic
But it's also approachable that a lot of people here who've worked in the industry and or just as hobbyists could understand it
Yeah, is it nice for you to see people out in the world?
Who understand the concepts that you deal with on a daily basis kind of back at work?
Yeah, it's nice to talk to people who understand some of the concepts because often with you know
Being an engineer some of the family and friends
They just kind of stare at you blankly when you try to when you try to explain the technology
And whereas with this crowd they're like, oh, yeah. Yeah, I understand
that's you know, that's linux and you do these kinds of things in linux and you know, that's flash memory and it's
It's running a computer an arm processor. That's like the raspberry pi and so on and so forth
So they get it and they can relate it to things they've done in their own career
So it's in many ways easier to explain it to that crowd
These meetups that we do, you know
We've done a few of them now and it's always a treat because you learn something new you meet people who have these
Wild backgrounds and you know having you here is a special treat
But actually every single one of them is is great to talk to you as well. Yeah, absolutely. It's it's not like i'm some
A special person i'm just a somebody who grew up probably similar to many of the people here
I was just fortunate enough to get a cool job at a place like jpl
And apply the skills that I learned and you know, I always
Take time to step back and just realize
Even though i'm an ordinary person. I've really had a chance to have an extraordinary career at a place like jpl
But you know all these people too have their own special niche
Where they've learned something and they've had fun doing it and they they're enthusiastic about it. That's why they're
Listening to the podcast and coming to events like this because they just enjoy it
Okay, tim i've been asking a few questions of almost everyone. So, uh, hopefully you're ready for this one
The question is what do you hate the most about linux and what do you love the most about linux?
What I love about it is it's a really nice
Stable environment to do software development in it's one of the reasons we picked it for the helicopter. It's very stable
So that part I like about it
I've been living in that world for a long time doing software development
And compared to an environment like windows where you're just it feels like you're always forcing yourself to do
Unnatural ways to do things but linux just has a smoothness to the the whole development
Environment and you know all these tools especially open source you can take advantage of
I think the thing that is the most frustrating is that
even though it
Is in its core really stable a lot of the user facing features just seem fragile at times you try to configure a program
You know or a desktop or try to set up a video card
Or something like that and things just break with mysterious errors and you just don't know why
And so I think
You know, you live with the good and you live with the bad right you live with the nice parts and live with awards
You just got to know how to
How to manage a system like that and use it for its strengths. Yeah, you were talking about using 1604
and uh
Just trying to port a few gooey's and that's actually some of the some of the worst stuff
You're dealing with because it's just super annoying and you want to move to more modern stuff
And uh, that was interesting to hear you talk about that. Yeah, we just had to reconstruct an older environment
And a lot of the hardware has moved on a lot of the software has moved on so kind of rewinding back to that era
You know 1604 would be 20 2016 which is an eternity for something like linux
But having to do that and trying to reconstruct this environment was tripping me up
And so I was gnashing my teeth a little bit trying to do that. But you know
It's still on the on the sum. It's it's a great environment to work with
Uh tim, thank you a for inviting us to jpo and we had an amazing tour yesterday
I know you wanted to join us on the tour, but you didn't quite get a chance
But you were there for a little bit. So thank you for that
You're welcome
And I always love to meet up with people who are kindred spirits
And i'm glad that the group was able to get together and have a really good time
Exploring a place that i've really loved to work at over the years nice and also
Thanks for coming to the meetup as well. I mean, it's been a real treat to have you here
Yeah, it's nice to just kind of sit back and relax. Enjoy the crowd. Enjoy the food and just talk about life
Even apart from technical issues. It's been a great group. Hey, well, thank you
You're welcome
And we really can't say thank you enough because it just gave us a great opportunity for us to come together as a team
And it gave us a great opportunity to do something that will
Last with us forever, right? We created some great memories there
Yeah, and I feel like some great friendships too. Tim has already invited us back. He said anytime you're back. Say hi
Maybe the airbnb could have been a little better. Uh, that was a funky airbnb
We stayed at but I guess it had some gems and it had some rough edges
You're just mad because you started a greets fire. There was the grease fire. I blame barbecue maintenance on that one
I don't blame that on me
Uh, I I am grateful for the star trek the next generation live stream that played the entire time
We were there we made it through 94 episodes of star trek the next generation and we didn't even plan that
No when we walked through the door
Episode one of season one just happened to be playing on the television and when we went out the door cupid was playing
Um, we didn't see all of them obviously because we had to go to bed sometimes
Wesson I tried. Yeah
You got to a lot of them, this is good memories it's good time and it's so exciting to see uh
linux and all of this technology coming together at a point that makes it approachable and accessible for these kinds of missions and then they're
Performing and exceeding expectations like for example those little sony batteries that tim mentioned there
They're holding up in the deeply deeply deeply cold martian winter
Uh, the way tim put it is the lithium batteries are turning into battery cycles every single night and they were paranoid
They were they were absolutely afraid that that would destroy the batteries, but they're holding up
It's making it and the linux little copter just had its 33rd flight recently. I mean we've got one planet down
How many more to go for linux, right?
Bit warden dot com slash linux go sign up for yourself or an enterprise account go try it and you know
October is cyber security awareness month and bit warden would like to remind everyone about key actions that the federal agency for cyber
Security recommends that you take and it starts with what I always say use strong passwords bit warden can generate and store strong passwords for you
Enable multi-factor authentication on all your accounts including your password manager
They also recommend that you keep your software up to date
And take steps to recognize and report phishing as well
Remember weaker stolen passwords represent the majority of successful hacking attacks
Using a strong unique password for every account protects you and your business from these attacks
Bit warden can create save and auto fill passwords for you and multi-factor authentication. That's the easiest way to add extra security to your accounts
Enabling two-step login on bit warden improves the security of your password vaults
And there's options like verification through email or an authenticator app that's available for all your accounts
Fido 2 or yubikey odp if you're a premium subscriber
Premium subscribers can also have bit warden generate time-based one-time password authentication codes for your accounts
Adding strength to your passwords and bit warden supports security for all with fully featured free accounts available to everyone
This cyber security awareness month protect yourself and help protect loved ones by educating them about password security
And by starting up a free bit warden account today
So get started today at bit warden.com slash linux. That's bit warden.com slash linux
As always we got some great feedback this week, so thank you very much for sending some in
Sid wrote us about some photo adventures
Sid writes I wanted to add to the discussion around replacing google photos
I've been using image since last week when you mentioned it and it's been working great for me
Regarding storage though. I've written software on top of storage and I plan to use it for automatic off-site backups
Using something like duplicati or restic
However, I found that their documentation is pretty bad and overall it was a headache to implement
I would not recommend it for anything sensitive and I feel like you should definitely use encryption on your end if you're using it
Yeah, I agree on that. It sounds like sid is still pushing ahead with using storage
So it knows those weren't enough of a deal breaker. Yeah, isn't that interesting? I am too
And I think the documentation point that depends on what you're looking for, right?
Like I found pretty good documentation on getting duplicati configured
But I could see if I was trying to write an app that lives on top of storage
Maybe I wouldn't be as happy
And then you got to figure it's kind of early days too in regards to image. I am m I ch which is a google photos alternative
Also early days what I love about image is that it has a local app
So it'll run on your phone and uploads to the server. That's great. It's got a nice ui nice
But it doesn't have all the classifications and search features that something like photoprism has right now
So um in my book photoprism is the further along solution for the problem that needs a solution today
But uh, I am definitely keeping an eye on image and I have a suspicion
That we will do future coverage of image on the self-hosted program
If you'd like to hear more we did talk about some of chris's early investigations
Into some of this photo syncing in a linux unplugged episode 476. Yeah, and shout out to listener tony
Uh, they stayed up to the double up and watched it on jupiter.tube last week. Wow. That was a five hour live stream
so
That is very impressive. I have to say I don't know. I don't think I could watch it
I don't even know how we did it to tell you the truth
I don't even know how we did it to tell you the truth. I don't even know have we mentioned that we have the best listeners?
And now it is time for the boost
Speaking of those best listeners listener
Michael b boosted him with 3000 sats and said I was just listening to your chat about package managers and I wanted to share something
I just recently switched from ubuntu to fedora and now due to work and other reasons. I ended up with four
different
Package managers i've got dnf flatback homebrew and snaps
I admit that sounds crazy, but so far
It's all working without issue. Thanks for the great show
Michael, okay. Now we tell michael about next so we can get to lucky number five
Exactly. There's also pip that can come in handy. Oh, he probably has that he probably does have pip installed
He's just probably not using it very often
I mean michael, I think you could add a couple more to that list. Um, is that a problem or is it a gift?
You tell me because according to our listeners at the meetups is the thing they love the most
And the thing they hate the most so
I don't know what that tells us
Gene being boosted with 2048 sats
Hey chris, if you edit a synced photo on your internet phone
Does that updated image get pushed to your server? Remember reminder i'm using photosync with photoprism
He says for example say all your photos are synced up
Then you decide to crop a picture from full size to a square on the phone
Does that one on your server also now appear cropped? If not, how would you deal with this?
I ask because a lot of my post processing I do as an amateur on my phone
Great question, you know, i've noticed doing this on android
In a variety of different apps that it typically saves a duplicate photograph with the very similar name maybe an extra
Prefix or suffix that means that you just have two files
You have the original and now you have the crop version and I would assume that both of those would get synced
Yeah, I think it would on android. I think on the internet phone. They do like a layered thing of revisions
And so when you crop a photo
Photosync and this is a photosync issue doesn't necessarily see it as a new photo if you saved as a copy it would
But if you crop the original photosync is like what there's no changes. What's the big deal?
Oh, so it doesn't even sync the edit rather than the edits wiping out the original. You just don't get the edit
Yeah, it doesn't see it as a new file as far as I can tell on the iphone
I think it would on android, but if I tap it and manually sync that file
Then it updates on photoprism just fine. It overwrites the one in photoprism the way you'd expect
So i'm going to play around a little bit more with that even these kinds of things
I'm fine with working these out because not only is there all the issue with google
And the things that we talked about recently
But just after we recorded our episode about getting rid of google photos
It turned out that google photos was messing up old backed up images for some users like way back in their archive
and people's images were getting screwed up and they've been rolling out a fix, but
I mean, I just think it's just time to get off google photos and I think that just sort of underscored it
Agreed, we're gonna have a big land this week
So next cloud introduced a new photo feature that I think we got to dig into and try it before this week's land
Because that could be another option could be we'll see
In the meantime sky push boosted in with 1000 sets
I've been running calyx for about a year now after the privacy bug bit
I wanted something that straddled privacy and stock functionality
The majority of my apps come from f-troid while aurora store anonymizes the two proprietary ones. I still need
Calyx is kind of perfect for my use case and clock's creepy uncle google
I commend the devs and at this point we'll never go back
So the number one thing i've heard since i've installed graphene os on my pixel is that I should try out calyx
I had to tell you it's something you know, this happens every time I do an android rom
Whatever rom I didn't try is the one I hear about a whole bunch
Have you heard about stock bro?
At the meetup a lot of people liked calyx again a lot and what i've kind of pieced together
I don't know if this is true or not because i'm new to all this but
It seems like calyx is really popular with the linux community
And it seems like graphene os is really popular with the security community
And i'm kind of going more for the security angle of things and the one thing that graphene os
Has going for it that seems super appealing to me is you can install via their tool
google play
And the play services in a sandbox and then you can restrict
everything the play and uh services can get to and you can run apps that require the play api
Or are only available in the play store or the new one I discovered is a pain in the butt
To require in-app purchases and sometimes then require the play store with graphene os
You can sandbox all of that stuff and that is so appealing to me
So i'd be curious to know what people think about that
What they think about the quality of the sandboxing and how that compares to what calyx offers
Well on that subject bond boosted in with one thousand two hundred and thirty four satoshis
Former iphone user here turned calyx os user for about one and a half years now, and i'm loving it
calyx makes google camera available in the aurora store, but
Turn off network access to it and don't allow any permissions before you open it
Then you get the best phone camera available without the google access
That sounds like a really nice trick and actually fairly simple. Yeah, no sandbox required. It sounds like yeah, but again with
Graphene os. I just installed the play store and I can just get the google camera and it all works pretty well
And now the google google camera is also sandboxed and limited on what it can do
I like it. I like it a lot, but i'm i'm open
I'm i've heard a lot of good things about calyx. Well, we've got a little more for you then four-legged emu boosted in with
3000 sets coming in hot with the boost calyx os is worth looking at for your pixel
I haven't tried graphene, but i'm very happy with calyx
And uh frozier boosts in with 5000 sets
A little representation here because frozier is a three-year graphene os user
Everything works perfectly no paper cuts at all. And then I think they're throwing a little shade at you here chris
Google play services can be enabled
If you wish I get that I do get that like like I when I mentioned this to people in person like you realized
The point of this was to get away from google
You realized the point of this was to get away from google, right?
Oh, yeah, I know I know
It's just sometimes I want to be able to take pictures that look decent too
true grits wrote in following up on some of chris's questions around listening habits with
2468 sets even live long and prosper
I try to listen to all the episodes as they come out
However, sometimes such as during the summer I get a few weeks behind been slowly catching up and i'm almost there. No worries true grits
Thank you for letting us know i've been curious to hear people's various listening habits and how far behind they are
Just so we have data on that. So, uh, if you want to share that with us, please boost it in
But how how far behind was true? Chris? When did we when we posed that question? I think about three weeks ago
There we go. I just want to I just want to creep a bit on sure gets that's my there you go
Yeah, I feel like listening math is hard. Yeah, because we pre-recorded so it's technically maybe a month
The golden dragon also boosted in with a set of lead sets
Love mascot
Golden dragon writes long time no boost. So gold by imagine dragons seems cool
I'm, not a huge pop rock guy, but that song kind of grooves
I was aiming for something from free music archive, but it's a bit of a mess over there
Also, what do you think of magic wormhole as far as i've researched?
It's a great way to send files across long distances that's encrypted and compressed kind of like bit word and send
Hmm. Yeah, okay
I like wormhole a lot wes and I use it frequently to move files back and forth
And I think the encryption is probably adequate for what you're looking for
Yeah, I mean, you know if you want to you've got something really secure then
Layer something on top but the you know, the fact that it's nice and ephemeral
And it means, you know, you can transfer that file and then once you're done walk away
And one part I really like is just that you know, it's it's a python program. Uh, so
To brent's point earlier. It's really just like a pip install away and that means it can work on
It can work on your mac on your linux or even your windows box
And it does and it's also packaged by everything too. So, you know brew linux packages
They've all got it and the syntax is so easy. It's wormhole send then you point at the file
So if I were a little more paranoid or doing it for myself, I might just use tail scale send since I have that
On all my machines now and that's kind of like airdrop, but using tail scale on the back end
Um, or you know, maybe you could look in a bit word and send I think that'd be another option as well
Just kind of depends on what your security requirements are. I have another one to throw in there as well
Uh simply wormhole dot app and uh, I think what really gets me there is just really the background seems to work fine
And of course with lots of these tools you can uh, host your own little relay server if you need to and that's another way
To add on some layers of security
Oh, whoa, see sneaky double boost this week from frozier with 5 000 additional sats
Dwm was very difficult with nixos for me
Because it's meant to be configured by the user
in the source code
Before it's built so I gave up and I used awesome wn
Here's my config. Oh, that's nice. Yeah, I could see that being a little tricky, you know
I mean nix is great at building stuff
But then you got to kind of maintain your own version and hook that up to everything surely possible
But as a former awesome user myself
Love it and uh, thanks for thanks for sharing the codes and the bits. That's that's great
Yeah, we'll put a link to that in the show notes
So people want to check that out wolfman 2g1 boosts in with 1500 sats. You're doing a good job
Just got my ham license and it got me thinking
Is any of the jb crew amateur radio operators?
Oh, no, another ham question what's happening? I know I think our next boost is about ham radio, too
Ask might as well read that i'll be 1984 boost in with a thousand sats
first boost ever
Hey, oh, hey, congratulations. Hey, you know what you're doing a good job, too. You're doing a good job
Oppie goes on. I also would be interested in a ham radio discussion
Here's a link to a ham site with some dedicated ham linux distros. We'll keep that one in the notes nice
Okay
All right. All right. Well, you know something that we should mention on air and rust a cast of versa boosted with 2000 sats
Linux and ham. Did you know there's a whole podcast around this called linux in the ham shack?
Maybe a little special with noah would be cool. That is the best linux podcast name
I've ever heard it. That is pretty good. And you know what it would be a lot
It would make so much sense to do it with noah
So, uh, I think that's something maybe that's how we'll handle it
We'll talk a little software defined radio because the matrix room has been talking about this quite a bit in the feedback rooms
And they think we should do something around software defined radio
So maybe we bring in a little noah we get a little brown bear going on the topic and we have some fun
I could see that coming down in the future. So keep your radios tuned. You never know
There might be something in the near future
Rasta also boosted with another 2000 sats. It's a dubs
He writes was the dev1 unboxed in the bat cave I swear I hear lots of water running
Yeah, you know I meant to address that when we recorded the dev1 unboxing. Um
Unboxing. Um brent has a urination issue. It's true
It's just all that hydration
So we've rigged the studio up special to handle it because you know, there's sanitation issues. No, I have a frog tank in the studio
In the living room and we were doing the unboxing and it's one of those things that i'm totally used to because it's been in
There forever
But it does sound a little obnoxious in that particular recording. It sounded like you set your
Recorder right on top of the thing. It was so bad. I apologize about that. Um, you know
Just think of it a little ambiance resta, you know picture a little froggy in there swimming around while we're unboxing the dev1
It's pretty great
Also, I just want to say a big thank you to some folks who boosted in but we didn't read their boost on the air
There's so many that come in. We are just selecting some of them now
But a couple of just a couple of quick shout outs here
Here
90 sats from retro penguin a long time first time sending in their very first boost
We got 50 sats from couch fox who earned his first sats that day and then sent them into the show
Absolutely amazing. It's so great. And then we got nine thousand sats from sultros
Who just got himself an hp x?
360 convertible laptop and he's running Debian testing on that thing with gnome and he says the touchscreen support works
Well, I like it. I'm loving that. I'm loving that. Keep keep the hardware reports coming in folks
We can just slowly but surely let people know what's working out there
So they know what hardware to get if you'd like to boost into the show
Go get a new podcasting app at new podcast apps comm get one that supports podcasting to know like fountain or pod verse
which is GPL and available for the web Android iOS and
It's an f-troid. It's right there in f-troid, too
So go check that out
And if you really want to nerd out you can use boost CLI or breeze
That one then you don't got to change your podcast app
I'll tell you what and we should mention to thank you everybody who's boosted in we've been doing splits with Brent so that way he
Has some sats for his gas tank in office hours 13
We bought some steaks with those fats too since we had a few extra ones and we grilled up some steaks for everybody and
Then the barbecue caught fire
Yep, the barbecue caught fire like not intentionally on like like not like we turn the burners on kind of fire
But like an emergency fire where we were afraid to open the hood because we thought we might get back drafted kind of fire
Thankfully we saved most
And we talk all about it and officer's pretty great clip if you're curious how we convert the sats into real-life goods
Well, we just send Brent out on the street and he comes back with cash. I'm not exactly sure what he does
We don't ask we thought about doing that but instead we went for the easier option
we went with bit refill and
bit refill calm lets you actually use Bitcoin on chain or lightning and then you buy a gift card and then you spend that so
Like Chevron Texaco instacart the grocery store
Banks, there's so many gift cards on there
And so it was actually pretty trivial for us to be able to convert those sats and then you know
Put them in instacart and we ordered groceries for the Airbnb
That was something else that we were able to do with those sats. So thank you everyone that split worked out fantastic
Not only did it give us the funds to get Brent down here
But then we're able to treat the crew to some steaks as well
And you know, sometimes we did that just kind of on a whim like we weren't even really planning it
But it's like we got a couple of hours tonight. Let's just get this. Let's do it
And we just had a lot of fun. So thank you everybody. That was really a treat
We have a pretty special pick I don't know if this is for everybody
but those of you who are into this kind of thing are gonna absolutely love this up on the jet propulsion laboratory github page
They have the open source Rover project. Yep. That's right
the open source Rover project and
It has so many goodies on here about the little Rovers out there including just like
stats and specs and information on how to build your own and
Even how to emulate one and control it with an Android device an Xbox 360 controller and a Raspberry Pi. That is so incredible
It's so perfect
So we'll link to this in the show notes you can go check it out because it looks like a lot of fun
Even if you just want to geek out on the 3d models that they have there in the different parts
It's really amazing that you can build this with just off-the-shelf stuff now, you know
If we built one for the studio
We'd have a little company for the days that Levi's not here with us and maybe we could teach this one to bring us a cider
Hmm, we could just build a little cooler into its back. Oh now you're thinking, you know
I've been pretty impressed at JPL's open source mentality. Tim's mentioned several times how much he loves that
Paradigm and way of working with software and hardware, but they just really prove it with their github page
There's like projects galore on there that you can dive into Chris you and I had a blast
Just trying to pick a pic for this episode. And I mean this one's great, but there's a lot of other stuff in there
So there's a lot we could have picked
Totally. Yeah, why didn't you pick this automated low latency global glacier flow and elevation change data set?
I mean, come on, obviously we were saving it for next week spoiler
You know speaking of next week
Hopefully we're back in studio. We should be back at our regular live time, which is noon Pacific 3 p.m
Eastern over at Jupiter dot tube and
You know things are just gonna be back to normal. No more on-the-road shows
Just a call really now that we're back is gonna be trying to start working on the taxis
But I'll still be on the road. That's true, but you'll be at the studio. Yeah, it's all the way from home
It's like home 2.0 home be for you. You know, I'm telling you what home but with better internet home with benefits
Podcasting benefits. So join us on Jupiter dot tube for that. See you next week same bad time same bad station
and of course links to what we talked about today will be at Linux unplug calm slash four seven eight er and
Thank you to our members over to unplugged core comm you are still getting a special version of this show
Unedited extra content even though we weren't live
We still made something for our members because we love them and they are investing our ongoing content and last but not least
There is more Linux content out there and it's gonna be a big episode this week
So go check out Linux action news Linux action news.com. Don't miss it
All right, everyone. Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of the unplugged program and we'll see you right back here
next Sunday
You