have you seen mario 35 have you seen this no so the it's a switch game that
takes like the the original mario game and then versus 35 other players and as
they like kill Koopas and stuff like that or goombas whatever there they've
come to your screen and sort of a last-man-standing kind of game fun it's
an overlay on top of a mario super mario bros emulator it's it's really kind of
fun like it is you know and you know what they can just give me over and over
and over again with mario I tell you what that's classic
hello friends and welcome to episode 375 of your weekly Linux talk show my name
is Chris my name is Wes hello Wes this episode is brought to you by a cloud
guru so many career possibilities in the cloud so little time ACG's learning
paths help you take the right courses to prepare for architect developer security
and many other high-paying cloud jobs get hired get certified get learning a
cloud guru calm mr. Payne 375 is packed with lots of good community news and
then once we get through all of that we're gonna try something new it's an
idea that I'm kind of stealing from another tech podcast accidentally if you
will and it's the idea of an exit interview so we're gonna do an exit
interview with Papa Wes today I've been running it for a few weeks on a Dell
precision test laptop and I wanted to try different distros and at one point
it crossed my silly little head that it'd be fun to run Papa Wes on a Dell
laptop and then I found myself sticking with it for a bit so I've been using and
last night I sat down with Wes and I said Wes I gotta I gotta confess
something and it was kind of embarrassing if you know my history
with Papa Wes so I I brought Wes over so I didn't want anybody to find out I
said Wes come here come here and then we got in the cone of silence the cone of
silence and I think Wes I think I after using Papa Wes have discovered
something that makes it stand out and different than any other Linux
distribution so big claim I'm gonna try to prove it later in the episode but
don't tell anybody okay I don't want that I don't want anybody little secret
okay all right well now they're out of the
colon let's bring in the mobile room time appropriate greetings mumble room
hello hello that was a good one that was a really good one well let's talk
about some news there's a brand new fancy plasma plasma 5.20 is out and it
is an absolutely massive release running it right here on the machine I'm reading
this new story about and it's one of these releases where everyday things
have gotten better like the little utilities you use the task manager
notification system settings it's just gotten some nice improvements and been
overhauled just to make it more useful and usable and you can really say that
about all of plasma from the way on-screen displays are handled some new
tricks that Kaywin has and for me I'm always super appreciative of
improvements to the way notifications work and there's a lot of changes on the
notification system in plasma 520 for one you now get notified when your
system is about to run out of space even if your home director is like on a
different partition yeah that's really yeah there's just a lot of little things
in there about like you can make certain things sticky now and in there it's
continued to get a lot of improvement and I think plasma remains out of every
desktop environment not just Linux desktop environments but in in the world
I think it's got some of the best some of the best notifications management now
oh yeah it really does it's just full featured they've clearly thought about
it they've iterated over a few releases now so it feels kind of polished yeah
it's really solid and I'm on neon right here so I just went ahead and did the
old update and was kind of prepared for things to go sideways since it is such a
huge update but seems like everything's nice there is a change they've made and
the way plasma works that if you've already modified the default and you
upgrade it won't it won't leaves it there yeah it won't change it but if
you're installing it fresh there's a pretty big change to the way the task
manager works now yeah there's lots of improvements over in the task manager
world I mean they did change the looks to its icon only by default yeah but
there's also big changes in how it behaves when you open several windows
with the same application like maybe you might do if you're opening a bunch of
libre office documents say a task manager will group them together clicking
on the grouped windows will cycle through them bringing each to the
forefront until you reach the document you want and yeah that's kind of a
different way to do it but I'll give it a try yeah I'm not a big fan of grouping
it together you know one of the things I kind of do on a plasma desktop is I
really often all I'll just keep the task manager on the bottom and I know it's
hip today to put it on the right side of your screen or the left side of your
screen because you know you got more vertical or whatever but I like the long
taskbar and I feel like if I got a long widescreen monitor I might as well
stretch that task manager I'm doing anything for you there I don't need it
I like having all the windows a square pop pop pop pop I'm more of an alt tab
kind of guy anyways though so not really gonna impact me really kind of kind of
one of these releases where you know maybe you're gonna base a distro like
kaboom to off of a future version of one of those would be a really good one
because there's also some really good Wayland of improvements that have landed
you know back in 2019 the KTE community decided to set off as an official goal
to prioritize building for Wayland essentially and I think the efforts
really starting to pay off big there's lots of features that have landed now
the clipper clipboard utility and the middle click paste stuff are now fully
functional in Wayland love me middle click copy and paste and the
multi-purpose launcher calculator search K runner app that's part of like my
favorite thing of plasma yeah will stay in the correct places and works in the
right place on Wayland it just behaves a lot better mouse and touchpad support
are nearly on par now with the X counterparts and screencasting is now
supported and Wayland on plasma 520 it's awesome task manager got better over
there too it's got window thumbnails and really in general the whole desktop is
more stable and and you'll like this Chris and no longer crashes when X
Wayland us that is an improvement in it yeah and this so the task managers
showing thumbnails we know that really tells us is that they've come up with a
way now for one Wayland component could to get information from another
application that one of the big things that's been the problem here is that one
Wayland application couldn't necessarily read the other at contents of the other
application you know take a little tiny screenshot and show it to you it's a
good time to be a plasma user well really it's a good time to be a desktop
Linux user because our desktops are really dialing this stuff in now I got a
couple of just nice quality of life improvements when I went to 520 I had
some icon rendering issues in my system tray area some icons were essentially
overlapping each other fix now you know it's funny when I go to other platforms
we don't normally mention on this show there's other platforms you know
especially with like you know max got a terminal Windows W cell to the Linux
story is way better there now I think I'm finding I miss the most honestly
sometimes it's just the desktop because our desktops are so good we've got all
the different kinds you could want and often they're very configurable yeah and
the we're getting to the point where these releases are really just
whittling off some of the niggly kind of not quite right or needed another go
kind of stuff or or they're positioning us for future technologies we're getting
both of that kind at the same time it's a good we're in a good maturity cycle
for these desktops amen and 520 of plasma looks like a really really good
one I'm actually really grateful of for all of the hard work the team does over
there because it just has been such a consistent performer recently of course
everybody's freaking out this week because NFS after being around for a
hundred years got extended attribute support so Colonel five nine baby we're
gonna have ourselves a little party but yeah otherwise five nine release came
out recently and looks to be a pretty good release but that got overshadowed
by another announcement then I don't know how many people have caught and I
think this could be huge VMware has announced VMware's you they have like
this fling have you seen this where VMware fling have you heard of this no
what is a fling okay yeah so I didn't know either so I'm glad I'm having one
I know right so a fling is a VMware program sponsored through the office of
the CTO at VMware designed to offer early-stage software to the VMware
community it's not generally available it's not necessarily production code
it's not even necessarily gonna be a product but it's something that you could
submit bugs against you know it's something they have an old kind of an
opener process so they're just having a fling not guaranteeing and stays around
or goes anywhere but yeah testing this stuff out letting users play with it and
now their latest fling is with ARM hardware and while they announced
support for a bunch of different ARM platforms the most notable is that
VMware ESXi is now available on the Raspberry Pi you can run VMware ESXi on
a Raspberry Pi now that's only the 4b mind you but still that's interesting I
happen to know someone you might be familiar with who has a lot of Raspberry
Pies and has a lot of workloads on them yeah funny because the number one thing
that I kind of don't like about my Raspberry Pi empire of servers is that
it's all on the metal I don't have it virtualized if I was gonna have one
layer of protection and redundancy and you know all of that it would be to have
everything running in a VM that I could snapshot or that I could move around and
I just didn't know if it was possible in the Raspberry Pi I played with KVM and
boy was that was that a rough rough rough experience I'll be curious to have
this does you know if it's any better maybe give KVM a shot again to compare
ESXi does have a lot of nice interfaces APIs just a familiar world for people
already familiar with that from you know from the server space they do recommend
you go with the 8 gig model if you can though just to get more features of v
sphere which I happen to have one right here so I think I'll be doing that I
don't think this is something people are gonna really use in production I think
it's more of experimentation it's about learning so this is a problem that
VMware had and this solves this problem pretty easily in the past if somebody
wanted to learn VMware you kind of had to tell them to go buy a $5,000 server
to go learn how to do this right I mean yeah you had to have stuff to run it you
had to actually have access to the software you had to build up yeah you
had a lot yeah even if you had a demo you know it would last for 30 days and
you got a license it you got to run it on a machine that's I didn't tell
processor with a certain base minimum set of features you got to have some
storage there's some minimum really designed around those you know yeah
data center work work cases and it is very popular in the data center so this
now solves that problem because now you can say we'll go buy this $75 raspberry
pie you can learn some of the fundamentals about the interface you can
learn our language you can learn how to build these systems yeah it's just one
more thing that the pie is good at if you're trying to learn and set up things
to play with all this technology huge but also also think about this from a
data recovery standpoint so if you have a VMware server that has a big old set
of VMware fsd you know you maybe got a big VMware fs device something like
that and the host computer dies the only way you're gonna get access to that is
to buy another $5,000 server install VMware and then mount the disk now you
can buy a $75 pie and mount that same VMFS device and get access to that one
or two three or four files that you needed to recover with essentially a
Raspberry Pi acting as a data recovery node but additionally these stupid
things I believe are gonna support vMotion which is the live migration of a
VM host very cool so you could live migrate a host to a pie and then
migrate it off again and you could do it with load rules right so you could say
the VM runs on this pie until the load gets to a certain requirement once we
have a certain amount of processing and memory requirements or CPU requirements
or disk or whatever it is whatever the rules I haven't used in a long time
automatically migrate that workload over to a powerful x86 server and then
really burn you know burn the coal and and address that load and then after it
settles down migrate back to the pie I can tell you're already gonna abuse
it is interesting you know they say this evaluation program is for the
enterprise architects who are considering the viability of virtualizing
ARM workloads so there's also this sort of you know get people who are used to
running it just on Intel machines yeah all right this can work on ARM too yeah
and I think it's mostly gonna be for testing mm-hmm mostly for people that
are already VMware shops already familiar with it mm-hmm and the Zen
project recently announced that they're also working on virtualization on the
Raspberry Pi and other ARM CPUs and in fact to get Zen working we'd covered a
story recently where they had to solve some really particular problems and so
people are in multiple groups actually are taking virtualization on the
Raspberry Pi really seriously and I say good on them because look where this
thing's gone and where's it gonna go in another five years and I'm sure it's
gonna just be even more powerful more into more places it's eating the world I
think you and I should give it a go you know we got some other things coming up
for the next couple of weeks but in a bit we should give it a go I checked in
on it people already submitting bugs great stuffs already getting fixed so it
seems to be a pretty active project out of the gate already and I think I think
they're onto something here I think they're onto something so anyways we'll
have a link to it if you want to download the ISO in the show notes you
can try the fling version without a license it's free for anyone to use I
don't think you're supposed to use in production I don't know if has any other
limitations I'm not very familiar with the with the program but you or I or
whatever whoever that doesn't even have a license can go download this and try
it so if you do if you try it out there go to Linux unplug calm slash contact
let us know how it goes tell us how it goes it's just a great I mean you know
like four years ago I would never have thought that this would happen but you
would ever take the Raspberry Pi this seriously right yeah yeah you know
you're gonna be limited right and how much the pie is gonna be able to run
you're gonna be really limited and I guess and you're gonna end up with just
arm virtual machines so you might not be able to unless you could virtualize arm
on the exit you still need stuff that runs on your architecture you still need
yeah yeah exactly so I don't think I don't think it's gonna emulate x86 right
but if you could run it on a on a Raspberry Pi you're probably building it
I would imagine for a much larger production arm server like they do
support a set of arm servers and that's probably where you'd see that workload
kind of making sense is you build it on a pie in your office or something like
that and then you deploy it on a like an Amazon arm box or something like that
you've got some sort of edge devices out there which I wonder if I wonder if that
won't be a use case for the Apple Mac arm machines if people might be buying
those for arm development for the arm in the cloud it's a whole new world it's a
whole new world Wes it's a whole new world we'll give it a go we'll report
back I don't think there's much we don't really have much to say on it other than
that because it's still new and we haven't tried it yet so when we try it
and we have formed I think an educated opinion on it we'll do an episode
dedicated to it maybe see how it stacks up sound good yeah virtualization on the
pie take two congratulations to the folks at VMware though I know they've
been working on this for a couple of years they teased it a little while ago
and it took a ton of R&D you gotta hope and figure they're doing the math that
this is gonna turn to something big if they put all this effort into it
Linode.com slash unplugged go there to get a $100 60-day credit for a new
account that's awesome Linode started in 2003 is one of the first companies in
cloud computing three years before AWS and now they remain as one of the
largest independent cloud computing companies in the world and you know
what's something that we haven't mentioned on this show before is Linode
has been a longtime supporter and sponsor of our beloved Linux fest
Northwest sure has I mean I can't count the number of conferences I've seen them
with their you know green booth set up I know and actually there's been a lot of
times when maybe we had a different sponsor on here that wide walk by their
booth longingly when we sold JB and I wanted to keep things separate from what
was JB infrastructure what was my personal infrastructure that was my
excuse to go check out Linode that's when I was like let's go see what Linode
has to offer and been using them since then so that's about two years ago a
little more than two years ago and I've watched them really respond to a very
fast market so you'd think a company's been around like three years before AWS
got started would be slow to adapt but that is not the case at all like they're
clearly following this stuff they're just always modernizing their
infrastructure they started using user mode Linux and you know one data center
and now they've totally modernized the infrastructure they have 11 data centers
worldwide they have a cloud manager that's super easy to use Wes was just
looking at their GPU compute options I think you said you saw a machine that
you could have up to four dedicated GPUs oh yeah so they got everything from like
a $5 a month rig up to like four GPU rig and for the most part when we're
building a system these days we've been doing the dedicated CPU rigs didn't we
do a dedicated CPU rig for the matrix server yeah we did just in that way it
kind of has the performance we need and it's really nice because everything's
backed by native SSD storage 40 gigabit connections and they're super crazy fast
really the great thing about Linode is you can do the math like this if it
runs on Linux it runs on Linode that's really just it I mean they they started
this whole thing with a love for Linux to begin with so they've always been a
fan of giving you access to everything you want every plan comes with their
amazing human-powered customer support 24 7 365 and you know not just Linux
Fest Northwest they're also a sponsor of the Kubuntu project which is a
favorite here on the show and that's just really great to see that too so you
can support the show you can get a $100 60-day credit and you can spend
something up on the node that matches your needs you start by going to Linode
calm slash unplugged that's the URL that tells them yep I heard about it here on
unplugged and that's the one that unlocks the $100 60-day credit for a
new account they have a 99% uptime they have a really easy to use DNS manager
that allows you to easily switch your domains to your host that are running on
the note something we've had to do a couple of times indeed it's really
pretty simple and straightforward though so don't worry about it you'll be able
to handle it and if you want to use Linode to learn they've got a lot of
great options for that but if you just want to get something started you can do
a one-click deployment and get going they provide virtual servers that make
it easy and affordable for you to host anything in the cloud so check them out
Linode calm slash unplugged thanks to Linode for sponsoring this show and
thanks to everybody who supports this show by visiting Linode calm slash unplugged
and getting that $100 60-day credit on your new account a little more community
news I think this is pretty great there's a project that we followed on
the show before called nebula which if you recall is a software-based overlay
that Wes and I just went bonkers over it's really simple to operate it's
resilient to devices coming and going it's a software-defined network like the
one you've always wanted lightweight modern crypto straightforward to use
and it just focuses on letting you build the network you want completely
independent of where your devices are so they could be across multiple providers
slack uses this to just essentially bridge different public cloud providers
and to create one flat network yeah that's how they connect their
production infrastructure we've talked about it before here on the show yes
episode 329 network truth there's go check that out if you want more info if
you missed it and we had a chance there to talk to one of the founding
developers about it and do the gushing that we did because we loved the
project so much and now it appears not only do they have apps for mobile that
are official we have some links in the show notes you can you can run nebula on
Android or iOS to be part of that flat mesh network but more importantly the
two founding developers are going full-time with the project they left
slack back in February and are now doing this as a full-time gig they've launched
a new company yeah defined networking incorporated and they're focusing on
nebula full-time man they're still like working with their former colleagues at
slack and I think really grateful just that you know slack did this in an
awesome way where they got to build it test it have it work internally open
source it and now they can shift to just doing this all the time wow I mean yeah
it really seems like it's one of those ideal situations where they talk to the
people at slack and they said we have this thing it's taking off this is what
we need to focus on and slack said yeah but we're using this in production we
need to keep working with you and they came up with a way to amicably split and
they've done it well and didn't continue to test new releases on slacks production
network that's crazy so good for us it just seems like such a neat like this is
possible partly I think because it's open source right you don't have to
don't worry about this stuff slack contribute to it internally from their
own engineers still this new company can focus on it and nebula just exists as an
open source project yeah I need to play more with it you know that there's you
know upgraded mobile support yes yes they've been toying with that for a
while but and they actually are tying in on the iOS level at the kernel with the
kernel VPN module so it's like full-fledged ever it'll work with every
app it was really well done like the wire guard support is yeah exactly
it's funny that these two open source free software VPN like solutions that we
keep talking about nebula and wire guard they are really first-class mobile
experiences to the developers were keenly aware that they needed to be on
mobile doesn't that show you the times yeah but it's true I mean like that's a
huge benefit and the whole thing about nebula is having this one flat network
of all your devices but if the device I use most commonly can't be part of it
it's not maybe as useful yeah like I want to get to my notes or I want to
back up some photos from my phone or stuff running at your home land if you
haven't checked out nebula go listen to Linux own plug slash three two nine and
get a taste of what it could offer it could solve some problems that you may
have been kicking around they found it very useful congrats to Ryan and Nate
totally very excited for them all right so last story of the week and this is
one that's been getting getting some grief and the headline reads the AMD
Radeon graphics driver makes up roughly ten point five percent of the entire
Linux kernel it's a bit of code shaming through size is what's happening here at
scale and and we're looking at the five nine kernel and there's about twenty
point four nine million lines of code and more right when you include
comments and you know like three point five eight lines of code comments three
point seventy two million lines just blank lines something like twenty seven
point eight one total lines of code in five dot nine I mean for a while the AMD
GPU kernel driver driver has been huge making it the largest entry kernel
driver easily but with Linux five nine comes that additional two point one six
million lines of code plus you know even more than that when you include comments
and line spaces and all of that and a lot of it is auto generated headers for
GPU registers that's what one point seven nine million lines of the Linux
five nine code are it's just a lot of generated header files but I had an
actual like insightful comment I came across on hacker news like hey when does
that happen right it's occasionally well it happens when it's a comment that's
made by a kernel developer so this is a comment that will link to on hacker news
from brood bucket and it goes my two cents as a kernel developer the driver
is pretty abominable compared to the code quality of the rest of the Linux
kernel however and I think this is the point we should all take here having a
GPU driver not just be open source but upstream in the Linux kernel is a
gigantic deal that's why I don't like the code shaming I don't like it when we
look at the lines of code and we and we oh look at all these lines of code and
then we kind of code shame it when it's like as a from AMD's position it's like
well you wanted us to open source the code and contributed upstream what did
you expect it's got to be what they're thinking right like so we finally do
what you ask and now you're bitching that it's too much code one you know
there's some cultural differences I think a lot of this hardware or an
embedded world you know you just have this duplication you've got similar
boards that are slightly different you copy the code base you make the changes
you need it's not this like highly polished Linux kernel type open source
atmosphere so there's a little mix-match and to kind of bounce off
your point a little more they're revving the GPU one or two times a year so
there's a lot of change right much more than what you see in the x86 or even in
the ARM world this commenter goes on to say kernel development takes a long time
we have millions of lines of code in the AMD GPU driver and if every one of those
dealt with the lengthy review process it would have never made it into the tree
so it's a necessary evil they say I do wish they would clean it up I've even
sent some fixes upstream for them to fix things up where there is massively
largely duplicated files and that kind of stuff just doesn't fly anywhere else
in the kernel but it's kind of like the compromise you make to get something as
complicated as a GPU driver that covers such a wide span of not just
architectures but different vendor implementations of those boards it's a
massive chunk of code and perhaps gives us a little bit of insight into why
Nvidia keeps its card so close to its chest right this is something that the
company released after they knew it was gonna be public and they took they
probably went through a process oh yeah right yeah to vet go through maybe clean
up right and so can in Nvidia having not done that work it probably isn't a lot
less publicly polished state yeah well and you know the other the other part
here to sort of unsaid is you know this commenter submitted a change in the fix
so like having it in the kernel while it doesn't mean it's where we might want it
to the extent possible like fixes can be applied the kernel community is in
control it would be funny though in a alternate reality where Nvidia has just
all of a sudden released their code and it was also about this size and then
like 20% of the kernel is just I mean it's already huge chunk of drivers yeah
really seriously I feel like people don't understand the complexity of like
what you have to do to deal with another processor on your computer that has to
just do stuff and unlike normal as you know CPU processors which if you look at
the kernel code is not an insignificant chunk in its own right based on all the
different architectures and whatnot but GPUs have to deal with multiple
different instruction interfaces you've got GL you've got glass you've got
Vulcan you have direct 3d like all of these things happen in the GPU and I'm
not even talking about the compute stuff like open CL you know and spare V and
and all that other stuff yeah fair point and they're they are essentially like
another computer in the computer and they are a constantly moving target plus
then you have all of the management code that is necessary to just get those
frames onto the screen for the different operating systems I mean it's it there's
a lot to it for sure so I just I'd say yes it does seem like a lot of code
clearly does seem like there's some room for improvement but I don't know if I
like the idea of campaigning for years to get code released and then code
shaming when they do it it just doesn't feel quite right but I guess there is
probably a room for improvement to mr. Payne there's some room for improvement
around here it's a mess let's do a little housekeeping around here mini Mac
rumor has it that there is something special going on for the luck log this
Sunday indeed it is in fact we would like to talk about browser experience
how you harden your browser what browser do you use and how do you handle cookies
and stuff like that so we try to get a group together that's talking about
their experiences with browsers and with extensions they have and it would be
cold if you join us and even if you have some input we would be really happy to
hear from you yeah you can find the love plug on Sundays at noon Pacific it's on
the Jupiter broadcasting calendar and we have the mumble server info at Linux
unplug calm link there at the top you get that set up you join in the lobby and
you hang out with a bunch of other Linux loving users and this week talk about
browsers I think it's been browsers are actually once again going from boring to
interesting all over again so it's a good time to talk about that I also want
to suggest you consider grabbing the Jupiter broadcasting all shows feed you
never know what we have in the works or what we might put out in that feed and
get every show place to find it yeah everything it's like the ultimate JB
experience the Jupiter broadcasting all shows feed is in your podcatcher of
choice or linked on our website at Jupiter broadcasting comm let's check
it out I also we should just put a link in the show notes let's do that we'll
put a link in the show notes too and we'd love to have you subscribe and get
everything that we put out because we have learned many things over the years
and we've learned kind of what Jupiter broadcasting focuses and we're really
proud of everything we produce like if you're not listening to self-hosted or
Kota radio or Linux action news you're missing out on some great content that's
all in the all shows feed over at Jupiter broadcasting.com all right so we
wanted to try something new the exit interview after we've used a
distribution for a while instead of giving you the review when we first try
it we're gonna give you our thoughts after we've used it for a little while
but I wanted to do it for pop OS which is the current version as we record is
based on 2004 god you this is this is really embarrassing this is
embarrassing for two reasons actually for me to talk about number one I shit
on it when it first came out just gonna say it I did I did I didn't think it was
a good idea and then skeptical and then I ran my mouth like multiple times on
multiple shows about it so I got it I got to eat my hat on that I don't
normally get get it wrong so badly but that's when I got it wrong on and I got
to admit that it's also embarrassing because system 76 is a sponsor of Linux
action news and Kota radio that may cause people to think that is influenced
my thoughts but those two things have no bearing on what my opinions are of the
pop OS desktop itself and the experience that I walked away on a Dell so I loaded
it on this precision that I am going to give you guys a review but I loaded it
on this precision because it has a badass quadro in video card in it it's
got an MVME SSD it's got a gorgeous edge to edge 17 inch 4k display beautiful
right I mean it is the creme de la creme of Dell precision laptops and I wanted
to see what the system 76 pop OS experience was like because they have
focused on a lot on high DPI and the general I would say kind of you know
word on the street about pop OS is it's great if you want a game which is
exactly what I wanted to do for a little bit you know part of the review is to
put it through gaming paces and so I spend a couple of weekends trying
different games on it just seemed like pop OS would be a good way to go as I do
is I start using it I run into things or I start having questions and I have the
privilege of being able to call up the people at system 76 and so I did just
that and I asked them some questions about it and got a few clarifications
on strategy and stuff and I thought I'd share some of those experiences as I'm
now taking it off that Dell I'm gonna I'm gonna remove it so I wanted to just
share my thoughts as I transition off of pop OS yeah you spent some time with pop
really lived in it yeah this I swear is not hyperbole but it sure sounds like it
when I what I'm about to say is I think with pop OS they have something no other
distribution has and if I were to boil it down into a couple of things and I'll
expand on that it is limited scope of what they have to address and it is
sustainability and staffing sustainability and staffing let's go
with those two honestly not a lot of distros even have that they don't
necessarily have full-time people it's it's the exception of the exception like
we can count on our one hand what distributions have full-time desktop
staff yeah right I mean like many open-source projects there's a lot of
volunteer time or an off-hours time or a lot of integration of upstream right
that's essentially what the volunteers are integrating upstream and it's the
good work of upstream that is making these distributions possible and then
they these volunteers will theme it or they will modify it or they'll bring
some of their own special sauce to it but they choose put things together yeah
but they're not working a nine-to-five they're not commuting into an office to
go work on that thing they're not building software that is at the scope
of like say the system 76 firmware tool right even if system 76 say has three
people working on pop OS that's three more people than just about any other
distribution has when you look at all the distributions out there but
additionally because they've decided to ship Ubuntu well that the desktop team
at canonical is doing some of the heavy lifting there and they're shipping the
heavy lifting that the GNOME desktop team is doing right system 76 hasn't
come up with their own desktop environment there's no you know there's
no system 76 desktop they have taken the hard work of the Giants underneath them
and what's left is something that their small team can easily address yeah right
and they're they're working directly with customers they've got an interesting
sort of vantage point hearing people using their desktops and figuring out
where maybe there are some rough edges and they're in a position to actually
not just hope upstream fixes it but fix that themselves right the support
department acts as sort of a unique feedback cycle to the development
features that go back into pop OS again that's unique but additionally when we
talk about sustainability system 76 has come up with a way to make it viable to
release a Linux distribution for free to anyone and they distribute it via
digital ocean spaces so even downloading it cost yeah right it's fast but they're
paying for it so they have come up with a scheme in which they can give the
distribution away for free but still have a sustainable funding model because
of the benefits and features it brings their laptops and they have a while it's
a small team they can do things like work on auto tiling and because they
have time to do the research they'll base it on something like TypeScript
which is much more sustainable and portable well yeah I mean if you've ever
used the GNOME flavor of JavaScript it works just fine but you don't have all
the niceties of modern JavaScript by choosing TypeScript not only do you have
the nice TypeScript compiler to help you out but you've also got all the
abilities of modern JavaScript tools access to library ecosystems if you need
that and a much friendlier development experience if they were maybe choosing
other features maybe I would have a different opinion but what they focused
on is auto tiling that seems to work for mortals they've brought fractional
scaling to standard GNOME shell yeah they have enabled just recently hybrid
graphics for external displays which is kind of a big deal for a lot of
customers who are buying nice GPUs it's workstation features yeah right I mean
they they realized that the firmware updates were the thing that needed to
happen the customers weren't going to want addressed in a good way and they
were early on that game they can work on these 10% gap closure features because
they're they're building on all of the work of the other projects and then they
can focus in on that kind of stuff if I could wave a magic wand and make pop OS
anything I want I might prefer to have it based on something like art oh no
that's an idea you know but a second pretty good second desktop it would be
Ubuntu LTS or an Ubuntu base right I mean I also I feel very comfortable with
it I can have all the benefits of pop but I still feel like under the system
you know I can do whatever server side things on my desktop I need and so that
actually makes it a pretty reasonable choice too if I'm not gonna run arch on
the desktop I'm probably going to run an Ubuntu flavor or something like pop OS
because it just well it just makes running meant running a lot of
applications I want to run simpler it just it's one step removed supported
environment yeah it's one step removed from being on one of the commercial
platforms essentially and so you get those benefits and pop as well and then
you look at some of the other choices they've made like the installer they
worked with elementary OS they didn't go out and and like create their own
proprietary installer instead they funded development for an elementary OS
to create a free installer that they collaborated with elementary OS to
modify it for pop OS and now pop OS has a better installer than Ubuntu does
it's real nice the pop shop is better than gnome software yep and it's just
simpler and cleaner and faster and it looks better too yeah everything feels
very integrated it feels like a holistic integrate you know complete experience
so you've got you've got something unique here in that you've got dedicated
development time by people that where it's actually their job and they're held
accountable and they have features they need to ship to match product releases so
there's actually that drive to ship you have a sustainable system where they can
give the distribution away for free to people that want to run it on their own
hardware but yet it still returns enough value for them on their hardware that
they can justify the cost to make it and you have them developing features that
close the gap that add usability and pro features like keyboard navigation of
gnome shell is a lot better on pop OS you could you can you almost don't even
need the mouse now and and the reality the reality of that is that it's while
developed at for pop OS it is being upstreamed it's available it's open
source code so they're they're also doing that aspect of the good open source
citizen aspect when you take any one of those slices like auto tiling or
independent development staff or any of that you slice it on its own I mean it's
neat it's good yeah but when you total it up in totality I think it makes pop OS
a very unique distribution that I didn't fully appreciate until I saw a few
iterations of it and then spent a half a month with her three weeks with it and
realized oh oh it does feel like it's very broad appeal in a way that sort of
surprised me as well like I'd feel comfortable letting my mom use it but
I'd also be entirely comfortable having it as my you know workstation desktop in
the office yeah that's what I'm thinking about you know eventually when I do get
my own laptop I kind of assumed I would just go mangero plasma and watching
gnome shell it we know you know what it started with it started when we started
beta testing fedora 33 it's so nice to be home it really felt like going home
yeah yeah and I thought okay so then I actually put fedora 33 first on the Dell
I can't remember do you remember why I think I was troubleshooting some sound
card issues or something completely unrelated and so I tried out Ubuntu 2010
and then I tried out pop OS 2004 and stayed if it's funny because it's so I
just recently did a snap snapshot of 33 2010 pop OS and pop OS is the one I
stayed home with gnome shell at the dark mode and you guys if you listen to these
shows for a while know that we've gone on about like trying out regolith and
we've done different discussions about tiling window managers and I always end
up just going back to to wanting a windowed environment but having the
auto tiling built in where I turn it on and then about once a day for an hour I
turn it off for that particular work thing and then all the other times I
just click a button in my toolbar and it's on and it's so much nicer it's so
much nicer plus they have an option where you can highlight the window
that's active with like a border and that's just a little bit quicker for
when I come back to my machine I can just look immediately at the screen I
know what is the active windows I don't start typing in the wrong chat box it's
very practical I really like it I really it's like the first auto tiling that's
ever stuck for me it just makes it better doesn't get in your way it's easy
to turn off if you don't want it just enhances you know I can't believe that
got me because you know the thing is is if I could have anything I would just
have all of this be in one in mainline Ubuntu you know that would be the
mainline Ubuntu just has all this stuff but that's not the world we live in
it's just just not there it's just not the reality I also I have to be
completely frank I prefer that pop shop defaults to Debs you know it'll it'll go
for like that when I install telegram it installs the deb of telegram and the
reason why I like that is because when I'm sending and receiving attachments I
just want to be on my actual file system and I like the faster startup time of
the of the deb file and I launched telegram every day so I prefer that
about pop shop too there's just little things like the installers a little bit
better auto tiling the theme means better the software install looks they
install by default a very practical tool to just be able to double click and
install a deb file without having to launch the entire software center it's
like yeah that's these little tiny things that all really add up plus the
development focus I think make it kind of a special contender I I mean I'm not
switching anything to it today but I think when I do get my next laptop I
think I'm gonna go pop I think that's gonna be the way of the future for me
especially if it's one that has a video cut in it if I'm gonna do a little
gaming I went well super solid I know you gave it a little bit of a go to how
did your Steam experience go yeah that was actually really pleasant you know I
just installed it right from the pop shop loaded everything up and played
very nicely much better than the previous gaming setup I had mm-hmm yeah
yeah I was just thinking about it for my son if I was gonna reload my son's
machine I think I'd elementary's work so well but I could see elementary for some
of my family and then pop for the more technically inclined members of my
family right that'll probably be the distro I start recommending to people
when they asked me what distro should they switch to move from windows it's a
big change for you yeah I'm pretty impressed and I think I think part of
what my calculus is is assuming that system 76 takes this trajectory and
runs with it right and kind of he builds on where they're going yeah if they if
they fade on it then my opinion of this is gonna change you know but right now
if they continue their current trajectory or even add to it I mean then
we're really talking about something special and I was an idiot I was an
idiot for getting it wrong well I think it was just you know we some of the
things that have worked out in their advantage of finding the right levels to
contribute I think that's where we were skeptical we're kind of like well do we
just need this you know additional theme or this customization but what the work
they've put in it really made a bigger difference than I would have guessed
yeah so I really recommend you check it out this is the you know so I guess our
exit interview is you are a better performer than we expected in just about
every every single category they have also some slightly different software
selections available in the pop shop that I think are kind of nice and all of
that just made it really simple to get up and going and just keep it all up to
date really easily that's it it feels tasteful to me I think you can really
tell that you know the folks that system 76 use and love desktop Linux are in all
about that and are using pop as they're working on pop and so it's just feels
already well lived in and makes me comfortable you and I were speculating
like will this long-term payoff for them will it create like the iPod style halo
effect where today you buy an iPod tomorrow you buy a Mac will pop OS
users like me who are running it on Dell hardware would we be more inclined to
buy a system of 76 machine think I've had a great time here on pop maybe I'll
uh yeah just get the real deal that I'm I could see it but I'm a little more
skeptical because it's not like it's not like the brand is smacking you in the
face anywhere like I don't even see it really so maybe I mean I could see the
argument that it keeps the system 76 brand for front your mind so maybe when
the time comes and you're thinking hey I want to buy a computer well they do a
good job with their operating system yeah maybe I don't know I'd be curious
to punt that one to the mumble room does anybody have any thoughts does does
creating a distribution that you end up running on HP hardware or something does
it make you more inclined what well I don't know Toshiba maybe you have an
old Toshiba satellite I don't know it's a rockin but what does it make someone
more inclined you think to maybe want to purchase the hardware later when the
time comes I don't know so like if the aspect of it being made by system 76
might be a little bit more prominent in pop OS it would it may introduce some
kind of interesting effect where people see that you know pop OS is from system
76 and they make integrated computers and that provides like a best of class
experience with it maybe but on the other hand I don't think that's the
point of pop OS because and it kind of shows and how they think about it and
how they release it and how they brand it I think they make pop OS you know
just to so that they have an area in which they can drive their own opinions
about how a desktop experience should evolve and how it should support how
they feel it should support their users and that itself is shipped on their
hardware because of course they make hardware but they're totally okay with
supporting other hardware as long as it's supported by their upstream
distribution because the point of pop OS isn't to drive people to system 76
hardware the point of pop OS is to drive people to their opinion of how a Linux
desktop should function sure and maybe in the future drive them to a custom 76
keyboard because like I can see the way this is going so if anybody tries out
this auto tiling extension one of the things I recommend you do is bring up
the keyboard shortcuts and look at what you can do in in gnome shell now from
the keyboard and tell me that that doesn't get extracted out into the
future when they ship this system 76 custom design keyboard that happens to
work great with pop OS I mean it's gonna be a perfect it's gonna be a perfect
combo I mean if I'm running pop OS at that time I might buy the keyboard you
know back in the day when we had the computer it was like oh cool I can
install for example Ubuntu on it you put it on and there was pretty much always
one thing that didn't work and that annoyed me and it also was one of the
things where I couldn't promote Linux to other user that there were like yeah but
there's also always something little things that don't work and you always
have to think tinker with it and what pop OS is doing is standardizing hardware
where they can provide support so this way you can promote it to a family like
okay this is going to work and you don't have any problems with it if you've got
some problem with it you can report it and they will fix it and this is also
where companies get more and more more comfortable by purchasing hardware from
for example pop OS with the surface they can get with it and this way there is
more and more adopting of Linux because their standardization of hardware with
software right it kind of means it's a it's like a safe bet in a way because
you know that the vendors integrated it but also they have us they have a
support system for it too a long time ago there was also on the show where
someone tried to sell the software and they were like yeah it's free and
companies didn't bite for it right and when they sold it with the support and
the software was free with the support companies started buying it yes an old
an old lesson there I so there's two things that this makes me kind of come
to like if we were to shoot this way out number one is system 76 more compelled
to brand the UI in a way perhaps to bring their branding more forward to the
user could that shop you know and we've seen this we've seen a mistake here in
the past like with canonical never really got over the putting the Amazon
links in the search results I mean but you know is there something they could
do that would make system 76 more front of mind you could see going that
direction perhaps one day maybe not and and if Neil's analysis is correct then
there would really be no motivation for that but yeah my other thought on this
is is this a play we start to see become much more common and we're starting to
see it now with announcements of distribution a with hardware why and a
partnership between the distribution and the laptop maker or whatever right we're
seeing a lot more of that and I wonder if that isn't sort of a validation of
hardware integration with software does provide extra value to the customer I
think we're seeing that when you start to see all these projects that have
announced laptops like just this morning slim book which is a spec is a Spanish
laptop maker or a PC maker because they actually do make desktops as well they
announced they're now shipping the slim book essential an affordable sub 500
euro laptop they're shipping with fedora and they're they they do the work and
they work with the distributions to kind of you know make sure their hardware and
software work together and I think what this is what this what this kind of goes
to what you're saying Chris is that the the key issue that has always been the
case and I think even Linus Torvalds has said it like back in the days of when
Linux world was a conference and you know he's he's always said that the
reason that Linux doesn't win in the desktop is because there are no pre
loaded Linux on computers that's changing and it's happening at big
vendors and small vendors you've got tuxedo slim book system 76 Dell Lenovo
Hewlett Packard and others like it's just starting to happen everywhere it's
happening Dan Johnson in the mumble room has some breaking news for us as we wrap
up the show here man jero arm 2010 has been released and you have anything you
want to share with the class on this on this fresh new release well updated
kernels and laser stacks on most of the devices hey that seems great I'm looking
at it right now it looks like a pretty nice plasma image is available so are
you spinning these images yourself yeah oh thank you for all of the hard work
this is a lot of images you're spinning you got us you have sway of course you
haven't for the Pine Book and Pine Book rock pro 6-4 you have it for the
Raspberry Pi this is a big matrix of download options yeah that must have how
long does it take you to do all of that well talking in there about 12 hours now
oh well thank you for doing the good work we'll have a link to that in the
show notes so people can go grab that before we go into the feedback though I
want to thank a cloud group we're sponsoring this episode of the unplugged program they've
got a course that might be good for you especially if you are administering a
system with system D they have system D management for Linux we'll have a link
in the show notes this course has 5.8 hours of content 40 total lessons and
eight hands-on labs yes it is a course designed to help you demystify system D
you can get things done in system D perhaps today already but did you know
there's more and more added to system D all the time there's a lot to learn so
you can take this course learn how components work together and how to
configure manage monitor and troubleshoot system D check out the
link we'll have it in the show notes at Linux unplugged slash 375 and thanks to
a cloud guru for sponsoring this episode of the unplugged program go check out
system D management for Linux from a cloud guru alright mr. pain
after the show last week you and I had to think about the feedback and pics
segment and I like what we came up with we got two emails this week and one
wicked awesome pic like so so cool but I'll save that first we get to the
emails this one came in from Eric and he was listening to the back catalog so I
guess he just recently discovered the network and thought I'll start from the
back catalog and listen up hey that's a great idea that is kind of a fun idea
that would be interesting by the time he gets here I wonder what he's gonna think
about about I'll catch up about all this stuff but anyways he's in that 293 right
now so this is 375 some work to do but he said that in that episode we were
mentioning power top and TLP which is the the power management solution for
Linux he said I'd never tried TLP before I installed it thinking it would give me
more battery life well not only did it do that but I also fixed a really
annoying issue with my Wi-Fi where it would randomly disconnect from the
network nothing I ever found on the internet and research had fixed it but
somehow after I installed TLP my Wi-Fi was fixed well how about that yeah we
were scratching our heads about that it must have been some sort of power
management rule that was knocking his Wi-Fi off like maybe putting his card to
sleep or something and TLP actually changed that to be less frequent perhaps
I mean that could be right yeah I mean that sounds plausible it does but it's
not the kind of thing you would expect and it really shows you how interlinked
all of this stuff is and you never know trying one of our random suggestions on
the show might just improve your system you never know or the reverse what's all
writes into us about Chromebooks and education something I think you know a
little bit about yeah all all three of my kids are using Chromebooks right now
okay well here's how what's all handled that hello there longtime listener first
time mailer I was writing to talk about kids using laptops specifically
Chromebooks in school as we all know kids all over the country are going
back to school now whether it be in person or online my oldest just started
kindergarten this year we all have computers at home including him all of
which run various flavors of Linux we've got a Linux household here he's never
used anything else awesome so when he was getting ready to start school and
they announced that they were going to be giving all students Chromebooks I of
course did not agree with this at all I know right I mean talk about I know this
sounds weird but I would have almost preferred they would have had them use
iPads I just cuz like the the Chromebook means the Google account the Google
account it's it's like you're starting your whole online identity and it works
my kids think everything web first and Chrome first like even video editing and
picture editing like they just browser first everything I mean it really works
so Google's very clever in in pushing this so yeah when I heard that I was so
disappointed but you know as a parent there's so little you can do because
this is how the school does everything now like they turn their papers in this
way through the Google stuff they do the classroom meet tools like everything is
powered by this and that's how they're doing the entire Rona home homeschooling
oh yeah okay so when let's all ran into that he writes that I called the school
I spoke with his teacher the principal and even the superintendent and explained
my concerns I also told them that I would be more than willing to provide an
alternative for them to use and that's what it sounds like he's been able to do
so it might still have the Google account integrated but at least you know
instead it's on OS that he has some oversight on at least yeah his son's
using a ThinkPad t420 with Kubuntu installed so how about that perfect
that's great so I I could have done that I suppose I could have petitioned the
principal but I did not I relented yeah and I think that's that's really the the
heart of Wessel's message here is you know if you care about it if that's the
right thing for your family and your setup hey doesn't hurt to ask yeah I
guess that's he says for anybody that has a kid in school that got out of the
Chromebook call the teacher administration and talk to them like I
did you know and maybe it will work you know you can ask for a special
accommodation there you might be surprised what you hear in response I
wonder though if they still end up having to have a Google account I bet
there's some there's got to be some integration right online management
because they're using Docs and everything and meet I mean they're gonna
have to be there in Google Meet for the for those school sessions yeah so I
don't know what you really gain other than having full control over the OS
which has its advantages but my solution there is they just use the Chromebooks
for schoolwork only only yeah yeah and you know their school property too they're
not bad little devices but just not what I what I would have picked all right
speaking of picks how about this how about a system that automagically
manages different tiers of storage for you so like imagine you got yourself
some fast storage and if you access a file a lot you want it on the fast
storage but then maybe you got your files that sit around like for me I have
movies that will sit around that maybe get watched once every five years right
you still want them but you don't need a much I don't need them on the most
precious storage either and this is where our pick comes in it's called
auto tier it's a pass-through fuse file system that intelligently moves files
between storage tiers based on frequency of use file age and tier fullness and of
course anything like this you're gonna want something that has a very easy to
understand and read config file and I think that's where auto tier really
nails this it's you just define two lines plus the definition tier one and
then another you just define another tier and you just give it the mount
point to that and then another tier and you give it the mount point to that and
you can tell it what your watermark is which is essentially your water line in
a tank how high do you want the storage to get and you can say I want this
waterline at like 70% and then once that tier reaches 70% it's it's taken out of
consideration and then it just sort of acts merging them together so you get
like a transparent view you don't have to see what how all the tiers work when
you're actually interacting with it through fuse I've not extensively tried
this but I'm definitely give it a go I mean it's pretty neat and I could
really see you could have online discs that are you could even I mean you could
even do something like where you mount some sort of like backblaze or glacier
storage right and that's another tier in this whole thing with like our clone or
similar or even a USB like a large USB just like Alex Alex sent me a link this
morning for a 12 terabyte external USB disk for 175 bucks I mean that's not bad
for 12 terabytes yeah and you you wouldn't want to run you would want to
be streaming all of your Plex videos or MB videos or jelly thin but you would
definitely maybe be okay with things you haven't accessed in two years or
something being migrated off to USB storage that seems totally fine to me
especially if it's just doing it on the back end when my system isn't super
busy or on schedule times there's if you're on fedora you can basically just
DNF install this sucker otherwise you're gonna have to do some building but when
it comes installed when you install it it includes a system be unit file so you
can set up to run automatically or you can just run the auto to your command
and do what like a one-shot spread things out so you could just do it from
time to time if you prefer to do it and more hands-on and I'll have it automated
or you could schedule it to run automatically and just you take
advantage of the system D service that's so cool it is really cool West it's I
kind of wish I kind of wish it was built into the OS I kind of you know like
using fuse next layer yeah wouldn't it wouldn't it also a bonus pick because we
love the folks at antenna pod the free Android podcasting app has released a
brand new version version 2.01 with over 20 volunteers and I think the team's
pretty proud of this release I think so yeah I think a new logo refreshed user
interface hey here's a nerdy one for us support for chapter images yes there's
only a couple of podcast players that have that right that's nice they also
have included a new set of app shortcuts allow users to go directly to their QR
episode from the home screen so tap it there and goes right to that so you can
have a Linux unplugged icon on your desk or on your Android screen and just go
right to it it's also available in 17 languages I just love that about antenna
but you know it's so cool that we have such a nice mobile podcast client that's
open source oh that is Sony you know this new logo came after a call to the
open source design community and they received 12 proposals of which two were
selected and then put to a public vote well over 6,000 users participated so
hey that's so cool good for them good for them yeah and we don't talk about
antenna pot enough because it's just one of those apps that just works and you
don't really think about it but when you use some other podcast players you
realize it's got features the other ones don't is really yeah if you have you're
doing something slightly off the beaten path yeah it's the way to go and as
podcasters we really appreciate that also thank you to our core contributors
the members of this show that keep us independent forever and also get two
options a limited ad feed or or if you so crazy an extended live mix that is
pre-edit it is every flub every mistake but it's also what you get before and
after the show that never makes it into the final recording honestly sometimes
we cut topics too because we try to keep the show to a certain run length we're
not intentionally excluding that from the public release it's just a
production call and that stuff is also in the live release it's all there you
can become a member at unplugged core comm and we really appreciate it you're
making this show possible we'd love your feedback at Linux unplug
comm slash contact reading your emails and whatnot is a big part of the show
you can get links to everything we kind of talked about or maybe implied we
talked about or thought we were gonna talk about at Linux unplug comm slash
three seven five and last but not least we'd love to have you join us live oh
please do it's a great experience you get to participate either in the chat
room or in the mumble room if you so are inclined and you can find the link at
Linux unplug comm for how to set up the mumble how to get in there and then
don't forget once you have it set up you can also participate in the love plug
every single Sunday it's like it's like just a great hangout and I haven't been
able to make it as much now I've been feeling sad cuz I've been doing Linux
action news but I can tell you there has been some great conversations you get
great project ideas if you're stuck on something or if you're chewing on a
piece of hardware and now this Sunday you can also talk browsers and we will
be back next Tuesday noon Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern over at JB live TV get that
converted to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar thank you to our mumble
room thank you to our chat room thank you to you Wes well thank you to you
also thanks to everyone out there for listening and sharing the show with
somebody word-of-mouth is the number one way podcasts get marketed pretty much
nothing else works so if you know somebody who would like this show share
it with them thanks so much for turn this week's episode of the unplug
program we'll see you right back here next tues tues Tuesday
we have forever on Kota radio discussed the Oracle and Google lawsuit I want to
play this clip that I found for Kota radio it's it's Sun Microsystems from
1995 really just top of the world you know ZFS perhaps was a twinkle in their
eye and Java was gonna be this thing that took over the world and they're
actually very forward-looking considering how this how old this clip is
when you think about where the rest of the industry was it's great so I thought
this would be fun little post-show thing to listen to so check this out see how
retro it is already oh yeah you know the first 25 years at Sun have been just
huge amounts of innovation we popularized TCP IP we stunned the world
with NFS we've delivered spark and Solaris and Java and all the other new
technologies that you've seen Sun deliver and we're on six billion devices
Sun started with a very simple idea which is to take open standards on the
software side and combine them with open standards on the hardware side which at
the time was apparently quite revolutionary and everybody liked it so
this whole notion of open systems really started with Sun Microsystems 25 years
ago early on in Sun's career long before I got here was a fundamental idea that
if you propagated a standard across the world literally shared it with the world
you would create for yourself more opportunity for yourself and for your
customers and all the developers who worked with both of you our whole
strategy of sharing open interfaces open source even open sourcing the hardware
is going to create just an explosion of technology I think what really sets Sun
apart is the idea that we live so fully by the idea that you should share your
innovation with the world someone's really the first company to define open
standards and open systems in the computer area and I have every reason to
believe that that strategy will be very successful going forward
I'm not sure any companies ever had a tagline that has been as enduring and
as right on the button as the network is the computer
we try to identify one phrase that would really show what we were trying to do as
a company which was to make the computer in the network in the single show from
each other it is all about giving people access from anywhere any device any time
to open and share technologies and innovation