I just got done trying out Windows 10 for a few days, and I honestly wasn't that impressed
over say Windows 7. So, Popa, you think it's the best, but what would you say draws you
to it over, say, if you just needed a simple Windows install to do something, to get something
done, why not just use Windows 7?
Well, you could. There was nothing technically wrong with my Windows 7 install. I mean, it
was basically my Steam machine and anything else that was Windows only that I want to
try out or I want to play with. But I quite like the cleanness of Windows 10. It just
feels more polished. It just feels like... You know how Windows 7 was Windows Vista
done right? Windows 10 feels like Windows 7 with just a little bit of extra polish.
I mean, Windows 7 was fine on its own.
Yeah, I don't...
10 just feels a little bit nicer.
Yeah, I guess I just... I guess I just disagree with you. Because I don't... I mean, it does
at the very high level. The way the start menu slides up, the way the desktop, virtual
desktop slide, the way the windows pop open, you know, it kind of feels like the best of
comp is. A little bit just sort of turned down a slight touch. And I like those things
about it. But I find to be... What I find to be just sort of disappointing is sort of
the settings within settings and just settings and settings, different kinds of UIs for your
settings. There's a really good blog post, actually, that really summed it up very well.
And so I bookmarked it because the guy went through and he essentially book... He screenshotted
basically every spot where Windows 10, he says, is unfinished. And I think it's a pretty
compelling argument. Like, he goes through here and documents, like, here's two sections
that are identical in the UI that accomplish the same task. Here's, like, two display settings.
They look completely different in how they function, but they do the same task. And he
points this out over and over again. Here's where our right click menu is weird and dark
and gray. And here's where our right click menu looks like our traditional Windows menu.
And all these different inconsistencies in the icons, even in the toolbars where they
use different languages in the icons to mean different things throughout the entire UI,
it's not consistent at all. I think it's much less consistent than Windows 7 because it's
mixed with this modern UI now.
Exactly. And I've heard Microsoft in their official things, Microsoft has said that Windows
10 will never be done.
I could have told you that months ago when I tried the 9900 series technical preview.
I saw that right away. I was like, wow. And it's still not fixed. To me, Windows 10 is
a beta.
Well, and I believe it always will be.
We have gotten feedback about that. Yeah. No, it's not. Have we all really? We've all
bought into this? We've all bought into this?
Yeah. Most of the chat room. Am I really at JV on the IRC? Because, like, people talk
about Windows 10 like it's the best thing ever. I think what you guys are saying is
they rushed it to market and they're using vernacular that's hip to justify why it's
an incomplete product.
I think that would be accurate. And also, I think the whole free upgrade thing is like
really like hook, line and sink people into their market.
I mean, I paid two hundred ninety nine dollars. OK, so I could unlock the features. Oh, my
God. Well, I mean, JB did. I didn't. Wow. I didn't personally pay for it, but even so
that's a lot of money. Exactly. And I feel like I bought an unfinished product. But to
be you like to be honest with you, to do a fully genuine, honest review of the product.
I bought it because I don't have like I have I have OEM licenses from the past that I don't
I don't have that hardware anymore. And those are those machines run Linux anyways. So like
my best option was to install it from the ISO. I downloaded from Microsoft's website
and then I had to activate it to get all the features that cost two hundred ninety nine
dollars. And I figured, well, at least now I'll own one copy of Windows 10 for testing.
But in my opinion, this this this line that I've been getting from the community after
our episode that Microsoft's going to roll out new features in October and this is a
rolling release and Windows 10 is the final version. It's never done. So did you say community?
Really? Yeah. Well, we've been getting Microsoft community. No, no, no. In the last community,
in the last community, after I reviewed Windows 10 on Sunday and people said, well, it's not
fair. It's not done until October. And I can't believe we bought this line because this is
see, you guys, maybe maybe I have a different perspective because I've literally had Microsoft
family members and friends that I've been been close to my entire life. I've watched
this company. I mean, I live next to Microsoft. I've watched this company forever. This is
what they do every single time. It's the same kind of basic message, just different language
every single time. And this time we're buying it. We didn't buy it last time because they
they didn't use the right words. This time we're buying it. And if you just if you just
change what they're saying and look at the look at the ship product that cost two hundred
ninety nine dollars, I think it doesn't hold up. Exactly. And right about it's the same
stuff again, because the the article that points out the consistencies in the Windows
10 UI, that's nothing new. IBM were pointing out inconsistencies in the Windows user interface
when they were marketing OS2 against Windows and pointing out that, you know, OS2 was a
consistent object based desktop environment and everything behaved the same way in every
spot and Windows didn't do that. And was it Windows NT? Windows NT and the Service Packs,
you know, that was the original Windows rolling release, wasn't it? Every Service Pack delivered
new features and it took an awful long time for us to get off Service Pack 3 to Service
Pack 4A when just a whole ton of stuff arrived, including, you know, new browsers and things.
So this is this is nothing new. It's shinier, but it's new and it came out yesterday whenever
it was. But it's the same. It's the same tactics. I still actually say it's new language. I
think in a lot of ways, Windows 7 is still a better product. I just think that Windows
10 is probably the best you're going to get with modern support. And really, at the end
of the day, because we're talking Windows, for Linux users, one of the things that matters
with Windows 10 is it's going to support the latest version of DirectX. And that's one
of the most likely reasons a Linux user would be running Windows.
This is Linux Unplugged Episode 104 for August 4th, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that ponders if a Linux-powered
tent is a good idea or a great idea. My name is Chris and yeah, I've got camping on the
brain. We've got a great episode 104. I can't even believe that we crossed over the 100
mark and just kept on chugging because we have so much to cover. A little Ubuntu heavy
at the top of the show, but it's going to be worth it. There's some really interesting
things being clarified by Ubuntu, some big changes that I'm looking forward to and maybe
some speculation on my part and hopefully we'll set the record straight on a few things. There's
a new roadmap for the Ubuntu projects. Well, going over the next few years, it gives us
a lot of insights. They're sharing a lot of good information. And then there's also been
some discussion on the development list if maybe it's time for Ubuntu to drop the software
center in favor of GNOME software. And actually the reaction to that's been kind of negative.
We'll talk about that. And then later on in the show, the numbers are in and it looks
bad for Linux gaming. Let's just hypothesize. Is the dream failed? Is Linux gaming just
not materializing? And then also some, some of the latest games, some really great games
that came out and the benchmarks are in and the performance is devastating under Linux
compared to Windows, like 60 to 70% worse under Linux. Why is that? We'll talk about
that and what that means and if it's a bad news for steamOS, but we also have some good
news. I found in the archive a lost interview from self 2015 with the guys who made the
internet possible itself and it is so information packed about deploying good Wi-Fi, troubleshooting
Wi-Fi, and what it takes to make wireless work. You could apply it to your house or
to a major event. It is a segment in this show that I think people refer back to over
and over again when they are visiting or troubleshooting a Wi-Fi network. I can't wait to play that
for you. That's coming up later on in the show as well. So talk about that and then
if there is time, we are going to make a major, major experiment run this Friday on the Linux
Action Show. We are going to make a huge change to the show, hopefully in an attempt to be
more genuine and honor the show and the fact that it covers Linux and open source but also
to raise the quality and make it even better. And we are going to try something extremely
new and we are going to be doing it live on Friday instead of Sunday. And I want to brace
you for it. Maybe just try to bend off some of the immediate reaction that might happen
because it is going to be a big change. And I don't often talk about the show in the show
but I am going to do that at the end of today's episode of Linux Unplugged if we have time.
And I don't know exactly how much I am going to share yet because I am a little nervous.
But you know what, I have a beer here. I will just keep drinking. I am about halfway through.
We will see if by the end of that bottle if I feel like sharing anymore. But first, I
want to bring in Mr. Popey who can help me dig through some of these, well, basically
clarification that have been posted on Ollie's blog. He calls it Ollie's Random Thoughts
and Impressions. And Popey, can you tell me so that way I don't get it wrong, who is Ollie
and what does he do at Canonical?
He is VP of Engineering so he runs basically the whole show for everything that is user
visible at the moment for the most part.
And he points out, he made this post on August 3rd that there is only 242 days left until
the next long-term release of Ubuntu, Ubuntu 16.04 and so it is probably time to clarify
a few things. So remember, we have talked about Snappy on the show. Snappy is an adjective
describing a collection of technologies that allows for transactional atomic updates, rollback
and better security guarantees for apps and users. So remember, it is a transactional
updated system so the applications and the OS can be updated separately and you can roll
back.
And you are going to have Snappy Core which things can be built around. But there is a
new term being kicked around that I wanted to make sure we all understand here on this
show because I think it is going to have the largest impact for our audience. It is Ubuntu
Personal. Snappy plus Ubuntu. Ubuntu Personal. Snappy Ubuntu is the logical consequence of
all the things said so far except that it has the most beautiful user interface sitting
on top of it. However, Ubuntu Personal will be snap-based from the start and hence the
distinction Snappy Ubuntu Personal is redundant and we are simply calling it Ubuntu Personal.
Ubuntu Personal will provide all the benefits of Snappy apps to users of devices with built-in
and attached displays. Considering that Snappy systems were born out of our experience with
mobile devices, Ubuntu Personal is the next evolution of phone code based on our path
to reach code convergence.
Now I do not know exactly how to interpret that, Poppy, but it almost sounds like Ubuntu
could be something that somebody who wanted to follow like Unity 8 and Mir and maybe even
try it on a laptop would maybe be interested in Ubuntu Personal. Or is it just something
for mobile devices? What exactly is it?
Yeah. So like longer term, you could think of buying a device that has Snappy on it and
that could be a router or an autonomous device like a flying thing or, you know, it could
be a fridge or anything. But Snappy Ubuntu Personal is more about the desktop user experience.
So that's like laptops, desktops, like Chromecast style devices, things that have a graphical
user interface are more likely to be Ubuntu Personal. So they're machines that a normal
user would interact with like directly.
Does that include a laptop?
Yeah. Yeah, totally.
So it's everything from a tiny device that might have a UI on it up to a fairly powerful
personal computer.
So like Invisage, like distantly in the future, everything running Snappy. But the ones that
you sit out and type at and touch and swipe and, you know, use a mouse with, those might
be running Ubuntu Personal. But the ones which don't have a display, which are embedded
IoT things, routers, flying things, would just be Snappy Ubuntu Core. And you interact
with those differently. That's the kind of distinction between the two.
So also Ubuntu Personal kind of replaces Desktop Next, which was sort of the way to currently
try out Mir and Unity 8, right?
Yeah. Desktop Next was a kind of image that you could play with that was never really
designed to be a production desktop. And the goal with Ubuntu Personal is that that will
be the production desktop. It's the next evolution of Desktop Next.
Yeah. And now keeping in mind that the actual Debian-based Ubuntu distribution isn't going
away, this still seems like a ginormous, mind-bending, completely game-changing evolution for the
project. Basically, you're going, I mean, your star products are going to be Snap-based.
They're not going to be Deb-based. They're not, it is an entirely new creation that you
guys are...
From my perspective, really, when you think of star product, some people will think, well,
from my perspective, a star product is something I can install Debs on and I can go and randomly
build code on.
Today. Yeah. Yeah. For the next few years.
And to do it in the future. It could well be the case in the future. You still want
to be able to go and get a random Deb off the internet of your favorite app, whatever
it might be, and install it. And away you go. Whereas other people will say, my star
machine is the thing where I open the lid and it works every time when I open the lid
and it updates itself in the background and I don't have to worry about PPAs or Debs
or, you know, Pseudo or all that kind of stuff. It just works, right? So for some people,
that is their star platform.
To me, what it sounds like is it sounds like Ubuntu Debian-based is a transition platform
for those people who have based products around it or have environments around it. And so
because of that, it will be around for many years. But really, I think if transactional-based
systems take off, which I can't imagine they wouldn't on the server, especially with people
trying to deploy applications who are not necessarily the best at understanding how
systems work, I've got to imagine that a transactionally-based, container-based system is going to really
go big and a lot of people will switch. And it also makes a ton of sense on the desktop
and it makes delivering desktop applications so much simpler on desktop Linux. I mean,
I see here, so I'm looking at this timeline you guys have posted and you can see where
Desktop Next comes to an end and where Ubuntu Personal kind of becomes a thing, especially
around 16.10 where maybe, like, there's actually something people could try. And really, I
mean, the distro that everyone's going to be wanting to use, even next year, you run
16.10 time and so forth, is going to be the Debian-based version. But you go out a few
more years, if people are really starting to contribute to the Snap Store and a lot
of people are building and delivering applications in Snaps or whatever the hell they're called,
you know, DigitalOcean has a droplet you can fire up based on Ubuntu's Snappy Core. I'm
sure they'll do that. It's going to go big, I would think.
Well, yeah, and there'll be certainly a period of time where both things are running in parallel
and Ubuntu Personal may take off and become, like, the Chromebook-style OS that just works
and you don't have to worry about devs and PPAs and all that kind of stuff.
I just love it, like, in a production environment, Poppy, like in a studio, I love the idea of
a transactionally-based system. Because if I go to do a show and it's not working, I
can roll back. That's a lifesaver.
It certainly has, like, use cases that people outside your listenership might be interested
in, like, you know, my mum would not really care about PPAs and devs and release upgrades
every six months and that kind of stuff. She just wants to work and carry on working every
day. But there are people out there who are engineers or developers who want the flexibility
to be able to get under the hood and tweak around with it.
And while you can do that with Ubuntu Personal, obviously, then if your level of tweaking
means building devs and delivering software as devs and hacking in a way that Personal
maybe isn't appropriate for, then the Debian-based distro is still there and will continue to
be there. And that's one of the key things to take away, actually, is we keep getting
– this blog post was partly to clear up a lot of misconception in the community. People
keep saying, oh, well, they're going to switch to clicks, they're going to switch
to snaps, and the Debian desktop will disappear. Well, no, it's not. The whole point of this
is the archive is what everything is built from. So we can't take away that archive
because it's all built from that. And that is our special source, is the archive.
The way Ollie put it, he says, the underlying center of gravity for everything I've described
so far, however, is Ubuntu, which is bigger than any single technology or product or code
base. Ubuntu, the Linux distribution, as we all know and love it, will continue to be
there on the internet, freely available to anyone and everyone.
Exactly.
So, yeah, because Snappy and all that is based on that. And it's interesting, and I'm looking
forward to maybe one day sitting here and having my machine that's displaying visuals
on the stream be powered by Ubuntu Snappy. I think it's going to be, from a show content
and review and just digging into stuff and talking about it standpoint, super interesting
and fascinating. Can't wait. Cannot wait. It's going to be a lot of fun. At least, if
nothing else, fascinating to watch it. Who knows where it goes? Who knows? My bet's all
on Plasma Mobile.
All right. So, before we get into our last Ubuntu thing, just to kind of wrap up our
conversation and I'm actually, it's great also because it just kind of fits in nicely
with our conversation we had with Wimpy last week. So I want to talk about that in just
a moment. But first, I want to tell you about DigitalOcean, the first sponsor of Linux Unplugged.
And if you actually want to support the Linux Unplugged program, I got a secret. Well, it's
a secret, like the kind of secret I'd like you to tell every single person you know.
You have secrets like that? Yeah. Well, I'm not going to go there. We can get dirty quick.
But use the promo code DEOUNPLUGGED and you get a $10 credit over at DigitalOcean and
spread it around like HSV1. Just spread it around and let everybody have some of it.
DEOUNPLUGGED over at digitalocean.com. Whoa, whoa, whoa. You don't know? You don't know
what DigitalOcean is? Oh, let me tell you about DigitalOcean. DigitalOcean is a simple
cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to
get your own rig up in the cloud. Now, they got free BSD machines. Well, I mean, you know,
maybe you want to use free BSD. It's pretty cool. But they have like core OS. You want
to talk about, boy, talk about something, talk about, talk about something snappy trying
to rip off. Oh, I'm just kidding. No, it's cool. Core OS, you know, you have the rolling
base OS on DigitalOcean because their bosses, they work directly upstream with the core
OS team. So you get great core-based OSs and then the applications are containerized, which
is slick. Of course, they've also got Ubuntu LTS and they got several versions of Ubuntu
up there. They got Fedora. They got Debian. They even now have Fedora 22. How about that?
Not bad. Now, this is the best part. You can get started in less than 55 seconds and you
got that promo code DEOUNPLUGGED. You don't even have to worry about the cost. So just
go over there and get started because now your time, what, you don't got 55 seconds.
Give me a break. And check this out, $5 a month. Well, DEOUNPLUGGED is going to give
you a $10 credit. For $10, you're going to be able to run a rig for two months. Now,
check out this $5 rig. You get 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSDs. They're all SSDs.
One CPU and a terabyte of transfer. And DigitalOcean is data center locations in New York, San
Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London, and a big old bad boy in Germany. But their interface
is what I love about them. I've been in IT for years. Well, I had been until I got into
podcasting because, man, I had to get out of IT. And you know one of the reasons I had
to get out of IT? I'm looking at you, VMware ESX, running your whole entire infrastructure
on Linux and forcing me to use a Windows client. I will never get over that. I will never,
I will never forgive you. And how complicated it is and all of these different, even you,
Proxmox, I'm looking at you. Even you, Proxmox, you're way too complicated. All you guys with
virtualizations, you're making it way too complicated. You need to go over to DigitalOcean.com.
I'm talking to you, Proxmox. Guys, I love you. I love you. But your web UI, you need
to go over to DigitalOcean, okay? VMware, you need to go over to DigitalOcean, all right?
Okay? Everybody, go over to DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED and learn how
to really build an interface. Man, you can spin up these droplets like a boss. You can
deploy applications with one click. It's really nice. Full DNS management, snapshots, templates,
transfer them to somebody else once you're done with the project. I love it. And remember,
DOUNPLUGGED, you can try it out, two months for free. They have great tutorials and also,
they're often hiring Linux positions and content editors. Check out their We're Hiring page
too. And I bet you if you told them you heard about them from us, you might get moved to
the head of the line. I'm just saying it might work. DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code
DOUNPLUGGED and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
So you know what I love is when mailing lists, when developer mailing lists turn into news.
Oh man, only in the open source community and it creates so much drama. And then we
start to question ourselves and like, oh, we shouldn't behave like this. Commercial
companies have never been, no, commercial companies behave like this too. It's just
they don't have a public mailing list. So what the hell's going on? In the mailing list
on the, over on the Ubuntu developers mailing list, there was a post that suggested dropping
the Ubuntu software center and adopting GNOME software. Now, GNOME software is not bad.
I actually kind of do like it in some regards, but it got me thinking. Yesterday show, last
week show episode 103, we talked to Wimpy about a lot of feedback he got around the
software center. And Wimpy, just as a little follow up to that, did you make a final decision
or was your decision final at the time of the recording? I can't recall.
Yeah, it was final then and it stands. So I'm going to provide the Ubuntu software center
and upgrade as options in Ubuntu Mate. Welcome.
So what do you think about this idea of maybe like in the, let's just for fun, just say
Ubuntu shipped with, instead of the Ubuntu software center, for giggles, let's say it
ships with GNOME software center and maybe a few, you know, canonical fixes have been
applied. Wimpy, would that be something you'd be willing to look at and maybe consider including
in Ubuntu Mate?
I'm prepared to consider all viable options.
Do you think it's a good idea?
I think it's a lot of work adapting GNOME software to replace Ubuntu software center
because there's a super set of functionality in Ubuntu software center. So given the time
required, I think that's a big ask. And fundamentally the way GNOME software works is different
to the Ubuntu software center. So with GNOME software, each application has to ship its
own app data XML file, which is the information that gets presented in GNOME software. Whereas
Ubuntu software center and app grid use confusingly something else that's called app data, but
they're packages that you install and they're effectively databases of metadata for the
packages that are in the official archive and the partner repository. And that's where
all of the, you know, the descriptions and artwork and stuff comes from. So they're fundamentally
different and you don't have reviews in GNOME software, for example. So I'm prepared to
keep an open mind on this and I will happily, you know, move to other solutions that present
themselves that are a viable alternative. And I've even said to Popeye I'm prepared
to help with the development effort on whatever the viable alternative might be. I don't know
how much time I'm going to have to devote to that, but I'm prepared to pitch in and
help with that, yeah.
So I like to, so SB5637 in our last subreddit had a pretty, pretty well voted up response
to this. He says, I personally think it's a bad idea. I've extensively tested and tried
the like GNOME software on Fedora and OpenSUSE, but it was pitifully awful in my opinion.
You can't browse apps while another app is installing and some apps just simply don't
appear in search results even if they're available in category listings. Search results in general
are pretty bad and I don't like how it refuses to show apps that don't have AppStream data.
At the very least it could fall back to package name and a short description like Synaptic
shows if AppStream data isn't available. Instead, they're just ignoring the software
altogether. And the other thing I've noticed is sometimes it fails to load certain screens
for me. There are oddities to it. The other thing too is it seems like it would be a little
bit waste of time. I don't know, Poppy, feel free to correct me if I'm wrong, but it seems
like Energies and Times would be focused on building QT and QML apps, not adding code
to GTK apps that are contributed by other projects. Poppy, is that?
I think one of the problems is that none of the App Store apps are perfect. Software Center's
got its issues. There's lack in functionality in – if we're just talking about Apps
Store's honorability. App Grid has issues in that it's proprietary and there are missing
features. GNOME software obviously is very tailored for GNOME and might not fit Unity
quite so well. They all have issues, but they're all solvable. It's simply a matter of programming
and it's where you want to devote your attention. My personal feeling is if we rallied a bunch
of people around Ubuntu Software Center, we could probably fix up some of the issues,
remove some of the things that are maybe less desirable or less applicable these days, or
convince the App Grid guy to add features and freely license his code. I don't know.
I'm not entirely convinced that adopting GNOME software when we're 80% of the way
there with the other tools is the right way to do it.
Yeah, I'm surprised there hasn't been more of a community rallying around. Couldn't
there be community patches applied to Ubuntu Software Center and just maybe –
Yeah, of course. It's free software. It's free software like anything else. Part of
the problem is that it's a canonical project and we haven't devoted enough attention to
it over the last few years. People think it's dead and nobody's maintaining it. That's
a perfectly reasonable perception to make when you look at the code that there haven't
been any releases for ages and nobody's done any features and it's idle for a long time.
That doesn't motivate community people to actively work on something when the maintainer
and owner of that project isn't maintaining it themselves, right? That's the same for
any Ubuntu software project.
I think if there was a reboot of Ubuntu Software Center, not a rewrite, but find out what the
features are that shouldn't be there and the features that are missing and the performance
issues. Really, it would need to be updating for Python 3 because we're looking to remove
Python 2 and it's a Python 2 app. It would need to be updated to Python 3. There's a
bunch of things that need to happen to it, but it's whether people are willing to contribute
those things. I'm sure we could find someone in Canonical to help and mentor those people
and people in the community like Martin was suggesting to help update it. We need people
to help out. It's all very well throwing broken bottles at us and telling us it's crap, but
someone's got to throw patches attached to those broken bottles.
Just kidding.
Thanks, Chris.
Just kidding. All right. Well, good. The thread is linked in the show notes if you guys want
to read it. It's fascinating. I'm glad there's discussion around it. I think it's a conversation
worth having, so I'm glad it is happening.
I want to play a clip that I literally found in the archive. Noah was like, hey, I think
you might need to check over here, and I dug through it. It is a fascinating clip by a
couple of guys who work at an ISP called Global Vision, Linux-powered ISP, Linux on the infrastructure,
Linux on the backend. They claim they're able to deliver wireless internet more reliable
in some cases even than fiber. That's what they say. They describe it in the interview.
One of the other things they do is they rock the wireless at trade shows, so much so that
we were able to get live Wi-Fi coverage using streaming video over Wi-Fi walking around
the floor itself. They do all of this using Linux laptops and Linux tools. It's not so
much about that angle in this clip that I'm about to play, but this is an incredibly fascinating
insight into how to manage a good wireless network. These two gentlemen break it down
in such an easy to understand way that I walked away from this interview feeling like I have
an entirely new understanding of Wi-Fi, and I think so often on our Linux laptops we blame
drivers or the Wi-Fi chipset, which it often is the problem, but sometimes, honestly, it's
the fact that we have messed up Wi-Fi networks, which are extremely tricky. So this clip is
very valuable even if you have a small Wi-Fi network or a huge enterprise Wi-Fi network,
and I wanted to play it. It was from the archive of SELF 2015.
Welcome. Southeast Linux Text 2015 walking around, came across one of the booths we were
at last year, and now if you're watching the live stream or had been watching the live
stream, you probably heard us talk about Global Vision. These are the guys that brought the
internet to SELF and did an amazing job. I'm here with Zach, and I actually didn't catch
your name. Ethan. Ethan. Good to meet you, Ethan. Thanks for taking the time to be here
with us. So I wanted to talk, first of all, if you could tell me a little bit about Global
Vision itself and what it is you guys do. So Global Vision is a, particularly, it's
a wireless ISP based out of Greenville, South Carolina. We have wireless networks in both
Pickens County and Greenville County and Spartanburg County, and we provide both residential and
business internet along with phone service, and we do it via VoIP, voice over IP, and
we also manage the public wireless network for the city of Pickens.
All right. Now, when you say wireless ISP, if somebody's not familiar with that, most
people have, you know, a cable modem in their house, and then they plug it into the router,
and that's how they're getting their internet. Now, you were telling me last year that there's
actually, there are some places in your neck of the woods where getting a cable modem,
that's just not going to happen. So you're actually giving internet or providing internet
to people that ordinarily may not be able to get internet.
Yeah, that is correct. Our product specializes in the rural areas or in new neighborhoods.
When they build new neighborhoods, charter could take two years to come into the neighborhood
where we can roll in there from day one, even when there's just one house, it's still profitable
for us to roll in. And essentially what we do is we put an antenna about this big on
the outside of your house pointing up at our tower, which is on Parris Mountain, and then
we just run an ethernet cable into your house and power the radio via PoE, power of ethernet,
and that will provide internet to the house.
When you talk about these radios, what frequency are they running at?
We run exclusively at five gigahertz for the residential stuff. Now on the business side,
we also get into some different ones like 24 gigahertz, and we also use 11 gigahertz
licensed links.
Now at that frequency, how picky are the radios about being exactly, the antennas about being
line of sight to each other?
So the five gigahertz, it is a requirement that they have clear line of sight to get
the range that we're talking. Our nearest client to the towers is just over a mile.
So when we talk wireless links, we laugh at people that say, oh, I can do so many feet.
I can do so many miles. And so in five gigahertz, it needs clear line of sight. So a tree doesn't
count as clear line of sight.
So there's obviously some challenges then if you work in a place that's densely populated
with trees or has fences. How is it that you're going to get around if somebody has property
that there is no part of their house that has a clear line of sight to your tower?
So what we've done with some customers is we'll get up on the roof, and we can barely
see the mountain through some trees. And we'll tell the customer, all right, that tree, that
tree, that tree, and that tree is in the way. And we actually had one client while we're
still standing on the roof, went to his shed, pulled out a chainsaw, and cut down five trees
before we left so that we could install his antenna and he'd have internet for his kids.
Welcome to South Carolina. Tell me a little bit about what it's like to be providing Wi-Fi
for self. Typically, conference Wi-Fi is horrendous. Most attendees kind of have come to expect
that. And you guys have done a phenomenal job. My Wi-Fi has dropped out maybe twice
the entire time I've been here. And other than that, I actually, it's been so reliable,
I actually have our production laptop running on Wi-Fi. Even though you've given us a hard
drop, it is that good. So tell me how it is you've been able to achieve that.
So part of it is we use dual frequency. There's 2.4 and 5 gigahertz. We're broadcasting over
the entire conference area. And the problem with 2.4 is all these dang hotspots. So people
will fire up these hotspots. It will create 2.4 gigahertz interference. And the signal
strength and the ping times and latency will go down the toilet. So with the 5 gigahertz
network is really reliable. And there's a lot more channels. So we can do a better channel
payment with the 5 gigahertz. So to get to help encourage people to use 5 gigahertz,
we renamed the 2.4 network to dash slow to encourage people to connect to the 5 gigahertz
because at this day and age, the vast majority of devices are 5 gigahertz capable.
We matched that with decent channel planning. We mapped out all the APs on one of the maps
that the event provided us. And we did some good channel planning. We also had to turn
on the minimum RSSI setting, which allows you to roam a little better. Before we had
turned that on, I was all the way in the other ballroom. And I was still connected to this
AP with one bar. It wouldn't jump onto the next one. So once we turned that on, you move
more easily from one access point to the next and you just get a better signal overall.
Now is the minimum RSSI, is that something that everyone should be looking at doing if
they're planning to put access points in to an infrastructure across the building?
So minimum RSSI is necessary in a multi-AP environment because without it, you cannot
roam effectively. Essentially what it does is the AP itself looks at the difference between
the signal and the noise and basically the quality of the link. And if it drops below,
in our case, 20 dB separation, the AP will simply kick the client off in an attempt to
force the client to reconnect to another access point. And in most environments, you will
only see about a one to two ping packet drop during that kick process.
Now tell me this, if that happens, if there isn't a stronger access point available, like
let's say I'm at the fringe of the network, am I just going to continually get dropped?
Yes. Okay. And for the benefit of the entire network, that is the best thing to happen
because the system can be only as good as its weakest link.
Okay. All right. When you guys go to set these access points up, how important is placement
inside of the rooms?
Extremely important. You want to try to stay away from RF bad materials such as brick.
You don't want to put one of these access points right up against a brick wall because
all of the access points that we use now are omnidirectional. So the radio is not compensating
the fact that it's up against a brick wall. So it can actually damage the AP if it's running
too high because too much of the RF interference will come back into the AP bouncing off the
wall.
That's incredible. Anything you guys want to add about what Global Vision is doing or
what it is that you guys have done to make self possible or future endeavors that you
guys might get into?
So one of the things that we're starting to get into is more high end dedicated links.
We have the capability now of delivering gigabit internet to our business over wireless where
you could spend $20,000 and build up costs for AT&T fiber or another fiber provider and
then on top of that pay $2,000 or $3,000 a month for that gig service. We can go in at
a much cheaper price point and deliver it wirelessly and we don't have backhoe fade.
Backhoe fade in the fiber industry is when a backhoe cuts the fiber and that your fiber
circuit is super reliable until the backhoe gets it and then you could be two or three
days without service where because our product is wireless we don't have that problem.
One of the things we've been focusing on lately, Zach came up with a solution a couple months
ago for our VoIP service and we were constantly answering phone calls about complaints about
the hostess service that we were using before but what it seems like we've been doing a
lot of is coming in and just doing an end to end install from phone to radio including
the cabling, the switches, the routes, everything all the way back to us that we can then manage
from our own desks without even having to go to anyone's actual office building and
that's really caused us to, some of the stress is gone as well as some of the things are
just way, way easier to manage. We get a lot less complaints. We've had a company recently
where we did inside and out everything was Global Vision and I have not heard a call
of complaint yet from them. Completely different from coming in with VoIP phones and plugging
into their $19 Netgear router and having SIP ALG issues and things like that and then they
just blame Global Vision because they were able to check their emails on it before and
how come they can't get VoIP service now? When we come in and say okay, let's put this
router in here and if it works you can buy it from us. They always buy it from us.
Yeah, I've actually done the same thing. I've got into a place and I say listen, I'm so
confident in the equipment I sell that I'll put it in first. If you don't like it, call
me in a week and I'll come pick it back up and no questions asked but if you do like
it we'll send you an invoice and the reality is once they get it and once they use it and
they see that once they get accustomed to it and it works. Well, thank you so much for
taking the time to talk to us. Thank you so much for your commitment to Linux community
to bring all of this stuff here so we all have good Wi-Fi and if I see you walking around
with your Yagi sleeping hunting for people, I might have to come follow you around.
Absolutely.
Those guys are great. So now one of the things that Wimby reminded me about in the chat room
is that he's actually talking to us over a four mile wireless link right now so you have
some insights in this particular topic, don't you Wimpy?
Yeah I've been using wireless broadband for six years, something like that. So for a few
years I used 3G as a means to get internet access and now I use a local ISP who is an
ex-Motorola radio engineer and he specializes in wireless broadband services in rural areas
in the UK.
Well your sound is pretty good. How has it been as a service?
It's been 100% reliable since it was installed about three years ago so the services 12 meg
download, four meg upload and when I do the podcast with Popey and the others and we've
been checking network response times, mine are in the same ballpark as everyone else's
who's using 5G.
Yeah you're looking pretty good here. I'm looking at your mumble stats right now. Less
than a 1%, I mean it's really looking good, like not bad at all. We've had 10 late packets
out of like 198,000.
Yeah, yeah. So yeah I've got no complaints. It's certainly far better than the 512k ADSL
service that I can get from the major BT provider in this country.
Well now Global Vision is just a local ISP as far as I know in the Charlotte area but
I gotta say we go to a lot of these events and we go to pro events and we go to community
events and CELF is a community event and it has some of the best Wi-Fi out of all of them.
Now they're very judicious, they go around with sensors like no it was given a hard time
at the end there and they kick rogue APs off and things like that but you know I gotta
give it to them. Like it's really nice to be able to go there and have good Wi-Fi. When
you go to a technical event and the Wi-Fi sucks, it's like, I don't know, it's like
a real weird disconnect between like the interest of the community and all of a sudden they're
in like offline mode. It's almost like camping but really hot and sweaty. I thought some
of those tips would be really good and maybe if you've had some wireless issues, maybe
it's not Linux's fault, maybe it's the wireless in your house.
I think what is in common there is I'm with an independent ISP, you've just interviewed
an independent ISP. I think there's a lot of value in having a small local company who
know what they're doing over being one of millions of customers with a national provider
and you really don't matter to them.
And that is kind of the nice thing about wireless, right? Is they can, it actually gives somebody
like an independent market a place to move into. The wired infrastructure is owned, right?
You can't really be an independent ISP on the wired infrastructure but in the wireless
spectrum, there's still space for the third party small independent person or company.
And the organization I'm with, they even do mesh networks in the community as well. So
each of the houses mesh together and you can have community mesh networks with them as
well, which is kind of neat.
Well, the other thing that's nice about these guys is being a local ISP is, you know, they're
Linux enthusiasts. So they go to events like this and bring in the internet for the event
and they run Linux back at the office and it's just really neat. It's a pretty cool
thing to still see out there because when I was back when I was in high school, the
dial-up ISPs were local, you know, and like they had, they ran fake servers back at their
office and stuff like that. It was a community. And so it's neat to still see that out there
a little bit. It makes me a little nostalgic.
All right. Well, I want to talk about the gaming stats that have come out recently.
And maybe part of me, like I like to, I don't like to pretend like the sky is falling but
gee, sometimes I think we just maybe just need to have a dose of reality. So we're going
to talk about some of the things I've been reading and maybe what it means. Maybe it
means nothing. Maybe we'll get through it all and I'll be okay. But first, I want to
tell you about something that makes me feel great. Something that makes me feel like I'm
moving forward, striving. That's Linux Academy. You can get a great discount if you go to
linuxacademy.com slash unplug. Get our 33% discount. Now Linux Academy is an institution.
It is a learning institution created by Linux and open source enthusiasts, people who are
really passionate about this stuff, which also has the great benefit of means they really
follow the good stuff closely. Linux Academy has step-by-step video courses for you to
go and learn about all kinds of topics. More than 1600 videos, almost 1700 videos, you
get different experience levels on all kinds of topics around Linux and open source. Seven
plus Linux distributions that you get to choose from. You always get to keep track of your
progress. They have all of the great technology stacks like Vagra and OpenStack and Docker
and Nginx and Apache and PHP and Perl and MySQL. All of it. Really all of it. It's kind
of awe-inspiring when you go there. I will not say though, it's not overwhelming. There's
a few things that help you understand it. First of all, it's all broken down and how
long each section is going to take. There's guides you can download and read offline or
listen to while you take a shower. The only thing that's really cool is the scenario-based
labs help me actually apply what I'm learning to a real scenario, as the name would suggest.
These labs spin up virtual servers for you so you get to actually work with the technology
and those virtual servers match the courseware. There's seven plus Linux distributions that
you get to choose from and then the courseware is set by the distribution and the virtual
servers are set by that. Of course, if you get stuck, there's Instructor Health. That's
no bigs. Now, if you're looking at getting some of the Red Hat certified courses, which
I have done many of interviews when I was a contractor for my clients and also for hiring
for the company that did the contracting. I'm a bit of a diva when it comes to a lot
of certifications. I think a lot of them are hot air. I actually have mad respect though
for some of these Red Hat certifications. There's a lot of other ones I have respect
for too, but the Red Hat ones, really. The thing is, you have to go actually do that
work in the Red Hat course. You have to go actually apply what you've learned and try
it. It's not just answering the questions. You've got to go do it and there's no Google
and they don't give you an internet connection. You have to do it all offline. I mean, that's
tough. I have mad respect for that and they have the best courseware on the Red Hat stuff
and they update it all the time. They really pay attention to that. Also, if you just have
a little bit of time, you can set your availability and they'll generate courseware around that
or you can go check out some of their nuggets. These are just like deep dives into one topic,
six to 10 to 20 to 60 minutes long. Like this one's manipulating logs with SED. That's a
new one. I like that a lot. I like getting your announcements too. If you have a great
new success from Linux Academy, like you got a new cert or you passed a course or you got
a great mark on your review, let me know. Tweet me, at chrislas. I like to cover those
too. Those are really cool. Go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and see what I've been talking
about. 33% discount's great and you can try it out. It includes the cost of a virtual
machine when you spin that up with the courseware. It's really cool. Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program. Now, I'm not trying
to be chicken little. I'm not trying to run around with my head cut off, but these latest
numbers are no good. We've got to talk about gaming on Linux just really quick. A couple
of different places, Ferronics has their post up. I have that linked in the show notes.
Boilingsteam.com has their post up. Shadow of Mordor, the latest big, big game to come
to Linux. We covered it in the news segment on the Linux Action Show. It's such a big
game. I don't normally do that anymore. And so, Boiling Point Steam had an i7 rig with
an Intel GTX 680, eight gigabytes of RAM on Ubuntu 1504 and Windows 10 Pro, both 64 bit.
And the results are in and they're real bad, you guys. So, on Windows, he was able to get
81 frames per second on max. On Ubuntu, 50 frames per second. Average frames was 55 frames
per second on Windows, 30 frames per second on Ubuntu. They tried it on another rig, one
with the GTX 980 and the i7, four gigahertz. Again, Ubuntu, 1504, 64 bit this time and
Windows 8. Windows 8.1, actually. Oh, no. Max frames per second, 152 frames per second
on Windows, 114 on Ubuntu. 107 was the average on Windows. It was really 108. And on Ubuntu,
it was 73. Man, that's pretty bad. Now, here's the other thing that sucks. This is just like,
boy, that hurts when a brand new game comes out and it just plays horrible on Linux. You
just, you know, you hate to see that. Something else that really kind of you hate to see and
I guess it's just unavoidable. It's the nature of the beast. It's a game, it's the number
one gaming platform. It's not too surprising. There's already more Windows 10 Steam gamers
than all Linux distros combined on Steam. Kind of depending on how you break it down.
But 44% of Steam users are running Windows 7, 64 bit. 31% are using Windows 8.1, 64 bit.
Windows 10, 64 bit now clocks in at 2.21%. And the 32 bit variant is 0.09%. Yosemite,
if you take all the different versions of Yosemite and put them together, Mac OS Yosemite
is 1.10%. But if you combine them all together, it gets up to 2.4% for the Mac. All Linux
OSes combined that Steam actually tracks, 0.55%. So Windows 10 technically was released
on Wednesday, but people had it for a little while. And it's already surpassed by a pretty
fair margin, the Linux number of Steam users. Which doesn't matter at all. Well, I think
it's kind of depressing because I think the line is always... No, it's not. Because those
numbers are skewed immediately. Yeah, yeah. Like for example, the Mordor, oh, the one
game performs better. Okay. It's not just one game though. In fact, the really depressing
thing is, and I have this Phronix article linked in the show notes, in a lot of cases
native Linux games are only performing slightly better than games that are wrapped in the
Eon wrapper. They're only slightly outperforming Wine games. On average, most Linux games with
a few exceptions are performing worse than the Linux counterparts across the board. What
about the Valve statistics that show that... Yeah, that is the Valve, that is the outlier
actually. Right, but like Counter-Strike Global Offensive was like 30% better on Linux. I
think it's probably not a matter of... I mean, maybe there is some issue with Linux, but
I think it's also just a matter of how hard they're working on it. And I don't... See,
I think the main line that we always get is, well, wait till Steam OS comes along, and
then Steam OS will solve this. But all these games are not console games. I mean, they're
not going to be great console experiences. And this is... Steam OS isn't going to fix
this particular problem. I mean, maybe Linux just isn't a good gaming platform. Is that
impossible to admit? Yes, because it hasn't got to the point where it's even been tested
yet. There's only been, what, three or four AAA games? And one of them was a Batman Arkham
game that came out that was atrocious in every platform. So they screwed up massively on
every platform, so that's not a metric. Shadow of Mordor, do we know if it was native or
if it's wrapped? Do we even know? No, it's native. Okay, well that's good, but that's
one game that messed up. So there's other games that were wrapped that perform really
good, like The Witcher 3. So does it really matter? We can't use any of these metrics
yet because it's making a decision to say that this is not good enough and we're not
there yet when we're barely even on the starting line. North Ranger, you think it really does
come down to gaming profiles that make drivers optimized for certain games? Yeah, definitely.
We had the news the last couple of weeks that changing the name of the binary to fake out
the driver, thinking you're Half-Life 2, automatically gives you an extra 30% framerate. Yeah, I
do recall that too. That's a good point. Yeah, I guess I'm somewhere in the middle here,
because I just wanted to kind of open this up for discussion. WW, you have a clarification
on Arkham Knight, go ahead. Yeah, Arkham Knight is because of the PC release, which was Windows
only, and they're literally fixing it. So by maybe the end of this month, maybe the
start of September, we might get an update to that. There's still that, just because
of that alone, that's delayed the Linux port until next year. So you can't even count that
among the games that are on Linux yet. So, I mean, it's not even worth to mention it,
just because we can't even test it yet. I guess, I wonder if, I just feel like perhaps
the issue is that an operating system like Linux just doesn't necessarily make itself
a very good platform for games, because games kind of require the opposite of what an ever-evolving
operating system fundamentally provides. And that's why Valve is creating SteamOS. I don't,
but, and I think Valve recognizes this issue, and that's why they want to create SteamOS,
which is a safe landing place where game developers can have certain expectations that will always
be met. That's because marketing for Linux is terrible. But is it that? Yeah, all these
factors combined are an issue, yes. I'm not saying that one is better than the other as
far as the sense of why they're doing it. I'm just saying that there's multiple factors
that they're making these decisions on, and that there's more likely that the reason why
we don't have a good gaming infrastructure right now is because it's only been a few
years. It's been, like, what, two years at the most that it's been even reasonable, whereas,
you know, for a while Steam was ignored on Windows, too. And it took them, like, they've
been around for ten years, and it took them, well, no, they've been around twelve years,
it took them, like, six or seven years to get any relevancy on Windows. Yeah, I actually,
you know, when I, the practical, so here's the practical side of this. And Rekai, by
the way, agrees that game profiles make a huge difference. But here's what I see. The
games I play, and I don't really give a big crap, the games I play play, oh, fine enough
for me, like, the framerate's good enough, like, I don't notice the framerate being slow.
And I got so many games in Steam now that I can't play 70% of them. And I recently,
like last weekend, there was, like, a super badass sale for Linux, a SteamOS sale, I hope
some of you guys got in on that stuff, because it was sweet. And I picked up, like, this
new Mordor game, the Shadow of Mordor, and it runs fine for me. I just picked up, I got,
like, three new games that were, like, crazy cheap, and I'm set now. And, like, we are
now at the point with Linux gaming that if you are just not super picky, there is a ton
of selection. And I don't think it's, I don't really think it's a huge gap to go from where
we're at now to really being a competitive system. But I don't, I am skeptical that desktop
Linux will ever be the right candidate. I think, I think people might maybe one day
go from dual booting desktop Linux and maybe even SteamOS or something. I mean, I don't
know exactly. Because it just seems like all these games keep coming out, and the developers
are just unwilling. It's not even, like, Linux is incapable of it. It's that these developers
are unwilling to put the effort into it because of preconceptions or because of technical
limitations that they don't know what to work around to or whatever. I mean, they could
have a legitimate reason for all I know. But they don't seem to be willing to put the effort
into it. And if SteamOS promises to solve some of these problems, even if it's just
through marketing and branding and Valve brand loyalty, maybe we'll start to see the performance
on SteamOS inch up and inch up and inch up. And, you know, I'm sure we'll trickle, I'm
sure that'll trickle down to other Linux distributions. I'm sure there'll be wikis updated on how
to take advantage of those things, so.
Well, couldn't you argue that that was true even, like, years ago before SteamOS existed
and that developers never cared in the first place. And now that SteamOS exists, they are
starting to care and it's been proven by all these games actually coming to SteamOS.
Yeah, I mean, I guess. Right, yeah. Okay, yeah. Yes, the existence of the games, it
proves they care to some degree. I'm just, I'm major disappointed that the games consistently
are not performing as good as they could. And I don't...
Right, I'm just saying that they're, the changing of the developer's opinion is actually happening.
That's my point. I mean, regardless of whether it's working or not, as far as, like, how
good the performance is and stuff, I don't know. Not because I don't game that much,
but...
That's the problem. Don't you think that's the problem is, like, they are, like, testing
it out. Like, they're putting their toe in the water. Yay! At the same time, they're
doing such a crappy job that the Linux market share is really just not responding. You know,
it's not increasing. It's not, like, they're just not doing a good enough job to really
move the needle and that could send the wrong signal.
They're not doing a good enough job, but that's only because they're not doing enough. They're
not doing as many games. There's, like, I mean, as far as, like, AAA games, how many
are there on Linux? Five, maybe?
Yeah, I mean, there's, like, three that I think are really great, yeah. But, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, and there's recently a new SteamOS exclusive, which is quite adorable.
Yeah, I'm just talking about AAA and the AAA on, like, not whether they're good or not,
just the fact that they have, like, marketing behind, like, EA or something.
Oh, yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah, and they were available on other platforms first
in those cases as well.
Yeah. And, like, Borderlands is awesome. And it's one of the AAAs that's available on
Linux and it runs great.
Mm-hmm. I do enjoy Borderlands a lot.
Yeah.
There are some examples where it is working and it's fantastic, because I never even heard
of that. I mean, I've heard of the game. I never bothered playing it. And when it came
on Linux, it's, like, awesome. I'm playing it.
Well, actually, most of my experiences, like I say, like, I say this with sort of a disclaimer
that for me, the problem is really not that bad. Like, I don't actually, I consider myself
to be kind of picky and I don't really notice any problems until I go read these blogs or
these reviews. And I'm, like, oh, well, I guess that's an issue. I don't particularly
have that issue, I guess. I mean, I suppose. And so then I'm, like, well, I guess it could
be a little bit better. But for me, I'm not too picky. Usually, I just kind of, I'm more
casual these days. So it's not as big of a deal for me.
I think it's the issue of these blogs are taking the example of Happy Days and Jumping
the Shark.
Oh, wow, dude. All right. Okay. Very good. I want to, speaking about Jumping the Shark,
the Linux action show is about to jump the shark in a really big way. Oh, my God, I hope
you guys don't freak out. I'm going to tell you about what we have coming up. But first,
I want to tell you about our friends at Ting. Go to linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com. Ting
is on a mission to make mobile make sense. Why? Well, actually, because you're going
to love the way Ting rates work. Ting makes it simple.
Ting keeps rates simple. We don't make you pick a plan. Instead, you just use your phone
as you normally would. How much you use determines how much you pay each month. You can have
as many devices as you want on one account. That's good, because when you use more, you
pay less per minute, message or megabyte of data. Your usage plus six dollars per active
device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill. Simple. That's what we mean
when we say mobile. That makes sense. Now, if you go to linux.ting.com, you get a twenty
five dollar discount off your first Ting device or twenty five dollars off your service. If
you have a Ting compatible device, they have GSM and CDMA too. You probably have a compatible
device. This is a great way to try out Ting. They also have SIM cards available for just
nine dollars. If you want GSM or CDMA in a device, like a security device, like my buddy
Chase does, that's a great way to go. If you want, like Noah's got a bat phone. He picked
up a super tiny bat phone off of eBay that he gives the number to me. Hello, isn't that
neat? I got it. And his wife. Isn't that adorable? I think he probably gives it to a couple other
people too. But I know I'm on that list and I don't even know the number anymore. I just
have it written down somewhere. And it's great because he just pays for what he uses. We
have all kinds of devices. A couple, if you want some great budget devices, because Ting
has also an early termination relief program. So you can really start stacking up the savings
when you go to linux.ting.com and you take advantage of their ETF if you're on a duopoly
contract. And then you can go grab something like the Motorola E second gen. It's just
a real nice baseline Android phone. No contract. No early termination fee. And it's unlocked.
And you can go get it. You can go get an unlocked GSM phone from Ting right now. They have the
blue studio, which is a nice phone for $209. The one plus, you know about that. They got
the iPhones. They got all the Galaxy devices. They have some really good MiFi devices as
well. I really liked that one with the OLED screen. Motorola G though. And the Motorola
G is really nice. And so is the Moto X2. All of those are over on Ting. If you go to linux.ting.com,
they'll take $25 off. You can get an ETF. They'll help you get out of that contract
if you're in one. And then you're all done. You got an unlocked phone. You're no more
contracts. Ting is really nice. And if you got a few devices, you should really check
out the Ting savings calculator. It's kind of nuts. You put your current usage in there
and you'll be pretty surprised. Also, nice thing about Ting, no whole customer service.
You can call them at 1855-TING-FTW and a real human being answers the phone. Go to linux.ting.com.
And a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged L program. Yeah, you see
that? I'm multilingual now. Not offensive at all. Speaking of offensive, man am I fired
up. I am so effing angry right now. It really burns me more than you might actually think
and I'll tell you why. So you might have noticed this week that the Linux action show was pulled
down from YouTube. Episode 306, Windows 10 versus Linux. Boy, what a great title for
YouTube too. And not many people had had it by the time we posted it. I did a little search
before the show went out. So boy, that was going to be a good episode for YouTube. Windows
10 versus Linux. And it got pulled down by Conde Nast because we played a video from
Wired in the news segment of the show. Now the Linux action show is going in on its 10th
year now. It has done news every single week, well that we've been on the air, for 10 years.
And in this particular episode, we were covering a Linux powered rifle and we were covering
the fact that A, Wired was covering it and B, the fact that Wired was doing video and
C, the production of that video. So not only were we covering the news item itself, but
we were actually also covering the video as part of our coverage. That my friends, I consider
to be fair use under the US copyright law. But the way YouTube systems work, even though
it's content creators that make YouTube possible, that allow them to sell ads that made YouTube
actually exist, even though it was stupid cats playing keyboards and people getting
kicked in crotches, it was the content creators that made YouTube possible. And now it's the
content creators that are guilty first. And then we get to try to plead for innocence.
I filed a dispute Sunday evening. It is now Tuesday at 3 o'clock in the afternoon as I
record this. We have lost all potential to gain any revenue off this show. Of course
YouTube revenue sucks anyway, so it would have been $10 at best. But now, we're three
days into it after release, we won't make any revenue. Even though in my opinion, it
was absolutely legal for us to play that video. And the really burning thing about this is,
and this is the thing you don't even know, is for this particular episode of the Linux
Action Show, a real shit ton of effort went into making the video presentation possible.
In fact, I had to mow down three of my Linux laptops that ran Linux and had to install
Windows 10 on those things, trying to get them to hook up to our video presentation
system so I could actually demonstrate visually the things I was talking about in the video
version of the Linux Action Show. I destroyed three of my Linux laptops to get them hooked
up between Windows 10, the drivers, and our capture rig, so I could display Windows 10
in the video. And then a couple of hours after that video goes up on YouTube, Google has
it pulled down because, well, Conde Nast thinks they should. Even though the show has been
around for almost 10 years, we've been publishing on YouTube for a very long time. We have thousands
of videos up there. They don't care. They pull us down. After all that work, I spent
two days just to get the video setup working. I spent more time just to do the visual presentation
than I actually had to spend on the content of the show itself. Thankfully, Windows 10
kind of writes its own review. But still, the point remains, I spent more time to get
the visual aspect working than I did on the actual content just to get my video pulled
down. Now, thankfully, I don't rely on YouTube as a primary distribution platform, and I
never will because of crap like this. But, man, is it a kick in the nuts when we're already
dealing with some other problems. One you may have noticed, if you were somehow able
to say, oh, I don't know, download the video from our website or watch it in HTML5 from
our website, but you might have noticed how crappy Noah's video looks. In fact, it seems
like Okiwan, Linux fan, did. He says, I love the show, but Noah's camera is really distracting.
I know it's a Linux solution, but the quality of the show, which used to look so good, now
looks unprofessional. Sorry I have to say it, but it's a fact. I tried to get a friend
who was new to Linux to watch the show, and that was his first comment. When I see videos
like this on YouTube, I immediately switch to another video. The Linux action show is
well produced. Why drag the production quality back 10 years? I think the free software crusade
has drifted a little too far into the Stallman dimension. I'd like to hear what other viewers
have to think. One last thing. Why does Crystal look so good? If you're not going full Linux
solution and production, why go halfway the expense of the show? Just bring it up, because
I care. Well, obviously I have to look good so that way my hair looks good. I mean, hello.
That's obvious. This is something that Noah and I have struggled with a lot. We want the
Linux action show to be produced and edited and created and all that stuff as much as
possible under Linux as we can. But to do high-resolution video production sometimes
requires sort of using proprietary solutions, which we have been fighting with since Noah
became a co-host. And so you see the different versions of that in the video. Like sometimes
his video looks a little weird. Sometimes it looks like he's from 1980 and it needs
anti-aliasing applied. And sometimes it's fine. It's been all over the board and sometimes
he's in studio. But as Obi-Wan Linux fan here, or Oki-Wan, Oki and whatever, Oki and Wan,
whatever. Let's just call him Obi-Wan Linux fan. That's nice. As he points out, it does
look unprofessional. And that really does burn me. It really gets me upset, because
we work really hard on the show. And that's got us thinking. You know, the show is actually
coming up on its 10th year in June, in next June, June 10th. So we're coming up on it.
And 10 years is a long time for any person to do any one thing. And I don't really tend
to stick with anything, actually. It's kind of funny. Somehow I've managed to stick with
these shows. But for the most part, I got to be honest, I can't even stand to drive
the same route to work every day. I sometimes stay at the studio to avoid it. Sometimes
I drive a different route. Monotony drives me insane. So somehow I've managed to do the
Linux action show for almost 10 years now. I don't know how that's happened. And all
these shows, really. And so it's been, recently we've been discussing how to get the show
more genuine to the fact that we cover open source and Linux. And every time we go down
this route, we always run up against the wall of video production. It's always the main
issue is video production. It's always been the problem. It's why we use Wirecast now.
It's why we edit under Final Cut. It's just never up to snuff.
So that's really been something we've discussed a lot since before Noah was even a co-host.
And so we've decided this Friday to try something a little different. Now you saw the beginnings
of this last week, perhaps. You might have noticed that we did a remastered version of
episode 103 of Linux Unplugged. Multi-track recording, each person, each presenter, and
the Mumble Room gets their own track. And then our editor, HamRadio, goes through and
cleans up the individual spots. And then he turns it over and passes it on to our other
editor, Rekai. It's double the work, really. And it's a process we don't really have worked
out yet. But the sound is much better. It's much more presentable. It sounds much more
professional. And honestly, it's much more doable under Linux using open source technology.
Or hardware, even. And we have a limited budget as well. And the kind of money, you know,
like say you have $6,000 in a year to spend on hardware. Well, the kind of distance you
get out of audio hardware is just unbelievably more than you get out of video. I mean, one
camera can cost $6,000. So we've kicked this back and forth a little bit. And what we want
to try this Friday, live, is an audio version of the Linux Action Show. Now that doesn't
mean the video is going away. It's going to be more like Linux Unplugged for one episode,
maybe two. We're going to try it for a little while and see what we do. And what that means
is we're going to build it quality first. We're going to try to get it to sound as good
as possible. We're going to try to focus. When I put together a segment, I'm going to
focus on the information, not on the visual presentation of it. And we're going to try
to put it all together and then release it on the regular Sunday release date with basically
a version of how Linux Unplugged is done now with the screen showing some visuals. But
the primary focus will be on the content. Now, we're not going to switch the whole show
to this. We're trying this out as a concept because it's something that excites us. And
after you've been doing something for 10 years, it's nice to get pretty excited about it again,
to try to have a new idea to make it really, really good. And we even have an idea, and
it's something I will be willing to share as we go along, but we even have an idea to
make remote recording, local recording of guests very straightforward. The idea being
eventually, and we won't be able to nail it in the first or even second attempt, but the
attempt is to really have the best sounding show possible, really something that sounds
unbelievably amazing, local in studio if possible, as much as we can, and really because we have
so much we can apply to that. And it is going to only be an experiment, a temporary experiment.
We're going to try recording on a Friday to give us extra time for extra editing production.
Normally we record on a Sunday, and we have it out a few hours later. That's an amazing
turnaround time, I mean not to brag, but really for like an hour and a half HD video podcast
that also releases in several formats, including audio. To get that out in a few hours is pretty
good turnaround. Most podcasts don't even get that with audio only. So what we're going
to do is record on a Friday, A, to give us a little time to sort of experiment with things,
and B, to give our editors time to put it all together and still release a video version
so those of you who consume last in video will still have something to watch. And hopefully
it'll sound better, and you'll see while we'll hear, you'll hear why we are trying this.
And we'll take these lessons we learned from this and see how we can incorporate them into
the main show or what direction we want to go. It's a big change, and if it's something
we go with permanently, it's something we'll be very upfront about. But it's something
we're at least going to experiment with for a little while. And I'm a little unsure of
how people react to it, because I know for some people the video component is a big aspect
of the show. It's something that, you know, and it is nice to be able to showcase some
of this stuff, you know. When there's a new version of KDE or GNOME or Windows 10, it's
nice to be able to actually visually capture it. And I'm not saying that's going to go
away completely. I still want to have some elements of that. But what we would probably
do instead is what we would try to do is have individual video releases when necessary.
So if something is inherently video-centric, an interview on location at Red Hat, a demonstration
of an open source application or a desktop environment or Windows 10 or something great
that happens down at LinuxCon on August 17th, we can still individually publish those as
YouTube videos or as download videos like we did with OSCON. If you go back and look
at our OSCON 2015 coverage, we individually published every single video interview we
did. So that way the audio audience, which is the majority of the last audience, that's
somewhere between 60% and 70%. It depends on the episode. My best guess is a lot of
you just kind of move around. But the majority are audio. And we realized, well, if the majority
are audio and we're talking about the Prism laptop or we're talking about Firefox WebVR
or we're talking about keyboardio, you guys might want to be able to see that. So for
the audio listeners, in the show notes of OSCON 2015, we individually uploaded and
published the interviews. And this is an area I think we want to explore a lot more, is
if we have an audio version of last, we could individually publish the video elements still
for viewing. And on top of that, there's an element of this that I haven't told you about
yet. And I'm not going to tell you about it a lot yet because it's still in development,
but there is a plan somewhere in the September timeframe where I'm going to go on the road
and try to do some of these shows while traveling. And if we can nail this down during this time
period, this will make it much more possible for me to be able to do this from the road.
And so there is a bit of an ulterior motive. We're sort of experimenting with some ideas
that we might need to apply later on down the road. And that's something else that we're
going to be experimenting with. So that's why we might do one or two episodes of it
because there could be an element of that that we need to cover. So yeah. All right.
And then like Konseco points out in the chat room, this is a good time to try out a new
Ardora release. Yeah, exactly. And it's a big change, especially since we've been doing
video. We've been more and more video focused really since episode around, what, I don't
know, 100, 120-ish. We started transitioning to video. And then 100 episodes after that
was pretty serious. And I think a lot of people, I think we have a good balance in our audience
of cord cutters and people that watch video primarily and a lot of people who commute.
I mean, the download numbers suggest a lot of more people download over audio on a podcast
catcher. But the video is still a pretty significant portion. And we have Roku apps and TiVo apps
and all and XBMC apps. So we want to still continue to deliver video as well. And I'm
just going to try to experiment with striking a balance there and seeing what works. Because
I want, if nothing else, I want you to be able to listen to Linux Action Show and go
like, damn, you can make a show that sounds that good under Linux? I mean, things like
that. And I don't want you to watch and go, man, why does that video look like that? It's
distracting from the content. And it's not that I'm against using proprietary software
and proprietary hardware in the production of a show that talks about open source software.
It's just it chews at me every single week. And so for a little while, I want to try doing
it. And we won't make a complete transition because this is going to be a temporary thing.
But it's kind of putting a test balloon up and seeing how it goes. And we'll still continue
to do video production and continue to test all of that. Now, does anybody have any thoughts
or comments before we wrap up today? Because I know I just kind of dropped a big bomb there.
But anybody have any immediate reactions? Go ahead. The room's open. No? No? You sure?
Because all the software you want is free and available on the Linux platform. Well,
I'm a commuter, so I've never watched the video version. You're kidding me. You've never
watched the video version? Never. Yeah, I am slightly terrified by the fact that if
we make this transition and we discover that it's not a huge deal, that all of these years
focused on video have been wasted. I'm a little worried about that. Because there was a time
when it was a really big controversy that we launched video, where people have been
around for a long time. That really blew up on our face when we said we're switching to
video. People really were upset. And so now I'm kind of saying we're going to refocus
on audio. So this week's episode, our plan for Linux Unplugged is to, and of course I
probably should have said this earlier, but our plan is to delay the MP3 and AUG versions
of the show. We'll release the video versions as fast as we normally can. And we're going
to release the AUG and MP3 versions as the multi-track remastered. Sounds really good
because we figure those people are the people in the car, most likely. And those are the
people that need the remastered version the most. So if you're subscribed to the Linux
Unplugged MP3 feed or AUG feed this week, it might be a little delayed, but the result
is you'll get the higher, better produced version, I guess is a better way to put it,
the better produced version of the Unplugged program, which hopefully is better for headphone
users and commuters. And we also have a version, we have a version of it, episode 103, that
you can go find in the subreddit if you didn't get a chance to listen to that. And I'd like
to hear your feedback. We'll always, we have feedback threads over at LinuxActionShow.reddit.com.
I'd like to hear your thoughts on this. You kind of now know what's coming up. Not everybody
who watches last and listens to last listens to this show by a long shot. And so those
of you who do kind of have a little bit of the inside scoop of what's coming up. And
I just want you to know, I just, to recap, the core reasons behind it is we really want
to make something that is fun for us to make and gets us excited to produce. First of all,
I want to be excited to make it and creating something new is, it honestly gets me excited
in a way I haven't been excited in a long time. And just, you know, experimenting like
this. And it's a podcast. Like if you don't get to do this with a podcast, when can't
you, you know, it's not a radio show, it's not a television show. Like if you're ever
going to do something crazy, this is a place to do it. So that's, you know, keep that
in mind. And second thing is, is honestly what we really want to do is create something
that's really truly genuine to producing content under Linux. And we have ideas to make it
so if we really did this, we could have, it would require some internet connection, ISDN
connections or some hardware, something over IP. But really, you know, you flip a few hardware
buttons and we could really do this entire thing under Linux eventually. If we got there.
And that really excites me. And that's something else we're going towards. And then last but
not least, I really think we can, we can experiment in a new way with the medium. We can do something
we haven't been able to really do is create stories around open source and around projects
that are truly fascinating and genuinely interesting to listen to. And that's something else I've
wanted to do for a long time. And something we might experiment with. I mean, we might
not when the feedback might be so hostile and so negative that we chicken out. But currently,
that's where our momentum is at. And I hope you understand it. And I wanted to share it
with you guys. I know it's a little cray, but you stick in there and you can join us
live on Friday. We'll have it up on the Jupiter Broadcasting calendar, jupitabroadcasting.com
slash calendar. And see how it goes at jplive.tv. All right. Wow. Man, I feel good. I feel like
that was a little bit of a counseling session for me. Like I had a big secret that I needed
to share with you guys. And now I've gotten it off my chest. That's nice. Thank you for
listening. Thank you. Thank you. Now also, I'd like to get your contents, ideas, topics,
suggestions, feedback, linuxactionshow.reddit.com. I say this every week. I kind of feel like
a jerk, but really, we get no love for Linux Unplugged. Subreddit just gets no love. Go
over there and love on this show, won't you? Jeez. You know Wes? He didn't show up this
week because no love. I'm sorry, Wes. If you're listening, I'm sorry, buddy. They love you.
They just didn't say anything. It's sad. It's sad. No, really, it's fine. linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Go to jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact to send us feedback, jplive.tv to watch us
live. We do it live Tuesdays at Pacific. You can get it Pacific time. You can go to jupitabroadcasting.com
slash calendar. You get it in your time. Alright, everybody. Thanks so much for tuning this week's
episode of Linux Unplugged. See you right back here next week.
I love it. I don't know, Wimpy. You are like a master podcaster now. You are good at the
tease. So as we're signing off, Wimpy says, the next USC mailing list discussion could
be show content. Wimpy, what do you know? What do you know?
Ask Popey.
Popey left a while ago.
Has he left?
Come on. Come on. Just give me a little tease. Give me a little tease.
I don't know anything. I don't know anything. Just keep an eye on the Ubuntu Devil mailing list.
Okay. Okay. I see. I see how it is. Very good.
Or just subscribe to Softpedia because I'm sure they'll pick up on it.
Right. No kidding, right?
Hey-oh.
Hey-oh. So all right. JBtitles.com chatroom. Go pick our title. Now the show's over. Am I crazy,
you guys? What do you think of the test we're going to do for last?
I don't think you have to see it. You absorb the content. I mean, if you're going to do something,
like you said, with Linux Unplugged where it's video enhanced, I mean, that's perfectly – I mean,
that's better than most of the other podcasts I listen to.
Okay. Software Center Woz isn't bad by Creepy Uncle. Yeah. I mean, I suppose that's true.
Yeah. And, you know, some people think the green screen looks old, too, and I agree.
We didn't want to really use the green screen very long. In fact, for a little while,
we thought about just trying to use the studio shot. But, yeah. I don't know.
Software Center Woz, JBtitles.com.
Go ahead, Debbie.
I think it's better that you experiment and find something that works overall well for you,
well for the audience, and just doesn't put that stress on you because people can tell, I'm sure.
Yeah. I hate being stressed out. That's the other thing is I hate – what happens so often is I have to
troubleshoot something video production related for the first 10 or 15 minutes for a show.
So 10 or 15 minutes before the show starts, I'm not thinking about the show at all.
I'm thinking about this video issue, and it really gets me frustrated.
Alex, you wanted to mention something?
Yeah. One of the features of video I liked really much is that I got to see the chat logs.
And I would like if they would be saved and published in text form if you are going to give up video.
We've thought about it, but we'd probably be showing the chat room more in the video version if we did that.
But the only reason I don't do that is because all it really takes is for somebody to just log a chat client
into the chat room and set their buffer, and then you have that.
Yes, but if I'm not online at the time –
Yeah, that's true. There's probably a great system that does this.
If anybody out there knows or wants to set us up on it, let me know.
All right. So miles of Wi-Fi is not bad either. I kind of like that www.
JBtitles.com, JBtitles.com, everybody.
Speaking for myself, Chris, if you're going to get rid of the video feed as far as being able to see you and Noah,
I think it'd be nice to at least have the video feed of the chat room.
Yeah, okay. Yeah.
And if we did interviews and stuff in that episode, some of them would be audio only,
but if they're on location, they might still be video.
And like in Unplugged, I just played that video clip of Noah.
The only thing is I don't totally want to commit to that because I've –
at least just in my real initial sort of last run,
I've noticed I seem to get better, more genuine conversations with people when I do audio interviews
because they don't have a camera in their face.
And so I don't want to commit to doing a bunch of video interviews because if I can get a better interview
when I use a little portable Zoom recorder, that's what I'm going to do.
I mean, the interviews I got at OSCON with our audio, the people are much more relaxed,
the conversations are more jovial and joking and funner to listen to
because they're not all freaked out by a camera.
And I just can't ignore that.
And that was the other thing that sort of led me down this path was we went to OSCON
and the interviews we did on audio, man, we banged those things out so fast
and they went so smooth and so natural and I had such a good range to pick from
and I had so much room to clean up mistakes and cut out things that were just dumb or superfluous.
And I was able to get through all four, five, or six, or seven clips we played in like an hour.
It was just like for my availability, I was able to do more and the people sounded better
and I was able to put the Zoom recorder in my pocket when I was done.
It was really nice.
Yeah, I know, the hair, right, wimpy the hair. Yeah, that's true.
Well, see, the thing is...
I don't know what they're talking about.
The thing is wimpy, some people like the hair.
You know, they like to check in and check in on the hair.
But I can just every now and then I'll just flash the webcam and prove that yes, the hair is...
I'm not going off camera because the hair is looking bad.
The hair is actually looking better than ever. Look at that.
And it's great looking hair.
I think one day Kogi should sit down wimpy and film wimpy watching an entire episode of Last One.
Oh yeah, he's never watched it.
That'd be great.
I haven't got time for that.
I have about two and a half hours of commuting a day.
So I've got, as I'm driving in that time, so I've got lots of time for listening to podcasts.
I'm currently subscribed to about 18 or 19 Linux and Floss podcasts at the moment.
I think that's super common. I think that's the majority.
And you know what?
You know, even somebody who makes video content, I over time...
I was watching, you know, four or five video podcasts a week.
I've whittled it all down. It's all audio now.
Not intentionally. I just reflected on this a couple of days ago
and realized that all of the podcasts I listen to now, which...
Let's see how many... Let's see here.
Man, there are so many great podcast apps right now.
If you guys... Pocketcast is really good, by the way.
Yeah, I use that.
Yeah, Pocketcast.
Pocketcast is awesome.
Yeah, yeah.
So here's a couple I'm listening to right now.
99% Invisible, Daily Tech News Show, Mission Log, No Agenda, Radio Lab, Surreal,
This American Life, This Week in Trek, the Accidental Tech podcast.
Actually, I just actually recently unsubscribed from that.
Common Sense with Dan Carlin, Everything Sounds.
Oh, that's a good show.
The History of Rome.
All of these shows, Random Trek, all of these shows now are all audio.
Like, I've just accidentally, just over time, because I'm using...
These podcasts are like... These are my time.
Like, when I'm not hanging out with family or friends
and I'm driving or I'm working or I'm laying down, like,
podcasts are for me. They're my time.
And so I like them in audio.
And our downloads kind of seem to bear that out.
It's really tough to tell because what I've basically gathered
by looking at the stats over the years is
people might find us on YouTube, then they move to the site,
and they watch us, and then they decide, well, there's no reason to watch.
I could just listen.
And then every now and then, an interesting episode comes along
or they have the day off or it's something extra in their routine
or they decide they want to watch on the Roku today
instead of listen while they drive.
And that time, they decide to go video.
And so an audio listener maybe once a month goes to video
or once every couple of months goes video.
And so it's not just a clear break.
I can't just say, well, I'll only lose 10% of the audience
because that's not really true because the other percent
also watches video from time to time.
So it's not a clear-cut decision to make.
And the other thing is it's nice to be able to showcase this stuff
because if I show you what GNOME looks like today,
well, when you watch the show in five years,
it's pretty quaint to look at that.
Like if you go back and look at the old shows of LAS
and we're showing off old versions of SUSE's KDE desktop,
it's adorable.
It's adorable that it looks like that.
And because we had video, we are able to document that in a sense
and capture it.
And it's like a time capsule.
So I'm cognizant of the fact that LAS does provide that aspect
of Linux coverage, and it's kind of unique in that respect.
There's not pretty much any other Linux podcast that does that.
And so if we stop doing it, nobody's doing it.
So I don't intend to stop doing that altogether,
but I just, you know, to be honest with you,
to be completely frank, what happened was we got into video
because we could.
Because live streaming became possible,
webcams and cameras became cheap enough,
and it was approachable.
And so we did it.
And we didn't really ask ourselves, does it make a better show?
It just was, well, technology has enabled us to do the next thing,
and because we like to follow technology, we do it.
And we went into it, and we didn't really think about how it's actually
sort of it sticks you right in the middle of you can't really make
a fantastic audio show and you can't really make a fantastic video show.
Like you go back to Noah demonstrating Yubikey or something like that,
and he has to sit there and he has to dictate out the commands to type,
and the video audience just has to sit there and watch him
while he wastes time because we don't know if you're listening
to this tutorial or watching this tutorial.
And so when you put a tutorial together and you have to consider
the audio audience and the video audience, it's basically, it's a wash.
It's like trying to write for multi-platform.
It's like you kind of just get the worst.
And so we, I feel like, have done a very, not to pat ourselves on the back,
but I feel like we've done a very good job of trying to walk the line,
of making the show approachable to audio listeners and video listeners.
But if I'm being honest with you, I could do a hell of a better job
of making an audio show than I'm doing currently,
and if I know I'm shooting a video segment that I'm going to release independently
and embed in the show notes, I can do a hell of a better of a job
making a video-specific thing too.
And that's just the reality, is right now we kind of walk the middle line,
and because we do a fairly good job of it, I think personally,
people don't really give us a hard time, but I think if you really know content
and you really know how it works, you can see it.
What about doing both video and audio, but doing less, not on-camera video,
but doing the just like, like the tutorial stuff would be separated
and embedded in the show notes, but then it would be like other stuff
where the chat room and then like websites displaying,
and playing another person's video or something like that
would still be involved in the main thing.
Yeah, I think that's probably what we'll kind of get to.
I don't know, yeah.
I think it's kind of...
Yeah, essentially I'm thinking plus more.
Yeah, yeah, with more...
And I think the YouTube channel will have more individual releases,
which actually could be very good for people looking for content
because shorter content does better on YouTube.
So if we had a 10-minute video explaining how to set up YubaKey,
people are way more likely to watch that.
Like I'll give you an example.
We did a digital photo workflow on Linux like a month ago,
and a big part of that segment was how to back up your photos on Linux
to SpiderOak.
And then two weeks later we got a question in the subreddit,
can anybody recommend how I back up my digital photos?
Now the problem is if you're looking to solve that one particular issue,
how do I back up my photos on Linux,
you're not very inclined to watch a two-hour video
on digital Linux photo workflow.
And so that's what we run into is people don't even know
that we've answered their question
because they're not willing to watch an hour, 32-hour video.
So if we could take those individual pieces
and still include them in the show but also release them as separate videos,
we might find that the need for a show like How To Linux pretty much goes away
and that solves that specific need and issue
of people trying to solve these problems on Linux.
It burns me that even in our own community,
people are constantly asking about apps that we have recommended and suggested,
how-tos we have done and solved and shown,
and it's not their fault, it's because discovery in a podcast is basically nonexistent.
And if you don't listen to the whole thing every single week,
you don't get all the information.
And so my idea is we really focus in on content,
we focus on making a great audio show that sounds amazing,
that's great to listen to,
that you are proud to have somebody who's checking out Linux listen to,
and when it calls for it, and not every episode,
but when it calls for it, there is separate releases of video
that either showcase something or walk something through,
and then we would also just play those as clips in the show as a video in the show itself,
so you don't have to go out and watch them separately if you don't want to,
but they are available if you are just out there searching for them.
We are considering transcribing the audio too,
where we have been doing that for Women's Tech Radio
and it's something we are considering doing for Linux Action Show as well.
Transcribing is good for SEO too,
but the part where it may not have video and it may have video,
wouldn't that pretty much guarantee that people are,
unless you specifically say in the show that there is a video component in this particular episode,
no one is going to know about it, no one is going to click it.
Yeah, and that's no big deal.
I don't think it's no big deal.
I think that's going to pull a lot of people out of it,
because if there are people who just watch video,
because they want to see the demos and stuff like that,
but then there may or may not be there, then they might not even care.
So it's two different audiences.
So here is how that works from a practical standpoint.
In the show we cover it and we say if you would like to see the visual version,
it's embedded in the show notes.
And that's all you have to say in the show, that solves that problem.
Now for people that are just watching the video version,
they just want the small episodes, the snippets.
Now when we post the video separate,
it starts with a splash that says this is a segment from the Linux Action Show,
like a two-second long splash, boom, goes into the segment,
then it wraps with a wrap screen that says,
you can listen and find the entire episode over at bit.ly slash last 357 or whatever.
And then they have more information if they want to watch the entire episode.
But the reality is somebody who wants to watch a four-minute how-to
is not at all the same person who wants to listen to an hour,
hour and a half, two-hour podcast.
Certainly.
I actually found last for looking for an how-to,
and it just happened to be in the video, the title of the episode.
Yeah, right now we basically, we rely on titling.
That's the truth.
If it wasn't in the title, I probably wouldn't have found it.
Yeah, that's why we go through the trouble of being anal about the titles.
You either have to know it in the title
or know exactly what to search for in the show notes sometimes
because I've run into that a few times.
Yeah, and so by breaking these things out,
we kind of want to try to solve that problem a bit.
And then we're hoping that when people see those,
they're like, oh, there is a podcast behind this.
And then you listen to it and you're like, oh, this is the real show.
And the idea is you kind of do give away a little bit of the farm,
but the truth is we put the content out there for free anyways.
So it's not really like it's that big of a deal.
And people can already time code link on YouTube, and people do.
Whenever we do get posted to Reddit, which very rarely happens
because people don't want to watch a two-hour video on Reddit either,
but when we do, people usually link to the time code,
which I'm actually totally fine with.
I have no problem with that. I think it's a nice feature.
Anyways, so yeah, many people do think the show notes are the video description.
That's true.
All right, so there you go.
And so tune in Friday. Let us know what you think, you guys.
And hopefully all goes well.
And it turns out to be, you know, it's not going to be perfect on our first attempt,
but hopefully you'll at least get the essence of what we're trying to accomplish.