I think Star Trek has some of the best sound effects in the sci-fi biz, one of the things
that's kept them around.
And so I was pretty excited when I saw on the subreddit that KabiLinux, K-A-B-I Linux,
he wrote this post saying, hoping some here will like this, but if you have the package
SOX installed, that's S-O-X, you can run the code below in the terminal and it will pump
out what sounds like the hum of the Enterprise without the wobble, unfortunately.
But you also don't need the warp core.
So first you have to have the SOX package installed on your machine, and then you run
this play command here, and once you hit play, it creates the engine sound effect of the
Enterprise D, which is a pretty cool white noise effect.
And then if you're like a professional internet broadcaster, you'll have other sounds ready
to go, like Star Trek bridge sounds, and then it really sounds like you're in Star Trek
now, which is pretty cool, just using SOX.
I got a kick out of that.
So you don't have to have, although, I mean, I added the sound effects from the bridge,
but there you go.
So maybe instead of doing Linux unplugged this time, today we'll do Star Trek unplugged.
You think that'd be a hit?
I think we tried that once, I don't think it worked very well.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that spent more time on a spreadsheet
this week than the last 10 years.
My name is Chris, and we have a heck of an episode for you.
This is episode 94 of the Linux Unplugged show, and joining us in just a little bit
will be Michael Arabell from Ferronix to discuss a new initiative he's working on, Linux benchmarking
automated style.
You know, wouldn't it be interesting to track the progress of some of the most important
projects like, oh, I don't know, the Linux kernel, GCC, LLVM?
When they release new builds, how does that impact their performance?
Well, over at linuxbenchmarking.com, Michael has set out just to find that out, automated
builds after new releases with charts.
Go in there and say, how's the Linux kernel been trending the last six months?
And this site might just show you.
What's this initiative all about, and what is his goal?
We'll talk to him today.
Also, we'll give him a little congrats on the 11th year of Ferronix.com, so that'll
be coming up.
And then later in the show, we're gonna talk about Fedora 22, a new release that just hit
the web today.
I installed it.
We've got some initial reactions.
We're gonna give you a full review on Sunday's Linux action show, but today, I ran into a
snag or two that you might run into if you have a certain make Nvidia card that'll prevent
GDM from starting.
I'll tell you how to fix that in today's episode and give you my first reactions, get some
mumble room takes.
But before we get to any of that, we do have some serious business to get to, some unfortunate
sad news.
Every now and then, a great distribution comes and goes.
The company and people behind them come and go.
And this week, it appears to be official, Mandriva, the company behind the Linux distribution
so many of us, so, so many of us started out with, is officially going away.
Yes, apparently, according to a post over in Germany, or maybe it was France, there's
a translation.
Thankfully, Ferronix has one for us.
Even though the company made $553,000 last year, not enough for 10 to 19 employees, Mandriva
as a company is now being liquidated.
And to help reflect on this once great distribution, I'll bring in our mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings, mumble room.
Hello.
So any Mandriva users, say I. Any Mandriva users in here or Mandrake users back in the
day?
I.
Me.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's kind of sad.
That's what got me started.
Yeah, it really was.
I mean, I probably started with dubbing a Red Hat technically, but when it came time
for Linux for me that I wanted to cut my teeth on and use for on my systems, I used Mandrake.
And I even became a Mandrake club member.
I was in the Mandrake club, so I got the special URPMI repos.
I felt pretty cool.
And I don't know what this means for the offshoots, like Mandriva and others.
Magia.
Moondrake?
Was that the other one, Rotten Corpse?
Yeah, there's Moondrake.
Well, I think that was a spinoff of the original Mandrake.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, yeah.
I don't know what it means for those guys, and Open Mandriva, of course, like that.
That doesn't seem to have been like a lot of interest taking up in those, though.
Mandrake 8.
Yep, Mandrake 8.
Whiskey.
I had that in the box.
That was great.
Mandrake 8 in the box was great.
You know, one of the great things about Mandrake back in the day was that it had the Drac config.
Let's see if I can find a picture of this Mandrake Drac config.
You guys know what I'm talking about?
I mean, Open, or Drac Conf.
That's what it was.
Drac Conf.
OpenSUSE, of course, had Yast, which was, you know, pretty great.
But I felt like, in some ways, Linux Mandrake's Drac Conf had the leg up when it came to like
the Samba automation and user creation and just managing services.
It just felt like a quicker, faster tool.
Boy, looking back at it now, it really looks antiquated.
But this was sort of like, this was sort of your only front-end option, really, when configuring
X really meant getting into your Xorg comp file.
And if you just, you know, didn't want to hassle with that stuff, this was so perfect.
And it did get more refined over the years.
And it got forked.
It's still out there in different iterations.
But there was a time where I was able to, you know, fully set up Active Directory authentication,
automated NTP setup.
All these things that you just had to do by hand back then in Linux, Wi-Fi, like when
Wi-Fi was brand new, like Mandrake made it easiest to get it working back then.
It was a really great distro.
And the other thing they did, and they gave you really, you know, straightforward front-end
options for starting and stopping services.
The other thing they did early on is they provided a really solid solution to how crappy
RPMs were.
You know, they had URPMI, which really was, in some ways, maybe better than YUM, maybe
not, I don't know anymore, DNF, like who could say.
But it was definitely way better than any other RPM-based distro out there.
This was really, in my opinion, the usable RPM-based distro at the time because of URPMI.
And then they had like, you know, one of the first software source managers where you could
manage between online sources, update sources, and CDs.
And again, SUSE got all that and yassed pretty quickly.
But that's what made Mandrake work so well, I think, for people.
And man, they had the best installer.
Mandrake had a really unique installer where the progress was all down on the left-hand
side of the installer.
Yeah, here it is.
Here it is.
Yeah, I don't know if you guys remember this.
They also had the best partitioner back in the day, too.
They really had a great partitioner.
And so you always knew right where you're at in the installation process, and you could
jump back and forth.
And they kept that look for years.
They refined it over time and made it look a little better.
But they kept that basic functionality.
So I'm showing you right here, I'm showing you like, this is like a super old version
of Mandrake.
And then here's Mandrake 9.1.
And then here is Mandrake 2005.
And they kept that, and here's 9.1 again, they kept that list along the side.
It was so cool.
I think they had, and they had a great text installer, too, if you had to go that route.
Oh, man.
Oh, wow.
Oh, this screenshot, Mandrake Linux 8, here it is.
This was my bag back in the day.
Oh, wow.
This is so old looking now.
I can't really get any better on it.
And they were one of the first to make it easy to use riserfs, too.
Like they made it super easy to use journaled file systems when journaled file systems were
brand new to Linux.
And they had security things you could do in the installation that would sort of tell
you how secure it was going to be and give you sort of like a report.
You could make a boot disk during the installation.
So in case you ever screwed up your bootloader installation during the installer process,
it'll ask you if you wanted to make, of course, it'd be up to a floppy disk, because back
then everybody had floppy disks.
But it would make you an emergency bootloader floppy disk that you could always get back
into your Linux installation with if you somehow hosed your bootloader.
How come we don't do that now?
Why did we stop doing that?
And then of course, because X was a total monster back then, the last thing you did
in the installation, because it was actually, technically it was fine if at this point the
installation totally locked up, because everything was pretty much done.
I don't know if it was unmounted the file systems, but beyond that, pretty much everything
was done.
So the last thing it would do is launch their super cool X configuration thing where you'd
go into this X configurator and it had arrows along the edges of the screen so you could
see if you had overscan on your CRT monitor, and you could tweak it back in and position
it just right, and then save that, and it would write your Xorg config for you.
It wasn't even Xorg back then, it was just X11.
It would write your X11 config, and they'd put it intentionally, if you're watching the
video version, you can see it's the last step right there.
They did it intentionally because that was always the thing that crashed.
Because you had to tell it what your video card was.
You had to tell it everything about your, you had to tell it what your monitor's capable
of doing.
It couldn't detect any of that.
And a lot of times the CRT monitors were very particular, oh and so were the early LCD monitors,
and they had, again, one of the best setups to do that, that final X11 step.
It almost makes me want to go find an ISO and do it one more time, except for old Linux
is actually never quite as great as you remember.
In Mumble Room, you guys have any passing Mandriva or Mandrake thoughts you want to
share before we move on?
I think it was time.
They didn't have anything in their final few years that made them stand out, and the community
fell away, went to their fault products.
They didn't need to keep going on because they had nothing left.
And they were of a product of a different time, where you had these problems, like you
had to have the Xconfig, you had to have XF86config was the command, thank you Minimic.
You had to have things like that.
You also, at the end of the installation, towards the end of the installation, had to
figure out how was the user going to get online?
Because it was an assume they didn't even have an ethernet port.
They might have had USB, but they probably had an ISP that required something like PPOE
or PPTP, and so they had to build these things in.
They had to accommodate for these.
And then later on, when the new generation distributions came around, they didn't have
to really account for kinds of these things.
Now, Kernelix, I wanted to give you a chance.
Were you a Mandrake user back in the day?
So Mandrake Linux was actually the first Linux I ever used.
I'd been asking around if anyone knew of this Linux or where I could obtain it, and finally
I found a guy that said, oh, here, I got a copy for you.
So he gave it to me on a CD, and I remember sticking it in my computer, and I was all
excited because I was going to try this Linux thing that was going to be more stable and
more secure and was going to do everything for me.
I stick the CD in there and I boot off of it, and I remember an X showed up.
The cursor was an X back then, and I was so excited because I was like, I remember thinking
to myself, wow, what an awesome cursor replacement, an X rather than an arrow.
That makes so much sense.
I got it and it really didn't make any sense.
I was just happy that it was not Microsoft, and I booted into Linux, and I was so excited.
I was like, oh, look, it comes with games, and it comes with a word processor, and wait,
network doesn't work, and sound doesn't work, and my display is limited to 800 by 600, and
here's a couple other things that don't work.
So all right, no problem.
Played with it for a couple days and decided I'm going to go back to Windows.
I stick my, at the time I think it was Windows ME or Windows 2000, I stick the disk back
in there, and it didn't recognize the partition that Mandrake had used, and so it just didn't
see my hard drive, and I just didn't have a computer with internet for like three months.
And after that experience, and when I finally did get it fixed, I swore I would never touch
Linux again because it was such a horrible experience.
Well, good thing that didn't stick.
Yeah, well, there you go.
I remember I also, I was such a Mandrake fan, I tried out their Mandrake Enterprise servers
they rolled out.
The first squid proxy server I ever deployed ran on Mandrake using Mandrake in a server
edition.
Like I said, I became a Mandrake club member, whatever they called it back then.
I was all in.
I was all, I bought every box set that they sold.
It was pretty cool.
So hopes and our best to the Mandrake folks and the Mandrave company, and to the offshoots
that continue on in sort of their legacy.
So that is being very nostalgic.
Now let's go to the total opposite end of the spectrum, and this is so cool, and it
really does make it feel like 2015.
Then you're going to be able to share your smartphone GPS location information with the
location services built into the GNOME desktop to make that more accurate.
And you might be wondering why, but it actually is sort of useful.
The GNOME desktop derives a lot of information when you allow it based on your IP location
primarily, unless you actually have a computer with a GPS chip in it that talks to the Linux
system.
And what it does, the things I'm aware of, and I'm sure there's many more, is it sets
things like automatically your time zone, best NTP server, calendar settings, a lot
of little things like this.
And the more accurate you get that, the better GNOME is, especially if you're in a laptop
and you're traveling.
Like, say, take Noah, for example.
When he's in Grand Forks right now, and then he comes over here to the JB1 studio, if GNOME
is aware of his location, it'll automatically adjust his clock and his calendar appointment
reminders for him to be in this time zone.
And so as part of the Google Summer of Code project, there is a developer who is aiming
to set up an app that'll share location information when you have this other companion app on
the Android device called GeoClue.
And this is pretty cool.
A GPS position is something that most of us are obviously pretty familiar with, but you
might not always understand why.
So this would kind of be a way you could play with it on your Linux desktop without having
to have a GPS chip in your computer to see if there's any value in it.
I think that's kind of neat.
And they're adding more and more things in GNOME, like maps and things like that, that
could use this.
Plus, you got to assume other projects could take advantage of this.
So each time the Android location listener application in the background gets a new location,
which Android is doing this all the time for Google Now or for your weather checking application
or, you know, the way it works on Android is for the most part, not always, but for
the most part, if an application needs location, it just asks the location service instead
of having to hit the GPS itself.
Because if another application just checked 55 milliseconds ago, five minutes ago, why
hit the GPS antenna again when you can just check that database?
So that's essentially what the service does.
So anytime that database is updated, this app also gets notified, this GeoClue.
Using MDNS on your Wi-Fi network, it'll auto discover the companion app running on your
GNOME desktop, and anytime that location database gets updated on Android, a copy of that notification
will be sent over the network, over Wi-Fi, to the companion app on your GNOME desktop.
So any app that checks the location on your Android device will then also update the location
information for GNOME.
So you kind of get the benefit of getting constant location information without having
to hit your battery really hard because it's just hitting it when the other apps are already
hitting it.
And of course, you could just turn off the bridging app if you didn't want to use that
or not use it.
I think it's an interesting start, and it's an interesting use of Google Summer of Code,
and it could make the location-based stuff that we're seeing the GNOME project work on
more relevant without having to have expensive hardware in your laptop or desktop because
I'm never going to put a GPS.
I might maybe one day have like an LTE card in a laptop that has GPS built in.
That'd be pretty cool, but I'm never going to have that in my arch desktop upstairs in
my office.
So now I can take advantage of some of those same location things using that without a
big battery drain.
I think it's pretty cool.
And you can also power other machines.
It's not just a, this is the other thing I thought was interesting, is you could have
like five of your desktops to this one Android device.
So five of your GNOME desktops, for example, could all be getting location if they're all
like all in the same spot.
See, it's not a one-to-one ratio.
So one phone can update the location for multiple desktops as well, which is kind of a neat
feature, I think.
I'll tell you about another neat feature.
That'd be our next sponsor right here on the Linux Unplugged program, and that is our friends
over at Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com to get a limited time $50 discount off your first Ting device or
if you have a Ting-compatible device, they'll give you a $50 service credit.
Now, when I signed up, I got a $25 service credit, and that paid for more than my first
month.
So I can only imagine what $50 is going to do for you guys, or really, just go get a
brand new device.
Ting has a great range of devices, from starting literally like around $50 for a feature phone
all the way up to the best Android phones and iPhones out in the market today.
And they just recently added the OnePlus, which you can get right from Ting, which is
really great.
So go to linux.ting.com to take advantage of that $50 discount.
Now why Ting's service?
Why switch to Ting?
First of all, I think you're going to like the fact that you only pay for what you use.
Finally, right?
That's how it should always be.
And sometimes outside the US, that is how it is, but not here in the US.
We have a duopoly in place.
This duopoly controls the market with a strong arm that you wouldn't believe.
And so there's very little flexibility in here.
So Ting had to come up with a whole new way to do this.
So you only pay for what you use.
It's just flat $6 for the line.
And then your usage on top of that, you just take your minutes, your message, your megabytes,
whatever bucket you fall into, that's all you have to pay.
That's really super nice.
Because then if you want to have multiple devices for testing applications, or maybe
you have a small business, or maybe like in my case, I have a nanny that is, I can't really
afford to pay for her phone all the time.
But if I only pay for it when she needs it, because some sort of emergency, that is absolutely
worth it for me.
And that's why I love the Ting services based around me and my usage, not my individual
devices, which I think is a superior model to begin with, and they have no whole customer
service.
So if I give the phone to somebody and they have problems, they call Ting at 1-855-TING-FTW,
and a real human being will answer the phone, so I don't have to get stuck doing the troubleshooting.
I really like that.
I just don't want to get tied down helping people with all of the little technical issues.
So the fact that I can hand that off to Ting, they also have a really good help site.
So like in case of Rekai, he doesn't ever have to call in, he'll just go to the Ting
help service, and he can just take care of all his problems that way.
So there's a great range depending on your ability, so it makes it great for a small
business or a family.
I love that.
So go to linux.ting.com, start there to get our special discount.
That'll give you a $50 discount off all of their great devices, and then you can check
out the fact that they have an early termination relief program, so if you're stuck in a stupid
contract right now, they're going to help you get out of that with their ETF program.
Check that out.
And of course, your phone's going to be unlocked, so you're going to get long-term value out
of it.
So here's what you do.
You go to linux.ting.com, check them out.
Also check out their blog.
Like, they just recently posted this video, now this video isn't narrated, but I think
I'm going to do the narration for them right now.
They can just do this for free.
Ting, I'm doing this for you.
So this is a Ting tip, and I'm putting this out here because it's probably good for you
guys to automatically download podcasts over Wi-Fi.
If you're using Pocket Cast, you open up the Pocket Cast app, and then once it's in there,
open up the settings menu, where you go to that little hamburger menu, it slides out,
and then go down into the settings cog at the bottom of that, and then select episode
updates in the app, but it's the second option.
And then in there, there's the option check enabled under auto download, say enabled,
automatically download, and then make sure only on Wi-Fi, so that way, when new episodes
come out, it'll automatically download the new episode, but it won't do it when you're
on cellular.
It's kind of the best of both worlds, so when the new Linux unplugged, hey look, there's
Linux Action Show right there.
When the new Linux Action Show comes out in HD, you don't have to feel guilty about doing
the high download, but you also get it automatically.
That's how I do my Pocket Cast, is I have it set to auto download every show that comes
out, I keep the last two to three episodes, depending on the podcast, and I have it set
to only download when I'm on Wi-Fi.
And so when I'm on the road, I get an idea of what I have coming up, and I could opt
to download over cellular if it's really important to me, and I do sometimes do that, but really
what I do is as soon as I get on my Wi-Fi connection, Pocket Cast just starts pulling
all of them down for me, and the next time I'm on the road, they're ready to go, and
I did not use any wireless data, and so I'm not paying for any wireless data.
And that's just a great way you can, if you're just a little bit technical savvy, just have
a little savviness, you really don't have to have much, you can really leverage the
way the Ting model works and save a ton of money.
So go to linux.ting.com, use that savings calculator, see how much money you'd freaking
save.
I've saved over $2,000.
You can hit the savings calculator and find out how much you would save.
Linux.ting.com, and a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Okay, I have to mention something.
Next week, the Linux Unplugged show is going to be live at 11 a.m. Pacific time, and I
know, you don't know what time that is in your time.
Go to jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
You hear that, Popey?
I'm talking to you!
You go to jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get it converted to your local time, but
yeah, I have some, or I lied, we're doing it at 10 a.m., see, it's a good thing I'm
checking the calendar.
This is why you gotta go to the calendar.
We're doing Linux Unplugged at 10 a.m., so right after Tech Talk next week, it's gonna
go Tech Talk, and then Linux Unplugged on Tuesday next week.
So just a little heads up, we're moving the recording schedule for Linux Unplugged, and
I'm making a big stink about it because the Mumble Room's super important to the show,
and I'd really like to have some people there.
I love you guys.
I love you so much.
So important to me.
So join me at 10 a.m. Pacific for Linux Unplugged next Tuesday.
Just moving it that week because I have some family that's coming to town that I have to
go pick up at the train station, and they're, see, this is what happens when family schedules
stuff.
They literally arrive at 2 p.m. when we would normally be going live.
Like, could they have picked a more perfect time?
I don't think so.
So we're doing 10 a.m. next Tuesday at jblive.tv.
Give us the Eastern time?
Dude, I gave you a website that automatically converts the time zones for you so I can accommodate
everybody.
How much more can I give?
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
Go take advantage of our robots.
After all, I pay them in Bitcoin.
You might as well use them for something.
Okay, well, I'm really excited to welcome back Michael Larabelle from phronix.com.
Michael actually joined us back in 2012, shortly after he'd gotten back from his visit with
Valve and we'd had all the big Steam news for Linux.
And this week, I invited Michael back on the show because he's launched an initiative that
I think is pretty interesting.
And I want to see if I'm grokking this right, Michael, so I'm going to run it past you.
Tell me if I've captured this right.
But it looks like you're kind of taking all of the work you've done with the Phronix Benchmarking
Suite, all of your experience you have with benchmarking for Phronix website and the Open
Benchmark project, and you are launching an automated testing site that essentially will
be monitoring some of the most popular open source projects and trending their performance
impact over time.
Am I kind of grokking this?
Hi, Chris.
Yes, you're mostly correct.
It's basically to monitor the performance over time of important projects like the Linux
kernel, the GCC compiler, LLVM and Clang, and then I've also been working on some other
trackers for all the latest R-Clinix packages in real time and everything else like that.
And you're doing these testing and the results on a daily basis, correct?
Correct.
The majority of the trackers right now are running on a daily time basis, but there's
also the ability within the Phronix test suite to do per-commit testing, so basically whenever
there's a new get revision that the triggers would automatically fire off the new round
of testing.
But for my testing over the past several months, I've just found the daily testing to be best
off rather than having so many triggers per day of kernel benchmarking when each kernel
benchmark will end up taking several hours per system, etc.
So first of all, I got to say, if I'm following you correctly, this sounds like a massive
sacrifice of your man cave.
I just finished remodeling the basement and I basically devoted it entirely to this linuxbenchmarking.com
testing.
I'm seeing that.
It looks like it was at one point going to be a very nice theater with a bar and a projector
and a bench seat, and it looks like it's now dedicated to a server farm for doing benchmarks.
Beforehand, there are some pictures on one of the older Phronix articles that's linked
from linuxbenchmarking.com, but it was just like a complete wreck in the basement.
I actually just added the bar just because of whenever there's Phronix test suite customers
over here and then the projector is just nice for seeing the real time status of all the
systems running.
Oh, I love it.
So the bar is for the benchmarking.
Oh, that is so cool.
That is way cooler.
I thought it was like some sort of sad sacrifice and instead it is actually way more badass
than that.
You have a bar in your benchmarking suite.
That is really cool.
So you say when customers come over, what kind of customers come over for the Phronix
benchmarking suite?
Is it like hardware manufacturers?
Can you give me a picture of what that's like because that's an area of your business that
I don't have any insights on at all.
Yeah, it's basically for any enterprise customers for the Phronix test suite that either want
customizations done for the PTS or openbenchmarking.org to better suit their roles and whatnot.
One customer that's able to be talked about publicly is actually GE that sponsored much
of this recent work which in turn led to the linuxbenchmarking.com is where they were rolling
out thousands of servers where they run benchmarks every day entirely powered by the Phronix
test suite and Floramatic.
So I'm sure for them and also really for the community in general, JB Hawke of Truth in
our chat room asked a great question and this is something that whenever you talk about
benchmarks, people always will try to poke holes in how the benchmark is constructed
or how it's ran.
So JB Hawke of Truth in our chat room says, could you give us an idea of who maintains
the test cases used to measure the target application?
Is that something you maintain?
Or is that like an open source project sort of like where different people are contributing
to that?
Do people add their own metrics from different projects?
How is that driven?
It's all powered by the Phronix test suite which in turn pulls it from our openbenchmarking.org
website that basically acts as a repository for all the test cases.
All those test cases are basically comprised of work that's done either by me or many other
contributors.
There's everything from like code weavers, they've submitted like wine test profiles
for measuring that.
And yeah, it's basically an open project and not anyone's able to recommend any new test
cases or adapt their test cases and upload them where the test profiles for the Phronix
test suite are just basically a few bash scripts and XML files.
Right.
I see.
Yeah.
And we've also uploaded like popular audio encoding tests to the open benchmarking site.
And so if I, for example, in Jupyter Broadcasting, if we developed a benchmark maybe for like
FFmpeg encoding setups, we could essentially upload like an FFmpeg benchmarking script
test suite and then if the community liked it and it got popular, then it would sort
of become a well-known.
Is that how it works?
Yes, indeed.
That's correct.
And though actually there is already FFmpeg benchmarking there, yeah, basically anyone
can submit new test profiles and from there it rolls out to anyone that's doing a public
or private deployment of the Phronix test suite, including linuxbenchmarking.com, which
is different than all the other tests, well, to back up a few steps, like Red Hat, Canonical
and others also maintain their own benchmarks against the latest Linux kernel and whatnot.
But yeah, their test cases are often limited without any intervention and they're also
often focused just around their use cases of like Apache web server performance or other
scientific areas rather than say running Linux gaming benchmark since the Linux gaming benchmarks
or Linux gaming customers aren't what leads to lots of their revenue.
Is that a fan behind you, I hear?
I guess actually just one of those servers that was just rebooting because it's now getting
ready for its new round of testing.
Yeah, that is exactly what I thought it was.
Man, those things are just banshees when you reboot them.
So when I look at this, I think daily GCC benchmarks, daily Linux kernel benchmarks,
what's driving you to do this?
What's the core reason?
What is the core benefit of making this information public and putting it out there like this?
Why not keep it some secret sauce you can use for special Phronix reports and things
like that?
It's mostly just being dissatisfied over all these years with how many regressions
still enter mainly the Linux kernel, but yeah, there's also regressions in many other projects
out there that there just isn't too much action being done about any upstream latest git trying
to be universal benchmarking because besides Red Hat not caring about gaming benchmarks,
they and other distribution vendors often just care about testing the kernels they're
going to ship in their next product as opposed to the very latest git code.
Right.
And so I feel like you touched on something that I have noticed is an undercurrent, an
undertone in your writing.
You I get the sense really hate regressions and you I think in some ways are driven to
find when regressions happen and point that out based on data to the best of your ability.
Do you feel finding regressions and helping people fix them, identify them, is that part
of what drives you to do all this benchmarking and do all of this?
Are you a regression hater?
I mostly just hate regressions, yes, but I'm just really interested in Linux hardware and
trying to ensure everything achieves their peak performance possible in your Linux.
This is the disconnect that I don't get.
So how does it not seems like then you would be in a position where you would be constantly
tormented because you're going to see regressions everywhere because that happens in software
development and they're right there out there for everybody to see an open source, but also
you've run the numbers.
A lot of times you can run the same benchmark for say an open GL application or a game and
get a much better result using a proprietary driver on Windows than you might get with
a proprietary driver on Linux.
So how does somebody who's constantly checking for the best performance and who has a little
bit of regression hate, how do you not just get frustrated with Linux?
Here you are almost 11 years into Ferronix, I would think by now you would have pulled
your hair out.
I've pulled plenty of hair out, but overall Linux performance is still pretty much on
par with Windows.
There's certainly some cases where it's not, but it's improving a lot and it is frustrating
though when you see such performance drives being made and then all of a sudden on the
next kernel release you see your battery power usage just go horribly and no one notices
it until after the kernel ships.
Yeah, I've always wondered when I'm reading that.
And so I think now with these benchmarks, I look at this and I think, I wonder if maybe
it's time to sort of try to incorporate these kinds of benchmarks into reviews even.
Do you see the possibility there for, where do you really see this going?
Do you see it more for hardware makers and big projects or do you see it more as more
used by the community?
Where do you see it going?
Is it more of a community effort or more of an enterprise effort?
In terms of linuxbenchmarking.com, it's a community effort, but with the Ferronix SysWee
Informatic, anyone is able to test out their own software on their own hardware and everything
along those lines.
And there's plenty of behind the firewall for automatic deployments for running all
these benchmarks that various companies use, but yes, for linuxbenchmarking.com it's mostly
just a community effort because I have to test out my latest code anyways that I'm shipping
to customers.
So I'm basically making all that data public and trying to be as most real world and applicable
to the community as possible and all this data that I have to produce anyways.
Well Michael, before we wrap up, I'm just curious, obviously you follow the Linux news
pretty closely, like big picture wise, what's going on out there in the last six months
or so or whatever that you find to be particularly interesting?
That's a very good question.
There's many things that's interesting to me right now.
LLVM and Clang continue to be quite interesting, particularly for how they're being adapted
by so many different projects and now with Vulkan as basically the next generation OpenGL,
but there's going to be the Sphere V2 LLVM converters, all these other LLVM based products
will now be able to easily interact with the GPU.
That's one interesting area that always excites me over the past few years.
Bluetooth Snappy tends to be a little bit interesting, I still have to read up a lot
more on it, but they have a lot of nice plans.
I've noticed too, you seem like a close follower of the Fedora project as well, what do you
think about where Fedora is going?
We're going to talk about Fedora 22 today.
I'm quite happy with Fedora 22 and Fedora 21 for that matter.
I've had Fedora 22 on a couple dozen systems now and it's running fairly nicely.
I've had that Nuovo regression that's a bit annoying, and the other day I had an issue
with the WiFi where I'm getting really awkward internet connection speeds out of it, but
aside from that Fedora 22 has been performing very nicely and it's quite stable.
I've tested it both under X11 and Wayland, and the Wayland experience has been pretty
much on par now with X11.
That's going to be a big story, and I could see a specific angle there for your site too.
As Wayland rolls out and more distributions start shipping it, there's going to be lots
of performance regressions, there's going to be lots of new territory there.
That's got to be a story you follow with some interest.
Yes, certainly, overall the performance under Wayland or X-Wayland for that matter is pretty
nice with X-Wayland right now on the gnome shell there's some issues just around full
screen apps not being redirected properly, so there's a performance penalty, but at least
according to the developers that should be fixed in due time, so there isn't anything
too major.
It's not like you're suddenly having the performance in half, it's just that it's down 10% or so.
I love that's where we're at.
That's great.
That's better than you might expect, I suppose.
Heaven's Revenge wanted to ask you a question, Michael, go ahead Heaven's, ask away.
Well with the new release of Clang 3.6 and LLVM 3.6, have you tried out the OpenMP support
as I have, and have running on my system using a few test programs, so do you have any benchmarks
coming up with the OpenMP support for Clang?
Yes, I will, a few months ago I did run some of Intel's OpenMP branch of LLVM and Clang,
and then now that everything is settling in Mayline, I am in the process of this week
running some new benchmarks, and we'll have those out either this week or next week.
That's one thing I'm so excited for, and I'm very relieved that they finally have it merged
into their master branch.
Yeah, it's very great, and then on LinuxBenchmarking.com is the latest LLVM and Clang benchmark results,
and just yesterday I updated the test scripts to make sure that it's installing the latest
OpenMP runtime libraries, so within the next day or two you might be able to see those
results for that dozen or so systems organically switch over to the OpenMP support.
That's really cool.
Derek Delvin, you had a question you wanted to ask, Michael.
Indeed.
I'd like to know what are the kinds of features that you would like to see coming to the kernel
so that it will help you better test and do what you usually do, because I'm interested
in that.
There isn't any one feature that I'd like right now, like the tracing features in the
kernel are going nicely and everything else.
It would be nice if there was some universally expected benchmark flag for the kernel and
user space that people would expect.
Like right now, between the different Linux graphics drivers for X11, they all have a
different option for how to disable basically vblank.
There's no standardized way of doing that, and of course you want to disable vblank,
but within the Fronix test suite and my scripts, I have to make sure that it accommodates every
driver and make sure it checks or not, and then writes to their proper name and whatnot.
There's no simple universal way to say, hey, we're going to benchmark, so basically make
it in performant mode.
That makes sense.
So, Michael, my last question for you came from Corky in the chat room, and just kind
of curious, what is your main daily Linux driver?
What is your setup?
What distro and what's it look like?
My distro right now is Fedora 21.
I'll upgrade to Fedora 22 in the next few days or a couple of weeks after I find out
if FedUp is working nicely since I know when Fedora 21 rolled out that FedUp had some issues.
So once I can be comfortable upgrading that, I'll do that.
On my main production system, I'm using Intel Haswell, or actually I know it's already
Broadwell, Ultrabook, and that's basically just using that driver since I'm not running
any games or anything graphically intensive on that system, and I can generally rely upon
the Intel graphics driver to not give me any regressions for mode setting and other key
functionality between the kernel releases.
Yeah.
When you can get by with the open source driver, it does make it really nice.
I ran into a snag in Fedora 22 that I'll talk about in our review in a little bit, but yeah,
that was one little snafu for me, but other than that, yeah, the open source driver, if
you're not gaming, I can't believe where it's at now.
Really between that and the Intel stuff, looking back at 11 years of this stuff, it has come
so far.
Just looking at the nine years we've been doing the Linux action show, it is fundamentally
different.
Listen to that discussion we had earlier about how you set up Mandrake to where it's at now
with these open source drivers.
It blows my mind.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
I had a lot of fun reminiscing over that with the Mandrake sex config.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, Michael, thanks so much for coming on and updating us.
Great initiative here, and folks, I want you to go check it out.
It's really cool, and we'll have links to all of it in the show notes.
It's linuxbenchmarking.com, right, Michael?
Yes, that's correct, but I also have linuxbenchmark.com, and pretty much any other variety should also
redirect there.
Nice score.
No worries.
Wow, that's a good score.
That is some prime real estate right there.
You keep it up, and I'll be watching that.
I'm curious to see after you've been publishing these results for a while to see what kind
of trends show up and things like that, especially in some of our favorite projects.
And Michael, of course, you are always welcome to join us.
We have an open Mamba room, and you can stick around for the rest of the show if you'd like.
We're going to get into taking care of some little bit more transitions to Linux.
I tried to solve some issues for Angela and her Switch that really came down to compatibility
issues.
I'm going to talk about what I did and how they worked.
I've tried a couple of different suites, including Kingsoft, a different file format than Office
365.
And I tried to go all in when I did Office 365, integrate it into our desktop, give her
a dock icon, make it feel like a true Excel experience.
I'm going to tell you all about that here in a second, and then we're going to get into
our Fedora 22 review, which I'm really excited to talk about.
First, I've got to tell you something I'm super passionate about, and that's Digital
Ocean, the next sponsor of the Linux Unplugged program.
What?
You don't know what Digital Ocean is?
Digital Ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy way for you to spin up your own cloud server up in the sky.
You need root access on a box that's super fast, connected to tier one bandwidth based
on Linux.
All SSDs throughout, that's Digital Ocean, and the value is incredible.
You're going to get a root console.
You can go right up to that website, HTML5, Badmama, Jamma, Written in Go, you can watch
that thing from post all the way up to the login screen, and you can get your droplet
created in less than 55 seconds.
And pricing plans start at only $5 a month, a month, $5 a month for 512 megabytes of RAM,
a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte, a terabyte, a terabyte of transfer for $5
a month.
Like when it's that price, it's obvious why I have four of them, isn't it?
I mean, come on, hello, it's nuts.
And they have data centers in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, Germany,
and London.
That one in Germany is brand new.
It's super hot.
They got great connectivity to all their neighbors.
The individual hypervisors have 40 gigabit E connections, the fastest SSDs they've ever
deployed.
You don't even have to put a droplet over there because it just sounds so dang fancy.
Seriously.
Plus, you know, help out our folks over in that neck of the woods, too.
But let's talk about how you manage DigitalOcean.
Because yeah, you know, 55 seconds is pretty badass, and the value is amazing, and the
fact that it's all based on Linux and KVM is super killer, and the fact that they have
great data centers everywhere is obviously essential.
But it's that icing on top of that cake, let's not lie, we all like that icing, and that's
DigitalOcean's interface.
Their simple intuitive control panel kicks butt, and PowerU is going to replicate it
on a much larger scale with DigitalOcean's straightforward API that they just revved.
Brand new revision of the API, and I love hearing about how you guys take advantage
of these APIs, and there's a ton of amazing applications.
You know what?
I got to go look at some of these apps.
So here, go over to DigitalOcean.com right now, remember our code DOUNPLUGGED, and then
click on that community link right there, and then go over to the project section.
And when you're in the project section, look at all of these freaking amazing applications
written around the DigitalOcean API that you just get for being up on DigitalOcean.
There are so many really awesome apps that make using DigitalOcean blow your mind, like
stuff where you can just do incredible things from your phone, snap it right into your puppet
management infrastructure, your vagrant infrastructure, use Drizzle with it.
They have so many great little indicators for your desktops.
There's one in the Arch repository.
There's a PPA for the Ubuntu desktop.
So many cool tools built by the community around this API that you just get for free.
And then they have a ton of really great tutorials, I mean, not just great, the best tutorials
on the web, how to set up SSH keys, how to set up open VPN server on Ubuntu 14.04, all
free, all up on the DigitalOcean website.
And you know what else?
They want to double down on that.
So they're hiring content editors.
In fact, if you're a technical writer, go get a job at DigitalOcean, because they're
serious about this stuff.
And this is the kind of company you want to work for, where they really see the value
in this kind of content.
So they're hiring editors, and they're paying people to write for them too.
They're back at it again.
They're taking more entries.
Go check it out.
They're a Linux sysadmin.
They're also hiring those.
So there's so many great opportunities over DigitalOcean.
They're an awesome company, built their entire business around Linux.
And if you use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, one word lowercase, you'll get a $10 credit
tryout, that $5 rig, two months for free.
You guys, it's crazy nuts.
It's so much fun.
They're super fast.
They have local repos.
So those updates, they blow your mind.
I'm not even kidding.
Go try it out.
Go create a droplet and install the updates.
That alone will blow your mind.
DigitalOcean.com, DOUNPLUGGED, go create something cool.
My last droplet was a Minecraft server for my wife and son.
They fricking love it.
And before they do something crazy, I just take a snapshot.
It's all possible with a straightforward, super simple interface.
DigitalOcean.com, promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
And a huge thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
You guys rock.
You're on fire.
Love it.
DigitalOcean.com, DOUNPLUGGED.
You guys are wrecking it up.
Okay, Noah.
So, Ange came to me and she said, honey, I can't pay the bills.
And that wasn't a good thing to hear from the wife.
And it's this damn Linux.
And you never want to hear this when you're trying to switch a new user over to Linux.
So the problem was is she had a pretty fancy spreadsheet that she created in a newer version
of Excel.
It was a.xls file, xl, xlsx.
And this is like an imitation of LibreOfficeCoke?
Yeah.
And basically it's like a knockoff, but they've sort of messed up the UI really bad, so it's
hard to use.
I don't know if you've seen this.
I see.
They just have these huge buttons across the top.
And it's more recent.
And the other thing is, this is really weird, but it's like this standalone binary application.
It's not available in any repo.
And you have to buy it directly from this Microsoft company.
And then you can download it, but you have to run this weird proprietary installer that
doesn't add it to your package repo.
Really?
And they're not even Linux executables.
So that was a huge way.
So that didn't work out.
I couldn't go in with Microsoft Office.
But then...
It sounds like that company's out of touch with reality.
I know, right?
Well, then I found out they're trying this new thing called Office 365, an online version
of Microsoft Office.
So like a ripoff of Google Docs.
Right.
Actually, so I went for the business essentials, because I'm a business, and I had business
to take care of.
So it's $5 a month or about like $60 if you buy it for a year or something like that.
And I'm thinking, I'm getting this for her, because you know what, I want to stay on Linux.
And if the price I have to pay is $60, so that way she gets access to Office, then I
never have to worry about this again.
Right?
That's...
It's worth five times that.
Yeah, right?
Right.
That's what I was thinking.
That's exactly what I was thinking.
Then I discovered when you pay $5 a month, you don't just get like Google Docs and Google
Spreadsheets.
Like that's all I wanted for $5 a month.
In fact, I didn't want anything more than that.
You get like the entire Microsoft business enterprise suite.
You get like Active Directory on demand.
You get Exchange.
You get MobileSync.
You get provisioning of user accounts.
You get calendaring, groupware.
You get shared OneDrive storage.
You get your own customized domain for all of it.
You can do branding with all of it.
Like it is this massive, total, overarching competitor to Google Apps for business.
It is a beast of a service.
And she has every...
She has her own Exchange server now.
Like every...
So you don't just get Office, which was a little intense.
It was more than I really wanted, but nonetheless, I log in and I discover that you can't upload,
at least from what I could tell, you can't upload into Excel from the local file system.
The only way to open up an existing document in Word or Excel online is to either import
it from Dropbox or to open it off of OneDrive.
Yeah.
I was going to say, I think that is their prescribed method, right?
Put the document into OneDrive and then you can access it through the...
Yeah.
But you see the slippery slope I'm on.
So I go from, I'd like my wife to be able to open up the spreadsheet to now my wife
is a OneDrive user.
She's uploading files to OneDrive.
She's importing them into Excel.
Like it's just this slippery lock-in slope.
So to be clear, so your expectation was that she would have the file locally, but able
to edit it and manipulate it in the...
I guess because...
I feel like that's a little unrealistic.
Yeah, because in Google Docs, you can upload a file directly into Google Docs and yes,
then it's stored in Google Drive, but I don't know.
So it's semantics then at that point, you're uploading it to OneDrive or you're uploading
it to Office 365.
But for her, the semantics matter because you have to upload to OneDrive first.
So from a user perspective, you have to go to the OneDrive area, upload a file, and then
you can...
But in theory, you should spend maybe 10 minutes picking files that she needs to use and put
those up.
And then once they're there, you should never need to pull them back down.
Everything should just remain there and you edit them, right?
Yeah, I think so.
And if you ever create a new document, it's always going to automatically be saved in
OneDrive.
Yes, that's true.
But see, then this is also what I'm concerned about.
See, I was hoping she'd be able to download them locally and save them in our own cloud
folder.
And see, now what I'm worried about is this OneDrive stuff is sort of wedging out the
own cloud usage because now I've got...
Yeah.
So, to summarize, you went to Microsoft and expected to be able to integrate Microsoft
solution with another open source solution.
I know.
That was the recommendation of the mom room last time we talked about.
You know what I really wanted?
It's a good recommendation.
It will solve the problem.
I think.
What I want is I want to go to docs.microsoft.com and I want a Word editor in my web browser.
I actually want Spreadsheet.
I guess I want spreads.microsoft.
Because she just needs to be able to pump up a spreadsheet.
Right.
Okay.
But I just wanted to walk you through my logic train on this, like why I was going down
the Office 365 route.
Right.
So, just to complete the picture because I did try something else and I'm going to tell
you about that.
And this is I think going to be my recommendation.
But just to complete the Office 365 picture, what I opted to do is I went into Chrome and
I made the Office 365 site a standalone app for Excel.
And so, I was able to put an Excel icon down in her GNOME doc and she has a little Excel
icon that when she clicks, it opens up a dedicated Chrome window and launches what looks a lot
like Excel.
That's awesome.
So, yeah, it's not a one-to-one, but she launched it and she dug it and she thought it was okay.
And what's great about that is you say it's not a one-to-one, but the reality is Microsoft
changes Microsoft Office so freaking gosh darn much that really what is one-to-one now would
not be one-to-one in nine months anyway.
Well, and for her, I think in a way this works because she still has a Mac, although she
hasn't been using it very much.
But if she did move back or wanted to use it for something, the files would be there
I guess and I don't have to worry about getting Office for her stupid Mac now, so that's good
I guess.
Yeah.
I'm not like thrilled about it, but
So if we talk about the lesser of two evils, 365 is very much the lesser of two evils between
that and the actual Office Suite for a number of reasons.
One is like you said, it works on Linux.
And two, you're going to upgrade your regular Office Suite for the $300 or $400 or whatever
it is anyway and then you get four years of use essentially before you have to upgrade.
The reality is most businesses are upgrading every one if not two years at most and so
now you're getting that if it's really, would you say $60 a year?
That's actually a pretty competitive offering.
It's not bad if you figure it's kind of a business standard and it's nice to be able
to say you can do this under Linux now.
So I totally dig that.
There is another route that I'm going to have her try for a little bit and see what she
thinks and only she can really tell me about the true compatibility because I've tried
to open up her spreadsheets and I'm a total spreadsheet idiot and they look like they
work fine to me.
But it's Kingsoft Office and they have like a very competitive, I know you're pretty familiar
with this, right?
They have a competitive looking spreadsheet program that in some ways has sort of a ribbon
UI.
It's supposed to have fantastic compatibility with Excel spreadsheets.
It comes out of China so some people are a little uncomfortable with that I guess.
And it has like full importing of the more recent 2010 style files.
You can switch and toggle between different UI styles which is kind of neat and it has
the benefit of being a local app and it's free.
It's not open source but it's cost free.
So it's in the Arch Repos like WPS Office I think, yeah WPS-Office is the Arch Repo
package.
So it's called WPS Office now and it, I don't know if you have the video version up Noah
but it looks like a, it's definitely got a nicer UI even than say Open Office does.
We talked about it at last a couple of weeks ago and I looked into it then.
Now did you look into Collegra?
I haven't looked into Collegra, no.
No I haven't done that.
Okay that's the other one that I'm talking about.
I haven't personally used it but I've been told now by three different people that were
previously Microsoft Office users that said LibreOffice wasn't cutting it for them but
Collegra did it.
I actually looked at that too.
Kingslow, this is looking really solid.
And the downside again, Collegra is to the best of my knowledge, it's not open source.
Oh it's not?
Well see here's the thing, I remember it came from KOffice so I always thought it was but
somebody told me.
No, I'm pretty sure it did.
It was the old KOffice and that's one of the reasons I haven't done this because she doesn't
have very much QT stuff on her system.
But I would install all the QT for the KDU4 based libraries but Collegra itself should
work always fine for me.
So yeah.
I give it a go.
So they, yeah it looks like the chat room agrees, they say oh wait no, Ram says it has
worse compatibility compared to LibreOffice.
Well I don't mind installing it on my machine and giving it a go for her but right now I
know she can get it done with Office 365.
Like I know that works so I feel pretty good about that.
The only thing I'm a little worried about is it sort of negates her need for own cloud
a little bit or I'm going to say hey Ange, I now need you to use OneDrive, own cloud
and Dropbox.
It's a bit of a mess so I need to kind of work that out but I feel like this is some
good insights I'm getting to help other potential Linux switchers out there in the audience
in the future.
So they're good little bumps to hit.
They're not unsolvable but they're stuff that if maybe you didn't have somebody helping
you would be a big sticky point and so if we can learn these things then maybe we can
help people make that transition.
So WPS Office is one and if you don't mind giving Microsoft some of your hard-earned
dollars or whatever your currency is, Office 365, at least make it a business write-off
for God's sakes people, that's what I did, geez.
And I got to say if you're a little Google paranoid you could totally, literally you
get Outlook, you get Active Directory, you get everything.
You get all the Microsoft stuff for five bucks a month and then you go like nine bucks a
month and you get some other crap too like you get the actual like desktop apps and crap
like that.
So the five dollar a month is just the web apps from Microsoft which if you're a Linux
user that's fine, that's all you need.
If you've got some Windows in your life, I'm not going to judge you that much but you can
pay nine bucks.
That's funny, that's funny, you'd think the people running Windows would get a cheaper
deal.
So anyways, wps-community.org for the Kingsoft version of the WPS Office, that's wps-community.org
and you can Google search for Office 365 and good luck to you because they've got like
a hundred different websites you can land on to order that crap.
It's like all other Microsoft products, it's super confusing.
But yeah, other than that, other than that one small complaint, I think she's actually
going to be okay.
I think we're finally sort of in the green, Noah.
The one thing we have to work out is the drive space issue, that's getting a little tight.
And really, actually if you think about it, really that's more of a monetary issue than
everything else because we can, I'm just looking here, we can order an M.2 drive and she had
a one terabyte before?
Yeah.
So I don't know if they make one quite that big, well they do, Samsung has the Evo, it
is $465 so we can get a one terabyte.
I wonder if they, I wonder what she would need.
She and I have been talking about changing her photos to drop that down and maybe we
can get by with a 512, but I'll talk to her tonight about that, see what she wants to
do.
Yeah, if we do a five, that cuts the price in almost half, it's $265.
Maybe we pick that up and fries when you're down here this weekend.
Yeah, yep.
Noah's going to be in town for the Linux Action Show on Sunday and I got a few things I'm
doing to get ready around here for you because I know you have some shenanigans in the works.
What kind of shenanigans are you up to while you're out here this weekend?
I have, well here's the thing, I had more shenanigans when I originally started planning
this trip because the original thing I was going to do was, well I was going to build
a box to fix your HDMI capture and then fix the nook, but actually sounds like for the
most part you got the nook thing straightened out thanks to system 76.
Yeah, at least for now I'm using their Miracat, although I do have to send it back at some
point.
Right, well so maybe we'll still tackle that and then I need to fix that other HDMI capture
because even if we have it replaced, we can either use it as a backer or we can put it
in the mobile production rack.
You know what would be an awesome, totally crazy, not going to happen stretch goal?
What's that?
Is if we could dig up some extra hardware around here and put OBS on it and give me
that secondary streaming machine so I don't have to reboot the stream anymore between
shows.
Okay, it's going to happen.
Because then we would have our live stream powered by Linux.
I just decided it's going to happen.
Well, it's a stretch goal, but I think we might be able to make it this weekend.
I don't know if we have the hardware for it, but maybe we can move things around.
It's going to happen.
We'll see, we'll see.
So yeah, I'm looking forward to it.
So Noah will be in studio.
You know what's funny though?
Rotten went to all that trouble to make that really great art, the frames, which we're
tweaking like my look and Noah's look still, but the frames themselves look amazing on
this week's episode of Linux Actual.
Thank you Rottencorpz again for making some great frames for us so we have a nice consistent
look for the show now.
And of course, we finally get it rolled out and now Noah's going to be in studio.
So I don't know how that's going to work.
So I mean, yeah, we can have a tweak those frames, but the reality is I might be there
this week, but the remaining 50 some weeks in the year, yeah, yeah, right.
I don't know.
No, it's good.
It's just ironic that we finally got that all in and then the next following episode,
we're going to probably undo it because it doesn't really fit for, yeah.
But I don't know.
In that case, I'll just make one.
I'll make an extra overlay for it when he's in.
Like a one shot camera?
Because yeah, we're both on one camera in that one.
Yeah.
It's kind of, but it's going to be fun.
And it's going to be a packed episode because we'll be doing the Fedora 22 review and we're
going to interview the folks from the Autotest site, right, Rottencorpz?
Is that Autotest?
Is that what it is?
I'm blanking on his name.
Yeah.
Autotest.
And these are the folks.
Lucas.
Thank you.
Lucas from Autotest.
Autotest is the project behind the automated testing of the Linux kernel, Ubuntu, Red Hat.
Like whenever, like you hear a big project saying, we automatically test our builds for
automated QA every single day to ensure quality.
When you hear them say that, they're probably using Autotest.
So we want to talk to Lucas and say, hey, you know, you are the folks behind all of
these projects that we depend on and making sure that they are doing build really good
solid builds.
And hey, by the way, this is really important for rolling software too.
Obviously that's my angle a little bit.
So we want to talk to Lucas this Sunday, which is great, right?
Because so on Sunday, we're going to talk to Lucas about auto testing for build quality.
And today on Unplugged, we talked to Michael about benchmarking.
Two sort of similar veins and I thought it's great.
If you are, if you listen to both shows, I think they're going to fit together together
really well.
But here's the catch.
That interview with Lucas is probably going to air in a couple of weeks or a week or so.
We'll probably air the Fedora 22 review this Sunday.
So if you show up live, you're going to get extra show because we're only going to air
one of the two segments first.
And but we'll record them both this Sunday since Noah's going to be in studio with the
Fedora 22 review and that interview.
Join us on Sunday, jblive.tv, 10 a.m. Pacific, then the photo show after that.
Go to jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get that in your local time zone.
I also just wanted to give a mention, Ange was intending to join us for the ThinkPad
transition of the Linux switch update because she has a lot more to share.
But her mom is in the hospital today and she needed to be with her.
So my thoughts are with Ange and her mom and she will hopefully join us maybe next Tuesday
because it's it's fun to see her enjoy it.
You know, I come down, I mean, every now and then like she runs into issues and I'm like,
oh, I'm sorry.
I'll fix that.
But more often than not, she's smiling, which is pretty, pretty fun because if you guys
listen for a while, you know, this is not always worked out so well.
So it's kind of a nice change of pace to have her say, oh, this is so cool.
I love how it does X.
So maybe we'll get her to share some of that when she joins us next Tuesday.
In the meantime, though, I want to tell you about something you should try out and then
we'll get to Fedora 22 and that is Linux Academy.
Go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged right now.
Once you go there right now to get our special discount, you go to linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged and you get a 33 percent discount.
Linux Academy is a great service set up by people that had a vision before I did.
I wish I would have thought of this.
This is totally brilliant.
It's created by people truly enthusiast, truly enthusiastic and passionate about Linux and
open source and all of the technology in the ecosystem around that.
Why do I tell you that?
Why does that matter?
Why am I telling you that when this is a training website designed for people who love Linux?
Because there's a lot of training resources online.
There's crappy YouTube videos.
There's generalist sites that get paid billions because they teach you everything from fixing
your refrigerator to changing the tire on your car to Adobe After Effects and there
is a place in the market for that, obviously, but that's not what you need.
You need stuff created by people that truly care about Linux and open source.
You guys know that makes a difference and that's why I tell you where Linux Academy
comes from.
Before we brought them on as a sponsor, I sat down on the phone with them and talked
for a long time about where they came from, what their passions were, where they're going,
why they're doing this and in fact, we actually hit the pause button a little bit early on
in our relationship and we said, why don't we hit pause because you guys are about to
do something really cool and I'll tell you what that is in just a second.
Once you do that, I think you're going to be perfect for my audience and we waited a
couple of months and they rolled that out and they were really on the ball with this
whole thing.
They told us what their vision was and man, they didn't only execute on that.
They overshot and they achieved even more so I was super impressed.
We brought them in as a sponsor right away and they've been with us every single week
since then because they're perfect.
Here's the feature they were working on that I knew you guys were going to love is they
were working on integrating their lab system to spin up automatically in the courseware.
You just get to that spot in the courseware and the virtual machines just start up in
the back end, give you an SSH login and you're working on a real Linux box.
But the part that was really genius is they said, we're going to have it so you can choose
any Linux distro in your courseware so the system is smart enough where if you chose
CentOS or you chose Debian for your courseware, when it gets to that part in the courseware,
then they'll just spin up a Debian VM or a CentOS VM and then almost every week that
we have a spot, there's something new to talk about.
I love these nuggets, these single how-tos and just get in there and do something real
quick.
In fact, check this out.
They just updated it.
If you go to linuxacademy.com, start by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged but then
check out their nuggets section.
We've been adding this all the time because it's quick contents, you don't have to have
a whole course on it, just something you need to know to make you better at doing your job,
make you faster at doing your job, make you a little more confident at doing your job
or maybe help you learn something so you can get a new job.
So if you go to linuxacademy.com slash nuggets, here's a new one they just posted, virtual
box, clone a VM and change the UUID using the command line.
Here's another virtual box, running a headless VM mode, building a firewall with IP tables,
another quick nugget.
How great is that?
You can do quick video courses and when you log in, you just take it and watch it and
you're done.
Creating a pixie boot server, setting up linux single sign-ons, all this stuff.
Look at all these freaking nuggets they have over here.
You could just spend all your time right there if you wanted to and just learn individual
things and get better at each thing, setting up SSH keys, editing an ISO image, working
with DOS box, securing SSH, I love that one, configuring Linux kernel parameters, writing
custom Java services, how Nmap can be used to compromise your system, how NetStack can
be used to compromise your system, MD5 checksums and how to use them.
All individual topics that we could all probably stand a little bit more on.
Linuxacademy.com slash nuggets to see those.
Start by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, you get our 33% discount, they have new stuff
they're rolling out all the time, like the new DevOps courseware, the Red Hat certified
stuff, the AWS stuff is always being updated, first on the scene with Docker and the best
material on Docker, all of it.
Linuxacademy, more than that.
I literally could spend the whole show telling you it all.
They have an unbelievable amount of content and that's why the subscription service makes
so much sense.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for freaking rocking
our face with the awesome support and creating a service that's truly great for Linux users.
I really love being able to say that.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Alright so Fedora 22 is installed on a, System76 was very nice to send me a test bonobo, it's
like a couple of generations old, but that's fine, it's like a core i7 with, I think it
has 120 gigabyte SSD in it, I think it has 8 gigabytes of RAM in it, an NVIDIA 7 series
GPU dedicated, 17 inch screen, really nice laptop, I love the bonobo series.
So this is such a good machine to test this stuff on, absolutely love it.
So today Fedora 22, or was it yesterday, no it's today, Fedora 22 was released and we'll
be talking mostly about the workstation spin, of course the big feature in Fedora 22 is
GNOME 3.16 which means you're gonna get them new notifications, that little bar down at
the bottom is gone now and your icons are off in this little tray area off to the side,
I happen to like it, I know some people freaking hate it, and they've done a few tweaks to
the default GNOME setup that you don't get on your standard GNOME desktop.
The one that you don't care about is that little Fedora logo that's in the bottom of
the corner is actually an extension, so whatever background you change I believe it stays overlaid.
I thought that was kind of interesting.
They've done a few other tweaks too like when your terminal completes a command, it'll generate
a notification using the new GNOME notification system, that's a Fedora specific tweak, that
is not in general GNOME, I thought that was kind of an interesting little, like where
they chose to make their tweaks was kind of funny.
Of course GNOME 3.16's backend has better OpenGL support, you have the improved Edwardia
themes, GNOME's image viewer has been redesigned, files now comes with bigger icons, thumbnails
by default, re-run as menus, this is cool, I really love to see Fedora doing this, installation
of GStreamer codecs, fonts, and certain document types now handled by software.
And this is where I realized Fedora's, for me as an end user, Fedora's edge comes up
over distributions like Arch.
All this stuff I just said, except for the terminal completion thing, it's been in Arch
for weeks.
But what Arch can't do is sort of have a unilateral decision on how we're going to deliver something
and everything pivots and does that now.
And what Fedora does, like when they rolled out GNOME software, well that's just how you
get stuff now.
You know, like codecs, you need something installed, updates, everything is just done
through GNOME software.
So with Fedora, not only do you get the latest and greatest software like GNOME 3.16 and
all these great improvements, but it's presented in a way where it feels like a more cohesive
package than it does when you put it together yourself.
And so my initial impressions with Fedora are really positive.
I'm starting to finally become a little more comfortable with the installer.
I have a little bit of complaints still about how you'd partition with the installer, but
the installer's looking pretty good.
All of it's pretty nice, pretty fast, graphical boot's pretty good.
I did have a major technical snafu.
I'm going to tell you guys about that.
Before I get into that part, does anybody have any Fedora 22 experiences in the Mumble
Room they want to share with us?
So I've been playing with Fedora a little bit.
I haven't downloaded the official ISO yet, I was just playing with the beta one.
But have you had a chance to play with DNF at all?
Yeah, I've only installed a few things with DNF, but there's a couple of interesting things
about it.
Yeah, thanks for bringing that up.
Yeah, DNF seems to be faster.
There's a couple other things that I thought was interesting about DNF.
Updates that don't work, like a bad update or something, it's just totally skipped.
Before in YUM, you had to do dash dash skip dash broken, but now DNF just does that by
default.
Repositories, the 404, DNF doesn't lose its crap, it just skips right over them, doesn't
care, which is nice because some of the RPM Fusion stuff isn't up to date.
There's a few repos for Fedora 22 that aren't up to date, I think Fusion is now.
When you remove a package with DNF, it will automatically remove any dependent packages
that were not explicitly installed by the user.
This one, I wonder if it's biting me in the ass, because I feel like I couldn't get my
software installed at one point.
DNF will check for updates in the background every hour... Wait, no, I'm sorry.
By default, DNF will check for updates in configured repositories hourly, starting 10
minutes after the system boots.
After your first 10 minutes, and then every hour after that, it checks for updates.
I don't know if this is why, but I launched software, and I tried to install a re-edit,
a re-text, whatever, the markdown editor, and it just hung.
It never installed.
I was wondering if maybe it was because DNF was trying to do an update in the background
too to check for updates.
What's really nice is the GNOME software, so when I search, so if I do gparted in search,
it's doing a really instant good job of pulling results out of GNOME software too.
If I don't have gparted installed, it'll show up, and it's just one click, and it's installed.
No password has to be entered, nothing.
It's really nice.
That's largely why I like to stick with Fedora, at least on one of my machines, and why I
kind of consider it my main distro, is because I do so much work in the server sphere where
we have so much Red Hat Enterprise.
YUM is going to die.
DNF is going to be the eventual replacement for it.
In Fedora 22, the YUM command is symlinked to DNF now, and then it gives you a warning
saying YUM is deprecated.
The same thing happened with the service command, right?
I don't know if this still works in Fedora, but it definitely works in Red Hat 7.
If you type in service sshd stop, it redirects that to system control, which is great for
people like me.
So I'm going to use DNF now for a couple years before RHEL 8 comes out, and when RHEL 8 comes
out and everyone's going, oh, well, and this is assuming they've replaced YUM with DNF
in RHEL 8, if that happens and everyone else is saying, oh, this is something new, I'm
going to say, well, I actually have been playing with it for three years, so it's great.
And that is fundamentally why I continue to use Fedora.
So a couple of big changes for graphical desktops have hit this version, and I think some people
have hit some snags with those, and that's where one of my snags was.
Oh, Minimac, I wanted to give you a chance to chime in.
Go ahead.
Oh, yeah, actually, this is exactly the line where I was going next.
Lib input, yes.
Exactly.
Jump in on that, would you?
Yeah, I would like to.
So as I told you before, I'm running this on a Chromebook, Acer C720P, and the touchpad
was not the best one using the Synaptics driver, and it's working quite better with Lib input,
but Lib input has less features than Synaptic has.
So some people that are upgrading from Fedora 21 to Fedora 22 will have some problems using
their touchpad in the normal way they were using it before.
Yeah, I noticed immediately under the Bonobo that the touchpad has worked like there's
just something different about it.
It feels like maybe they put butter underneath my mouse cursor.
It just is a little smoother.
It feels like it's really locked onto my finger.
I like the speed.
I've heard complaints, though.
I've heard people complaining the speed doesn't work for them.
It's a little glitchy.
On the Bonobo, it's great.
Lib input is great.
I don't know what it's going to be like now going back to other distros.
I think I'm going to notice a difference.
So I loved it, too, basically, but I have some special workflow.
So I'm using a software for mouse gestures, and I was not able to do my normal mouse gesture
with Lib input.
So in the end, I just removed that package, and I wanted to blacklist the Lib input.
I was not able to.
So I removed Lib input, and now I'm working on synaptics again, and I have to configure
it with Xconfig.
Oh, boy.
God, now you feel like old Linux.
So that's the one big change for X users.
The other big change, yeah, you can use, okay, I will try that.
So Blackout says you can use XF86 dash video dash Lib input on Arch to try it out.
I might.
The other big change is GDM.
If you have an open, if you're using an open source graphics driver, GDM, the Graphical
Login Manager, not GNOME itself, but GDM uses Wayland by default.
I know that's going to cause some people problems, because it caused me problems.
Essentially what would happen is I'd get grub, I'd hit enter, I would begin booting, I would
get the Graphical Fedora boot screen, which is quite nice, where it fills the Fedora logo
up as it boots, then it would hang with a completed boot logo for about 35 seconds,
and then it drops down to a text console, and I get some sort of libc string errors.
I can't even tell what it is.
I get some string of errors, and the system never boots after that, or it never goes forward.
It appears to hard lock even, because I can't control it, delete it, I can't ping it, anything
like that.
My fix, unfortunately, and I have this in the show notes.
If you guys run into this, if you, after your installation, even though your live session
worked fine, if after you reboot, after first boot, it doesn't go into the graphical session,
you can go into slash Etsy slash grub, or I'm sorry, slash, not grub, slash Etsy slash
GDM, because you're changing GDM not to use Wayland, so go to slash Etsy slash GDM slash
custom.conf, edit custom.conf in Etsy GDM, and uncomment Wayland enable equal false.
It's already in the file.
You just uncomment the file and save it, and reboot the machine, and it won't try to use
Wayland for GDM.
Now, here's the tricky thing, because when it tries to launch Wayland, it hard locks
the machine.
Your options are to do no mode set at grub, you know, edit your grub boot line, and add
no mode set, and then get in to your basic session, and then add that, remove that comment,
or what I did, because I knew this was going to happen after my second installation, because
I wanted to change my partition layout anyways, is before I rebooted the installer from the
live environment, I just did a mount command, and I looked where my root file system was
mounted at, and I just edited the custom.conf file right there from the live session, and
all you have to do is just remove that comment line, or just leave the Wayland enable equal
false, leave that, just remove the hashtag, the print, whatever, the number sign, so it's
not a comment anymore, and then when you reboot, your system will boot just fine.
You just have to disable Wayland, and that solved my problem, and now I'm able to use
the open source driver, I have full 3D acceleration under GNOME, I'm getting all the fancy OpenGL
effects, and my system boots, and it is running great.
I've done updates since then, I've updated the base system, I've been installing applications,
I can't believe how fast it runs.
I can't believe how fast this thing runs.
It's so fast.
So my initial impression with Fedora 22 was a little rocky, because it never is a good
impression after first boot to fail to get to X, that always kind of sucks, especially
when it's really reliable hardware, and you just had a live environment that was working,
so you know something's funky, but almost immediately to me it was probably like a Wayland thing.
So there was a bug, now here's the only thing that might be tricky for you, is if you run
into this, the way the Fedora project addresses this is they have a common problem section
in their release notes, and they say it's a Macbook specific problem.
So they'll say Macbook graphics aren't working, and even in the Wiki they say certain Macbook
laptops with dual graphics card, the Fedora 22 live environment boots fine, but after
installation there's just a black screen with no boot splash, followed by the GNOME login
screen.
This seems to be an issue with Wayland, the upcoming windowing system used by the GNOME
login screen.
But it's actually not a Macbook issue, because I had it on the Bonobo.
So I would bet it's probably a NuVu driver problem or specific model.
So Ray asks, does the GNOME software tool show GNOME apps?
And actually this is another problem with Fedora 22, and I have a link in the show notes
about this.
There is sort of a lack of apps in there right now, because there is an app description file
that has to be updated in order to be displayed in GNOME software.
That went mandatory starting with Fedora 22, and most of the projects that are in GNOME
software have not submitted this app description file.
So there is a lot of apps missing right now from GNOME software.
Developers will be re-adding those description files, or the package maintainers will be
re-adding those description files over the next few days.
So you might be a little surprised by a lack of items in GNOME software.
Now a little bit of silver lining here.
Red Hat has hired, or is actually moving another one of their developers to work full time
on the Nuvoo project, or work more on the Nuvoo project.
So while I just ran into this issue with Fedora 22, maybe it's going to be fixed by Fedora
23, and this has got to be good for Wayland.
Red Hat's letting another one of their developers focus on improvements to the open source NVIDIA
Linux graphics driver.
Ben Skaggs is already a Nuvoo DRM driver maintainer, and David Arley, the overall DRM subsystem
maintainer and contributor to Nuvoo, are already employees of Red Hat.
So Hans will be joining.
He's been mostly known for his Linux USB contributions in the past.
One year ago he joined the Red Hat graphics team, where he's worked on various Xorg and
Wayland things, and he was also one of the developers that worked on libinput that we
just talked about.
So now with the libinput work settling down, his next course of action is going to be working
on Nuvoo.
Right now it's not known specifically what he'll be focusing on, but he's still learning
more about GPU driver programming.
But it's really good to see Red Hat doing this, and he's already shared his new focus
with the Nuvoo community via their development mailing list.
So Red Hat's putting some more weight behind this.
So perhaps by Fedora 23 this was going to be a problem of the past.
It's just, yeah, like Blackout says, or Corky is saying, it's a transition.
Right Corky?
It's a transition to Wayland that's going to be bumpy for a little while, don't you
think?
I do think that, and there's a lot of work to do, but it's very clear that the Fedora
team are focused on this.
This is one of their main features as a Linux distribution.
It only really matters inside the Linux community, but it's a big difference.
And I'm kind of, I'm looking forward to, I'm going to continue to run it for the rest of
the week.
I was running the beta versions.
They also have the same Wayland problem.
So I was hoping, in fact, I think I even sent Noah like a telegram the other night.
I'm like, I'm hoping they fix this in the final ISO because this is the pain in the
butt.
But I'm not going to hold it against them because those things happen during these kinds
of transitions and it's easy enough to fix and it is documented.
Not necessarily documented correctly, but it's documented.
So now that this stuff's out of the way, I feel like I've got a great setup.
I've got a great performing system.
It's on a great rig.
It's going to be my main system for the rest of the week.
And then on Sunday, we'll give you the full take and see what I've been able to make of
it.
Both Noah and I will be running it for the rest of the week.
Noah, any thoughts so far before we close this topic up?
Nope.
I don't have, I'm sure, you know, it's hard to give any real feedback the day the, like
I haven't even installed the actual ISO yet, so I don't want to pass any, any of the problems
I'm having.
I don't want to talk about them until I actually get the ISO.
And then really you don't know all the problems you're going to have until you've actually
used it for like a week.
Are you going to run it on a laptop?
Is that what you'll be running on?
Yep.
So my thought process on that is I have a workstation at my house, my main machine at
my house, which does have Fedora, but I won't switch that over.
I'm kind of in the same boat as Michael.
I'll wait for a couple of days, maybe in a couple of weeks, until everything kind of
fleshes out.
And then once all that's smoothed over and I try everything on my laptop, then I'll move
my actual workstation over.
That makes sense.
I like it.
Yeah.
I could see my, I really can see myself one day maybe becoming a primary Fedora user.
Not yet.
I don't think.
Maybe.
I'll let you know on Sunday.
Maybe I'll use this for a couple of days and fall in love.
There's a couple of tools out there I've already found that I really like.
So it would just be a matter of getting some of my favorite applications I've had problems
with in the past.
I'm looking at you, Rupat.
Telegram.
I'm looking at you.
So I'll let you guys know.
I'd like to hear what you guys think.
Go over to linuxactionshow.reddit.com and leave us your feedback for Fedora 22.
And any tricks or tips that you would pass along to us to make it a better experience
that maybe we could even pass along to the audience in Sunday's review.
Love that too.
linuxactionshow.reddit.com is a great place to make this show even better.
You can also email us.
Go to jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact and choose Linux Unplugged from the dropdown
and send us in a note.
We love that.
That's really great.
In fact, I'll try to get to a bunch of those next week because I don't think I've read
any notes for a couple of weeks.
I guess I'm a bit of a jerk.
Sorry about that.
So we'll get to those soon.
Also, we'd love to have you join us live and don't forget we're doing it at 10 a.m. Pacific
next week.
Just next week we're doing a special early recording right after Tech Talk today.
So show up if you'd like for Tech Talk today at 9 a.m. Pacific noon eastern.
And then just stick around for Linux Unplugged right after that.
Should be fun to do.
It'll be a morning edition of the Linux Unplugged show and then I'll be hitting the road to
go pick up some family.
All right, everybody.
Well, thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll see you right back here next week.
There we go.
It looks like Mr. Laravel has left the room, I think.
That was nice of him to stop by though.
That was nice.
Good show, guys.
Thank you very much.
Now we need titles, jbtitles.com.
Now we vote to the death.
Has anybody tried out the plasma spin of Fedora?
Anybody?
Is that running Plasma 5?
I believe it is.
Nice.
Where's Dreava?
Mm.
Poor man, Dreava.
I've been running nothing but Plasma 5 on Arch lately.
How do you like it?
Oh, it's so good.
I've been such a Gnome fan for like ever since I started, you know, being part of Linux and
then Plasma 5 came out.
Really?
I'm like, oh.
Same here.
No.
No, no.
I started trying KD5.
Plasma 5 two weeks or so ago or something.
Yeah.
And you like it?
Yeah, but the Dolphin file manager doesn't have Qt5 support, I think, so the theme looks screwed up.
So I'm back to Gnome again, so I'm gonna wait for the Qt5 things to work out correctly.
I tell you, Plasma 5 is really great. I mean, it is really, really great.
I still think there's too many options for me, but it really comes down to my sound problems.
I switch for weekends. Like, I go on vacations to Plasma 5, and I'm like,
oh, it's so geeky and cool, and they've thought of so many neat things.
And then I get burned out, and I go back to Gnome.
Yeah, same here.
And I'm really in love with the window manager, KWin, and the Wobbluin.
Yes, yes, yes.
Chris, you mentioned once that Gnome has the great advantage now with 3.16,
that you almost do not realize that you're running a desktop environment,
and that's the way to go for me.
I like that too. Just totally out of the way, and except for when I need it, it is there.
Like, when I need to search for files, or when I need to check my calendar, or manage a setting,
it's there and gives me, I think, one of the best UIs to do that.
But primarily, most of the time, I forget I'm even using a desktop environment, which I like.
You see, on my dual-screen desktop here, I'm running E17 with Gnome integration,
so for me, the switch is E17, you don't realize that you're using it. It's just there.
So, the title should probably have something to do with our chat with Michael or with Fedora 22,
I would think. It's jbtitles.com. I like Fedora Explorer. I don't know, it's clever,
but it doesn't really tell anybody what we talked about. You know? You know? You know?
Wow, it says we talked about Fedora. Get it out of here!
Uh, Fedora isn't yummy anymore, that's clever. Lock-in, slip and slide,
I like that, but it doesn't really, again, cover what we talked about. Uh,
uh, exploring Fedora, yeah, I guess. Chris, by the way, you're using Gnome 3.16, right?
Yes, sir. In the bottom left corner, if you're not using top icons, is the drawer, like,
vibrating if you put your mouse in the wrong position? Yes, it does vibrate sometimes,
let's see. Okay, then it's not only me, because that's on three of my computers.
It kind of shakes, too, sometimes. Yeah, it shakes a little bit, yeah.
So, it's like the top left corner, but it vibrates and acts weirdly.
Yes, I wonder if they did that on purpose, or...
I don't think so, but if you turn on off animations, it stops doing that.
Yeah, that makes sense. But I want my animations.
Right. Uh, Chris, may I just ask, which age were you when you started using Linux?
Well, I was still in high school, so I guess I was 18 or 19, 18, I guess, I suppose,
is when I really first started, 17 or 18, I suppose. I'm 33 now.
Yeah, I'm 19 now, so, and I've used Linux for the past two years.
So, I'm somewhere in the 15 or 16-year range, but... Okay. Yeah.
What was the first distribution?
Well, I guess, technically, the first distribution I probably used was Red Hat
something, and then Debian around the same time. We had a Red Hat and Debian system,
but they weren't my systems. Like, I used them, I destroyed them,
I accidentally did rm-rf on the root while I was using the system, I did all of those things.
That's clever.
Yeah, but the first time I actually installed Mandrake or installed Linux for myself,
like, this is going to be my machine, I'm putting this on my computer now, it was Mandrake.
So, for me, I started with SUSE 6.1, so I still have the box here, and a huge book that came with
it. And then I started switching, I started switching from the different RPM distributions,
landed with Mandrake, then came a short Debian phase, and then Ubuntu started, and then I stayed
with Ubuntu for a long time.
Yeah, me too.
I suddenly feel like a noob here. My first distribution was 10.04.
My first was 12.04, but, well, I'm only 19 now, and I was 17 when I started.
Well, not for the first time, but for the first nerdy time.
I was going to say Fedora 15 was my first one, and that one's pretty old compared to now.
Yeah, that's funny. I remember when Fedora Core became a thing. I remember when they
dropped the core.
Yeah, in fact, what saved me from my Mandrake hate was Red Hat. It was Red Hat, I think it
was 7, and then they transitioned from Red Hat to RHEL and Fedora Core, and then they
dropped the core. It was funny because that's kind of what got me started on Fedora was I used
Fedora because it was the logical progression from Red Hat, and then I've stuck with every
core since Fedora Core 1 all the way up and just upgraded my system. In fact, the original
Fedora Core box I still have. I never nuked and paved it. I just kept upgrading it, and I think
it is on Fedora Core 4 or 5, and it still works. I turned it on in a while, but that's a testament
to live. I've never actually had to do anything with it.
Yeah. Hey, changing topics for a second, just thinking about the Mandrake story,
the Mandrake company story, I think the Linux Action Show subreddit broke that story.
I'm not positive because the guy that submitted it linked, well, obviously we didn't break it
because that French website did, but I think we were the first US website to have it, and then
LWN and Ferronix picked it up. Nobody linked to us, though.
Well, we would. The subreddit post was 20 minutes before the Ferronix post.
And you know, I've also been noticing, and it's fine, I guess. I mean, it's a subreddit,
it's a public subreddit, so what can I say? It's fine. But I've also noticed several Softpedia
stories based on stories out of the subreddit. It seems to be a resource for a lot of people,
which I guess in a way is pretty awesome. I mean, one of the soapboxes we're on all the
time is we need to improve the Linux press coverage, and if our subreddit's helping do that,
it wasn't exactly what I had in mind, but I mean, shit, at least it's something.
And the other thing is, too, is it would be nice if JB got some credit for it.
Yeah, that would be...
It's kind of common decency, even if it's not copyrighted.
Just give us a source link or something would be great.
Right. Or even if all they said was,
we pulled this from the JB subreddit and we pulled it,
Jupiter Broadcasting reported today, something.
That would be nice.
I guess the way to capitalize... Yeah, see, the problem is they can always get it from
our subreddit. Even if we had our own news, even if we published that stuff on the site.
But all right, so right now, Fedora Explorer is still our top title. I'm just not digging that.
Fedora isn't yummy anymore coming in number two.
Fed up Benchet?
What's that?
Fed up Benchet.
Yeah, that's okay, too.
Like, are you fed up?
Fed up, yeah. Fed up Benchet, yeah. It's not bad. None of these are really awesome.
How about Fedora Milady?
What, dude? What's that got to do with anything?
Madriva Falls and Fedora Rises.
Or Fedora Malinx.
Madriva Falls and Fedora Rises?
I got it.
Fedora Hipster.
Fedorable Benchmarks.
But then it sounds like you're benchmarking Fedora, though.
Madriva Falls, Fedora Rises, that's not bad.
He does use Fedora, so technically that's sort of relevant.
Would it be too much advertisement using the name Fornix in it?
I don't know.
I think it would probably hurt the emphasis.
Fedora gets benched, Fedora now and it's future.
I guess we'll go with Fedora Rises, Madriva.
What was it? What was it? What was it?
Fedora Rises.
As Madriva Falls, Fedora Rises.
Fedora Rises, Madriva, and Madriva Falls.
Whichever one sounds more catchy to me.
It's kind of long.
Fedora Rises and Madriva Falls.
Should it be Fedora Rises, Common, Madriva Falls?
Yeah, it doesn't really fall.
I mean, they were about to die and they got revived and they're still dead.
So it's kind of bad for them.
How about something like Madriva Passes Away and Fedora, Fedora's New Baby.
I don't even think there's a place for Madriva in the title to be honest.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think you're probably right.
I think that's probably right.
Let's see.
Fedora.
I don't even know if I necessarily have to go with the title.
I don't even know if I necessarily need Fedora in the title since Sunday's Linux Action Show
is going to be about Fedora.
I mean, you're fed up with seeing Linux regressions.
You're fed up because Fedora.
Because the program Fedora.
And you're benchmarking it.
Okay, you make it a good pitch.
I'll give you that.
You should probably use Fedora anyway just because it was released today anyway.
Yeah, that's true.
Madriva is the big news.
You think?
I'm not so sure it is.
In fact, I think the sad thing is that it's not big news.
Well, I think that it makes everybody start thinking back.
It's nostalgic.
Yeah, but to me, all it says is it's just verifying what I already thought years ago.
So you've had a guest.
Yeah, we did have a guest.
We named it after the guest.
Yeah, the votes.
Yeah, that's true.
I do agree with that.
It would be a good way to go.
Is Michael fed up with Bench?
The regression killer, regression hater, hating regressions.
The quest to kill, the quest to quell regressions.
What about that?
The quest to quell regressions.
It seems more just Linux books.
It sounds like the Linux benchmarking.com.
Actually, not terrible.
What about putting Linux performance on the record?
Is that too long?
How about just benchmarking Linux?
Actually, you already have Linux on the...
Linux Unplugged on the record.
I think you already have Linux Unplugged based on benchmarks.
It's on the record because it's the show.
And it's still on the record because we're really recording the benchmarks and all about it.
Benchmarking TNG.
Come on, come on.
There's got to be something in here.
The quest to quell...
Fedora chip to Madriva.
I'm not sure what that is.
The quest to quell... Fedora chip to Madriva.
I actually kind of like the benchmarking Linux one.
Doesn't that sound super boring though?
Well, here's the thing.
The problem with the quest to quell...
That's really catchy, but it's like the least descriptive thing ever.
Yeah, I know.
What about Madriva benched?
Well, it's not bad.
How about Madriva sits the bench?
Tip your Fedora to Madriva.
Or Madriva bench no more.
Microsoft buys Madriva.
That one keeps jumping out at me.
That would get some clicks.
All right.
Benchmarking benchmark.
You should just name it clickbait.
That'd be good.
Fedora next gets benched.
Michael, the regression terminator.
See, that's funny to me.
That's funny.
Let's see.
America's next top...
But then everyone's going to be Michael, what, Michael from Coder Radio?
What?
Yeah, right.
Yeah, that's true.
How about you wouldn't believe what Michael does in his basement?
I like that, yeah.
Michael's basement.
Yeah, that's good.
We should put something about that basement in there.
I guess we could do...
Basement benchmarking.
I mean, yeah, we could do benchmarking Linux.
That is like our basement benchmarking.
Yeah, it kind of downplays what he's doing a little bit though.
Linux gets benched.
Benchmarking Linux only has two votes.
Basement benchmark.
Linux coming off the bench.
Actually, no, I just typed it America.
Step into larable's basement.
Yeah, I don't know.
I think we're going to have to go with benchmarking Linux as lame as that is.
God, that seems lame.
You know, that feels like a committee compromise.
If we were doing benchmark Linux, I would want to do benchmarks as well
instead of just reporting on one site doing benchmarks.
I would do a lot more involvement in that title.
So say again, so what now?
If we were doing benchmarking as in the whole show's topic,
I would want to also do my own benchmarks and report some fun findings back to the show.
Yeah, yeah, it does seem like a title for a show where we're actually doing benchmarks, right?
I used to do file system benchmarks all the time.
That's why I landed on XFS back in like 2004 anyway.
Is the question in the title something doable?
Because if it is, you can ask, are you fed up?
Regression terminator.
Let's see, the quest.
No, I got nothing with that.
Let's see.
There's got to be something in the fact that he benchmarks because he hates regressions.
There's got to be a title there.
Regressing on the bench.
Which is terrible.
Yeah, I think we're gonna have to go benchmarking Linux as awful as it is.
Even though it kind of, oh yeah.
And it is true because it is actually benchmarking the Linux kernel.
It literally is benchmarking Linux.
Oh, oh, geez, get it out of here.
Oh, we can use one sentence that Michael pulled off, which is Linux graphics drivers are in
pair with Windows.
So Linux pairs Windows.
11 years.
Okay.
I do actually kind of agree.
Actually, you know what?
Micro 89.
I do agree.
Actually, Micro 89 is right.
He's totally right.
11 years of Linux benchmarking is sort of a call out to Ferronics and Michael, but also
still about benchmarking.
It doesn't make it sound like it's the episode itself is about benchmarking.
But has he always been benchmarking?
Close enough.
Maybe it's just news science.
I'm going to go with 11 years of Linux benchmarking.
I think it's actually pretty good.
That's actually, if you think about it, it is once you realize it's Liar Bell, it's,
I don't know, it's a good shout out to him.
You could do just a decade, a decade of Linux benchmarks.
Something like that.
No, you can do something.
Well, let's say even longer.
Yeah, 11 is shorter.
I know you're right.
It reads better, but yeah.
All right.
Wow.
Just when I was about to flush it too, right at the last moment, you know what that means?
We get a hello, everybody, from Obama.
Hello, everybody.
Hey, look at us.