We've been keeping an eye on the Steam Deck, and it seems Valve has updated their Arch
install to be basically fully up-to-date.
They're syncing it up with upstream Arch.
Some people start to speculate it might never happen.
Wait, they're going to do updates, right?
Yeah.
KDE 5.26 is landing in there.
There's new themes and new wallpapers.
That new fancy update to K-Runner.
I wonder, guys, do you think we're getting close to an actual public release of SteamOS
for regular PCs?
Do you think it'll get there before the end of the year?
No.
Really?
Come on.
This is Valve time.
Save it for your prediction, Chris.
I predict it's going to come out before our predictions episode, actually.
Whoa.
Prediction prediction?
Yeah.
I think it's going to come out around Christmas break time for schools and stuff.
What are you basing this on?
Just this one update?
Well, I mean, because why else go through all the trouble of getting everything else
synced up with upstream at this point and not do an update?
Because otherwise, you're going to have to do this all over again before you release.
So you think this is the hurry up, you know, a little quick spit shine and then...
Yeah.
And then they release the public ISO around like a week or two before Christmas and people
that are home for the holidays get to play around with it.
I mean, it's a Valvey kind of thing to do, right?
It's Valvey to me.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent.
Well, hello, gentlemen, coming up on the show today.
We're taking a look at Fedora 37.
Is this the one that breaks their streak?
We'll chat about that.
Plus, it seems Ubuntu is quietly moving away from ZFS.
We'll see what's going on there.
And then we'll take a test and see if these two can tell the difference between real Chris
and AI generated Chris.
And then we'll round it all out with some great boos, some feedback, some pics, and
a lot more.
So before we go any further, let's say time appropriate greetings to our virtual lug.
Hello, Mama Root!
Hi, friends.
Good evening, guys.
Greetings.
Hello.
Thank you for being here.
Thank you.
Very nice.
Got a good crew in there.
Good crew up in the quiet listening as well.
I also want to say good morning to our friends over at TailScale, a mesh VPN powered by WireGuard.
It's a game changer.
If you were early to Linux, you remember that time when people didn't know about how great
Linux was and you knew you were onto something great and everybody else hadn't figured it
out yet?
That's how I feel about TailScale.
So go over to TailScale and try it out.
Say good morning.
You get it for free up to 20 devices at TailScale.com.
If you get a chance, tell them the unplugged program sent you.
Wes Payne, you're running Fedora 37 right there.
Of course.
What else would I be running?
I've got Fedora 37 right here on the Dev 1, which has been an interesting journey.
We'll get to that.
And Brentley, you've been running Fedora 37, but a slightly different spin.
You've been using the Plasma Edition.
It's true.
I assume you went GNOME.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
So Wes and I went GNOME, and Brentley went the Plasma Edition.
Well, he protests when we make him use GNOME, so it's just simpler this way for everyone.
He needed a break.
And honestly, we need to try to represent the Plasma users out there that are considering
these updates, because I realized we kind of had a blind spot with the Ubuntu Mate spin.
We just really focused on the main Ubuntu release, and sometimes the spins have something
really great in there.
True.
So Fedora 37 was pretty delayed.
I don't think they like that term, because they basically have a window.
It spans several weeks.
It's ready when it's ready.
And in this case, things got delayed by a flaw in OpenSSL.
So the Fedora team decided to delay the release, so that way they could fix that and get the
updated package in there.
And so it pushed it.
We're like slow sockets.
Super slow, right?
It pushed it to this week, as this episode is coming out.
What?
Is it like Wednesday?
I don't know.
The ISOs are final.
And we've been kicking the tires throughout the entire beta process, and then we kind
of go in deep in this last week or so.
Fedora 37, I'd say off the top, is a tricky blank canvas to talk about.
This is hard to review, because quite frankly, not a lot going on in here, but there's some
good bones.
It is a showcase for GNOME 43.
Yeah.
It's been a little bit since I used like super up-to-date GNOME.
Ooh.
This is...
It just feels solid.
Everything is snappy AF.
It's just...
It feels like a very first-class desktop.
It's got that new quick settings menu, which I love, and that's been super handy.
And then several iterations now really all come together in the GNOME system settings,
where there's just a bunch of good new stuff in there.
And like you said, this is GTK 4.
We're doing a lot of video acceleration now there for that stuff when we can.
And they also shipped Raspberry Pi 4 support.
Fortunately, every time I went to test that, there were issues with the images either not
being available or whatever.
Which happens as we try to pre-review a release.
But I will give it a go when I can.
My take is a little darker, a little sadder, a little more disappointed than it normally
is.
I think really since Fedora 32, I've been coming on here after a Fedora release, and
I've been saying, this is probably worth updating to.
And I cannot really articulate a reason to upgrade to Fedora 37 outside of the update
to GNOME 43.
And that's even with a pretty big caveat, because if you've got a good GNOME setup right
now on 35 or 36, and you've got extensions you like, I'd just stick there for a while
because most of my extensions broke.
Very few of them are working at this point.
So I don't have some basic things like status menu icons and things like that.
So I really am not really a big fan of this release, because it felt like they took it
more than they gave it in some regards.
This is the release where we lose hardware video acceleration for H.264 and some other
codecs.
And unfortunately, the change to remove the flat hub filtering doesn't land in 37.
It's been postponed to 38.
So the software situation in this release of Fedora is a major step back.
And it makes the software ecosystem on Ubuntu with PPAs and deb files and snaps seem simple
compared to what Fedora offers now.
I had a horrendous experience.
It was just a huge hot mess, because I went to go set up my machine and I searched for
Slack and I got nothing in GNOME software.
And I searched for Telegram and I got a GNOME web link that it would install for me.
I closed the application.
This is, mind you, days after I've been using it.
It's not like the first time I ran GNOME software.
I closed the application, I relaunched it again.
This time I do the same search and I get a flat hub result.
Totally different set of results.
And it's just really just confusing, because the icons are missing, they don't have the
right vendor icons, it's not clear who published it, it's hard to trust if any of it's legit
when I just searched a minute ago and got a web link.
And now I get an application, but the application's missing the icon and I can't tell who the
publisher is.
And this is just a hot mess of software.
And there's some things that are on flat hub that I search for that I can't get really
common stuff, really basic stuff that you'd want to get off of flat hub that are just
not available in GNOME software.
And then they've chosen to partake in parts of RPM Fusion, but not all of RPM Fusion.
So for some reason I can install the NVIDIA proprietary driver from RPM Fusion, but nothing
else works.
And for some reason that's okay, but yet raw access to flat hub has to be protected.
So why can't we just set up all of RPM Fusion or all of flat hub?
And if they're working on a proposal to bring all of flat hub unfiltered to Fedora 38, why
can't I have RPM Fusion too?
What's the difference?
There is no difference.
The difference is, and you can see it in their discussion thread, the legal team just tells
them no.
Nope, you can do flat hub, but you can't do RPM Fusion.
Why?
We can't tell you.
And it's another example of how this distribution gets jerked around by lawyers at IBM that
decide what features can and cannot ship in Fedora.
And it's really disappointing because it affects even this experience of using software, not
to mention the issue we have with video codecs.
So the software situation is just sort of this result of the Fedora project has been
making transitions.
There's been a focus on flat packs.
There has been a discussion internally if they should be using their own flat pack repo
and then putting that in front of flat hub and then defaulting after that to flat hub
and then after that to RPMs.
And they've been sorting this whole thing out.
They couldn't get it figured out in time for release.
And the end result is it's a mess and it's just not a good experience as an end user.
And it's really frustrating because between the video codecs missing and this software
experience being so subpar, it feels like we just took five, six years back in terms
of usability there.
And that's my downside with it.
The upside is that it is a great blank slate in which you can build a fantastic workstation
on.
And so I'm curious if you guys got to that point.
How far did you make it?
Yeah, I mean, I just sort of, I think you're right, the flat hub stuff is confusing, especially
if you want to come in for a, like, I just expect this to work.
I sort of assumed I would just have to, like I do on most places, end up having to like
get maybe flat pack itself going, but at least flat hub, you know, as a repository enabled.
So once I was over that hurdle, it kind of got, you know, working pretty well.
I was actually outside of the initial setup problems, I was kind of surprised by how few
problems I had with GNOME software these days.
Like it feels way faster than it used to feel, like I can switch back and forth, it finds
the search goes pretty quick.
I still love the integration with the various parts of my system.
It feels like a nice, I don't know if I, I don't think I've installed any software on
the command line this time around, which is not my normal go to.
I mean, I just pop up a terminal most times because I'm lazy and I know how to do it that
way.
I was also, I continue to be pleased with just as everything keeps getting updated and
revved in the last couple Fedora releases, it feels like more and more of the little
edge cases have been worked out.
Like I think like where Pipewire and some of the GNOME plumbing and just on the desktop
as a whole feels, feels really nice.
Like Pulse, who cares anymore?
Like I just, this stuff works so well, I, it feels, I don't feel limited.
There was a time where I was like, Fedora, could I make it like a, like a creator space
for me that felt like maybe there's some hurdles, but with Pipewire, like there's a ton of stuff
in the repos, like Helvam, the Rust GTK patch bay thing that lets you, you know, drag inputs
and outputs around that works with Pipewire, packaged in Fedora.
And if it's packaged in Fedora, like, you know, it's, it's, it's recent, it's new.
Like I don't have to complain about it.
So that made it.
That does, that does make it nice as a workstation.
Yeah.
So once I got over a little bit and, you know, I had to go remind myself, how do I get Nick's
packages going on Fedora without disabling SC Linux and some of that, you know, so there's
a couple of things.
But once I got all the initial setup, you're right.
Like I like the system, everything feels real solid, you know, they've got system D tuned
really nicely.
They've got the desktop plumbed really nicely, up-to-date software.
So yeah, I don't know if the hurdle, there's more hurdles now, I guess.
But if you are an experienced user, you probably expect that already.
I think Fedora 37 benefits from years of good choices under the hood.
And so there's a lot there to work with.
I'll talk more about how sometimes it doesn't always come together in the end, but I wanted
to ask you, did you end up getting Nick's packages working on Fedora 37 or are you using
that to manage software right now?
Yeah, I didn't do, I just wanted to see, you know, go through the process.
I didn't install a bunch of stuff through Nick's or anything.
Mostly I'd mostly have flat packs on this because I've been using it as a, you know,
casual desktop, getting a little bit of work done here and there.
I think the one thing I installed, VS code just as a raw dog RPM, actually, because I
don't know, sometimes the flat pack doesn't feel worth it for that one, just because if
you want to dump a bunch of runtimes on your system with that layer is sometimes more trouble
than it's worth.
But other than that, it's been flat packs in the repo and, you know, I just wanted to
play around with Nick's because these days I just install it everywhere.
So you enabled flat hub, just full flat hub.
I tried it at first.
I was like, oh, this is not getting me the results I want.
And I figured on most, you know, some desktops, like you got to install flat pack itself
first and then enable flat hub.
So by comparison, yeah, it's quicker.
And they have a Fedora specific section on the site and you can just download the repo
thing and it installs it graphically.
I took it on as a challenge to not add the full RPM fusion repo or flat hub repo for
a while just to see what that experience was, to see what they were shipping.
And it's not great because if you do want to get to that stuff, if there's no instructions
on how to actually officially do it, so one of the things you got to do is just follow
some random instructions on Reddit that tell you to install these packages from RPM fusion
and supposedly they'll add hardware accelerated decoding back.
But it's like, which Reddit thread do you pick?
I mean, I picked the one I picked, I'll put in the show notes, but I can't believe as
a Fedora user, that's what I'm being reduced to is finding random Reddit threads.
But I did notice there was a codec section at the G streamer one in the store.
I don't know if that's only there if you enable third party repositories at the install.
But yeah, I think so.
But the nice thing is also is it will take you there when you go to when you first go
to play.
So I'll walk you through the scenario because here's the here's the scenario I recreated
and then I want to hear Brent's plasma experience, but the scenario I created is I filmed a video
on my phone and then I took that video.
Was it a Levi video?
Of course.
Okay.
I took that video and I put it on my laptop and I wanted to watch the video on my laptop.
It's 2022.
Everybody has a smartphone with a camera.
All of those cameras are recording in HD 64.
It transferred to my laptop.
It does not play.
That's a failure.
However, it does then walk you through the process of searching Gnome software.
And if you have the third party repos installed, you can install the G streamer codec that
has HD 64 playback.
I don't believe it's hardware accelerated because I got a I got a dev one here and I
was like pegging out like 40 50 percent watching a video from my phone.
But it installs it and then it begins playing immediately.
It's even a slightly smoother than it used to be back in the old days when I used to
buy my fluendo codecs and then add them back when we used to not have codecs on Linux.
It's a little bit smoother than that.
I had to.
I don't know if it was a flu.
I already had it open.
I had to restart Firefox to get it.
Hmm.
I just installed it right now as we're doing it.
Yeah.
But after that, I mean, yeah, watching Jupiter Tube.
So.
Right.
So, Brantley, I want to hear about your experience.
I know you tried plasma.
I don't know if any of this stuff bit you.
If maybe you're sticking with Fedora 37.
How'd it go, sir?
Yeah.
Well, one of our parameters that we kind of toyed with was not changing any of the repos,
not adding flathood, things like that.
So I thought that's a great challenge.
But then I kind of suffered for it.
So I had a quite a hard time.
Yeah.
I actually really suffered with that and I didn't expect that because I was just trying
to do really simple stuff like I wasn't able to find VLC.
I don't know.
Maybe I'm broken.
I couldn't find it anywhere to install, which seems odd.
I don't know why that is.
But to test the video playing, like you mentioned, Chris, I installed MPV and it must have taken
care of everything because H264 played just fine for me, actually, which was good.
But I just ran into a whole bunch of issues even from the very beginning, which was unfortunate.
I was really looking forward to having a great experience.
And some of it was like a day or two before those official releases were out.
Some of it was after and just continued, which is sort of unfortunate.
So one of the main things I ran into, well, I guess I should give some stats first.
So it was running Plasma 5.262 as far as I can find.
The latest is 5.263.
So pretty darn recent.
I think 5.263 just got released on the 8th.
So a few days ago.
But I ran into some issues that have sort of been my experience with KD the last six
months on various OSes, unfortunately.
So one of the main ones was that the lock screen after being suspended, when you try
to wake it up, was just a complete mess of distortion.
And Chris, I included a few screenshots for you in our doc there so that you could kind
of have a look at them.
And it was bizarre because the mouse pointer was perfectly fine.
But everything else was like this jarble mess.
I was able to find a workaround.
So I was able to use the old control alt F1 and F2 and F3 to kind of bounce between terminals
and get back to the screen.
And then it's presented just fine.
So that was an interesting experience.
And it just kind of persisted between restarts and was unfortunate.
And I had just application crashes out of nowhere and some notifications that came up
immediately just suggesting that things were broken.
And so I actually didn't get very far before losing all of my enthusiasm.
And that got me thinking about spins in a bigger context.
And I feel like the main release, especially with their release window, tends to focus
on the GNOME implementation, which is logical.
But it gets me thinking about spins and how they're at kind of the mercy of that release
cycle.
And sometimes they have to release maybe when they're not quite ready.
I would be interested in knowing a little bit more about how that works on the back
end.
But I feel like using the spins on release day is just rough, really, really rough.
Maybe it's better in a month or two, and I'd be interested in looking at that.
I don't disagree with you on that.
I know that Neil would tell us that the Fedora project has made critical bugs in Plasma a
release blocker for all the spins.
But my experience has also just been that it doesn't have the same focus.
I think that probably could be a topic we could dig down on in the future.
You mentioned errors.
Do you think they were SE Linux errors that you were getting?
No, they weren't SE Linux errors.
I think I meant to screen grab them, and then I had the other issues and just they got lost
in the mix.
But yeah, I can't speak to them.
Maybe I'll have another look and find them.
But they didn't seem to affect at least what I can tell, the operation of the OS, it seemed
just fine.
Might have been a notification subsystem error.
Hey, I'll take viewer notifications as a good thing.
Yeah, you still want to get the important ones though, don't you?
This is an interesting sort of pause in what has been, in my opinion, really strong releases,
especially starting at 32 and 33 when ButterFS came in.
And I think it's still a really solid base.
I don't know if it's worth upgrading today.
I'd probably, if it was me, I'd probably wait a month or two at least.
Unfortunately, sort of ironically timed, after the show today, I am playing tech support
for my son.
I installed Fedora 36 on his Asus laptop.
It's been working great for a long time.
Until about a month or two ago, and it started to just slowly have issue after issue.
One of the first problems that crept up was his Nvidia binary driver just broke.
It seems to almost segfault during boot or something, and then the nouveau driver has
to load.
So it does fall back.
It's not like it totally fails to come up.
But he uses it to game, so it's kind of a downside.
So then it starts up and you're like, wait, why is my gaming suddenly way worse?
Yeah.
And of course he's always paying attention to the frames per second and whatnot.
So this weekend, this is on Fedora 36, I just took all the Nvidia stuff off, went totally
back to a free driver stack, completely back to stock.
And then went into GNOME software, made sure I had the repos enabled and all that kind
of stuff, and reinstalled it from following their prescribed process, and I'm still having
issues with it.
But on top of that, when he shuts down now, it hangs at like KVM trying to do some sort
of KVM hardware shutdown process.
And his system just hangs there forever, and he has to hard physically turn it off.
And of course, he's doing that more and more, because it also doesn't sleep anymore when
he closes the lid.
It did when he first started using it, but it no longer does.
And this morning, I found out that now some sort of process in the background is just
going absolutely crazy.
I would not be surprised if it isn't related to KVM.
And his fans are going crazy, his CPU is getting pegged.
It just seems to me that Fedora 36 just didn't turn out to be as durable as I wanted, because
he only installs stuff from Steam, and he just does the system updates.
That's all he's doing.
And he had elementary OS for like three years, and it was fine.
We just moved because it was an old base, and he was getting a new machine.
And at the time, I was like, Fedora seems to be working really well.
But I'm concerned about this durability issue, because I'm not really clear what he's done
other than, I've looked at it, it's just updates, and things broke.
And I think that means it's probably not going to be the family OS for me.
And I really hate that, because I like just that clean blank slate that I can build a
little family setup on.
I mean, obviously, like, right, there's LTS, there's lots of options here, but it felt
like in a certain stride, like the updates, the update process itself, just everything
kind of coming together, reaching a very cohesive whole, like that even though, yes, there are
more updates in the Fedora model, you can still feel kind of comfortable being like...
You know, I'm glad you brought that up, because I say elementary OS was fine, but we were
starting to have packages that were like...
You can no longer get an updated enough version from the repo to support this.
Or like a repo was no longer online, because it was like a, you know, probably a four-year-old
distro by that point.
Yeah.
Was that the 1804?
Probably.
Yeah, it was probably the 1804 base, and it was about a year ago.
And everything still installs, right?
DNF completes, everything's good, every package is still working, all the dependencies are
resolved, there's nothing broken in regards to like package management, which is honestly
what I was trying to solve for, because I was very frustrated, because ultimately what
happened to elementary OS, I couldn't update Chrome, he couldn't use something he needed
for school, blah, blah, blah.
Right.
One too many PPAs, some weird stuff happened, who knows anymore.
Yeah.
I solved for that with Fedora, and it's working well, but it's just disappointed me in this
way.
My exit interview for Fedora 36 is, if you're a sysadmin, you're set, it's going to be fine,
but I can't recommend it for the set-it-and-forget-it-family type computers, because it has not been that,
and this has not been problem-free the entire install, about once every couple of months
I'm fixing something for them, you know, two or three times, not the end of the world,
but it's also, I think, honestly it shook his confidence a little bit in desktop Linux
as a result, which is kind of, which was not great, you know, because we were doing really
good, but when he sees the frame rate drop, and you know, he's having issues with it not
shutting down, and he closes the lid, puts it in his bag, and he pulls it out, it's like
110 degrees, and the battery's drained, you know, that's a bad experience.
And now if I were to put Fedora 37 on there, and not set it up for him, you know, if he
were to just try upgrading to fix it, he would upgrade, and he would lose video accelerated
playback, and he has an AMD graphics in there too, he's got both, and that's just, that's
a hard sell.
I mean, could you imagine trying to tell him that?
How do I even explain that to him?
I don't think you would, you'd probably just end up in stock, you know, tell him I gotta
do a couple maintenance upgrades real quick before you use this, bud.
Now I have a question for you both, or maybe it's more of a pondering.
We've seen some of the major distributions, like Fedora for instance, we were excited
about it for a long time, and now it seems maybe this one's a slump for a little bit.
But we saw the exact same thing with Ubuntu in recent years, kind of some maybe less exciting
releases, and it seems maybe they're on an uptrend now for us.
In that context, how do we choose, well I'm gonna make it personal, how do we choose an
OS for my dev one, because I need something and I'm finding it really difficult, you know,
in the shoes of a listener to just say, well, what does JB recommend as the OS that I should
run for the next year or two?
God, it really comes back to like, what problem do you want to solve for?
Because in a real way, the problem I was trying to solve with Dylan's laptop was system updates
that worked every time and didn't break, and I was sick of fixing a broken app to install,
that if you run an Ubuntu install long enough, eventually just doing updates, something breaks
to install, right?
It just happens, at least on all of mine it has over time, and it happened on his, and
I was solving for that.
So it's like, what problem are you willing to put up with?
And then there's this other element that I don't think we talk about, but it matters
a lot, and it's what's the corporate influence?
Because a lot of what we're complaining about today is not really because of a technical
issue, it's because of legal issues.
So what is the corporate governance look like, and what do the corporate politics look like?
And that's a whole other element you have to consider too, if you really get into it,
and I don't know how you explain that to people, and it's gonna be different at different thresholds
and different preferences for each individual.
So I think the option is, is distro hop for a while.
I think that's why distro hopping is so popular, it's why it's such a meme.
I'm not convinced that solves it, because you could try one version and have a terrible
experience six months later, have a great experience on the very same distro.
I don't know, is that true though?
I mean, I think that's true for people trying it, but I don't know, I think you either have
to be willing to accept what you get, or be hands-on in the Linux world.
You know, either you can't be that picky, and you gotta just take what the LTS gives
you and realize sometimes you're gonna get old, slow stuff, or you're gonna be running
something like Fedora or Arch, because you know how to take backups, or know how to roll
back software, or how to deal with the paper cuts that come.
I mean, maybe not, but that's usually the way I end up, as an extremely jaded, using
Linux for way too long person, is how I end up kind of approaching it.
Like either this is a kiosk, or it's somewhere that I fiddle.
Right.
It's a tinker toy, or it's an appliance, or another way people like to put it is a pet,
or it's cattle.
I think what it is, is when you pick a Linux distro, it's what set of problems do you want
to solve for?
And Fedora has, I think, in whole, when you look at all the different distro options,
a pretty good understandable set of compromises.
NixOS is the one that seems to be kind of hitting my sweet spot right now.
Yeah, I was just waiting for that.
But there's another set of compromises there, and that is complexity in installing software,
and just a new paradigm that you kind of have to wrap your head around.
And there's just sometimes an extra step or two.
Like I downloaded a piece of software the other day, it was actually the first time
I, this sounds weird, but the first time I ever tried an app image on my NixOS desktop,
I just don't really use app images that much.
No offense, but just don't really use them that much.
And I discovered there's an app image run package in Nix that essentially creates the
necessary environment for an app image to run successfully, and then lets you execute
the app image.
It meant I don't just download an app image and double click it.
And it meant that when I double clicked it, because I was curious what would happen, and
nothing happened, like my response can't be, well this damn thing, it has to be, all right,
well let's go Google this, because that's what I'm gonna be doing for a few minutes.
And usually the solution can be found in a few minutes.
And that's a different set of compromises.
But those are the ones I'm living with right now.
That's the real, that's the success to Linux.
Well, it is nice, I think, at least too, that we can, you know, distro hopping is something
that does work.
Yeah.
So you can have backup, you can dual boot if you like, you know, find one OS that you
really like for X activity and want some other LTS setup for, you know, this workflow doesn't
change a lot, and I just don't want to ever have to mess with it again.
And since so many of our tools, especially with flatbacks and app images and containers,
you can bring them with you.
And you got the choice.
And if one distro maker chooses to do something that bugs you, there's several other ones
you can try.
There's always Arch.
lino.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
It's a great way to support the show while you're checking out fast and reliable cloud
hosting.
The best in the business with real human beings behind the support number and a solid Linux
infrastructure.
Over 11 data centers today, right, but they're working on another dozen for next year and
a whole new concept for a micro data center, too, which I'm sure we'll talk about at some
point.
Everything we've built for the last couple of years, we've built it on Linode, in part
because it's great pricing, 30 to 50% cheaper than the hyperscalers out there.
But also the performance is better.
It's not just me saying that there's been benchmarks out there, but I've also just tested
it.
And it really is just truly great for the price and the performance and the mix of machine
that you can build.
Nobody gets it.
Nobody gets it like Linode.
And you know, they've been at it for like 19 years practically.
So that's kind of why they've really dialed it in.
And I bet some of you are thinking about potentially setting up your own presence in the Fediverse,
maybe deploying a matrix server or a mastodon server.
Linode's got a guide on how to set up mastodon on Linode in a way that's going to work perfect
for you.
And what I love about this guide is they actually make it available for one, two, three, four
different distributions.
I'll link to the Ubuntu 2004 one.
I don't know.
Personally, for myself, I think that's, I'd probably be considering CentOS Stream.
They have a guide for that as well.
That's what I love about Linode.
They're really distro agnostic.
Whichever distro is going to work best for you, they're going to try to work with that.
And if you ever get stuck, they got the best support in the business.
It's available 365, seven days a week.
I think it's probably the best out there.
Nobody else has built that because nobody else had to compete at that level.
And when you get that $100 by going to linode.com slash unplugged, you can actually try out the
different features of Linode and see why we love it so much.
See why we deploy stuff on there all the time and honestly, the one way you can really,
one of the ways, not the one way, but one of the ways you can really tell that we trust
Linode is when we do live things like deep fusion image generation or, or SSHing into
a box publicly and having everyone on a live stream try to figure out how we broke Docker.
We always do those events on Linode hardware because it's the only thing that holds up
to it.
And it just, it's so impressive every single time.
So go try it, support the show, build something or learn something.
It's a great platform for learning things as well.
Linode.com slash unplugged, get the hundred dollars, try it out and support the show.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
We got some baller boosts this week to support the show.
Wise Papa John came in with our first big boost, 40,000 SATs.
Keep the change, you filthy animal.
Here's 40,000 for a hard G in GIF.
And also Matrix can be a little intimidating for new users.
I feel something that's like more mainstream type social apps, AKA Mastodon, might make
the audience interaction a little more approachable for the newbies.
It also could be another way to discover old show topics.
I'm thinking a social media post for each new episode with a comments thread and whatnot.
Yeah, this Mastodon topic is going to come up again today later in the show.
It's a big hot topic right now because as we record this episode, Twitter is a fiasco.
People are trying out Mastodon in numbers.
It's a whole Pandora's Zoo, not just a class.
Yeah.
Pandora's Zoo is a good way to put it.
And so I've noticed that the podcasting 2.0 show does this.
They do a Mastodon post as a comments thread section.
Oh yeah, sure.
We could probably talk to Alex Gates, the podcasting 2.0 consultant on Office Hours
more about this, but there is also work on cross podcasting app comments using Activity
Pub.
I like that.
That sounds like a nice idea.
Yeah.
So they could be like part of the Federation, which I think would be really cool.
So we'll keep an eye on that development and maybe that kind of stuff could pull us in
or maybe I should just start using my Mastodon account on the podcasting 2.0 social thing.
I mean, I could.
I don't know.
This has worked so well for me because I can dip in and dip out, but I realize that's the
exact opposite for some people.
They don't want something that's moving all the time.
Me I just dip in.
Yeah.
Sometimes you feel real chatty or broadcasty and you want to follow up on what's been going
on.
Some days you don't.
But I gets it.
I gets it.
And then we got another baller boost from John A. He's back.
Twenty five thousand sats and he says, I'm back, baby.
Yes, you are, John.
It's nice to see you again.
Thank you for the support.
I hope you can make it over here before the snow gets too high.
It's going to be tricky over those passes soon.
I also want to mention that the baller support has really been great for the show in terms
of discovery.
We've got new listeners that find us because your boost put us high on the fountain charts
and pretty neat is I have a call scheduled with some of the fountain FM leadership on
Tuesday next week because they've noticed we're so frequently on the top boosted charts
and they're like, well, we got to talk to Chris more.
That's wonderful.
So I'm going to take some feedback that I've been hearing from the audience and talk with
them about it.
But, you know, as a podcaster that does this for a living where my actual livelihood depends
on this, having these channels of communications with the app developers are kind of really
important and critical.
And so your boost put us up on those charts.
We had new audience find us and the developers of Fountain FM.
We got their attention too.
And now we're going to have an ongoing dialogue with them thanks to your support and the boosts.
I really just I really love how it's working.
I really appreciate it.
So it's like a little audience vouch, you know?
Yeah.
It's a real clear signal is what it is.
It's better than any algorithm that the platform maker could come up with.
It's better than upvotes.
Yeah, upvotes are cheap.
Yeah.
It's better than a thumbs up or a retweet.
It's a real signal because people use their stats and it's a data point of enthusiasm
and people take note.
It's really cool.
And we appreciate it.
The stats are cheap.
They'll probably be cheap for a while.
Don't buy a bunch, but just grab a handful and send them our way with a new podcast app
at newpodcastapps.com.
I wanted to follow up on a couple of items and one that just I haven't really seen much
discussion and it's kind of been developing I think for about a year and I've been hoping
that we'd get some sort of official announcement from Canonical on the state of ZFS in Ubuntu
because it seems that they are transitioning away from some of the tooling that they have
created to manage ZFS, specifically the ZSYS tooling.
And it's even kind of in a deprecated, barely maintained state.
There's even potentially some bugs that are impacting data and it doesn't really seem
advisable to continue to use ZSYS with ZFS on Ubuntu.
I don't know what it means for the long-term ZFS on Ubuntu in general.
Wes, I know you sniffed around a little bit.
Can you kind of summarize what you found?
Yeah, it just seems like internally at least at Canonical there's no longer a lot of prioritization
around ZSYS.
So it hasn't had any active development.
And then people started noticing that there'd been various issues in launchpads suggesting
like, well, we're not working on this.
We're still installing it with the installer.
We should probably update this.
We should clean this up.
If we're not going to be maintaining it, then we probably shouldn't be installing it.
So it doesn't seem like there's any indication of so far anything changing in terms of shipping
the ZFS pre-compiled module, keeping that in sync with the kernels they deliver, all
of that good stuff we had since 2016.
But in terms of their more ambitious sort of, you know, deeply integrating ZFS with
the desktop experience, with the, you know, base underpinnings of the system, not a bright
future there, at least at the moment would be my guess.
Yeah, it seems that the team has just been reprioritized, right?
They're focused on other things and this tooling just isn't a big priority.
But it's funny because these things come triumphantly, right?
We get this big triumphant introduction of a feature set and it's really cool and we
talk about it.
And then sometimes things change and they just quietly fade away.
And it seems like no one's really been working on this since, you know, late 2021.
And there's just been a couple of wham bam fixes to just kind of cram into the installer.
Now, like you say, there's a Launchpad ticket right here to just remove ZSYS from the installer
altogether.
That feels like a downgrade to me.
And I wonder what your opinion is, is in terms of, well, they should have gone with Butter
FS because that was the first thing I thought of.
Not just because of the kernel module stuff and the licensing stuff, but to me it felt
like if Fedora and Ubuntu were working on tooling together around Butter FS and SUSE's
out there working on tooling around Butter FS and we have these three large distro makers
that just standardized on Butter FS.
Not only would that likely help us improve Butter FS even further, but then if one of
them faded, we still have other vendors in the mix.
But now what we have is we have Ubuntu with ZFS with tooling that's just kind of being
deprecated.
We've got SUSE that's doing their own thing integrated with their own package installer
with their own setup on Butter FS, which is probably the most mature.
And then we've got Fedora that's moved the ball forward since 33, but not significantly.
We're not seeing after you complete a DNF install snapshots that you can then go boot
from grub or anything like that, which it clearly could be if they continue to iterate
on it.
We've just got three different kind of hodgepodge with open SUSE in the best condition.
And I just look at this whole thing and I go, well, you know, when they announced this,
my first thought was, boy, it'd be great if they all just went in on Butter FS.
And now we're at the end where they're apparently deprecating ZSYS and my thought is, God, it
would have been great if they just would have gone with Butter FS.
Yeah, but I mean, does that ever, does it ever work that way, right?
ZFS is kind of their sauce, their thing that they know they can bring that other distros
can't or won't.
Plus, I mean, we know, not necessarily in a bad way, they've made some very nice tools
that I like a lot, but Canonical has a particular way that they build tooling and approach and
tool chains that they want to use, right?
They've got people who know how to use, you know, they seem to use Go a lot for a lot
of these tools, but they've got, you know, particular ways to go about and build these
things.
To me, it just makes me think it's kind of that ebb and flow we see, you know, at a time,
maybe there's a little more interest in some of this like enterprise-y desktop and that
space and maybe that's just kind of faded a bit recently.
Well, you know how I found out about this is if you ask the folks at the OpenZFS project,
they'll just tell you to just avoid Ubuntu now.
And they have on their front page like news about, at least they did this weekend, news
about how this is being deprecated and don't use it.
It doesn't seem like that's in a good place, that relationship, that doesn't seem like
a healthy thing because when you have like the upstream project saying, oh yeah, just
don't use Ubuntu, even though they're still shipping the kernel module, that's the...
It should be probably one of the better experiences, yeah.
I think it actually is.
Yeah.
I don't know, man.
We'll have links to the Launchpad issue as well as the issue on the ZSYS project itself
where the user ran into a data loss bug, but I want to do another follow-up story.
I'd be curious to know what the audience thinks and what their experiences with ZFS there
and honestly, if anybody's impacted by the deprecation of the ZSYS tooling, did that
really take off?
Maybe that's an element.
Yeah.
Maybe it just got really low adoption or something.
I don't know if they could measure that.
I did see some folks in the various like discourses and stuff wondering like, what are the KPIs
you want to see?
How do we tell you if some people really like this?
I don't know if we have a clear signal on that.
Yeah, that could be part of it too.
Well, send us some signal if you have an opinion out there, dear audience.
And then I want to go back to the topic of these deep fusion generated images and deep
fake audio.
Listener CB had a lot of fun generating some images that are creepy, eerie, close to me.
Like the first one in this album that I'll link to in the show notes, I think if I sent
that to you, you would think that actually was me writing a penguin.
Totally would.
I'm disappointed it wasn't you.
There's me talking to a penguin.
There's also me watching myself on the screen.
That also happens.
Yeah.
Very, very interesting stuff.
But of course, this here is an audio podcast.
And Listener CB generated something that is pretty close to the real thing.
So are you ready to hear what the current state of deep fake Chris after it's been trained
on our podcast sounds like?
Heck yes.
All right.
Listener Chris decided to create a virtual Chris efficient.
So I'm going forward.
I do not need to do these podcasts anymore.
And I can just go on vacation to relax.
Ah, I mean, you kind of understand it, right?
Yeah.
You listen to him for a few seconds.
It starts to make sense.
That vacation they may become in their West kind of sounds like a Chris Fisher on his
like third podcast of the day.
Yeah.
You know, I thought you're gonna say yeah, drink of the day, you know, that's also the
third drink.
I mean, what are you doing to show that?
Come on.
And then here CB sent in what he believes is the value for value exchange for this experiment
he engaged in.
So I need to acknowledge some value that a listener send in over and down.
Listener Chris had prayed something fakes him.
And I just want to say that his contribution is worth more than 900,000 boosted sets.
Over 9000.
It's obviously a little rough.
But what about in a year, right?
What about even in a year?
Isn't that something a little more effort, you know, get some more build a bigger, bigger
data set.
I'm going to play the first one again.
And I think it does actually capture some of my tone.
For this, I had to create a virtual Chris Fisher.
So going forward, I do not need to do these podcasts anymore.
And I can just go on vacation to relax.
Isn't that remarkable?
That's a lot of fun.
I would let that guy like guide me through a phone tree.
Yeah, you could totally see that.
Welcome to you.
But I'm wrong.
Yeah.
Press one like a version where you get Linux action news, but you have to call a hotline.
Like like telephone banking, but it's telephone Linux news.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Member special.
Yeah.
Enter your member code.
I'll you guys will have to if you I mean, if you care, you'll have to look at that handsome
gentleman.
I know some of the images that generated are really something.
Me talking to penguins is a theme, which is great.
One thing that I do really appreciate about the AI is that it the one thing it really
honed in on is consistent is where I'm overweight.
But to the hair, the hair, right, the hair is consistently good.
It really it really does that quite well.
Also you could learn a couple of styling tips from AI Chris, I think.
I am also I was just going to say I look good in a military uniform like this is the right
look for me.
Hoodie.
Not so great.
Military uniform.
Editor in chief or commander in chief.
Yeah, I guess my I guess my uniform left.
I've been lurking on building a personal uniform.
I'm going to have to just go for like the you know, like the actual like military style,
you know, because that looks good.
It looks good.
Yeah, I feel like I want to set up another one of these deep fusion instances.
Oh, yeah.
We're not.
It's too much fun.
It was a lot of fun.
It was a lot of fun for screwing around.
We use it for just low key stuff like over at Jupiter dot tube.
All of the you know, instead of doing like silly YouTube thumbnails, we just generate
a silly AI image.
Why not?
It's been working pretty good.
Bitwarden dot com slash Linux go there right now to get started with a free trial for a
team or an enterprise or try it as an individual by going to Bitwarden dot com slash Linux.
I haven't mentioned this before, but enterprise plans include complementary family plans.
So that's a great way to extend security not only to your entire organization, but also
to your team members, your coworkers at home.
So if you haven't advocated for Bitwarden at your organization yet, that might be a
great direction to go and send them to Bitwarden dot com slash Linux.
It's the easiest way to store, share and sync your sensitive data.
And Bitwarden is open source.
It's trusted by millions of us in the community.
It's what Wes and I use all the time.
I'm using it now for my two factor codes as well, which makes that so much more reliable
for me, especially the way I move machines.
You can use it for other sensitive data, too, like account recovery keys or other types
of secrets that either want to store in one secure central place that you can trust or
also something maybe like a secret you might need to share with a team member or a friend
or a family member at some point or a spouse.
Bitwarden is fantastic for that while not messing up your whole OPSEC, as they say.
And the mobile clients have made it really feasible to have secure passwords, unique
user names and unique email addresses for every site, service or even app you use, which
is fantastic since I'm moving between my desktop and my mobile devices all the time.
And Bitwarden is rolling out features every single month, including they just recently
rolled out DuckDuckGo email aliasing, support for fast mails, email alias, password protected
encrypted exports.
I love to see them working more with DuckDuckGo, too.
I think that's a real positive sign.
So go try it out for free right now by going to bitwarden.com slash Linux.
You sign up there or if you've already taken care of this, and I hope you have because
a password manager and something like Bitwarden that can help you store your secrets and all
your sensitive data very securely that you can trust, that's just an absolute critical
tool for staying safe and secure online.
So I hope you already know about this.
You probably do, but I bet you have a friend or a family member.
Maybe it's Brent.
Maybe it's somewhere you work.
I don't know.
Maybe they need a little convincing.
So have them go try it, bitwarden.com slash Linux.
It's good for you.
It's good for the internet.
It's true, too, bitwarden.com slash Linux.
As always, we got some great feedback this week, but we do have a special little something
from listener Jeff.
Let's just call it a geocache update for the Folsom location.
Captain, I am on location at the Sacramento geocache.
It is missing.
I repeat, missing.
Abort the search.
It is no longer here.
It has been found.
Data conclusive.
Thank you, Jeff.
So of course, for those of you who just need to be caught up is Chris was right all along.
Folsom was one of our first successful, maybe the second successful geocache that was found
by an audience member.
That's clearly what happened.
And Jeff went on location to verify and he confirmed via visual data that the Folsom
Linux Unplugged cache has been discovered, like I knew all along.
Like I knew all along.
But there was kind of another kind of funny coincidence while he was there, Brent.
Yeah, he ran into listener Jared again and his family, and that's the second time that
happens at that particular location, which I think is super fun.
That is so great.
Jeff mentioned that listener Jared's daughter, I think, or son ran up one of the kids.
Are you looking for the JB geocache?
That's adorable.
Second time that happens.
So good.
I mean, if you're going to meet strangers in the woods, I would hope they're fans.
I think we got to do more of these.
We should have given Jeff a geocache.
We need it.
You know, oh, oh, what we need are geocache bundles that we can mail out to listeners
that they could stash in their general area.
Now you're talking.
That's what we need to do.
I bet the listeners will be way better at hiding geocaches than we are.
Yeah.
So what we could do is we could have somebody email into the show and let us know if you
want to do this.
See if anybody's interested.
And what we could do is we'd basically send you a little Tupperware container full of
swag that you hide in your area, then you've got to send us video of you like kind of in
the area hiding it.
But we don't want to give away the location exactly.
So you just give us a little narration of where it's at.
You know, this is what you'd have to do if you want to participate in it.
So that way we can play the clip to give people a hint.
Got to craft your clue.
You got to craft a clue and then let us know.
And we could send a few of these out.
I think.
Oh, it's great to know I was right about the Folsom cache.
That's good.
We got some mail this week.
Benjamin wrote in about Jupiter.tube and I think he's looking for some peers.
He writes, for me over here in the UK, I rarely see more than two peers, usually one and I
get about 15k down if I'm lucky during live streams.
So it's usually a two seconds of video playback, a minute or so of buffering and just repeat
that cycle.
None of the other RTMP, RTSP or radio streams seem to work for me either.
So I rely on the YouTube streams for the most part.
I can, however, watch the published stream the next day without any problems from Jupiter
Tube.
So just not when it's live.
Well, now that is interesting.
Yeah.
Strange.
Now that's a curveball.
You're able to pull data from that server.
How does that make any sense?
Because when it's live, it's doing a web torrent from that server anyways.
So it's still coming from the server if there's no peers.
So how does that make any sense?
Yeah.
And it should just grab that HLS files at the end of the day, right?
This feels to me like one of those pieces of mail that gets us trying to figure out
a problem that we didn't know existed because we've had listeners, especially in the mumble
room, who have used Jupiter Tube while we're live for the most part.
And it's not, you know, we've had to add a peer or two, but it's for the most part, I
think working.
Yeah.
So it would be nice to have more people kind of taking us up on the Jupiter Tube peering
stuff.
I understand it's tricky because in some circumstances, YouTube or Twitch just works better or it's
what you have an app for or whatever.
But you know, these self-hosted open source platforms are only as successful as the user
base for them.
And it's like if anybody's going to use them, it's probably going to be us.
So we should try to actually be there to be customers for these things and demonstrate
a demand.
And we could use more people peering.
But the other thing that I think is doable, and maybe somebody out there knows the way,
we've gotten close, is a way to essentially set up our own peers, like maybe a headless
Linode that we deploy somewhere in the world that's just adding a peer over there.
And it's not just as simple as a web torrent.
It is also, so a peer tube, it uses torrents to distribute the HLS files and it uses WebRTC
to communicate something in some data channel.
So you have to have a WebRTC communications channel as well.
And there is an Electron app there that does seeding and does the WebRTC stuff.
You can't run that headless.
Maybe we can.
Anyways, if people out there have tips for us or want to just participate...
But we need to update it with each new live stream too, huh?
Jupyter.tube though, that's our per tube instance where we video stream the recording of our
shows and then we archive them over there for playback if people would like.
Noah also wrote in with a potential Odroid killer, he says, what do you guys think of
this particular single board computer?
As Intel NICs, six serial ATA ports, doesn't quite have RAID support, but might just be
an option for JB.
The N5105 or the N6005 NAS board, it does look really good.
You know what is nice is it's Intel NICs and way more SATA.
Six?
Yeah.
That's pretty sweet.
So the base price is $195 US greenbacks, then it looks like it goes up to about $480 depending
on when you buy it and what you spec it with.
Yeah, you can either get a Celeron N5105 or Pentium N6005.
It's got NVMe.
That looks good.
DDR4.
Lots of SATA.
It's got dual M.2s, looks like.
Man, how many USB ports does this freaking thing have too or whatever?
There's just a ton of ports on this thing.
Yeah, this looks really nice.
This is always the problem, is there's always so many options and this came up with the
Raspberry Pi too.
As soon as you mentioned you got a Raspberry Pi, there's like, oh, have you tried this?
And sometimes it's like there are better ones and this could be a better one.
And then sometimes you want to get behind the one that has a bit of an ecosystem.
Do you have opt case option, what's the form factor?
What do you know about the manufacturer, are they going to stick around?
Yeah.
Ugh.
It's hard.
This is a hard choice to make.
And we're not even done yet because we want to replace a couple machines here in the studio
too.
We don't want big computers.
I think we've got to crowdsource it, right?
People just got to start buying these things and let us know.
Yeah.
We just have people buy a whole bunch of different ones and we can all run the Ferronics test
suite on them, get a big comparison suite going.
Well, I think to add one more to the pile, Matthew also wrote in just about at the same
time and suggested a Nexcom mini PC.
He writes, Chris has been talking about that Odroid on Linux Unplugged and Cellposi quite
a bit, and I wanted to suggest the Nexcom devices.
They're an industrial, mostly fanless x86 platform for a variety of applications.
In particular, I use the Nexcom NDIS device.
It's meant to be a signage player, but I use the device as a fanless application server
running Ubuntu server, and I love the thing.
Mine is an i5 base PC and it's gone as far as testing 4k Plex trans codes and it handles
a couple of the trans codes at the same time without issue.
Praise QuickSync.
The device can be had on eBay relatively cheaply.
You should give them a gander.
All right.
Jeez.
Yeah.
This is the way if you ever want to find out what's really great out there, you buy something,
get really hyped about it, and then you'll discover all the other options.
But some of these are really cool.
I dig the built-in heatsink and the mounts and the DC power.
Oh, man, that's checking a box.
We could just screw that onto the back of you.
I feel like we almost need a tiny PC library.
You can just check one out for a week or two, give it a try.
I am really enjoying the small, low-power PC.
It's one thing to just get a crazy fast...
I mean, that's great.
I absolutely love that too, but there's just something about these that are just enough
machine.
Just enough machine, not drawing too much power, which is another big thing for me.
I feel like there's a big future in playing around with that kind of hardware and seeing
how much Linux you can get.
You're just going to try to fill all of your places with as many tiny little PCs now, aren't
you?
Yeah, man.
Yeah.
I mean, why have big computers when you can have lots of small, little computers?
That's my thinking there, right?
Swarm, swarm.
Booster Graham.
All right.
We got some big old boosts into the show this week that we want to cover.
And then I kind of also want to talk about, just as an aside, this whole FTX situation.
If you're curious what's going on there, why this whole Bitcoin casino crashed around them,
we just published an episode of the Bitcoin Dad Pod.
And you can find that at bitcoindadpod.fireside.fm and it's slash episode 50, so slash 50.
Effective scam tourism.
And we break it all down in plain English.
What's going on there?
Why the price of Bitcoin goes down with it, which is essentially people have to sell to
cover their positions.
It turns out that FTX was sitting on two Bitcoin, so they didn't have a lot of Bitcoin.
They were mostly dealing around with these scam coins.
But if you have questions or you'd just like to know a recap that's just a common sense
recap, go check it out in episode 50 of the Bitcoin Dad Pod.
And then we get to, I think it's going to be Mentat, I think, I don't know if I have
that right, but we're going to go with the Mentat.
And Mentat sends in a row of ducks, 2222.
Since you guys started talking about the shift in podcast advertising, I have noticed several
podcasts and podcast networks I listened to doubling or even tripling up on ads, as well
as starting up membership subscriptions at the same time.
Man, that's rough.
I hope that this goes smoothly.
I've been following the financial news of some of the big podcast sponsors in this space
and they are having a rough time of it, the tech sector in general.
So I think it is, if there's a podcast out there that you really like and you've been
considering joining the membership, it might be time to consider because I think some of
these podcasters are probably panicking.
If I were trying to get a membership program launched right now, I would be in like, you
know, disaster mode.
It'd be really scary.
I'm so grateful for our members because they really, it's like, that's how we know our
ongoing production is covered.
We may have to make big changes, but like the shows will continue.
And that's, you know, the members are like the insurance program for that.
And I'm very, very grateful, especially now.
Marcel boosts in with some enterprise at 1701.
As a one-off during a busy week, I think I actually would listen to a fully AI generated
show.
I think it'd actually be pretty good, but I don't think I'd want it every week.
Well, that'll be if you can tell.
That would be the benchmark, I think.
I think an AI generated show would only make sense for like a holiday show where you're
trying to do essentially like a best of, but from new content generated from the old content.
And you'd have to have like editorial control and it would take so much more work than just
doing a show.
Would we be able to generate the whole thing where we have to like sort of edit together
some of the stuff that did pop out?
Would this part be generated?
How do you have that?
How does the AI know how to give Chris enough sass?
That's finally tuned.
Yeah.
You really got to figure it out.
So, well, it's going to be a couple of years at least.
And then Rusticastroversa came in with a row of ducks.
And just simply says, boost!
B-O-O-S-T.
412 Linux boosts in with 2,048 sets.
Regarding packaging on distributions, Ubuntu MATE enabled Flatpak along with Snaps in 2204.
This has been a fantastic experience for me.
Initially, I found it beneficial to quickly switch Firefox from Snap to Flatpak.
Now I can use whatever packaging system works best for the application I am installing.
The Ubuntu MATE team have made this easy.
It's a really underappreciated feature.
That is nice.
Flatpaks on an Ubuntu system out of the box, that's just giving your users what they need
and want.
You got to respect that.
Yeah.
And then I think to 412's point too, it's like, well, maybe, you know, if you're already
sold on some Snaps, maybe you're doing the next Cloud Snap, whatever, like, you know,
you've got best of all them worlds.
The facial hair boosts in with 6,000 cents.
Boost!
I recall Chris mentioned he got his hands on a popcorn pocket PC.
I was wondering, what ever happened to it?
Well, we have it in-house and I kind of fire it up from time to time.
I dust off and I play around and see how things are.
This is one of those things that's tricky to talk about on air because it's got a lot
of promise, but it isn't quite there yet.
There's not a firmware that is really, like, I could just say, hey, go grab this and throw
this firmware.
Right.
And I don't want to come on air and talk negatively about it and sort of undercut any progress.
But at the same time, there's nothing really to say that's positive yet.
So I'm kind of in a waiting phase and I have been for a long time.
Hasn't found its way actually, like, into your life in a meaningful way yet.
Yeah.
So if you're not familiar with the popcorn computer, it's about the size of a Game Boy,
a little a little wider and it's got a full QWERTY keyboard, LCD screen, some USB-C ports
and yeah, it's supposed to run Linux and you grab a, you know, you grab a video out port
and you could hook it up and now you got a full computer and you disconnect it and you're
just walking around with a little tiny five inch screen kind of a thing.
But so far, so far, I have not really found the firmware that really brings it home.
But I'm keeping an eye out there.
So if anybody out there wants an update or you hear something, maybe I missed it, shoot
me a shoot me a boost or shoot me an email or something, let me know and I'll I'll give
it a go again.
Now we got quite a bit of feedback about Mastodon, we got a bunch of boosts in and we also got
a bunch of plus ones via, you know, the old email, Tekov 751 specifically boosted it in
with a mini row of ducks, 222 sats.
I tried to build out a smaller Mastodon server for a small community of 50 or so people.
Later though, I had to kill it in the beta trial.
It was obvious that even if it was really to put hours and automation into place, it
was just going to be too much.
The instance needs a load of resources, mostly for storage.
And the bigger issue is that massive moderation is required, at least a couple of people with
good moral compass to make it happen.
Yeah, there's, there's that whole element of having to manage that whenever you run
a community thing.
But I, I was wondering about what it is to run a Mastodon instance on the backend because
my experience with matrix is that the federation aspect actually is quite a bit of traffic.
And if you're, if you're following people across multiple instances, your home server
has to be pulling all of that in and subscribing to that on activity pub, I would imagine.
And so if you have hundreds or thousands of users that are doing that across multiple
servers, the backend has got to be managing all of that.
It's got to be quite the load.
Actually I would think to run a Mastodon server.
Maybe I'm wrong.
Maybe it's simpler than I'm picturing because I'm basing my experience on matrix, which
it, this is, this is a pretty big amount of data with matrix, but I, uh, I'd love any
insight people have from running a Mastodon instance.
Not that I'm thinking about doing it or Cinemotev also boosted in with 2048 sats, another plug
for Mastodon.
I never use the JB matrix due to chat and being, having to be there live.
I hang out one to two times a week and when I do, I just never know what's going on.
That's fair.
I hear, I hear a call for that in that same vein for a, you know, a discourse or something.
A place for offline chatting.
Yeah.
We also got a thousand sats from OP 1984, just a plus one for Mastodon.
Uh, just moved to Pontiacindex.social and already follow Chris there.
Hey Chris, you have followers already.
That's nice.
How about that?
Oh gosh.
Where he talks about that podcasting 2.0 nonsense.
And another 128 sats from Paul Asteluk who says, can JB set up a social network that
keeps me social?
So far you're, so far you're batting a thousand with your recommendations.
I'm still on matrix admittedly only in JB general chat.
Great show as always.
Thank you.
He also tosses a few sats for, uh, well, Chris, how am I supposed to read this?
I don't know.
Jif.
Yeah, but isn't that supposed to be a vote for how to, it's supposed to be a vote for
how to say it, but it just is written.
So I don't know how anybody's, how is, you know, I don't know how anybody's supposed
to know.
Cause when you're reading it, it's hard to tell.
This is part of the problem with the whole, the whole Jif gift thing.
Maybe this is a meta vote for a better name.
I mean, I don't know how anybody's going to beat Wise Papa John.
He put 40,000 sats behind a hard G. So somebody's, I mean, until somebody surpasses that, then
officially on the show, it has a hard G and that's how it is.
Yeah.
Boost decided, I guess.
Awesome.
Matt wrote in with 69, 69 sats as a boost, I haven't really used Macedon, but I've used
Pleroma.
Have you guys used Pleroma?
I haven't even heard of it actually.
Heard of it?
A lightweight Fediverse server.
Never used it.
I've actually kind of heard disparaging things about it, but whenever a technology gets cast
in one way or another, I always think, well, is it the technology or is it the people or
is it just marketing?
But it looks like a leaner, lighter Mastodon essentially.
Let's you participate in the Fediverse, but just as a little cleaner, maybe, maybe simpler
to implement on the back end as well.
Maybe a little more suited for a smaller group.
Tire boosts in with 2,023 sats, a little future boost.
I predict that JB will start its own Mastodon server in 2023.
I'm calling it.
I know how Chris thinks.
The seed has been planted.
Hey, that's our first 2023 boost.
Nice.
All right.
Future prediction there.
So a Mastodon instance in 2023.
Viridian boosts in with another 1,701 Satoshis.
I assume it's in reference to Viridian 3.
I mean, it must be, right?
Your discussion about signal was poignant, as I've been eyeing alternatives.
The lack of support for CarPlay, backups, and HTTP proxies, along with the devs' attitude,
make it abrasive.
WhatsApp solves all of these issues, but meta.
I hadn't considered switching the family to Matrix.
Intriguing, but as far as I know, no clients support CarPlay.
I'm also concerned about not being able to move accounts between home servers.
Any suggestions?
Otherwise, I'll just keep waiting for the one chat app.
For the one.
I've been giving more thought to the Matrix one.
I've been really kind of considering if I were to move the whole family to another chat
platform.
My first thought actually was, maybe I'll just stand up an XMPP server.
And that feels like a great idea until you think, yeah, but all the clients, they're
not really as featureful now.
And then that's a real challenge because I think your family now expects stickers and
emoji reactions and all that stuff.
And while Matrix doesn't have all of the things that those apps do, it adds more stuff that
people expect in a feature set.
So I think that's another plus one for moving this family to a private Matrix instance.
I think the question just becomes, which app?
Which front end?
And that might take a little experimentation.
Dreams Void boosts in the row of duck.
I'm a duck, D-U-K, duck, loaded with talent.
Something profound.
I'm finally caught up with luck now.
On to Office Hours episode 9, South Posted episode 81, and LAN episode 259.
That's nice.
Nice.
I wondered, were you on a road trip?
Yeah.
Did you go through a tear?
What happened?
Got all caught up.
Been out for a while?
It's nice.
Welcome.
Couldn't sleep at night.
Nice to have you here.
Whatever the reason, keep it up.
We're just in with 3,141 sats.
Well as the influencer that inspired me to buy my own Raspberry Pi, I'm saddened to hear
you've moved on.
I'm also saddened that I now have a new toy that I desire.
Yeah, we're all feeling that.
Don't worry.
Feel free to ship me all your unused pies.
I'll throw them in my Micro K8s cluster.
You know, I wonder, I'm not really, I guess I actually do have a couple that are not currently
in use, but I don't imagine I'll stop using the Raspberry Pis.
I just don't know if I'm going to buy any more Pi 4s, although I did hear some rumors
that there's some new Pi hardware we're going to get teased with.
You know, for me, if they didn't have a huge increase in CPU performance on the Pi, if
they just had a moderate CPU increase and a moderate memory increase, but had a big
increase on storage in terms of IO, not size, I think that would put the Pi in contender
category again.
I mean, it's nice being on x86 again.
There is that whole element as well.
But we'll see.
We'll see.
Maybe we'll get a tease.
Soham boosted in live last week with a row of ducks.
Thank you kindly.
And it was a live boost.
So that's pretty neat.
But what is even more rad about it is he used Boost CLI.
You delightful nerd.
That's pretty awesome.
And he says Nix is the greatest package manager ever created.
That may be true.
We will have to have someone confirm that.
We'll put somebody on that.
Truly there's research going on.
And then our last boost this week came in from JPC, who sent us a row of Grandpa Ducks
22,222 SATs.
This old duck still got it.
He says he loves the show and he's also using Boost CLI.
Well, well done JPC.
Thank you everyone for the support.
We really appreciate it.
We still love the SATs.
SATs are SATs to us.
So grab a handful on the cheap using something like Strike or the Cash App.
If you're outside the US, Blue Wallet.
I really like RoboSats too if you want to get really geeky, but then you got to have
Tor Browser.
I'm imagining if we had like a fancy like downtown SF, JB office or whatever, we could
have like a little Boost CLI terminal set up and ready to go.
It's got like retro term on there, right?
Like you're just, oh man, try your first boost.
Retro term or just a really old CRT.
Yeah.
Could go, you know, go clacky IBM PS2 keyboard as well.
Someday with enough boosts we'll get there.
That would be pretty neat.
That would be.
Yes.
We got some boost into the show, newpodcastapps.com.
That's where you go to upgrade to a podcasting 2.0 app.
We got more in the works there too, as far as podcasting 2.0 features.
So go check out Office Hours 16, where we talk about some of that stuff we'll be working
on.
Also just a random shout out because we got some boost in that we don't make it on the
show, but we still just wanted to pick a handful to say thank you and thank you everybody else
if we didn't call out your name or read your message, we still got it and we really appreciate
your support.
I wanted to do this one because let's see if I got this right.
Let me know if I got your name right.
One thousand sats from Firghazballs, something like that.
Is this deep fake, Chris?
We got a hundred sats from TheBooch asking about our thoughts on signal adding stories,
which is actually Office Hours as well as that.
So go check out Office Hours 16 for that, TheBooch.
And then Oppie1984 says that it's GIF, GIF is peanut butter.
Well you're gonna have to send in more than a hundred and sats, buddy.
And then NachoLinux sent a row of sticks.
He says I cranked through my Fountain FM subscriptions to earn some sats so I could boost in.
Oh, thank you.
That's very awesome.
Thank you everybody.
And we appreciate the members out there too who support the show.
They invest in our ongoing production, UnpluggedCore.com if you want to become a member of this show
or Jupiter.party if you want all the shows.
And as a thank you, we give it to you ad-free.
And we also package up the live stream and we make it available to you.
We put lots of extra content in there.
Sometimes too much.
Jeff, who went out on location to, you know, look at the Folsom Geocache, specifically
left the live show, The Mumble Room, today.
So that way he could listen to the live stream while he's road tripping.
That's a thing.
At the meetups, some of the listeners that drove quite a ways to make it to the meetups
were like, yeah, I just listened to the live version on the way up here.
It kills like, you know, a few hours.
Sometimes it is that long.
You know, there's only so much content in a week and the more the better.
Yeah, it's pretty wild.
Links to what we talked about today and all that kind of stuff are over at LinuxUnplugged.com
slash 484.
Is that where we're at?
484.
You heard our Mumble Room.
We got a Mumble Room.
It's over there if you'd like to join it.
It's a great way to listen in real time or participate in the show if something strikes
your fancy.
We have details for that at JupiterBroadcasting.com.
Find the Mumble stuff.
It's a slash mumble.
Same with the Matrix details.
And yeah, shout out to our buddy Carl George who got the latest and greatest mumble packaged
up in Fedora 37.
So you know, PipeWire, mumble, it's a great setup to join the show.
All I'm saying.
Yep.
If you're going to upgrade, might as well upgrade in style and go mumble with PipeWire.
You know what else?
Speaking of adding PipeWire support, as we record today, a new version of MPV is out
that has a PipeWire back in too.
Mm-hmm.
Loving that MPV.
I'm glad we gave it a mention today because we just don't talk about it enough.
And then last but not least, if you're not doing anything on your Sunday and you want
to hang out with your Linux buddies, head over to Jupiter.tube around noon Pacific three
p.m.
Eastern and, you know, watch the show.
We stream it live over there and you can see how handsome Brent is.
See how we make the sausage.
Here are all our mistakes.
Noon Pacific three p.m.
Eastern Jupiter.tube.
See you next week.
Same bad time.
Same bad station.
All right, gentlemen.
Did we do it?
Is that it?
I don't know if any of us are.
I don't know if any of us are sticking with Fedora 37 after this.
I don't think I am.
I might give Fedora 36 a go.
Yeah, I got to go fix Fedora 36.
Right?
I'm going to see how long it sticks.
I'm not going to get rid of it like.
Yeah.
Right away.
We'll see.
I am really enjoying this gnome.
So it is nice.
They are doing great.
Don't miss Linux Action News.
There's more at LinuxActionNews.com.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Unplugged program.
And we'll see you right back here next Sunday.
Minimac, you had a question, though, during the deepfake.
Yeah, I want to learn something today.
So the idea is, how does it work?
I try to imagine how it works.
Like you have a lot of episodes and then first you have to define the voice patterns.
So this is Chris, this is Brent, this is Wes.
Once the AI has recognized these voice patterns, you can probably pass other love episodes
and just let them separate the voice strings.
I would think it's more like he has to cut me out and just only supply it with my cuts.
So maybe we will have an answer afterwards.
Then I would probably you will have to pass a voice to text pattern to have a text database
with the words, like on the bottom you have a database with like 50 is and if the home
and I don't know what, then probably if that is possible, I will try to level that thing
so that the is is always like the same kind.
And once you have like if you have 50 times the same words so that that AI engine could
level it so it would define Chris normally uses the bird home like this and then once
you have it leveled, then you can start to make some sentences.
Well I use the tool, it's actually developed originally by Mozilla.
It's called Koki, C-O-Q-U-I and the way it works actually is you you feed it lots of
samples, generally between one second and up to 10 seconds.
That really depends on your training hardware.
I have a RTX Titan that I use for training.
And so with 24 gigs, you kind of top out at about 10 seconds with what did I use batch
size of I believe I use 48 samples per batch and what you do is you you get as many samples
as you can and what I did was a very painstaking process.
I went through a whole bunch of episodes including LUP, Coder and SSH and I manually went and
found clips of Chris speaking.
I got about 48 minutes worth, broke it up into various clips, then I ran a speech to
text parser over all of it, then I re-listened to everything just to ensure that the transcoded
text is correct and then that gets fed into the AI trainer and then as it goes along it
spits out the model after various steps and then you use that model to then you just feed
it a line of text to work out.
The problem is I just did not have the time or patience to get any more audio.
Already a lot.
48 minutes is way too low.
You need minimum 2-3 hours.
Some of the larger data sets that actually are used to build these text-to-speech models
are in the range of 20 plus hours worth.
So if I had the time and I went through all of the back catalogue of the shows of Chris
talking I could probably build a very comprehensible model.
I would not wish that on anyone.
Don't do that.
A JB intern.
So if you had some snippets of Chris reading some text, like some pages of text, it would
be much easier.
Right now you have to really cut the speech pieces of Chris from the show and feed it
manually.
Yeah, exactly.
I think really you just need a few topics that Chris can rant about on his soapbox and
then you've got enough content right there.
It's a great point because you actually need a variety of phenoms, I think is that the
right word?
Basically the individual parts of words.
You need a large range of that for the AI to be able to learn how the individual speaker
says that to then be able to reproduce it.
Yeah, if you don't have enough variability in the base set.
In the clip I generated, I didn't write one million sats, I wrote 900,000 sats because
none of the clips I had pulled out had Chris saying the word million.
So whenever I tried actually doing a million in the generated speech, it just sounded kind
of garbled.
It didn't actually make sense.
Very interesting.
Thank you for the information.
And to actually just put a finer point on it, if you've seen the show Kenobi, the voice
of Darth Vader was not actually voiced by James Earl Jones.
That was actually the same thing.
It was an AI generated model that they had built from James Earl Jones's voice.
And I don't know if you've seen the news, but he has signed basically, I'm not sure
what it's called, but basically a perpetual permission for Disney to now use his likeness,
his voice for Darth Vader going forward.
So going forward, any appearances of Darth Vader are going to be AI generated voices,
not James Earl himself recording it.
Yeah, I've read an article about that.
You know, CB, it strikes me too that like, say we were serious about ever doing something
like this.
One thing that if you were working with JB, like we have stems of just my track to a degree,
we don't have like a lot of them, but we have probably weeks worth of just my track in the
episodes too, which would probably make it easier, I would think to sample from, because
then you could just drop the silences and essentially just have...
It would be incredibly easier if someone had just handed me these pristine audio files
with nothing else mixed in.
Because I had to cut past some of the other speakers and over speaking and someone using
the soundboard, yeah, soundboard mixed in, yeah, that's absolutely true.
Absolutely.
Would the Mozilla organization feed some example text that makes it easier?
Because if they're working on that, it would be also cool if they hand out some example
text that someone could read and somehow you get really a good sample of the voice.
Like a script that helps train it a little bit.
That's true too.
But for example, even doing some of the visual deepfakes, so deepfaking a person's face,
if you're trying to get, trying to do it of a celebrity, for whatever reason, it's harder
to find all the different angles and the different movements of the mouth and the expressions.
However, if you're doing it yourself, you want to deepfake yourself or you're doing
it for a movie or whatever, you basically stand somebody in front of a camera and you
have them, I don't know what they're called, but there is these phrases that you can say
that force the speaker to move their mouth in a particular pattern.
And to capture that.
Exactly.
And the same thing with doing the audio.
If you had a script, you have a variety of words, something that forces the voice to
do the expressions and the different ranges that you would normally say in regular conversation.
Now read it again as a prospector.
Yeah.
Give me the prospector voice.
You got to get all the different iterations and you got to make sure you capture all of
the terms that we use a lot, ZFS, Linux, you know, that kind of stuff.
It actually did pretty well with all that stuff.
Did it?
I was going to ask you, how does it handle those kinds of terms?
Is it just, is it just because I say it and so it just learns it?
Well, yes, because you say it, but also because when it does the learning, it doesn't learn
individual words.
It learns the little, the parts of the words, right?
So you say ZFS or zebra, you still have that sound in there that it's going to learn and
then piece it together.