have you got any feedback from for the Leonard interview to read out on the
show you know not really not to read on the show because I was in one of the
debbie and for I was lurking one of the debbie and fork IRC channels was a guy
in there who was saying who's ranting a little bit about yeah yeah obviously and
wanted to come on and you know I said well you know come on the mumble and if
there's any feedback I'm sure you can you know get involved yeah I mean I I
know that we must have I wonder too if maybe people just kind of given up that
are really anti system D because I'm sure there was a whole there's more than
one debbie and fork yes what you mean it wasn't it doesn't have more than one
debbie that one is more there's another one there's def one in depth to yeah
really I actually didn't really I didn't know that how come I ever heard what's
it called poppy I let me just go and find it to me anything that's derived
from debbie and there's a fork of debbie and to me refactor now we refactor
refractor refactor can you link it in the in that there IRC hang on this is
so this project hasn't been getting as much of attention I wonder why that is
maybe because they didn't use the inflammatory language it's the other one
the Linux that you get oops I just pasted far too much in the IRC that's
actually the topic from the debbie and fork channel where they link to the
other debbie and the various debbie and folks including dead one refractor and
also on XE canoe so this is there's two so there's three three there is three
debbie and forks Wow burnout squared brilliant yeah so how is this gonna play
out I mean how can this can they really do they genuinely mean like the full
debbie and project fork when they say this or they just mean like the x86
derivatives that is there's no way they can for call debbie and there simply is
not enough people out there to go in to do it there's barely enough people to do
debbie it's well and there's three of them people to do one fork it's a three
forks I think it's a bit of overkill guest forking DB and why don't we just
make a diss why don't we guess make something else out even just by
removing system the inputting I guess it's not really they just don't want to
be tied on to a way of doing things that's why they're calling themselves
for for now they're a derived distribution until they get to the point
that okay it seems that Debian is going too far off and we are not tied to it
and so it's better to call it a fork from the beginning not get the flame
later on I yeah I guess it's also a mindset thing but yeah technically right
now what they're gonna copy them they're gonna copy everything and then just
start working to not integrate systems it's okay yeah I mean I mean there's
things like they need to find a replacement for login D and they need to
undo all the packaging that integrates system D into gnome for example and then
and then remove whatever else feature wise that system D does is saying that
they actually will try to maintain compatibility with the main Debian thing
because it not only will facilitate their work but also if Debian once
probably be able to reassess that back no so this now I guess is the time
isn't it because you got to do it now before system D has been so fully
integrated into Debian that it would be a huge chore to work it out so now is
the time to make your move what about a year ago would have been is everybody
totally freaking out about this Linux Trojan it's it's horrible right have you
guys all read about it it's on like every single news website ever right
now yeah until we know what that vector I'm not really caring it's terrifying
it's horrible it's infecting what I guess something it looks like it's
probably it looks like it's probably been around for a few years I mean it
does it it's also they're calling it an advanced persistent threat it looks like
it's targeted at government embassies pharmaceutical companies maybe even even
the code could even be 14 years old as OMG Ubuntu notes infected hundreds of
PCs on the Windows version across 45 countries something yeah yeah I have a
feeling this even though people are going on now it's not safe but it states
something I actually think this time it is actually states a state sponsored
because you have the money and the time to port a virus to nearly every single
major platform yeah yeah ever and the thing you have to realize is like it's
not just the NSA that does this stuff a lot of different divisions of the US
military have a cyber arm to them and they have people that work on this stuff
but in the terms of like the NSA what they have that tailored access division
and their entire purpose is to identify the technology that the target is
employing and adapt malware to compromise that system that is a
tailored malware even you think Stuxnet wasn't specifically tailored to go after
those centrifuges give me a break so if the if the system is running Linux or
free BSD or Mac OS 10 or Windows they're gonna take advantage of every zero-day
exploit they could possibly find and they're gonna tailor write something for
it and even here it sounds like it is from some of the speculation it sounds
like it jumps machines like it actually still comes in on a Windows box and then
jumps to up to the Linux box I think this kind of stuff is gonna be really
common well they're only getting to know it's not like they didn't exist right
not to mention it's like until we know the actual attack factor it doesn't mean
anything like for all that matter you might need a specific software to be
running so you can actually get infected in the first place so it can actually
leverage the permission issue yeah that point yeah and you know there's now see
and the reason why I think we hear about this more is it just makes it makes
better headlines now and the press has learned how to write about it in a way
that generates clicks but also outside of that there's just entire companies
now that were not really so focused on this like a lot of this came from work
from Kaspersky labs right you can find a lot of details on the Kaspersky labs
blog well this has now become a huge huge huge aspect of their business they
spend a lot of time and resources on so they're exposing a lot more of this kind
of stuff kids and kitty you said you had something you wanted to add yeah back in
my day Trojans used to protect you from a virus
welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show from a very windy
Pacific Northwest my name is Chris and my name is Matt hey Matt so is the wind
still blowing up in your area I'm getting some gusts you know I took the
dogs out here earlier they didn't blow away so I think we're doing okay I like
that you go out there and you get blown around a little bit and I thought so you
send me this message you're like hey so we still have power up here I'm like oh
I guess you're like congratulations you paid your bill it's stormy like oh yeah
no I figured you meant it was stormy but then I'm thinking to myself that either means
it's gonna come down here or we could go the other way but no a little bit later
it started blowing down here like crazy it's one of those where it blew over the
trash can so I go out in the front yard I pick up the trash because I don't want
the I don't want the studio to look like we're slumming it right so I got there I
pick up the trash can I come back in the wind trolls me blows the trash can over
again well you don't want the studio to look like it's one of those 24-hour news
networks right you want to have a little class here right looking like CNN up in
this business exactly well coming up in this week's episode fedora 21 ship today
Matthew Miller the fedora project lead joins us he talks about the process they
went to to transition to this new multi spin version of fedora also I asked him
to comment on the rumor that fedora is switching to a tick-tock release cycle
and then we also probing for some details and features coming up in fedora 22 so
that's coming up by a little bit in the show also later in the show
Ubuntu snappy core was released today Ubuntu snapper and I'll tell you right
up front it's not for the desktop but I want it on my desktop we're gonna talk
about what snappy is where you can get it what you need to know about it and
where you can find out more information very soon on your local Jupiter
broadcasting network but Matt yes before we get to all that we got to get to some
of our feedback and get going on some of that good stuff we we have a lot of
stuff to cover we have a really great showing in the mumble room today I'm
gonna bring them in here in just a second but before we do that I think
I'll just give like my last emergency plea we are looking for your best of
submissions for Jupiter broadcasting mace mostly kota radio and Linux
unplugged and tech snap at this point last ones are fine too but we got a
whole bunch of those because we want to give the host of the Christmas week off
so that way they can just sit back and relax but we can still have some new
shows with some new content some extra stuff in there and also you give you
guys something you can hand out to folks and say yeah go check out this episode
sort of cover some of their best of stuff but we need your submissions
because it's a lot to go through when you have a back catalog as much as we
do so I have a link in the show notes and it's our Jupiter broadcasting best
of submission form we just need the episode title a link to the episode the
time about when it happens and why you liked it in description any other info
you want to give us to help out the network we have a whole bunch of
hardware stuff and software changes going on during that week so the
downtime is gonna be used really well too and I'll be putting out more
information about that on the tech talk today patreon feed okay Matt well let's
get into feedback but before we do that we should say hello and time appropriate
greetings to our awesome mumble room time appropriate greetings guys
well we got a great showing today a lot of you I think there's like 300 people
in there not really no I would I think that would crush our server all right
Ubuntu addicted writes in with our first bit of mail and he says my ancient
original Apple TV runs crystal Ubuntu 2.0 crystal Ubuntu was developed by Sam
Nazarocko the same person who brought who brought the world Razz BMC okay
great crystal Ubuntu is based on Ubuntu 12 before which auto launches XBMC
Gotham so I love the show by the way you inspired me to spread Linux and open
source to the masses and he says keep up the great work so Matt he submitted a
photo here boy look at that zoom holy smokes here it is I'm triangulating now
he's got an old old Apple TV like the first gen oh yeah running this crystal
Ubuntu spin that goes right into XBMC this got me thinking though looking at
the setup I remember you and I kind of talking about hacking the Apple TV like
it was something like that you know hey you know you could do this this this is
a decent little device you could put XBMC on that was sort of like at the
beginning of 2014 and I'm curious for you if now here we are at the end of 2014
has the Roku killed the XBMC dream for you have you just gone Roku and and
called it a day well so I guess you gotta back up a little bit and realize
that you know I've others in the house that really don't care about the
geekiness of an XBMC setup so for me you know Roku has just been kind of a
natural fit for us it just does the job that will probably change as we explore
new things coming out but at this time yeah yeah for me it was Roku plus plex
yeah exactly it gave me a couple of gave me like three critical things like you
said it had the spousal approval factor which was very high and that remote is
great it's like it's like on the level of Tivo great it's a really good remote
and if you get the Roku 3 it's got the headphone plug so there was that a
spousal approval factor way high plus the price is good I'm gonna include that
in spousal approval factor the other two things though were that plex integration
which gave me resuming play play out playback and centralized metadata for all
of my content very easily and then the third and very important piece was is my
kids can operate it the Roku and the plex together it's simple enough where
it's very it's just straightforward you get in and they can use it and from three
to five they're able to operate this Roku player with with you know full
fluency whereas I that might be possible it probably would be possible with an
XBMC I feel like the simple nature of the Roku though made it more of a
possibility Popey what are your thoughts um I don't know I I would love to have
an XBMC box but actually I've been using a Chromecast a lot and a bit of popcorn
time now and then and I I can't motivate myself to build an XBMC box out of
anything really yeah that might be part of what it is too is like things like
the Chromecast and Roku just make it so easy to essentially get what you want
and you know Keller 78 in the chat room says yeah I've got three Roku's one for
myself and two for the family wimpy what are your thoughts on this well I went
the Roku route as well after having a couple of XBMC boxes and I had a Roku in
the bedroom and a Roku in the front room and in the last month or so the Roku's
have been replaced by fire TV yeah that's interesting oh I can see myself
going that way too Roku kills XBMC fire TV kills Roku yeah because the the fire
TV does everything the Roku does just faster and a whole lot more besides so
the fire TV has become my gaming in air quotes console in the front room hmm
yeah and this is all happened just in this year all right daredevil and your
final thoughts on this topic unfortunately for me as much as I loved
the projects it's like just my TV cable service provider the box they have
actually just just appears as a network device and I can send it any file to it
and shows me on my TVs and it actually makes me easier to exchange files we
do machines and everything so yeah I end up having that news for it yeah all
right I mean that seems reasonable and you know I was just thinking about it
though here in the studio if I got a really nice high-end display in the
living room that maybe I wanted to showcase content for visitors that visit
the studio and things like that I have a suspicion I'd still probably want to go
XBMC there when I want to really make a showpiece I want to have a you know a
really great Jupiter broadcasting experience you know XBMC has we have a
fantastic app right rotten corpse it's really quite good there's a lot of
really good content on XBMC that's great for showcasing on high resolution
displays same with Roku for sure but I just feel like if it was gonna be a
centerpiece I probably would want to go XBMC still so there's still I think a
pretty reasonable space for it well and I would also touch on that and say while
I love the Roku the UI makes me want to scream yeah it's horrible it's it's
really dated and that's where wimpy is coming in with the fire TV because on
the fire TV you get a you get a great hardware rig but you also get that more
full-featured Plex Android app that is really pretty good so and it's much
better than them but you know the thing is the Roku one is at least functional
this is true well and it definitely feels like we're kind of entering a
rock-paper-spock situation yeah and it feels like fire TV could be the Spock
move would be you agree that it's a on the fire TV it's really really nailed
it yeah the UI is terrific so if you're just using the remote control which is
almost identical with the number of buttons and the layout to the Roku
remote so super simple but the fire TV has this voice search facility and it's
not like an afterthought and it's not hidden away somewhere and the thing you
might use to sort of show off what it can do the voice search is fronts and
front and center and it's a principal way that you interact with the device
and it works really well and and it feels like the future has arrived when
you when you talk into the remote and then your stuff appears you are selling
me on this you know okay so then I think I would be remiss also to 2014 has been
a pretty big year for Netflix and it was even the year we got Netflix on the
Linux desktop and the fact that there's not a really like one-click you know app
install kind of dead simple way to get Netflix integration to XBMC or it's not
even called XBMC anymore but you know what I mean it's it that's also a factor
but rotten corpse I'll let you chime in as the final defender for our beloved
media entertainment UI you love it right I love XBMC but I also my bill I work on
add-ons and stuff like that too but the XBMC runs on anything you want it to and
it has like the UI is great by itself in the default one but you can customize
the UI to like hundreds of different options and like a on Knox for example
is beautiful yeah yeah yeah yeah and you got the Raspberry Pi which is a makes a
great to meet advice like I say there is there's still a great world there's
still a great place for it but for me and I thought maybe for man it sounds
like for quite a few folks in the mumble room this has been a year where we
transition more dedicated devices they've maybe finally got it right
actually you could put XBMC on the on the fire TV so you get back to both
worlds yeah so would that be the Android app then or would that be something else
entirely like a firmware yeah it's an Android the Android app that you
sideload and in the Android app for XBMC is a full XBMC interface and
everything so you can load it in so the fire TV wins that's amazing that's
absolutely amazing well now that fire TV is gonna work in 4k because I swear I
want to get a 4k display one of these days I'm skipping 3d Matt I'm going to
4k one day I don't know how to go fourth dimension yeah I'm just gonna I think I
think they're around that same time I'll also be single and living on the street
and your your living room will look a lot like the original enterprise yes it
will though I at least have that all right Matt well we have some really
great feedback to continue including I need to make a serious correction a
mistake on my part and a couple of you know what we're gonna call even an app
pic in unplugged but first I would be remiss if I didn't stop and thank the
folks over at ting go to linux.ting.com that'll take $25 off your first
ting device or if you got a ting compatible device which stay tuned there
could be a lot more of very soon you get a $25 credit so ting is mobile that
makes sense it's no contract no early termination fee and you only pay for
your usage your minutes your messages your megabytes you want to turn on
hotspot and tethering you don't have to have a special share plan or whatever a
smart plan all the plans are the same you just pay for the data usage the
control panel that you manage it and if you ever have any questions they have a
no hold customer support but something really crazy crazy exciting is going on
so I want to tell you about it because I think it's going to seriously change
everything before I tell you that though I should probably mention now has been a
really good time to switch because ting has a crazy great deal to get you out of
your your contract if you have an early termination fee an ETF as they call it
in the biz they're gonna pay up to $150 per termination and that's on top of our
$25 credit so you could get months of ting service by taking advantage of this
ETF relief but here's the great news they just announced it a couple of hours
ago in 2015 ting is going to start offering GSM network coverage on top of
their existing CDMA coverage it is going to be awesome for users like me who have
a Nexus 5 and I'll be able to have CDMA and GSM in my freaking Nexus 5 there
they made a really great video for you audio listeners imagine a tech spec
video where they break apart the product you know like when Apple introduced the
Apple watch only it's for the ting sim it's just so awesome I got to play a
little bit of it it's perfect for the occasion
the ting sim
and so as you can as you can imagine they're gonna support a lot more devices
and they have the coverage map up now so you can check to see what the coverage
is gonna be like this is gonna be crazy great you're gonna be able to take
advantage of a lot of GSM coverage and a lot of see to make CDMA coverage back to
back you're gonna be able to bring GSM phones over to ting that's gonna open up
a whole new category of devices and right now ting has that early termination
relief program you could go over there you could get yourself a device with
that ETF you could pay you could just grab a feature phone for now if you
wanted to February 2015 ting is gonna be supporting GSM it's a pretty big deal
they really are on a mission to make mobile make sense linux.ting.com go
there to show your support linux.ting.com also give you that $25 credit that's
gonna stack on top of their ETF relief programs it's a great time to switch to
ting linux.ting.com and congratulations to ting on the announcement for GSM in
2015 that's a big deal that is so cool man that is really cool I just it's
gonna be like when I travel now I'm just gonna have the best of both worlds it's
it's really it's really slick okay so I have a make good I got to talk about I
made a I made a mistake when I was talking about Docker last week Philip
wrote in to correct me says hello Chris and crew I just listened to your
reaction upon the announcement of rocket I want to point out that it is actually
possible to host your very own Docker registry where you can host your own
image without having to use the global Docker hub it's not quite as nice as the
global hub since it's essentially only the back end there's no web interface or
search or anything like that and it cannot be hosted in a subdir because the
Docker image name format I currently maintain the AUR package for it I'm
using it every day at my job at a big telco I know it's marked out of date as
soon as I get some time I'll update it and he also has pull requests and he
links to the the AUR Docker registry page that he set up and I wanted to
thank Philip you know because I've actually made the mistake even just as
recently as yesterday in Kota radio I wanted because one of the differences
between rocket is a much more federated approach to the to the namespace for app
containers and where its docker is very much doubling down on the Docker hub
centralizing through the Docker service use the Docker API and that contrast
stuck out to me so dramatically that I didn't really consider the fact that
there is this sort of roll your own not super fancy but would certainly work
Docker hub for you for your own network so Philip thank you very much for
pointing that out to me man I got it I got like a chest thing going so oh no
that's not good and I'm gonna sip on my coffee a little bit all right so Jesse
writes in and this is on ours this is almost our last email then we'll get to
our interview with Matthew Miller from Fedora Jesse says hello Chris and Matt I
was just wondering what you guys think about the new desktop environment called
moonlight you can currently only build it on arch right now and it uses qt5
it's a fork of LX DE or I'm sorry Alex cutie and he links us to the home page
which I have linked to the show notes I was running what you thought of this QT
desktop that's just yet another desktop for the Raspberry Pi or PC in a way this
may be a sign that GTK two or three is dying and it is the rise of QT so which
is cool maybe we'll get some more themes now so here it is it's called the
moonlight desktop a project that aims create a desktop environment mainly for
those who run on low performance devices anybody heard of moonlight have we
talked about moonlight I think we've touched on it a little bit I I'm not
uber familiar with it but then I'm pretty happy with what I got now yeah q5
is our Raspberry Pi guy and he's not in here right now but I wonder if he's
heard of moonlight I'll ask him when we get off air so anyways if you're
curious at no canoe org slash moonlight de but wimpy you have are you familiar
with it yeah yeah I've come across it in circles and I did take a look but I
don't think it's had any commit since sort of the end of September so well I
know I don't know if it was like a summer project or attention is 2013 on
the bottom of their page that jumped out of me when I saw that yeah nine months
ago looks like three months ago here's a here's a more recent commit three months
ago so I don't know maybe they're looking for help could be could be
there's there's been no recent get activity yeah all right Matt Jim wrote
in I think it was on the just on the live stream I don't remember if it was
actually in a show or not but you and I were sort of grousing that we missed some
of the old nice just simple down-to-business interface elements of
Winamp you remember that yes oh my gosh yes so Jay Lim writes in he says I
remember a few weeks ago when you and Matt were wishing for a small Winamp
like player for Linux a few people wrote in but I forgot to mention it's called
audacious it's an awesome music player now at first audacious doesn't look
anything like Winamp but it has everything and more but you can add a
skin with a dockable EQ and playlist manager just like you did back in the
day and Matt's all in the AUR so here for those of you watching the video
version I do have it installed like in if I like if I play I'm playing a little
track right now and it does the visualization and with the timecode with
the scrolling track name this is a theme that I installed from the AUR and it is
exactly like Winamp with no like yeah it's it's fun so audacious is a good one
so thank you to who was it let's see go back up here up to a jail J lim for
sending that in audacious and it's a make good it's something I've been
meaning to pick for a while but I just never get around to it I thought we
might have made mention to audacious before but I wanted to give it an
official plug now that yeah I saw this theme and I installed that thought I'd
give you a chance to check it out so it's very cool see audacious sweet
audacious music player okay just as good yeah audaciously good that's that's good
Matt I like that you should give that to him what's going on over there kids and
kitty what's going on over there alright so why don't we take a quick break and
then we're gonna we're gonna go talk to Matthew let's uh let's mention right
here right now DigitalOcean go over to DigitalOcean.com and get our brand new
promo code ready everybody because it's the month of December it's unplugged
December it's one word DigitalOcean.com it's a simple cloud hosting provider
dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to spin up a cloud
server you can get rolling real easy real quick go check it out users can
create a cloud server in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans start at only
five dollars per month for 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a
terabyte of transfer and DigitalOcean has fantastic data centers multiple
data centers in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, and London the
interface to let you choose between them is super cool too boy I should just like
go through the process of creating a droplet right now because it's that quick
and easy and Matt we've always talked about using DigitalOcean to easily
deploy a WordPress droplet absolutely I've been getting a lot of
recommendations to check out ghost which is a newer blogging platform yes and
DigitalOcean again one click install you deploy it it's really easy it's really
slick so I think on top of on top of the great interface on top of the
performance on top of the flexibility where you can put the droplets they've
also got an API that lets you get even deeper into that so their interface is
super intuitive their control panel is awesome but there's a lot of tools now
built around the DigitalOcean API like to snap it into puppet to do management
to just write scripts to just restart them remotely from your applet menu bar
a lot of take snapshots before you go do an update like this is really cool like
your SSH 10 you're about to do something crazy just go up to your menu bar
snapshot exactly and I do that all the time because I'm always doing something
crazy oh yeah and they're also they're paying now for tutorials because they
really want to have some of the best tutorials on the web so go over to
DigitalOcean.com use our promo code unplug December all one word lowercase
that's gonna give you a $10 credit you can try out the $5 droplet for two
months for free why not seriously check out ghost a lot of people have
recommended as an awesome blogging platform and there's some really great
free themes that I talked about in yesterday's Koda radio you can go grab
those it's a great way to display photos or just do text only stuff or journals
it looked really cool and you just one click boom you've got it up on
DigitalOcean and since they're paying for those tutorials they've got the best
tutorials and deploying ghost is one of them in fact they're gonna pay up to
$200 we've got a link in the show notes DigitalOcean.com and a big thank you
DigitalOcean for sponsoring Linux unplugged all right so we're gonna talk
with Matthew Miller he's the lead of the Fedora project Fedora 21 came out today
to congratulations to them this is a big one a lot of stuff but this was the
first release after they've refactored the way the distribution is done in the
multiple spins and so we brought on Matthew on the Linux action show on
Sunday and we pre-recorded this interview with him for today's show okay
yep so it'll be an it'll be not just for a little while all right very good well
here we go and I see two lights we would all right so this is for Linux unplugged
and I'm gonna start in three in two I started by asking him how the team and
how he's doing after such a major release and refactoring yeah first I
want to step back and say thank you to everybody who worked on Fedora and the
computers because it really this is an amazing release and so many people put
work into making it so you know I said it's at the top of the project but it
doesn't it's not quite a project where it's top-down I want to make sure
everybody gets there right of course yeah lots and especially I mean really
for this release too because this is now the release with them different types of
spins I mean the project in between releases went through a pretty dramatic
change in how it does development right yeah absolutely we've done a really good
job I think of spinning up work especially in the cloud and server areas
where we had a little bit lack of direction and focus there so it wasn't
easy for people to plug into it so now we have these new working groups which
kind of sort of an attachment point for people who are interested and those have
really taken off in a positive way yeah so if I'm new to Linux maybe I know we
run some reddit enterprise servers at my work or something like that I'm looking
at Fedora workstation do I need to be a little afraid that it's too complicated
for a new user no you do not so one of the things we are really focusing on
through our workstation is being targeting software developers as the
focus but software developers are generally human beings as well most of
you know I know some they're questionable really they need to have
some access to power user kind of things but the basic desktop needs to be slick
and get out of the way and so we think that the gnome desktop that our
workstation is based on is really great at doing that and it's really easy for
new users as well Fedora as a fast-moving distribution with a lot of
updates and things like that sometimes you have to be a new user who's really
willing to learn and adjust and figure things out so I think that it's not
necessarily something I would put on a new user who's off on an island
somewhere but a new user who's interested in learning and has technical
friends well I when I look at Fedora too I think there's a category of users out
there that I don't think we talked about enough in the Linux community and that
is guys like my friend Chase who have been maybe Windows admins for ten years
there you know they have a totally tricked out Windows install with
customizations and you know special drive like they deep dive into Windows
as far as you can deep dive so when when he was switching to Linux he actually
wanted a Linux he could tinker with because that's one of the things he does
and so I think Fedora for the for the users that are very comfortable with
their computers it's like a slam dunk but the one thing that you mentioned to
us on Sunday's Linux action show which really resonated with me because it's
something we've talked about on Linux unplugged a lot is you're also hoping to
reclaim some of those users who've switched over to MacBooks right
even a Linux conference these days and you've got people who are doing cloud
development and they've got the MacBook on there on their lab basically they're
sitting in the audience not paying attention to the speaker we'd like to
get those people back to running Linux as much as now but here's my here's the
one to punch to that is there anything the Fedora project could do to make
Linux not suck so bad on MacBooks like there I hear there's constant Wi-Fi
issues sometimes there's issues starting the eyesight camera no Thunderbolt
DisplayPort the Thunderbolt Ethernet adapter only works if it's connected
when the MacBook boots it's a very clunky experience but it's pretty well
respected hardware is there anything Fedora could do to maybe actually focus
on that so I know that some of our people on our desktop team and and I
know also at Red Hat people who are paid to work on the desktop are have some
contacts they're working on that at Apple and I don't know all the details
on that but we do really try to make that work but you know it's hard when
you're working with no documentation no source for any of that stuff that
manages it I know but it seems like we've overcome larger challenges before
but let's let's talk about another challenge that so while Fedora 21 is in
development this started happening before Fedora 21 went into development
but it seems like the container space went red-hot just super hot during the
Fedora 21 development cycle so not only is the team shifting gears for this new
spin style release cycle and development model but at the same time a big
underlying piece of Linux technology is really changing you have systemd which
is coming in at the same time you've got containers which is there's a lot of
movement there is is that a lot for a project that's in progress like Fedora
right now to address or was that just was that rolled in during the development
cycle was it a challenge talk a little bit about ongoing challenge I think it's
certain it also is it's the future of the operating system sure yeah seems
like yeah and so in Fedora one of the things we're doing is we have in the on
the cloud flavor of the new Fedora you'll see a thing called Fedora atomic
and this is basically a host image in the current incarnation meant to run in
cloud providers like OpenStack or an Amazon EC2 meant to run Docker
containers so it has basically tools for doing that and nothing else it uses a
thing called RPM OS tree so it has a sort of an image based version of the
base OS and then you run your Docker containers on top of that and I think
we're going to be iterating a lot on that over the next release cycles it's
going to be a big thing and so I think that right now we can have that off in
the corner of the cloud space which is where that I think the energy around
that is mostly focused but there's a proposal for Fedora 22 to make it
available on bare hardware bare metal as well and kind of expand that out and I
think we'll see that kind of across all the different flavors of Fedora
increasingly so I guess is so kind of is what your answer is there is project
atomic which is a very which is a really interesting container management
solution is sort of being developed first on Fedora yeah you know it's one
of these things that's moving so fast that it's hard to know where it's all
going yeah especially when we're looking at kind of the more forward-reaching
kind of things in you know how is this really going to impact how we put the
whole operating system together we want to look at Fedora as a space we're
experimenting with that and so we I know we've also have people who are looking
at containerized desktop which is another one so containerized apps are
obviously a really nice thing to have if you're having a desktop especially if
third-party apps that may be questionable or you know even first
party apps that you just don't want to I don't know which party I should count
there but you know you don't you don't want to put so much effort into because
it just takes a lot of time to package these things up so you can if you put it
into a container you can feel a little bit better about doing the worst job for
kind of edge of the operating system and so there's a lot of appeal to doing that
but containerizing desktop apps is a lot harder than containerizing server apps
which are sort of meant usually communicating over a network port and
that's what they do maybe some other in a process communication whereas desktop
apps are kind of used to being able to access you know the hardware access you
dropping files wherever reading files forever and so that's gonna be a lot
more work how how important do you think all of this is the container management
and containers themselves how important do you think that being successful and
will implement it is critical to Fedora being considered a production candidate
ready server OS because I think a lot of people right now don't consider Fedora
a server grade OS they'd probably rather go with CentOS scientific Linux
Red Hat Enterprise Linux itself and not necessarily Fedora but it sounds like
these kinds of changes are maybe an attempt to get people to change their
minds so are these a critical part of that well I think we've actually always
had a lot of people who have been used used Fedora even in production on large
scale server they tend to not talk about it so much I could believe but yeah it's
not on the scale that CentOS and Ural and the big enterprise distributions are
and that that makes sense because it kind of fits into if you look on the
technology adoption curve kind of thing we're you know way over in the
innovators and maybe some the early adopter kind of space and that's just a
much smaller segment and you know with CentOS in the long tail there there's
there's gonna be a lot more there and especially if you want to set up a
server and you know not worry about it for ten years right or it's not your
best choice for that but we want to make sure that we fit into the ecosystem in
places where it makes sense where you have it there's advantages in having the
newest versions of things if you are able if it's no problem to upgrade every
year like okay I want to keep the latest so I'm following that it's there and of
course people who have been following Fedora and making sure that they run it
in some corner of their infrastructure are not surprised when rel7 comes out
yes you know they not everything that goes into Fedora goes into rel it's a
you know downstream relationship that isn't always completely direct like that
but we try to make sure that everything goes into rel right yeah so if we can
get more people who are running rel and CentOS running Fedora it'll be better
for them and it also of course benefits our downstream distributions because
they get the feedback from Fedora users early and I think you know there's as
systemd finally got into rel7 and people were surprised I think that actually you
know we've had it in Fedora for several releases and got a lot of polish and a
lot of things that were it would have been it right made it much smoother oh
yeah yeah so it really really made it go much smoother there I think we kind of
we're gonna have as the container nation and all these things change the
operating system more and more we're gonna have more of that yeah so yeah
well so as I hate to do this to you as we are sitting on the release day I hate
to be the guy to ask what's next but you must be looking forward to Fedora 22 a
little bit and have a few low-hanging fruits that you want to pick and
something that you want to work into Fedora 22 what's what's in front of mind
for you yeah so after having a one-year cycle here of going back to the six
month cycle it's already like wow it's gonna be fast because we're looking at a
May release date which means working back you know from the betas and the
alphas and things like that that means that our feature work basically needs to
be done at the end of January so I think that there are some things that are
gonna be changes but I don't think that there's gonna be a lot of radical change
in order to it's going to be incremental on some of these things we talked about
I've heard some scuttlebutt of maybe refactoring the release cycle to what
people are calling a tick-tock release cycle to do you have any comments on
that yeah we just started kind of talking about that and that's sort of
the idea that we would one release concentrate on sort of the
infrastructure and the QA and release engineering tooling and then the next
release focus on the features that go into it and we're still working out that
conversation some people really like it some people feel like it would hold back
I think one of the concerns I saw is somebody said well would that mean maybe
like the talk release wouldn't see the latest version of gnome brought in it
would still have the release from the tick
the desktop people both gnome and KDE which is one of our other alternate
desktops that we consider very important they don't like that at all they want to
make sure their software gets in the hands of users very quickly so I think
even if we went to this kind of model we would do it in a soft sort of way so
where the releases that focus on the infrastructure would still allow new
things to come in as long as they don't get in the way of that and a lot of
those things like a new gnome release probably don't as much get in the way
okay right so something to watch and it sounded like an interesting idea and I
could see some some serious benefits to it so yeah so that so might that be
introduced during the fedora 22 release cycle or would that be a post 22 thing
I think that the conversation right now it's probably a post 22 thing and one of
the reasons for that actually is that just because as we're seeing running
into the holidays now it would be very advantageous for the feature cycle to be
the spring cycle and the infrastructure cycle to be the fall one
likely to be disruptive so we're kind of on the wrong cadence if that's what we
want to do right so having another release to talk about it is probably a
good idea especially since it's a big decision yeah before fedora 22 expanded
for atomic and more container stuff is going to be a big theme possibly even
some test containerized stuff for workstation although I don't know how
far that's going to go there's some talk of that there's a switch in the
package manager level there's a thing called DNF yes it's likely to become the
default replacing yum okay so it uses the hockey back end different from a
technical level the depth solver is different and it should be a lot faster
as well and more importantly from a development point of view although
users don't necessarily care it has a much cleaner design and a better API so
it will be more maintainable for the future that's exciting awesome yeah all
right well for now everybody can go enjoy fedora 21 it should be out a mirror
near you or a torrent near you as well
fedora org and also we'll have links to some of your social profiles in the
show notes anything else you want to touch on before we run I think that's
it for now this is gonna be a great release so I think you all enjoy it and
again thanks to everybody who worked on it yeah yeah I'll echo that great work
to everybody on the Fedora team this is this is a solid release and a real
screamer too at least on my rig so I'm pretty happy with it well thanks again
Matthew and congratulations thank you
and if everything goes as planned on Sunday's Linux action show we're gonna
break down the different specific spins and really deep dive into each one of
them individually and talk about talk about that and it should be if
everything goes as planned like I say because it's a live production it should
be a live panel of fedora experts that will be helping us with that I don't
want to say anymore just that way nobody's on the hook but it should be a
really great episode so expanded coverage in Sunday's Linux action show
hey mumble room why don't we do a community review of fedora 21 next week
on Linux unplugged so as many of you that are willing give it a spin ideally
on on hardware but a VM if that's what you can do would also be great fedora
21 I mean I'm I already have the gnome version installed I'm actually gonna do
a fresh install just to sort of start over clean cuz I was really having some
fun experimenting with all the different repositories and messing around with how
far I could push the Nuvu driver but so if you would join us next and also I
this is an open invitation to anybody listening that's not in the mumble room
right now you can join us next Tuesday we start at 2 p.m. Pacific go to Jupiter
broadcasting comm slash calendar for the live time in your local area you can
join us in the mumble room it's an open mumble room we'll just do a mic check
make sure you're not crazy or something I don't know and then we'll bring in and
talk about fedora 21 as a group and see what everybody thinks this is this is
supposed to be kind of our bag right fedora workstation that's right supposed
to be kind of be for the power users that's kind of us so let's see what I
think and I hope that is I hope as many of you can give it a go and I'll give
you my I'll give you my thoughts too and then on Sunday join us for even more
coverage alright so guys any thoughts on fedora 21 in the mumble room today it's
release day before we move on change topics sounds interesting and appears
that everyone is I fortunately everyone is now starting to look on making a good
developer experience which may render in good apps yeah isn't that kind of
exciting like the fact that you know he touched on that really made sure like
that we want to make it good for developers we want to make it you know
attractive to those MacBook switchers which that's a topic that kernel Linux
has brought up a few times on this show when we go to these conferences is that
it's a it's a sea of MacBooks and you kind of walk away and you go wow it
feels like everybody's on max what are we all doing am I the only one that's
doing this on the Linux desktop and then you know some of them have it installed
but a lot of them don't if you can make something compelling for them and he
says that they might even be end up talking with Apple that'd be pretty
great kits and what do you think so I'm on their website and I noticed that
under the workstation link it says user friendly but he's also talking about
focusing developers isn't there a little bit of dichotomy between the two I think
he means those are their users so it's friendly to them I think it's I think
what they're actually kind of doing is by saying it's developer focused it's an
acknowledgement in a sense that there is a barrier of entry and we're saying
developer because that is a label that we prescribe to something of a certain
level of knowledge but what it really means is if you're competent in some
level of system administration and configuration and doing a little bit of
research really maybe this is another caveat right what it's another way of
saying is if you're kind of good at googling and you know how to figure out
how to fix stuff on your own and figure out their own solution through googling
then this is a good desktop for you and they're not mutually exclusive either
being user friendly doesn't mean developer hostile and being developer
friendly doesn't mean user hostile it can be friendly to both right yeah yeah
for sure and that's pretty important if you can't get the developer to feel
comfortable it's hard to feel any user yeah that's yes all right so I'll give
you more thoughts on Sunday and on Tuesday 21 is the release I've been
looking forward to for a really long time because I you know I already said
this on Sunday and I know I'm kind of repeating myself I'm sorry but I'm
really excited it is really them trying to address some of the criticism I think
that we've given them over the years not I'm not saying they did it because of us
but I'm just saying it to me it seems to be focusing them more specifically
something we've said they've lacked and they're doing it a really interesting
time and they're going to do it in a really competitive way and I think
Matthew Miller is is also a really good leader I mean he's really good at
communicating he also runs the fedora magazine he's extremely good at
publishing relevant information the new get fedora website is really useful and
he's he's obviously very well at working with the podcasts and the community to
get the word out there it's exactly what the fedora project is needed so they got
the technology aspect of it right and I think they've got the community aspect
of it right too so they're really I think they're firing all cylinders and I
think I think and I would assume 22 is just gonna be even better but I'll save
my thoughts for another show so before we go on to Ubuntu snappy or I guess
maybe the technical term is Ubuntu snappy core which boy this is this has
been an interesting couple of weeks in the space I want to tell you about
Linux Academy though Linux Academy is your resource to go better yourself on
your own time and on your own rules at your own schedule for your own purposes
maybe it's a challenge yourself to see if you still got it like I like to do
from time to time maybe it's to just check another box off on that yearly
review this is yes I went and I took some education or maybe she gets
certified in something new something to make you even more employable Linux
Academy comm slash unplugged go there to get our 33% discount when you get that
discount and I recommend you go there because you're gonna want to keep Linux
Academy service once you get it once you get that discount you get that 33% off
you get all all acts you get access to all of the content all of it and all of
the new stuff that they add I got an email here from Linux Academy they say
they just launched their puppet professional certification preparation
course this course can take you from zero absolutely no puppet knowledge to
a certified ready-to-go puppet technician they've launched two new
courses one on Docker which is talk about great timing for that and one on
vagrant which is an excellent tool in the past 30 days they have added over a
hundred videos a hundred new practice exams tailored practice exams by people
that genuinely know the content that's the huge differentiator here the entire
site is run by Linux enthusiasts they fundamentally have it from that approach
which you know that makes all of the difference they've got video streams
they're doing all the time now too which you can interact and ask questions
directly to the educator step-by-step video courses downloadable comprehensive
study guides you can pick from seven plus Linux distributions and they
automatically adjust the courseware they'll spin up virtual servers for you
on-demand give you access over SSH public boom you can put DNS on there you
can do scenario based deployments of bind or all kinds of services Amazon AWS
it's a fantastic service and it's it's one of these where you can go in there
and say I'm a very busy person I mean I really don't have a lot of time but I I
can take advantage of Linux Academy you can go in there you can say I have this
much time available then the learning plan will create courseware for you
based on that availability and it does a good job keeping you motivated keeping
you involved sending you reminders about quizzes it's it's such a great resource
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged go save a little bit of money and I'm not
gonna I'm not gonna use the New Year's resolution line but think about it just
saying it's probably a pretty good idea to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged show all
right so a Popey's here but he swears up and down he's gonna he's not going to
talk to me about Ubuntu snappy right Popey not gonna happen
about it then yeah maybe I would understand no I actually and Dustin
Kirkland right is that is that his last name yeah yeah he's a canonicals cloud
storage solutions product manager and he's the leading technical product
strategy roadmap and lifecycle for the Ubuntu cloud commercial offerings he's
gonna join us on Sunday's Linux action show cool so that's the horse's mouth so
what we get to do right now is tell you what what it is and why I think it's
kind of a neat deal assuming I don't lose my voice before the end of the show
so Mark Shuttleworth and a bunch of other people today announced it I
actually have the video you know I'll play it I'll play just a quick just a
quick little bit of it I won't play the whole thing there I'll just jump I'll
jump ahead a little bit where Mark is talking about what it is so he never
break the device so what Mark does your applications that are super fresh today
he compares how they've developed a firmware like approach for the phone OS
where they can deliver updates to the base OS that are don't break and if it
does break there's a built-in recovery mechanism that don't touch the
application space they don't change the state information the application data
just like Android and iOS updates these applications instantly available to
users all over the world and to make sure that updates to the applications
are also transactional and bulletproof and you can try that out today take any
of our supported devices put Ubuntu on that device and then watch how
incredibly easy it is to update that device it feels like you're on rails so
going back okay so this is sort of the basic idea of what they want to deliver
with Ubuntu snappy now you might maybe remember Wimpy what was it called
Ubuntu juice the that's like super small Ubuntu core yeah right for geos geos
yes right now that that was sort of a maybe an early go at this when
virtualization was really you were gonna do all of your scaling through
virtualization which still happens but you really wanted the most base tiny
operating system for the host and then you just put all your stuff in the
virtual machines well now there's kind of a new approach where it's you kind of
the same idea but with containers and the idea here is you keep a really
minimal base operating system that's actually even as maybe could be read
only and then you deliver all of the applications inside Docker containers
and and the developers can publish those Docker container updates directly so
we've talked recently about how the own cloud project is a little miffed that
when you do apt install own cloud on Debbie and stable it's like a two or
three year old version of own cloud and it's not supported as real bad bugs it
makes them look bad they don't like that they would be self-publishing these
Docker containers and these would just slide right on top of a Ubuntu snap you
release that base OS is more like a firmware update where you use snap in a
new version of that base OS and there's a rollback there's a transactional
rollback if it doesn't work and the applications you know your own cloud
instance your WordPress instance your whatever that are all you know your
database all in these different Docker containers just like your smartphone
apps today don't they don't get really affected by the underlying operating
system being updated it's kind of like you know what core OS is going for and
it's not a you know it's it's it's a buntus take on it right guys so far
anybody want to fact check me I'm kind of getting all this right so you so the
the applications can take advantage of new features in updates so the
underlying read-only image that you that updates periodically might have new
features landing in it and that's defined by a framework and so an
application can say I I can use framework 1.0 or framework 2.0 there's
a feature platform aspect exactly that's something that was taken straight from
the phone so the phone has the same concept of framework so an application
that says I can only work on 1504 and above will just not be visible in the
store to anyone on a previous framework so you could see how this is a really
interesting approach to almost solving the rolling problem the applications are
updated maybe by the vendors or by the administrator in their own container the
base operating system you know it could be a nice stable LTS that just gets
features added on by the upstream vendor in this case canonical it's a it's a
very like a sealed off hypoallergenic like kind of like yeah approach to to a
Linux server any reactions in the mumble room William do you have any thoughts on
this I just want to see it happen all right that's one of those things that I
feel that they gotta try it kids and kitty what are your thoughts yeah I had
asked actually during the pre-show if this was the end product of all those
rumors that we're going through going rolling if this is the actual
manifestation of that well it's kind of it's kind of part of it in on the
server side and on the phone side you know arguably the phone is is somewhat
rolling in that we can send out a new system update image and developers can
put their new apps in the store for the phone the same thing happens for Ubuntu
core in the cloud so in the cloud will deploy a new version of the the read
only snappy image and the developer the own cloud developer in this case or
WordPress or Hadoop or whatever it is will update theirs and so it gets close
to rolling I mean it's not because there's still gates on all of those
things but it's it's a lot closer to rolling than every six months for
example and you end up with a server in the cloud with your deployment on that
you've got to think carefully about which bits you upgrade you know it makes
me think though and wimpy I'd be curious to get your insights on this I like look
at the Ubuntu Mate edition wouldn't it if you could start like if this Ubuntu
snappy you know it's been out for a while it's something you could build on
top of you think by the way by the way systemd based Ubuntu snappy right it's
systemd first server cloud version of Ubuntu that will use systemd heyo if you
could take Ubuntu Mate and and base it on sort of this base system where
components of your distribution are containers that ship on top of it and
when a new release of Mate comes out you would just ship out a new container to
your end users wimpy are you driving with this is this something you've
thought about it is something I've thought about and not just as a result
of this Ubuntu core release but also from Lennox proposal for namespaced
sub volumes and shipping a thin OS which you then provide libraries and
applications as sub volume overlays and if you think about it as the upstream
desktop developers so you could say the Marte development team or the gnome team
or KDE or any of the others they are package managers in their own right
because all of the components that make up those desktops come with configure
scripts where you can do configure make make install and that is essentially all
you need to build these overlay type systems and certainly it would make it
much easier for the application developers and much faster for the
application developers to ship their desktop environments their applications
in that sort of paradigm I mean the snappy is Ubuntu snappy core is
premiering on Microsoft Azure why because in their own words Microsoft
loves Linux they say but so it's clearly this is targeted for the server but I
I'm like okay that's neat I'll just be sitting over here eating my popcorn
waiting for the desktop implementation of this because this honestly sounds like
how I want my desktop I want a nice really stable core base that gives baby
platform features that sound like like Popeye was talking about but I want my
apps like I want my core set of applications fresh and rolling right
well we've already said we're going to do that for the we're going to bring the
technology that's in the phone to the desktop with unity 8 and siloed
applications and app armor and all the kinds of things and the click store and
click packages all the kinds of things are on the phone we'll bring that to the
desktop but over the next couple of years this kind of leapfrogs all of that
straight to the cloud I think because it's just easier and the time is right
for it I mean you mentioned earlier about juice and Ubuntu core from 804 I
think they're a bit ahead of the time back then and now it seems the time is
right what with core OS and Docker and the popularity of all of that I agree it
does seem like the the right time and I think that's why honestly when Mark was
on the Linux action show a couple of weeks ago I specifically asked him about
core OS because it seemed like it was filling a hole that Ubuntu didn't have a
plug for yet and this is sort of their take on it but I wonder if it it to me
seems like it has some clear advantages to start in the cloud number one
canonical has a pretty good track record there now they have already a really
strong deployment so there's a lot of stuff built around that the place you
have a significant portion of canonicals businesses is built around supporting
that so it's important to them so there it's a good bet if you're making from an
enterprise standpoint if you're betting on that product but also you have to
figure that there's a lot of users that are going to just easily transition and
I was starting to wonder if maybe Ubuntu was gonna sort of turn into a bit of a
runtime that like would be deployed on top of things like core OS you know
it'd be the runtime that the Docker container actually used but now this
this sort of prevents that from happening where a shop that would still
be using Ubuntu in the container sort of the Ubuntu runtime could now actually
also be using Ubuntu on the base and I think that's this came out a time before
that bleeding even begun so the timing of it's really good there so anyways I
think Ubuntu snap is it's cool for the server I want it for the desktop already
I mean screw right same here just stop just stop it just move it over the
desktop get get a get a gnome container set up get a get a chrome container
whatever it takes just get all that and I'll use that make it so right so we'll
get more information about that soon any closing thoughts on that mumble room
before we run anybody have any pontificating yes he mentioned
something about bringing this to the desktop so are we going to see snappy
and proper on the desktop or is this a totally different package manager or
what do you have that's great bringing over from the phone to the desktop how's
that gonna work with apt yeah so yeah it's not actually even it's more than a
package manager right oh yeah so on the on the desktop now if you want to
install some some application you go to the other Ubuntu software center or you
apt-get install something whereas on the phone we have a click store where there's
a siloed click application that you download from the store and install and
it's that that we will bring to the desktop there you go all right so we'll
cover more as we have info in the new segment on the Linux action show and you
can go play with it now there's like scripts out there to go get it if you
want to go play with a systemd powered version of Ubuntu you can have at it
it's an it's a new it's a new era of systemd and Ubuntu starting on the cloud
haters commence your hating yeah all right Matt well we have a pretty packed
show planned for Sunday I think we're gonna have multiple guests again it's
been really busy I know 24 the end of 2014 we got busy we doubled down it's
really it's thanks to our producers q5 system rotten corpse they've they've
really been hauling but Matt have a great week and I'll see you on Sunday
okay sounds good see you then all right everybody well thanks for tuning this
week's episode of Linux unplugged we do this show on Tuesdays we'd love to hear
your community review Fedora 21 next Tuesday join us over JB live TV don't
forget the big show on Sunday for more Fedora coverage all right everybody
thanks so much to in this week's episode see you back here next Tuesday
oh hi there so I'm playing a little video on the way out so great great show
thanks everybody mumble room you guys had a great showing and I wanted to
mention you know we talked about the Advent calendar last week and this week
there today the Advent calendar image of the day is the Ubuntu core for QMU so if
you want to go play with you yeah yeah so here's an interesting thought you
know we were talking about upstart versus system D like it seems like years
ago but it was not that long ago and I kept I kept saying to everyone you know
upstart has way more deployments than system D when you think about it it's
like millions of a bunch of users there's math that may mint users there's
Chrome OS users there's rail users they're all using upstart right there
cumulatively there's way more upstart users than there are system D now with
Ubuntu core given how popular Ubuntu is in the cloud it's possible that we could
flip that the other way around just with us doing that I'd have to go get my
measuring stick though Popey's and to tell but that would be a jolly big
measuring stick Wow well it is it is tis of course the new rails the new rail
seven use the system deal there's probably quite a few deployments of
that oh wow I was by the way just I was just playing a video I opened it up in
the other tab I just recorded a video for the tech talk today patrons if
you're a patron over there just posted a video it's it's me talking about
something very shameful that I have done and I come clean I even have my wife
there as moral support well I make my just one of those things where you stand
out in front of a podium and I don't know well it's pretty close to that it's
pretty close you're speaking from experience no I know I'm not gonna go
to details it's too much shame it's too much shame if you're a patron you can
watch it though don't forget about the best of to everybody alright so blaster
last week blaster I said you know I'm thinking about finally breaking down and
replacing the radio in my truck because I listened you know I drive about six
seven hours a week and I exclusively listen to podcasts during that entire
time and right now it's pretty ghetto I have a Bluetooth speaker box that I turn
on and I just put on my dashboard while I'm driving and I drive down the road
with my Bluetooth connected to that and like okay I'm kind of tired of being an
animal I think maybe I'm gonna go get like a and a dash replacement that has
Bluetooth and aux in and USB and I'm just gonna finally do it right and it's
about a hundred and thirty bucks for a decent one and blaster says to me and I
was like I don't really want to do it because every time I replace the
dashboard unit I'm I'm really unhappy I don't I usually think it doesn't match
the speakers and I feel like I need to replace the speakers and then I need to
get an amp and then I need to get a sub and I'm never happy with the way it
looks and it's always too bright and it kind of looks tacky compared to what the
what what what Dodge put in there originally so I was like I was telling
blaster I'm like I don't really want to do this but I'm just I'm an animal with
this Bluetooth speaker I feel like I'm in the 80s with my boombox and he says
well before you rip out your radio on your dashboard try getting an FM
transmitter and I said this truck kills all FM transmitters I don't know if it
has the world's weakest receiver but I have I have tried three or four solid
really well reviewed Bluetooth wired all you know remote antenna where it's up on
the dashboard all different kinds of FM transmitters in my truck they've never
worked right for me he says well before you go in and you make the big change
try get try getting the go groove flex smart x2 Bluetooth wireless in-car FM
transmitter and it's one of these deals where it's got it's okay it's got like a
bendable neck and it plugs into the cigarette adapter okay it's got a
separate power button on the cigarette adapter too so you can just turn off the
power it's got a digital display so you can you can dial in right exactly to the
FM station you want it's got call and hang up buttons because it does Bluetooth
hands-free dialing too it's got an extra USB port so you can still charge a
device over USB when you have it plugged in and it also has aux in and out audio
jacks so that way if you don't want to use Bluetooth you can have it go in over
a headphone jack and that's important yeah cuz good quality and he's like so
just give this a shot and you know tell me what you think I'm like okay fine I
mean it's this is way better than you know paying for somebody to install it
and ripping out my dashboard it's an old truck it'll probably get screwed up and
I gotta tell you Matt I've been using it for a week and it has been flawless so
it it does an auto scan that's not too new and you know you just it just auto
scans and finds the best frequency and you can dial it up and down a little bit
if you want it connects over Bluetooth so the phone just stays right in my
pocket and it just connects up and it starts broadcasting immediately so I
don't have like you don't turn the truck on and then until it connects no it just
immediately is transmitting and then it connects over Bluetooth within a few
seconds and then it has play pause and skip the play pause like starts the
podcast right up and the skip does 30 second forward so I can jump ahead or
jump back if I need to and it's just perfect it was and it was like 35 40
bucks so I have the $10,000 question because that sounds really enticing to
me where I live if I want to listen to let's say I like let's let's say I'm
trying to tune into one thing there's a lot of mix-and-match stations between my
county and your county mm-hmm it goes from Canadian rock to Marriott Marriott
music pretty quickly so you know so that type of thing so does it like self adjust
the frequency as it goes well you can but then you'd have to change it on the
stereo so what blaster recommended I do and this is what I've done although I
actually haven't needed to go to backup is I went to a trouble spot area that I
thought I would have some issues by the airport here and I went through on I
turned off all my transmitters and I listened in the truck I just dialed
through the dial until I found an empty station in that area and now I know if I
need to I can have a preset on the on the preset buttons and I can just turn
the FM transmitter to that and switch over to that really quick oh cool okay
yeah oh that's awesome so blaster thank you for the recommendation
Chris if you guys on it yeah it's great have you got a cassette player in your
truck Chris I don't just the CD yeah yeah yeah cuz in my in my old car I used
a cassette adapter that had a Bluetooth receiver in it so you put the cassette
in the cassette player and it's a Bluetooth receiver and then you can
send your audio over Bluetooth and it plays through the cassette system was
that in your car wimpy was that your Ford Anglia yeah no it was it was my
Ford pop which one was it you had the go grew flex my x2 yeah go grew flex smart
x2 all right now I'll let you go good all right have a good rest of your week
Matt I'll see you Sunday bye JB towels come everybody go boat I do believe
there's an x3 model I chose the x2 I think for a reason I think I remember
reading some of the reviews on the x3 they say you can still get in time for
Christmas it's defragging necessary on a solid state technology actually yes yes
very necessary depending on your solid-state disk spread out across the
LBA range in such a way that it's actually mapping to the same die on the
SSD and you lose all the parallelism effects of the SSD and your speed drops
to crap your bottleneck on the on the IO horribly okay I always thought that
defrag would cause wear on the device it does cause wear because you have to
rewrite the whole file somewhere else about that now really you could probably
write like a petabyte to most MLC SSDs and be fine so you're probably not
worried about where in most cases well on SSDs why would you defrag anyway
because if all of the blocks get mapped onto LBAs which are on one die then you
lose all the effects of the performance of the SSD because you have to
constantly be reading from one die one request at a time and that makes it
really slow the more channels you use the better yeah that makes sense
Samsung the Samsung SSDs that have a lot of they have a cache mechanism which is
sort of a species of RAM when you're defragging actually uses that cache
mechanism to avoid writing to and at that point when there's a version of it
which is a like about eight gigs or something of cache that is RAM it just
increases that so make the process a lot faster on the Samsung disks they have
eight gigs of TLC which is that that's actually used in SLC form so you're
actually using those three bit by two different process technology as a one
bit cell and so you're using all of them as one you're grouping a bunch of cells
together as one cell and so they call it fake SLC but you get the durability
approximately of SLC in this case and they write to that as a cache it's kind
of like an S log in ZFS if you're familiar with that concept they write a
journal to that eight gig space and then slowly copy it into the TLC LBA ranges
as time goes on and the nice thing is this persists even if you power off
because it's just you know more flash that they're writing to but you get
really good durability durability out of it and you can write in order and then
go ahead and throw stuff off and map them into different LBA ranges later so
it's not doing super huge writes right you can get really good performance so
if you're if you're if you're writing if you're writing a really large file does
it bypass that and go right to the slower stuff I would imagine it should
and that's probably okay for a really large file this is a lot of random
drives they pretty much negate that problem altogether it's flatline
performance all together at the one terabyte 850 evo drives nowadays no I
want that do this loud I have mostly evos