Utopian.io, I'll go look for it, yep.
Yeah, okay.
And they basically take open source projects, okay,
and they induct them into the Steemit blockchain
or Steemit blockchain and build up a community around them.
And people who actively contribute back to the project
can get rewards back in cryptocurrency.
So it doesn't have to be code necessarily,
it could be things like translations or manuals
or graphics or anything else.
And it builds this idea around the open source project
if you're making money direct
from people who are contributing to it.
It's a very interesting point.
And your comparison there would be something
maybe for content creators too.
Well, no, I mean, the point is that Steam also has Dtube,
which is decentralized tube, and DLive.
And they basically work in the same way.
So you put content out in Dtube
and you're earning money in cryptocurrency
by people upvoting your videos.
So the bottom line is, okay, right,
the popular ones get upvoted
and you earn money from being popular.
So you put out good content, you make money.
Hmm, hmm, that also could,
I can't, how does that not turn into Clickbait 2.0 though?
Yeah. Ooh.
This is the cool thing about it.
Okay, so the whole idea about upvoting people
for good content is that it's community-managed
about the weighting of the content.
So you have to have so many people, okay, right,
of sufficient steam power to be able to upvote your content
to say it's legitimate content.
So you earn the steam power
by being a good person to the community.
More steam power you have, the more your vout counts.
Interesting, ha, ha, ha, ha.
That's particularly interesting.
That's a really interesting take on that.
The problem with Dtube is it just sucks
at delivering video, that's the problem.
I get to see a single video actually play.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 245.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's running the numbers, looking at the distros,
and watching all of the projects.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wuz.
Hello, Mr. Payne, it's good to be with you again
on episode 245.
Coming up in this week's episode,
we're gonna do all of our traditional community news,
as well as some new project releases, some app picks,
and some development sprints.
But then, towards the end of the show,
we're gonna talk about Microsoft's new Linux powered devices
that will be coming to the market soon.
It's all of the news this week,
and it's part of Azure Sphere,
which is an overall, large, three-stage,
three-component effort that Microsoft's putting on
that may just wind up dominating IoT.
And we'll tell you how Linux is playing a role,
what component of this is Linux-based,
and what you can expect in the pretty near future.
Wes and I got on a phone call
with one of the core creators and developers from Microsoft.
They took the time to get the team on the phone with us
before the show, and we asked them all of the hard questions.
We got the specifics about what they're running
on these devices, and we'll share what we learned with you
later on in the show, straight from the horse's mouth.
We couldn't have gotten better people
to describe the tech to us.
It was really pretty awesome.
But before we get all of that,
there's like news, community stuff,
and a mumble room to bring in.
So let's do all of that right now.
Time-appropriate greetings, virtual lug.
Hey.
Wow, that kind of made me hungry, actually.
Now I have a bit of an appetite.
Well, guys, we have much to cover today,
and I don't really know where to start
other than maybe with Linus.
That just seems like the appropriate place right now.
Linus Torvalds on the Linux kernel mailing list
announced plans that you should not be excited about
and mean absolutely nothing,
so would you please stop talking about it?
Except for Linus keeps talking about it.
So he says, the next release doesn't really seem
to be shaping up to be any particularly big release,
and there is nothing particularly special about it either.
The most special thing that happened
is just sort of a numerology thing.
The Linux kernel has passed the six million
Git object mark, and this, he says,
is reason enough to call the next kernel version 5.0.
This version is completely meaningless.
It should mean that it's just silly
and that maybe I won't even switch to it
because even numerological rules would be a silly reason,
so I may not do it, and it may just surprise you,
but 5.0 will happen someday,
and it will be and should be meaningless.
You have been warned.
I like it.
I can't wait.
Yeah, right?
I can't wait for it.
I have no reason to be excited.
I am really looking forward to Linux kernel 5.0
for no reason at all.
I thought, okay, all right.
Thank you, Linus, thank you.
So that's how we start the show out today,
but let's talk about something
that's a little bit higher up in the kernel stack,
and that's the user interface,
and Mr. Martin Wimpress tooling away like a soldier
at Ubuntu MATE's high DPI support,
and it was almost a year ago that Wimpy came on here
and told us about the first steps
of bringing high DPI support to Ubuntu MATE.
In fact, I'm looking at the post right here
from April 2017, where it's a screenshot
that Wimpy took on his XPS 15 4K screen,
and with a few dirty hacks, with Ubuntu 17.04 as a base,
we had a high DPI.
So fast forward now about a year,
where are we at with all of this, Wimpy?
We're all done.
It's all high DPI to the max in all the right places.
So I think I last spoke to you about this
maybe five or six weeks ago,
and I said I wouldn't talk about it again,
but I'm lying because I'm going to talk to you about it now.
So what's changed since then is we had a few bits
that weren't implemented.
So one of the big changes is now that Marco,
which is the window manager for the MATE desktop,
that now all of its window controls and everything,
all of those scale and work correctly.
So where before, when high DPI was enabled,
we were standing up compers underneath
in order to fill that gap,
we don't need to do that anymore.
Wow.
So the behavior is just like what you used to have.
You can either choose to run Marco or compers,
and it's not constrained
by whether you're using high DPI or not.
So that's one of the big changes.
And then Kaja, the file manager,
has now had the full high DPI treatment.
Ah.
And in terms of user facing changes
that are going to be obvious there,
that's really sort of,
we've made sure that the icons are all using vector icons
and what have you.
So it all looks a bit crisper.
Very good. And nicer.
So, yeah.
And there's been a few tweaks and touches
all the way through to just improve things.
So there's some improvements
to the way that font DPI scaling works.
So it gives you the ability
to sort of do pseudo fractional scaling
by having a scale desktop
and then manipulating the font DPI.
So yeah, it's all looking really good now.
And all those patches have landed in 1804
as of about a week ago,
all being tested, looking in good shape.
So our high DPI journey's finished.
And interestingly, you said it was a year ago,
we had that first discussion
about here's a rather shonky setup.
But the actual journey started a year before that,
just after 1604 closed.
We embarked on our journey towards GTK3.
So this has been two years in the making.
Wow. Yeah, good point.
And congratulations.
Let me start there.
Let me just say congratulations.
And then also work well done.
Really nice to see this.
We were just talking on the pre-show
about how there's just a few systems right now.
I can't really decide like if my next rig
is gonna be high DPI.
And so I'm really happy to see this getting pushed forward
by more and more desktops.
Yeah, I think the state of high DPI in general
is in a good place for Linux now as well.
Yeah, I can remember some,
I think when you got your XPS,
I think that was the third gen.
So that was about two and a half, three years ago,
I think you got that laptop.
Correct.
And, you know, you were saying,
well, you know, these applications don't scale.
And I think Firefox and Chrome both didn't scale
at that time.
Yeah.
You know, these days, and it's not just, you know,
it's nice, obviously that the desktop
that I am involved in now has high DPI scaling.
But when I install lots of other applications,
I see just about everything scaling.
Now, you know, the one obvious standout
that doesn't scale is GIMP,
which is disappointing and they're getting there.
They've got some cheeky workarounds in GIMP 2.10,
which is still based on GTK2,
but they do some magic to use larger icons
and bump up the font scaling
to sort of fill the gap in the meantime.
But other than that,
there isn't a whole lot that I run and think,
oh, this isn't high DPI scaled.
It has gotten better.
It could be, the story could be a bit better still
on the plasma side of things.
There's still three or so places you have to go
to really get it all working.
But Cheese Bacon asks an interesting question,
and I don't know if you have the rough idea,
but just from like a raw numbers standpoint,
do you have any idea of roughly how many assets
had to be touched to get to a high DPI version
or had to be replaced, like icons and things like that?
Oh, crikey.
Thousands, thousands, every icon.
Those were retouched by Daniel Foray.
He did an icon rework for us in 1704.
Michael Tunnell did all of the small assets
to provide scaled versions and recolored them.
So that's everything from like the check boxes
and the outlines around the buttons,
cause all the buttons are styled and themes.
So, and then all of the CSS at the backend
for the GTK3 stuff, whole chunks of that had to be adapted
so it knew how to apply styling
when it was in a scaled mode.
So, you know, when I say it took two years to get there,
just building on top of GTK3 is only one of those steps
and, you know, reworking all of the themes
to understand how all of these assets scale
and are provided, you know, that was a whole chunk of work
and there were numerous themers and digital artists
involved in that endeavor.
So yeah, thousands and thousands of assets
have been touched along the way.
Wow, well, I'm glad you guys are doing the hard work there.
So that'll be all good to go in 1804.
So when I get the final 1804, I'll have that.
Yeah, I think there's one teeny tiny thing
we're gonna fix post-release regarding high DPI,
but it's so insignificant I'm not gonna mention it
and nobody will notice it.
Okay then, don't pay any attention over here.
Well, thanks for the update.
Yeah, it's misdirection.
Yeah, we're good.
You know, while we're on the Ubuntu vein here,
Eric, I know I saw news about a week ago, I think,
about the Ubuntu studio project rebasing
or making big changes.
Can you fill us in on that?
Yes, so we've got some great things going on.
First of all, we established a council
so that we can take some load off of the project later,
which is really a good thing.
But what we're doing is we are trying to do something
such as replace our metapackage installer
with something like the Ubuntu MATE welcome,
which I guess has also been forked to Budgie.
Cool.
And so we're going to be including that
to let people tailor the experience the way they want.
And we're also considering perhaps
a change of default desktop environment
and perhaps add additional desktop environments as options.
So there's a number of things we're kind of brainstorming
and working on.
We definitely want to get Ubuntu Studio out of the stagnation
it's been in for about the past two years.
Well, I look forward to seeing how that goes,
because I've used it on and off.
It's a pretty solid distro for people that maybe want
to get into podcasting, as an example, or something like that.
It's pretty great.
So Ubuntu Studio will have some change.
When do those start landing?
So it sounds like the council stuff is already in place,
but other changes, is that a release or two away?
We're aiming for 18.10 for the first of the big changes.
But 18.04 is really just going to be iterative.
And the only thing about 18.04 is for us,
it will not be an LTS just due to load manpower.
OK.
Yeah, I think I remembered hearing that.
Well, great.
Thank you guys for the updates.
And definitely keep up the good work
and keep us posted on how that goes.
I love watching them projects.
And it's always cool to see that kind of stuff.
It's just so darn great.
You know what else is great?
Ting.
Linux.ting.com.
It's smarter than unlimited, because if you use less,
you pay less.
It's just a base $6 for your line,
and then your usage on top of that for your minutes,
your messages, and your megabytes.
That's it.
So if you only get a dozen text messages a month,
you don't need to pay for 500 text messages.
If you can download podcasts and listen to music via Wi-Fi
and cache it locally, you probably
don't need 12, 15 gigs of data.
So just pay for what you use.
And if you want multiple devices, like a Mi-Fi
or a cell phone, or if you want a backup phone,
it's great for that.
Because at $6 a month, you can afford
to be really, really flexible.
And they combine that with a great control panel,
fantastic customer service, and ton of devices
that are ready to go.
And maybe the most important thing about Ting
that I don't talk a lot about, because it's just obvious
to me now, is they don't have a strategy to get into media.
They don't have a streaming service.
They don't have a Ting app store.
They don't have a branded experience with partners
that they want to push down to my phone.
They don't do any of that.
They don't care how you use the service.
They just want you to have service.
And you can pick from CDMA or GSM.
And they don't have some sort of Ting ROM
that you'll have to install.
So they don't get in the way of updates.
If you've got a phone that gets frequent updates,
like the Pixels, and the Nexi, and the Motos,
they don't get in the way of that.
You get the updates as soon as the vendor releases them.
That's, by far, one of my favorite things about Ting.
And embarrassingly uncommon in the US
when you buy devices from carriers.
But there's so many other great things about Ting.
The customer service, like I mentioned, is bar none.
The control panel, always the best, and much, much more.
Start by going to linux.ting.com.
Take $25 off a device, or if you bring a compatible device,
$25 in service credit.
linux.ting.com.
Big thank you to Ting for sponsoring the unplugged program.
Wes, you found this cool, cool terminal app
that, for once, isn't powered by Node.js,
but it's still super cool.
It's written in Go, actually.
And how would you ever know it's named GoTop?
Yeah, exactly.
You've got to make sure you know.
And it's another terminal-based graphic activity monitor.
And it's so epic.
First of all, because it's in Go, it's really simple.
It's a small little thing, no big deal.
And it has a colored end cursor,
it has a colored end cursor's graph,
and it has boxes of memory usage in your process list,
and it boxes everything out into individual segments.
It's the exact kind of thing if your boss is walking in
and you want to have something grayed up on your screen,
and you could just have this up in an SSH terminal,
and you just tab over to that when your boss walks in.
Oh, yeah, just pulling down some metrics off the old server.
Meanwhile, you're watching YouTube on another tab.
Yeah, right, probably also in a terminal,
but in the other team works pane.
Yeah, actually, you did have a pick
for bare minimal YouTube this week, too,
that almost made it in the show,
which could go nice with this.
Minimal YouTube, do you want to check?
Check your link, see if you have it,
because we should almost bust that out.
It has a light and dark mode,
and the installation is just dead simple.
You just get, clone it down, you run the shell script,
you've got it to go, and of course,
it's in the AUR, too, as gotop-bin.
Where was it?
Oh, yeah, yeah, so it's minimalist YouTube.
And if you go to tube.quinzel.tech,
it's Q-U, put a link in the thing.
Put a link in the IRC for that one.
Yeah, we'll put a link in.
That is like the Google search page for YouTube.
It's just nothing, it's just blank, it's minimal.
So simple. It's easy, clean, yeah.
It just gets you the video.
It's a great way to use YouTube
if you just want to go watch a video,
but you don't want all of the rest of YouTube.
So yeah, West will drop a linkskies
in the irc.geekshed.net.
Anyway, so this is called gotop,
and gotop is a super slick looking terminal
that we wanted to point you guys to,
so you have an app to download this week after the show.
And then a call out to a project
that used to make or break my day, it's Clonezilla.
And Clonezilla got a good update this week, version 25538.
And the most interesting feature
is a new massive deployment mechanism
based on BitTorrent technology.
So the machines that you're imaging
become part of the distribution network.
Well, that is just slick.
It's obvious, too, really, if you think about it.
Now, it does require some additional disk space
to do this, but I've worked on some large networks
where you're imaging 30, 40, 50 systems or more,
and this could be so useful.
It's such a neat, neat thing.
They're also baking in some part image support,
some additional part image support,
and the ability to change Windows 10 host names
when you restore an image in Clonezilla, yeah.
In Clonezilla, they just keep on going,
and it works so well.
I'm so appreciative, it's not something I use frequently,
but I am so appreciative.
Every time you need to, right, it's just boom.
And there's a live CD that has now been synced up
to Debbie and Sid and running Linux kernel 4.15.
So it's a pretty modern, pretty recent live environment
to run Clonezilla from, and then they're baking
in that BitTorrent distribution.
I gotta play with that sometime.
I don't have any need for that, but I gotta play with that.
It just sounds so cool.
And then to round out sort of an app pick-ish section,
Font Finder is a GTK3 application.
Yes, I'm still talking about GTK applications.
That is a really easy, smooth front end
to browse Google's free font archive from the comfort
of your Linux desktop.
And it's super straightforward.
It's exactly what you'd expect, but at the same time,
it's pretty nice.
You can search for the font you want.
So say you want to go get Google's Robo font,
or Roboto, I think it is.
So you put in Robo, and then it'll
show you Roboto, condensed, monoslabbed,
all the different fonts they have.
And then in the client-side decoration header bar thingy,
it has a nice install button.
It'll pull that font down from Googles
and load it into your Linux box.
Bob's your uncle.
Robert's your father.
Now you've got a font.
I like it.
Simple, easy, and we'll have a link in the show notes
for that, because it's up on GitHub.
So that's Font Finder.
I did notice there, Chris, it was, did you pick it,
because it was Rust?
Is that why?
Your little favorite?
It actually did.
That was legitimately what pushed it over.
You know me so well.
That was totally it, too.
I was going to make a Rust joke about it,
but then I just got to let it go.
But yeah, you caught me.
You caught me.
Saree was going to join us from System76,
but Mumble is off-putting if you don't use it
on an ongoing basis.
So I think they had some audio troubles.
I might try to grab him later on in the week
and just have an offline chat with him about it.
System76 is joining the Gnome Foundation Advisory Board.
And I believe it's actually Saree from System76
that'll be doing this.
And I find this to be a fascinating move,
because while the advisory board isn't super influential
over what Gnome does, because at the end of the day,
some developer has to do the work.
And it's not like they have a lever they pull on,
and then a developer comes out the other side.
So it can definitely set directions and things like that.
But it could also, my understanding,
I was going to ask Saree about this,
is it can be sort of a sounding board
for organizations that are using Gnome,
or groups that are using Gnome for different projects.
That seems like a super sweet position for System76 to be in.
It makes sense, right?
To be able to get sort of a wider industry data collection
of how people are using Gnome,
when they're building Pop OS on top of Gnome,
it seems really, yeah.
You're part of the conversation in the community.
Yeah, so good for them,
System76 joining the Gnome Advisory Board.
Boom, how about that?
It's a rapid fire set of app picks and news.
That's what we do here on the Unplugged program.
We busted through that quicker than I expected,
even with a bonus app pick.
Linux right to the brain.
Man, man.
If we could just hook it up to your eyeballs,
it would be even better.
Just suck it right in through the neurons in your eyes.
Coming next week.
Yeah, we're working on that, aren't we?
In fact, maybe I'll mention a couple of things.
So there is a new mysterious operator behind the scenes.
I can't say more than that,
but I don't know if you guys remember,
but many, many weeks ago,
I announced around episode 250,
we'd be making some changes to the Unplugged program.
Yes, we did.
I think I might've mentioned it around 200.
I don't know.
Well, they arrived a little early.
And so we've been, for about a month and a half,
we've been every week,
there has been small incremental changes
for the better behind the scenes.
The poor folks on YouTube have it the worst,
but the folks on the podcast version have it the best.
So it's been a mixed bag,
although we are adding new features to our YouTube video.
We're trying a new experimental encoding
that will post the video on YouTube
and in the show description section,
include time links for the different chapters of the show.
Slick.
Yeah, that's something we're working on for a bit.
So we've been making changes for a few weeks
on the Linux Unplugged program.
And the core of it is,
if you haven't updated your RSS feeds,
it'd be a good time to go to linuxunplugged.com
and slash RSS is the feed directly,
linuxunplugged.com slash RSS.
Subscribe to that new feed,
let us know what you think,
and start sending in your feedback about it
at the slash contact.
So you can go to linuxunplugged.com slash contact
and let us know what you think.
Because it's been a slow edit of change
and we're going through another change.
So we'll have,
we've hired someone to do the editing for a bit
and see how that works and see what you guys think.
So I have been editing the show for the last few weeks.
I'll be pulling back a bit.
I'll still be involved with all that stuff,
but more changes are coming, but they're starting now.
We're sort of at the end of it all.
So it's a good time to kind of take stock
and see what everybody thinks.
And if you're on the YouTube side of things,
just be patient with us
as we sort of retool some of that workflow
because that stuff is a changing.
But it's exciting times in the Unplugged universe.
Times would be a changing.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, and also speaking of times changing,
Tech Talk Today is back on the air twice a week,
technology show, Tech Talk Talk Today.
Yeah, yeah.
With me and Ange predominantly,
but we're going to have folks in town
for Linux Fest Northwest.
So I'll probably try to get folks to jump on the mic
and hang out with us.
Special guest stars.
Yeah, I bet that Noah Chalaya,
I bet I could talk that Noah Chalaya
and that Alan Jude.
There you go.
Getting on the mic from time to time.
And then of course, we'll do a live,
we may do a live Linux Unplugged from Linux Fest.
I don't know.
I think we're also going to try to do a Tech Talk.
So we've got a lot we're good doing,
but you can just stay subscribed.
You'll get the best stuff there at linuxunplugged.com
slash RSS to get the feed directly.
All right, so let's move into a couple of final news items
for the day.
And let's also then get into the huge item of the day.
The one that I think people are still processing
and that is that Microsoft is now shipping a Linux product
based on the Linux kernel,
which I think has caught a lot of people by surprise
this week.
So we'll talk about that as well.
But first we'll mention DigitalOcean.
Here's that.
Hold on Wes, let me pull out the prop paper.
You ready?
We gotta be prepared for this.
This is serious business.
dio.co slash unplugged.
That's where you go to get a $100 credit.
Go there, sign up with a new account
and get a $100 credit for 60 days.
You can try out their new mix and match droplet there.
Flexible droplet for $15 a month.
You choose how much CPU and disk and memory you need.
You mix and match the different resources.
They also have CPU optimized droplets
with massive high-end, great, just huge,
just massively powerful.
And then if you want to,
you can just throw in a few hundred gigs of RAM.
Just throw in a few hundred gigs of RAM too.
I don't know what you're doing,
but damn, it's amazing.
I mean, they have a whole scale.
But for me, for my humble needs,
I have my favorite sweet spot at three cents an hour.
Fact, the rigs that I don't have at three cents an hour,
they got upgrades recently from Digital Ocean.
And now it's like, they're more than,
I was like, I already have them as like,
at $5 a month total.
Like that's plenty.
Cause they're just doing like metric collection
or they're like alerts or it's one's a bot.
And it's like, it doesn't need a lot.
But Digital Ocean recently adjust all their prices
and retroactively just upgraded my machine.
So my machines just got better recently.
It's so great.
You didn't do anything.
They're just better.
I love it.
Do.co slash unplugged.
You can deploy a system at less than 55 seconds.
Everything is using SSDs.
They have 12 data centers all over the world.
20 gigabit connections, 40 gigabit connections.
I don't know, it's gigabits.
I mean, they're just gigabits for days.
Plus private networking on the backend.
Block storage, they have available as well
as S3 compliant spaces, storage.
Very nice.
Network level firewalls, monitoring baked in
to give you metrics on your CPU, your disk
and graph it all for you.
It's a really, really, really compelling offer.
And you can get a hundred dollars of credit to play around
when you go to do.co slash unplugged, do.co slash unplugged.
Well, my favorite Linux video editor
is having a development sprint as we're on the air, I think.
Or it's at least in the next few days, if not that.
Their team is going to Paris
and they're going to dedicate the time
to discuss long-term goals,
review application workflow with professional editors
and prepare for the next major release,
which is labeled 18.08.
So the KDN Live team is going there.
And then after that, after that,
they're going to the Libre, at least a sub part of the team
is going to Libre graphics meeting
for a KDN Live workshop on the 30th.
So if you're going to be in Paris,
you can come say hi to the team.
If you're going to the Libre graphics meeting,
you can go say hi to some of the KDN Live team.
That's fantastic.
So a couple of weeks ago, I'm like,
who is using KDN Live?
Is anybody else using KDN Live in production?
And I said that Crazy Cast over at Linux Game Cast
and Van Stone was editing an open shot.
I have been corrected.
They are actually using KDN Live.
So yeah, another one of the books.
I'm trying to keep track.
So if you know anybody out there,
a YouTuber or actually somebody
who's maybe not on YouTube too,
just somebody that's just making content
in some other capacity,
I'd love to know who is using KDN Live out there.
Me.
Who's me?
Who said that?
Popey.
Oh, Popey.
Oh, what are you using?
Popey is Ubuntu podcast video and I didn't even know it.
Well, it is, but we don't use KDN Live.
I used it just briefly today
because I wanted to record a video
and I needed to redact some personally identifiable
information and I didn't know how to do it.
And it turns out that I just Googled
blur credit card info or something like that.
And I found a tutorial.
And within under a minute,
I figured it out and added an effect,
drew a box around the thing that I wanted to pixelate
and it just did it, rendered it out, done.
It was so easy.
KDN Live is just awesome.
Really?
Wow.
So what about the fact that it was,
video's moving, right?
So the object kind of moves around in the frame.
No, it was a webpage with credit card info in it.
But it did show how you could move it.
But I didn't need to do that.
I didn't follow the rest of the tutorial.
I just went as far as,
oh, that's what I need to do.
That's enough, shut the video down.
I was, yeah, it was great.
Yeah, I've played with it lightly
and I like it quite a bit.
And I know that when you're working
with really long projects, that's sometimes,
that's why I was asking you like,
what is the Linux game cast using these days?
Cause when you're working with really long projects,
a program can get a lot, lot more crashy.
It's just totally makes a big difference.
If you ever watched him,
he sometimes live streams him editing his own shows.
I think on a Sunday afternoon, he does it.
My time.
And I've watched him on Twitch sometime
and he's just like chatting to people
and saying, does this music fit here?
What should I do here?
And you could just see him going over
and over and over the edit.
And I don't, I think I've seen Kaden live crash once
for him on a live stream.
But yeah, it seems to work for him.
Now I haven't seen it, I'm always,
that's usually probably when I'm recording LAN.
So I don't really have a chance, but yeah.
I've been experimenting on a couple
of behind the scenes projects just for like,
when we go to Linux Fest, if we have a camera with us,
how do I want to edit the resulting footage?
Because if I don't figure this out now,
it's gonna end up on a Mac.
That's what my thought process has been.
And I've also been experimenting with Reaper,
which is an audio editor.
Oh yeah, nice.
On the other end of things on Linux.
I think the situation with Apple and the Mac Pro
is the canary in the coal mine for Apple,
that they have no idea how to build high-end computers.
They have no idea.
The people that are making those computers
have obviously lost touch.
They don't understand thermal throttling.
They don't understand all of these things.
And it's just, I think it's too late.
Even if they ship something decent in 2019
by hiring a team of highly paid professionals
to tell them, yes, you're doing everything right, Johnny,
I think it's too late.
So it's just not a professional workstation anymore,
unless your workload is doable on laptops,
or laptop-like components,
or systems that are cooled like laptops.
So I think it's behoovent upon all of us,
if that's a word I can make up,
to try to replicate our workflow
or replace parts of our workflow as much as possible on Linux.
The only problem is KDN Live's getting better
for simple edits for me,
but Reaper is commercial software.
And so it's like, am I really any better off?
Because I'm just moving to another commercial solution,
but it needs to be sophisticated.
It needs to have certain support for industry plugins.
It needs to support multi-track.
I've got a mixer with ungodly amounts of inputs and outputs,
and my recorder needs to be able to read all of those
and bring us all in on our own track.
And it's stuff that just Audacity can't even do.
It's not even capable of doing.
So you have to have a certain level of software to do this.
It's a start, I think.
It tends to be commercial.
Yeah, at least it's on Linux though.
Yeah, no one's trying to convince me.
I'm not so convinced yet.
So I'll be curious to see what comes out
of the KDN Live sprint.
When these things happen,
it seems to be pretty good for these projects.
Like the results that we get out of it
seem to be pretty, pretty positive.
You know, I don't think I've given it a shot yet,
so now I have a new something to play with.
You ought to do like a day in Seattle with Wes.
Yeah, totally.
And then edit it on KDN Live.
I think I will.
I would so watch that.
Yeah.
You could be a vlogger, Wes.
You could.
I would watch the Wes vlog.
Downtown Seattle of Wes vlog.
Is there any Seattle vloggers?
You could just own the market
and become the next YouTube star,
which sounds wonderful.
Yeah, great.
Yeah, I've been debating whether to talk about this on air.
And so I'm not gonna put links in the show notes
because I don't want to encourage traffic,
but I also feel like it's something
that we need to be aware of.
And so I don't know if you guys have seen,
and I really don't know much about it,
but what's been going on with Linux Deepin this week?
It's really, it's a disgrace, really.
So there was an unsubstantiated YouTube video
that goes live that says that Linux Deepin is spyware
and that it's spying on you.
And then the project, after it gets enough traction,
of course, because Reddit is a cesspool of de-bags,
it gets upvoted, it starts getting a lot of attention,
so it becomes on the Deepin Project's radar.
And they respond with a blog post,
and of course, there is a communication barrier here,
so there was a couple of things that are misunderstood.
And they come back and say, well, we're not really spying.
What we're doing is we're collecting the number of installs
and they list the three or four data points
that are pretty basic bitch metrics
that aren't really gonna offend anybody
unless you're looking to be offended.
And of course, then there's a follow-up video
that then sort of just makes hay out of their admission
that they are collecting some metrics.
And I told you, here's proof of the spying.
And then everybody in the Reddit comments,
oh, they're saying they're not spying,
but then they write a blog post
saying exactly how they're spying on us.
And it's just outrage after outrage.
And I think we have a problem here because,
and I won't go through the whole thing,
but you guys know I'm a big believer
that unlike the Windows admin community
or the Apple user community
or these different sub-sects of technology,
the open source community is vulnerable
to this sort of insidious infighting
in a way that I think is destructive
to people's motivation to contribute to open source code.
So I think it's worth talking about just really quickly.
I won't go into it
because there's episodes dedicated to it
if you wanna hear this.
But I think we have a particular problem with YouTube.
It is a toxic cesspool of clickbait one-upism.
And it's compounded by adpocalypse
and constant demonetization
that forces people to continue to pivot
to try to flail around
and find a new way to get people's attention
and prey on their emotions
so that way they can click on a YouTube video
and somebody can monetize that click for a penny.
At the same time,
there is competition inherent in the platform
because there's multiple people
that are trying to cover these topics.
You've noticed that probably if you are on YouTube,
you've noticed, oh, well, really since we ended last,
Jupiter Broadcasting has been significantly
pulling back on YouTube.
And the rationale has been because I think it's toxic
and I think it's damaging to the open source community
because of its inherent nature of how the system works.
It's designed to encourage clickbait
because of the way the YouTube algorithm works.
It's designed to encourage people
to try to elicit an emotional click.
But the other problem is,
and this is a secret that Google
doesn't really like to tell you
because it's really bad for ads,
but anybody who creates content for YouTube
for a little while,
and I've been doing it for about 10 years,
I've been posting to YouTube,
so I have some standing here.
A huge portion of the audience on YouTube is kids.
And I'm grateful you guys are watching.
This isn't me saying, hey, kids suck.
It's just saying the reality is
a huge portion of the YouTube audience is children.
Not all of them are logged in, but it's a huge percentage.
And especially on the large YouTubers,
like your Roman Atwoods, your Casey Neistats,
your large channels where they get hundreds of thousands,
if not millions of views,
a ginormous percentage of that
that Google does not want you to know about,
because again, that doesn't play well to advertisers,
is children.
When you remove the child metric from YouTube,
what's left, the adults,
well, you have to realize that now these people
that are making videos about Linux and open source
are serving to a very small niche of YouTube already,
the adults.
And then it's a niche within that niche
of people who care about Linux and open source
and are willing to watch production values
that tend to vary,
and people who tend to be varying presenters
talk about these topics.
That's like a super double, triple niche, right?
Now we're way down the stack.
And so these people that are creating these videos
are really fighting for a small number of audience
on YouTube.
And I would argue it's a number that is actually too small
for them to successfully monetize.
So we have this really toxic nature
where they're competing against each other
because you only have so much time in the day
to watch a YouTube video.
They're competing against an algorithm
that's a total black box,
and it drives clickbait nature of content creators
to put something out there that I just need you to watch
because I have to grow my audience
because unless I'm getting about 25,000 views per video,
I can't really monetize this,
especially if I'm living anywhere on either side
of the East or West Coast of the United States.
You gotta get around 25, 30,000 views per video
to make a decent living.
That's not accounting for ad pocalypse.
That's not accounting for demonetization.
So don't say a bad word.
It's a very, very difficult landscape,
and it pushes people to do things
like call a Linux distro spyware
simply because it's checking how many people
have installed Firefox.
And it creates this negative momentum
and this negative discussion and this confirmation bias
that you see then spread throughout discussion forums.
Do you think that Deepin was looked at more closely
because it originates from China?
Yeah, yeah.
And do you think that that betrays
the content providers mentality?
Yeah, and maybe the people
that all got their pitchforks as well,
although I could easily see it happening to Ubuntu,
especially if Canonical hadn't been fully out ahead of,
hey, in six months, we're gonna start collecting
some basic metrics that we should have been collecting
all along.
If Canonical hadn't messaged that ahead of time,
it would have, and you guys, that's why you messaged it,
that's why Canonical messaged it, right?
Because it would have been a huge controversy.
Yes, but I just feel that there is a mentality
which is because something comes from China,
it should be eyed with suspicion first.
Absolutely, I think that's absolutely true.
I'm not saying I subscribe to that, by the way.
I think that it's actually a rather dangerous position,
a default position to have.
But I feel that Deepin has been picked out
in this way more than once in the past
by a similar group of content makers on YouTube.
There is a common theme that something that comes from China
is like cheap Chinese rubbish.
Yet what a lot of people forget is
they also buy expensive Chinese stuff.
Like, you know, they're very expensive device
that they fondle all day, every day.
It was almost certainly made in the Far East.
That's okay, but it's the cheap Chinese rubbish
that's terrible and decrepit.
Decrying everything is cheap Chinese crap
because they can buy something cheap on Alibaba.
But it turns out it's actually cheap
to manufacture something over there.
That doesn't mean it's all crap, right?
And the same goes for software.
Just because there's a vast number of developers
over there creating software at low cost
doesn't make it inherently rubbish.
Yes, they might make mistakes, so does everyone.
Nobody in any of those threads on Reddit is perfect.
None of them have ever not made a mistake in their life
and never been found out and then everything's okay.
Like, everyone makes mistakes, right?
And these people made a mistake.
There's a communication barrier
between our Western YouTube friends
and those guys over in the Far East.
And I think there's a massive misinterpretation
of basically what was in essence like Google Analytics
that everyone has turned on
unless they've got an ad blocker and everyone uses.
Yet it's not okay for them to use it over there
because they are them, that's why.
Yep, pretty much that.
It does feel, and you see it too, it's not just China.
You know, a lot of people don't trust Telegram
because it comes from Russia.
And that's reason enough to be skeptical of it.
But that's just as bad because it doesn't come from Russia.
It's not like Russia is one amorphous blocker.
That is how it is seen.
Right, exactly.
It's one guy who happens to be Russian who made that thing.
Russia is a effing huge place with a lot of people in it
that do lots of different things.
One guy who happens to be Russian
doesn't make all of Telegram bad.
There are other things that make Telegram bad,
but it's not bad.
Yeah, I think, Bobby, you nailed it on the head right there.
I couldn't say it better myself.
And so maybe that's part of what gets me going about it
is the sort of insidious thing that sort of creeps in.
You don't even realize it's what's driving your motivation.
And it just seems so damaging in the open source community.
I guess part of it comes, I got another email this week
from, I don't know if he's a well-known developer,
but the project is well-known.
And he's quitting because of just feeling
like the most common thread in there
is this awful sense of entitlement
and this sort of inflexibility in respecting the fact
that I'm a human being.
And it's just really sad to see that.
I can't agree more with that sentiment.
You know, the other thing that some
of these YouTube videos and other outlets on Reddit
is this huge sense of entitlement.
I'm just going to dog pile on this thing
that you make in your spare time for the love of it.
I'm going to criticize it like it's a professional project.
I'm going to build my own profile off
the back of shitposting about whatever Linux distribution
or whatever application it is that you think you've
got superior opinions on.
And it is extremely demoralizing for the people
that invest huge amounts of time in a positive way
to actually try and create something for anyone
to use free of charge in open source.
And then to have it shit on by a bunch of monkeys in Reddit
is really disheartening.
And it does make you think twice sometimes.
You know, I'm sat here this evening
whilst we're talking in another window.
I'm fixing the last of the bugs that
are blockers for release next week.
And I've been doing that to the early hours of the morning
for several weeks now.
And I'm pretty tired.
And when you see posts like that in the corners of the internet
where these discussions run, it really
turns you off putting the effort in.
Yeah, I find it super irony too.
So people that are sort of stuck in this cycle of trying
to create crazy content so that way they can build audience,
so that way they can reach sustainability,
it's sort of like pissing in your own well.
And they have devastating consequences
on people that are working on a passion project, that
are doing something that fulfills them.
And then these people come along and they just devastate them.
And the irony is, how fulfilling must their work be?
If they're creating content like this,
that is just this shit content, these shit posts,
they can't be proud of themselves.
They can't be fulfilled by this.
And so the very thing that's probably
robbing them of fulfillment they use
to take away from somebody who has found something that
gives them fulfillment.
It's sick.
It's the smug attitude that you see
in the comments and some of the content as well.
I'm making a funny now by pointing out this thing
that I've found.
And it's just like, well, if that's
the best you've got to contribute to open source,
I'd rather you weren't a part of it and shut the fuck up.
Yeah, I have found that it's not everywhere.
And it's not like I wouldn't say most
of these things about anyone in the Jupiter broadcasting
audience.
I have had so many wonderful interactions.
I get notes from people that just say,
thanks for working as hard as you do.
Thanks for doing what you do.
I get a lot of that.
I mean, I get haters too, but I get a lot of that.
But there are corners where it's really prevalent.
And it seems to be areas where there's
a lot of incentives around getting as many clicks
as possible, whether it's upvotes or ad revenue.
Wherever those dynamics come to play,
it just seems to be really toxic for open source.
I don't know.
I think we've made this point enough.
But it's something I've been thinking about watching
this go down with Deepin.
Because I see this go across my radar, and it's like,
how do I treat this?
Is this a news story?
I don't want to even give this legitimacy.
Now, if there was legitimately spying taking place,
I absolutely would cover that.
But when it's this sort of rough shot,
no fact-based opinion stuff.
It really breaks the trust that is oftentimes
kind of the heart of the open source community.
I kind of feel like we do this with stuff from Microsoft,
too.
It came from China.
It came from Russia.
It came from Microsoft.
So therefore, we're automatically skeptical.
And it was in full force this week
when Microsoft announced Azure Sphere, which
is a multi-part component.
But the most headline-grabbing component
is the fact that there's an OS involved
that uses the Linux kernel.
And I have seen everything from this is now everybody.
Actually, the most common thing I've seen
is this is Microsoft embracing and extinguishing Linux.
They've begun the extinguish phase.
And everybody's jumping to 11 on this one.
So we decided, let's actually talk
to the people behind the project and figure out what's going on.
And so we discussed with a couple of folks from Microsoft
that are involved in building the product, what it is.
What's going on?
What kind of Linux?
What are they using it for?
What's the hardware?
All of that stuff.
And so we'll share with you what we picked up.
Does that make sense?
We'll share what we learned.
We got the deets.
But first, let's mention Linux Academy.
It's linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
You go there to sign up for a free seven-day trial
and support the show.
It's a platform to learn more about Linux.
And once you sign up, you get unlimited access.
And they're about to add a whole bunch of new stuff
in the month of April.
70 new courses, challenges, learning activities.
It actually breaks down like this.
20 new courses, as well as some content refreshes,
50 new cloud assessments, hands-on learning activities,
and new challenges baked in, as well as taking advantage
of their new real-time grader platform
so you can get feedback as you're learning.
Ooh-ee.
Isn't that great?
That is.
Yeah, so go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Sign up for the free seven-day trial.
You support the show.
And then check it out.
They got hands-on scenario-based labs.
They spin up servers on demand.
You pick the distro and adjust the courseware and the servers.
They have full-time human beings that can help you
if you ever get stuck.
If you're busy, they've got a course schedule.
It'll work with your busy schedules.
And they got learning paths, which
are a series of content and courseware planned
by instructors for specific career tracks.
Now, you combine that with all the new content
they're rolling out in the month of April,
it's never been a better time to sign up.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
You can also try out the iOS and Android app, the flashcards,
which are forked by the community,
and the tiny bits of wisdom that they call nuggets that
go deep dives into single topics.
Like, you want to learn file permissions on Linux.
You want to learn firewalling.
You want to learn basic networking and ports on Linux.
They have deep dives into those specific topics.
Other topics too, including some development ones
at Linux Academy as well.
I love me some nuggets.
And MexiFries, because we had little MexiFries with us too.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there, sign up for a free seven day trial,
and try out the full featured training library
with everything you need to learn new skills
and advance your career.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the unplugged program.
So help me not mistake the pronunciation
of the primary gentleman that we spoke with.
Was it Galen?
Galen Hunt.
Yeah, it was Galen Hunt.
And Galen is the author of a whole line
of publications of papers that came out of Microsoft
that if you read them, would almost
kind of give you a clue of where they
were going with all of this.
Like the hint was out there.
Like the one that was published last year,
The Seven Properties of Highly Secure Devices,
or Challenges to Building Scalable Services.
And the background is you could see
that there's been a lot of thought that went into this.
So Wes and I wanted to be able to talk
on some level of authority of what Azure Sphere is.
And how Linux is being used by Microsoft.
And so Azure Sphere, think of it as something that
really has three aspects.
Overall, it's a solution for companies
that are building single chip computer products.
Devices that are often even smaller than a Raspberry Pi.
You know, truly like the toasters and the hair dryers
that haven't yet been connected to Wi-Fi,
but are just about to be.
Right, things that are running like just little micro
controllers now, maybe real time operating systems,
not big full featured things.
Yeah, we were joking, but actually very realistically,
things like those Bluetooth sous vides and whatnot.
It's really happening.
And Microsoft estimates that there's probably 10 billion
units around the world like this.
I think that might have been a yearly number two that
gets sold.
Lower end devices that you just don't traditionally think of,
but they would sometimes have like a real time operating
system on there.
Azure Sphere is stepping in here.
They're sort of making a product for these manufacturers,
a full end to end product to run on these devices.
So it's three aspects, and this is
where it starts to make sense.
You've probably heard of the new MCUs,
these machines that are a system all on this one slab.
It's part of a hardware solution that vendors
will be able to use.
It'll also be available as a dev kit later on.
And they've built in some of the similar hardware checks
that they have in the Xbox.
They took that hardware root of trust.
Each device has its own secured identity.
It uses secure boot capabilities.
It verifies that the device software installed
is legitimate.
And it's also possible to check them with the server
and have server side and client side checks as well.
Microsoft's going to be licensing that silicon.
And I didn't quite get the license out of them,
but it sounds like it's going to be pretty liberal.
And royalty free.
Yeah.
Yep.
And the second bit is, so this Azure Sphere is three parts.
That's part one, the hardware part.
The second bit is the OS.
This is where Linux sits.
It's a multi-layered OS.
And the reason why they call it that
is there's a lower level that's doing the hardware and software
verification.
The second layer is the Linux kernel.
And we pushed them for some details on this.
And they shared it with us.
It's using Linux kernel 4.9.
And Wes asked them specifically, are you
going to be tracking upstream kernel releases?
Is it based on another project?
Is this a derivative distro?
It is upstream Linux kernel 4.9.
And they said they're going to be aggressively tracking.
Aggressively.
That was their term.
Yeah, aggressively tracking upstream with that.
And so I asked, so what are you using Linux for specifically?
And they kind of shy away from this a bit.
Because to them, it's just part of a three-part solution.
I know that sounds so corporate.
But that's really how they see it.
Linux is sort of just like this enabling technology stack.
It's not like this huge come to Jesus over the GPL.
It's just practical.
Yeah, it wasn't designed around Linux.
Linux isn't a focus.
Linux was just a tool that fit into the architecture.
So we said, so how are you using Linux?
And so they're using process isolation via the Linux kernel.
And they're using sandboxes for all the apps.
And they're using the kernel features built into 4.9
for sandboxing.
And of course, they're using the networking stack
and the disk IO stack.
So they're using the base elements.
And I said, OK, well, honestly here,
is this something that you guys just slammed in because you
realized you couldn't get Windows down
on these real-time devices?
Or was Linux baked in from the very beginning
when you started this project?
And the answer was, we started this project four years ago.
And Linux was, from day one, part of the solution.
From day one, they were going to use Linux.
And then so that's the second middle layer of Azure Sphere.
And then there's the third part to Azure Sphere.
And that is the part that actually is on Azure, really.
It's the Azure Sphere Security Service.
It's a cloud service that can reach out
to every device that has a security Azure Sphere
chip in it that's part of the MCU.
It uses certificate-based authentication
for authentication to the cloud.
And it allows for device-to-device communication
directly using these certificates.
And it also includes the ability to collect
crash metrics of applications, which Microsoft
is planning to aggregate across the entire Azure Sphere
ecosystem so that way they can, at large scale,
see if all of a sudden a lot of devices
are getting this port banged on, or this application
is crashing on a lot of systems.
But on top of that, they can give those metrics back
anonymized to the hardware manufacturers,
and they can see how their devices are failing.
And then the last part of the hosted part of Azure Sphere
is a software update channel that Microsoft
will host and manage for them.
But the vendor will have a secure channel
to ship software updates.
And Microsoft will run support for 10 years.
They will support these Linux-based IoT devices
and give vendors a channel to ship updates
and give them metrics for 10 years.
They have an SDK coming soonish, probably like summertime.
It's going to include a dev kit board, hooks up via USB,
and then you can start banging on it.
Even Visual Studio integration sounds
like a pretty decent development environment.
The core problem they're really solving
is hardware manufacturers that, say,
want to make a Bluetooth sous-vide,
or a Wi-Fi sous-vide machine, or a Crock-Pot,
they don't have to now build a whole server infrastructure
to manage incoming requests, set up a REST API,
set up push services, build out through data centers
all around the world so that way they can have low latency
connections, and then have an on-staff software team that
ships out updates and looks and analyzes logs and ships out
fixes, Microsoft is now doing all of that.
They're figuring out the inner device communication security.
They're figuring out how to push out the software updates.
And they're even using a Linux kernel
for the actual low-end hardware devices.
It is truly like a, you want to make an IoT device product GE?
Well, here's Azure Sphere.
We'll take care of the silicon.
We'll take care of the software updates.
We'll take care of the metrics.
And we'll take care of 10 years of support channel for you.
You just have to figure out the product
and figure out what you want to do with it.
And we'll handle the back end stuff.
Seems like that's going to be a big, big thing.
And you tie it in with Azure, which is all over the world.
Microsoft would probably price it extremely aggressively
to get people to try it.
Right, yeah, I'm sure.
And then it's oh so easy.
Oh, we'll just keep you a host of other things in Azure
as well, of course.
Yeah.
And fascinating that from day one four years ago, Linux.
I thought another part that was interesting
was that a large part of that was that their vendors,
their silicon partners, they already knew Linux.
And Linux was open source.
It was easy for them to experiment,
to take Microsoft's code and iterate on it,
make improvements, ship them back, share them.
Kind of speaks to the things we like about Linux.
I don't know if they would characterize it this way,
but my personal takeaway from our call
was they were surprised how much attention the Linux
aspect has gotten.
They didn't see that coming because,
and kind of paraphrasing, they're like,
well, we've been shipping Linux on switches in Azure,
and Linux is a massively growing aspect
for that end of our business.
So when it comes to Azure, Linux
has been part of their business for a long time,
and it's totally normal to them.
They're not even surprised by it.
So they weren't quite expecting the amount of reaction it got
because their mindset has been, well, yeah, of course
we're using Linux, which was weird for us
to kind of get up to speed on.
Because they were like, I don't know why everybody's
so surprised by this.
I'm like, really, guys, you're shipping a Linux-based OS now.
Like, yeah, well, this is the Azure team.
This is what we do.
Like, OK.
Yeah, and from that perspective, it does make sense.
Yeah, it fits.
It was the right tool at the right time in the right place,
and good on them.
Yeah, I suppose so.
And they talk about, so you'll hear in the announcements,
you'll hear Microsoft has put certain Windows security
technologies into their version of Linux.
You may have read some version of that in the press releases,
and we said, what is that?
What are these Windows security techniques
that you're now applying to Linux?
And predominantly, it was around the crash reporting,
the Windows crash reporter, tying that
into their existing infrastructure for that,
but also came down like a couple,
the way they designed some of the permissions.
You remember, there was like a third thing
that they took from Windows.
It didn't seem like a huge deal, but I didn't note it down.
But the crash metrics collection, oh, oh,
the way they're slip streaming the updates in
to be low bandwidth so that way they can slip updates in,
they're using that same system that they
use for Windows 10 to do that.
Yes, right.
That's what it was.
So anyways, kind of a compelling offer.
I didn't ask them this, but when I first
heard the announcement, I was a little surprised
it wasn't based on an existing distro,
like your Ubuntu core or something to that degree.
I was a little surprised that they
decided to roll their own.
But when you hear about the other stuff,
they've wrapped around it.
I think I can understand why.
Yeah, and it may be that these devices
are special purpose enough that you
don't need a full featured regular sort of user
landing your tightly.
Yeah, the kernel really sounds like an enabling piece
of technology.
It's not like the core aspect of these devices.
It's just a sub-aspect of three parts of a component, really.
But a big turn of events for Microsoft, either way,
from where I said it seems like a big deal to me.
And they went out of their way to make
sure it was clear to us, including setting up
a conference call.
I think they said they were at a conference, at RSA callers?
Yeah, they're at the RSA conference right now.
So they grabbed a room, and they got a group of people
from the Azure team in a room and got on a phone call with us.
That's why we didn't do an interview.
But they got on a phone call with us
and let us just bang questions at them for a half hour
about this thing.
And I walked away feeling pretty impressed.
I went in not really understanding
what's going on, wondering, is this embrace and extinguish?
But I walked out of it with, well, those takeaways
that I just shared with you.
Yeah, I mean, it really seems like they are motivated.
They see the business case for all the terrible IoT
things that already exist in the world
and why that needs to be fixed.
Whether or not it's going to be adopted, I don't know.
But it might be a good thing if it is.
I wouldn't be too surprised if Microsoft doesn't have success
working directly with like fridge manufacturers.
And they can do that big business to big business.
And they're already in on so many different devices.
And some of these devices have tried
to ship versions of Windows embedded,
and now they can just shift those hardware partners over
to this, possibly.
I don't know.
Anyways, I was really thankful.
And I extended them an offer to come on the show down the road
if we have more questions.
So if you have some questions or comments,
leave it either where you're watching or linuxunplug.com
slash contact.
Is there anything from the Mumble Room
that any questions or thoughts about Microsoft
shipping a Linux distro?
That's kind of a big development in itself.
I mean, I guess it's not fair to call it a distro,
but a Linux-powered product, I guess we could say.
I think Linus Torvalds says he won.
Yeah.
Yeah, that famous quote, when Microsoft
starts making applications for Linux, I've won.
Yeah.
And there was a real just practicalness in their mind.
They just thought for these ROT devices,
these really kind of lower-end real-time operating system
devices, Linux was just a better fit.
And then you have to wonder, would they
have done this if the last few years of work on containers
and sandboxing hadn't been going to the Linux kernel?
Because those are some of the core features
they're using to secure the applications that
run on these devices.
Right.
I mean, you need a certain amount
of those primitives available so that you can build.
If you're trying to build a secure OS,
you need to be able to achieve that goal.
Yeah.
And if those weren't there, they wouldn't have had that goal.
Minimac, you have a point about sort of the future.
Yeah, see, with all these changes
they did, the last thing, meaning restructuring
the whole company, it looks like they
want to be a service provider in the future.
So selling software is not that important.
Selling services, that makes money.
We've been talking on the Coder radio program, Coder.show,
about Microsoft sort of becoming the new IBM.
And it started about three weeks ago or four weeks ago
when we did a retrospective look at Sun Microsystems
and their influence on the IT industry,
their influence on Android and Java.
And that retrospective then got us
talking about IBM, which we did last week.
And at the end of our retrospective of IBM
sort of at its heyday in the 80s,
we realized that Microsoft is very much getting
to a new version.
My co-host, Michael, calls it a platonic ideal of what IBM
wanted to be, is what Microsoft is becoming.
I don't know.
I'm watching this, all of these events.
And you go into it with, at least I can't help,
because I came up during the good old wars of Microsoft
and Windows and Linux.
I mean, that was the fire I was raised in.
Yeah, exactly.
So when I see these stories, that, oh, man,
this is embrace and extinguish does go across my mind.
And I have to really sort of just take a moment
and be self-aware and go, OK, well, that's
an emotional reaction.
That's an emotional reaction.
Be mindful.
And what could this really be?
And I think what's deeper is what we are witnessing
is that Microsoft is going to become
one of the handful of companies that has successfully,
and I mean very successfully, monetized Linux
and open source.
And we have a hard time with that in the open source Linux
community.
We don't like people making money.
You know, we have a few handful of blessed companies,
like Red Hat, that will even celebrate when they make money.
They're allowed to make money.
But otherwise, you're not really allowed
to make money in Linux.
And so when Microsoft is becoming
one of the clear leaders of people making a profit off
of Linux and open source, I think
it doesn't sit well with us.
I think below all of this is, what
if one of the companies, at the end of this war,
everything we fought for, at the end of all of it,
when all is said and done, the company that's
making the most money off of Linux
or making some of the most money is Microsoft.
I think that's what's really bothering people,
is they shouldn't be allowed.
They fought us the whole way.
They shouldn't be allowed to have this.
This is ours.
But they're a smart company with a lot of smart people.
And they made some smart changes.
And now they're going to be one of the number one moneymakers
off Linux.
You see, they don't have to destroy Linux.
They don't have to take over Linux.
They don't have to convince the Linux Foundation to slow down
development or any conspiracy theory
that people cook and bake and come up with.
Because they can make money off Linux just the way it is.
And they're making more money than ever.
And the GPL will keep Linux Linux.
That's done.
The GPL is done.
GPL too.
Unless they convince Linus to relicense,
I think we're pretty much safe here.
And so what we really got to wrap our heads around
is that Microsoft is going to be one of the biggest
moneymakers off of Linux.
And we've got to think about how that makes us feel.
And maybe that's what's influencing our reaction
to some of this.
Are they better at Linux than we are?
I mean, that's just it, right?
Not to be Mr. Linux podcast psychologist here,
but I think that's a play a little bit.
Because it's unsettling.
You're not allowed to make money off of Linux.
You fought us on this.
You called it a cancer.
But we all know that things change.
And this Azure Sphere, shipping Linux at the core of it,
may be just the tip of the iceberg.
Think about that for a second.
If.NET Core, Visual Studio Code, all of those things
have been brewing in the background for years, four
years, and then PowerShell Core comes out, another four years.
And now we've heard of this, Azure Sphere
using a Linux kernel, about four years in development.
Something big happened at Microsoft.
Well, we know what happened, but four or five years ago,
all those stories about Satya taking over,
we heard about the top echelon of management getting reorged.
But just like how it always goes,
the actual worker bees down below,
people that got moved, fired, shuffled around,
we didn't hear about them.
But that's where some of this work started,
down in the bowels of Microsoft, where lots of reorgs
happened that didn't make the headlines.
And that's the hard part, we're having a hard time
wrapping our heads around when it comes to how Microsoft is
behaving now.
It's because we've seen Satya, we've
seen the top layers, because those
are people on their websites.
And when they make changes, they got to update the website.
They make a press announcement.
But when you're 10 managers down the chain,
and you're working on some prototype product,
and that doesn't make headlines.
So it's a different Microsoft, too.
So it's a Microsoft that's learned
how to make money off Linux and open source,
and it's a different internal beast
that we haven't really learned yet.
We have so many decades of experience
with the old configuration.
But now we're dealing with Microsoft in a totally
different configuration.
They're not as static of an entity
as we want to think that they are, right?
I mean, I feel like an old version of Microsoft
would have figured out a way to cram NT on this,
or would have crammed some BSD that they didn't even
have to name on there.
There just would have been a hard line.
It's clear something deep down changed.
Right, yeah, clearly the leadership doesn't object.
There's not this entrenched resistance,
at least it doesn't seem to be.
And it doesn't feel like it's the light of Stallman either.
It's just simply.
It's just practical.
You've got to wonder if they're sitting around the boardroom
going, I wonder if we can make more money at this Linux
stuff than Red Hat.
Yeah, right.
Do you think we could make more money than Red Hat?
Let's give it a go.
You know, that's what's going on.
It's good old capitalism.
And then we're sitting back going, what the hell?
A Linux kernel, embrace and extinguish,
embrace and extinguish.
It's just reactionary.
But maybe now we'll be seeing, you know,
security-related patches flowing from Microsoft upstream.
Who knows?
Yeah, weird, weird.
Yeah, especially if they start shipping a lot of these things.
Going to be a lot of Linux kernels out there.
How are they going to do 10 years of support?
That's a huge commitment.
I guess that's just something else
I'd like to follow up with them is,
are they going to run their own internal forks?
Because you're going to have to do your own LTS.
Or are they just going to be updated a lot?
You know, is this going to be like a continuous deployment
style?
So they'll be on 5.0 in a few weeks.
Maybe not that current.
I don't know.
I guess we'll have to wait and see.
We also don't know quite what the licensing's
going to be around the silicon yet.
We don't know, like, what the, because they're
going to also release the specs.
We don't really have a clear picture.
They said royalty-free, but we don't really
have a clear picture.
And all that.
Like, will you be able to even design applications
for it from Linux?
We don't know.
All that is still to be determined.
But it was something.
It was really something to see that.
I did not expect that story this week.
Did not see that coming.
All right, guys.
Well, is there anything else we need to cover before we
get out of here this week?
Mention the Ubuntu podcast.
We've got to do that, Ubuntu podcast.
Go get more poppy and wimpy over there.
Good show.
And yeah, OK, go get more Westpane, techsnap.systems.
How about that?
Bam.
Should plug our own stuff, too.
I like it when we do that.
OK, everybody.
Well, we'll get out of here.
Thank you for joining us.
If you want to join us on a Tuesday, you're more than
welcome.
We do this show live over at jblive.tv.
Usually, the live stream kicks off around 1.30 PM Pacific.
You can get it converted to jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
Then you hang out.
You join us.
And then kick back and enjoy the Yatsunoa show, which comes
just right after this show.
Bonus show.
And then go get more.
Just go get more.
Just more JB.
Always, more, always.
There's more shows, linuxunplug.com.
There's more there, jupiterbroadcasting.com.
There's more there.
There's always more.
Tech Talk today.
Yeah, Tech Talk talk today.
All right, thanks for being here.
We'll see you right back here, next, to, who, who, who, who's
up next.
Oh, you know, ironically, I think most people catch the
show like on Wednesday, Thursday, and Friday.
So I really shouldn't say see you next Tuesday.
Just see you next week.
See you next week.
What do we call this thing, guys?
We covered a lot of things.
Thank you, everybody, for contributing.
I really appreciate it.
I enjoyed the heck out of the show.
Extend and extinguish.
Boom, done, title chosen.
Extend and extinguish, huh?
That's not bad.
That is not bad.
I'm sure that would get a few clicks.
I'm going to submit it.
JBtitles.com.
Go vote.
Can you give me a bit of YouTube consultancy, Chris?
Sure.
Can you create multiple channels under a single, like, Google account?
Yes, I have it.
How the heck do you do it?
What I've done is I have different Google accounts, and then I have them all logged in.
You know, you can use a little switcher.
That works better for me.
Because then you can just go in and add them as managers to the individual YouTube channels.
But yes, that's how I do it.
So I have like a Jupiter, I have Chris at Jupiter Broadcasting.
I have my personal one.
And then we have a couple of, like, behind-the-scenes channels.
Those are all different Gmail logins.
And then I've logged into the browser, and I just switch up in the little YouTube thing.
OK.
But I don't want another Google account.
So what's your trick, Bobby?
I'm trying to figure it out, because I did it a long time ago.
And I can see them both there in the Creator Studio.
I think there used to be a way to do it through Google+.
And I don't think you can.
I don't know.
There's some functionality that they used to do through Google+.
They've removed now.
And they haven't replaced it, but I can't remember what it was.
Azure goes Linux.
That happened a long time ago, though.
Azure as a service.
How much Linux is in that Windows?
The bonds of Azure.
It came from Redmond.
What did I submit on your behalf?
I forgot.
You had something.
Oh, yeah.
Embrace and Extinguish.
Maybe one called Lindows.
The end of Embrace and Extinguish?
Maybe.
There was a new snap that I saw recently that I was surprised could actually
be a snap.
And I thought it was something more like at the system level.
But now I can't remember what it was.
You guys, does that remind you of any bells?
It was pretty vague.
But there was some new snap I saw go across the news headlines.
And it was like, that's possible?
Notepad++?
The Windows version of Notepad++?
No.
I'm not even kidding.
That is the fastest growing snap right now.
Really?
I'll give that a go, actually.
Snap install Notepad-the-word-plus-the-word-plus.
It's pretty interesting that you can like.
And I know the first thing everyone's going to shout at me
is the Flatback guys did this with games
and chucked them on the pirate bay, bundled wine
and a game, dodgy pirated copies of games.
OK, yes, I know they've done it before.
But this is like the first time we've had a legitimate application bundled
with wine in the Snap Store, because it's an open source application.
It's not some proprietary.
It's not like someone took Photoshop and bundled it with wine
and shoved it in the store.
This is a GPL application that's been bundled with wine
and put in the store.
It's a weird one, but it turns out it's a popular application.
And so people install it.
And it got me curious as to what Windows applications that you
miss from Windows that are not proprietary, which is a tricky one,
would you want available as a Snap?
I can only think of commercial ones, you know?
Because that's the only thing I use Windows for.
If I want to use free software, I just use Linux.
The lunatic in me thinks we should bundle wine and Steam inside of Snap
just for the lulz.
Yeah, totally.
Yeah.
Let me change topics here for a second, because I
want to pick your guys' brain.
I have a little birdie telling me that an XPS 13 review unit
may land on my doorstep in the next couple of weeks.
Is that now we've finished with it?
Yeah, it's probably your used one, Poppy.
I was very good with it.
I polished it and wrapped it all up just like it was new.
Actually, it may be.
Like, is there any identifying marks on there I should look for?
Was it a high DPI or a standard?
I can't remember.
I think you got the standard.
Have you not listened to our amazing review?
I did, but I seem to recall you got the standard DPI screen,
but I don't remember for some reason.
We got the best model, in my opinion.
So we got the one with the 1080p screen, but with the 16 gig memory uplift.
My personal opinion is on the XPS 13, that 13.3 inch display, 1080p, super crisp,
and then you get the benefit of the enhanced battery endurance
using that 1080p display rather than a UHD display.
I think I should ask for that.
This is a thin one with only USB-C ports.
No, I think it has regular ports still.
It just has USB-C in addition.
They're not monsters.
Well, I mean, there are more USB-C ports, and they're very, very thin.
It is those things.
That's true.
Those are true statements about it, but I'm looking forward to it.
I'm just kind of figuring, like, what's a new take on a laptop review?
That's what I'm trying to think of.
So if you guys have any ideas, let me know on a new take.
I'll probably try all the different smattering of distros and different
functions, but take it to the beach.
Take it to the beach?
Yeah.
Take it to the beach.
Work a day at the beach.
Yeah.
Definitely trackpad.
Yeah, definitely trackpad.
Yeah.
I'm just curious.
We have time to think about it.
I think it'll be a few weeks, but if people have ideas, I'd love to know.