Well, I found something I'm gonna be staring at
for a little while.
It's a live tracker of Starlink satellites.
Have you seen this, Wes?
Satellite map.space.
Talk about a new distraction I did not need.
And it's not only Starlink, there's OneWeb on here too.
They're just flying all over the place.
They're above us right now.
Like I'm looking at these two here and it,
wait a minute, are they about to, oh no!
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Brush off all that Starlink debris.
We have a show to do, would you?
This episode is brought to you by the all-new A Cloud Guru,
the leader in learning for the cloud, Linux,
and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses, thousands of hands-on labs.
Get certified.
Get hired.
Get learning at acloudguru.com.
Well, coming up on the show today,
can you self-host your own shells.com-like alternative?
Obviously, at a different scale, but is it possible
to take a desktop environment and put it in a container
and then access it remotely?
Well, not only is it possible, thanks
to a really cool open source project,
but it really kicks the llama's ass.
In fact, you can do it with just about any modern web browser
and you'll probably be able to get it set up
in about 15 minutes or so.
We'll tell you all about our experiments
with Web Top on the show and how it's
going to solve a major problem during our Jupiter Colony
reunion road trip.
It's going to be like our hero tool, potentially.
That is, if I can get the server up and running
for any continuous moment.
It's been crashing all morning, Wes, and I'm a mess right now.
This is going to be a bad show.
I'm just going to warn you.
Normally, I say it's going to be a great episode.
Got a real big show.
We have a terrible show today.
It's going to be awful because of me.
I'd like to point out that we didn't just do an Arch update.
I'm not to blame.
No, you are not to blame.
It is, I think, the heat.
The server is locking up and it's
behaving very much in a hardware failure kind of way.
I got in this morning and I went to connect
to our beloved Arch server.
And my web dashboard for this thing
I'm working on for the road trip didn't load.
And the server has been so dang reliable,
I thought to myself, oh, it must be my workstation.
So let me check network manager.
It says I'm connected.
Let me see if I can ping other stuff.
Hmm.
Well, all right, I'll go to the console.
So I go down to the garage slash server room.
And I access the console.
And it's just dead.
No response, nothing.
I type in nothing, no blinking cursor, nothing, Wes.
Nothing on the console.
So this is not just a network problem.
It's not the NIC going out.
This thing's dead.
The server is so reliable that it did cross my mind that it
might actually be a bad keyboard.
So I swapped out the keyboard.
Because I thought, no way, the server's locked up.
It's never locked up.
The server has actually never crashed on us,
unless we screw up an update.
It's been a rock.
No, that's been it, yeah.
Sometimes we did stuff, and ZFS didn't build right,
and our root file system wouldn't mount.
But that was on us, not the server.
And honestly, every time we learned a lesson,
and it's been really solid.
And so I would swap out the keyboard, still not working.
I do a hard reset, power it off, power it back on.
And I'm watching the console output like a hawk
at this point.
Every BIOS post message, when grub loads, then system D.
Like, I'm watching every single thing.
The console loads up.
I type on it.
I get logged in.
I can ping stuff.
OK.
I go back to my desk.
The web dashboards load.
A few things need to be cleaned up.
A couple of the applications crapped themselves.
But I fix all that up.
Good to go.
So I come down to the studio.
I jump on the stream, and I'm kvetching
about how our server crashed this morning.
But I think everything's OK.
And I go check on it, and it doesn't respond.
And again, I go out to the console,
and it's totally locked up.
And this is what, Wes?
Like 20 minutes ago, 15 minutes ago, maybe, at the most?
Yeah, pretty much, right before we get on the air.
My baby, Wes.
My baby.
And I think it's dying.
I think the heat here in the Pacific Northwest
has just crushed it.
It has been too much.
And the worst part is it's about to get hotter
over the next few days.
Right.
You won't be here to manage it.
And you do your best at the studio,
as I've seen trying to manage airflow, cool it off
when you can, which isn't always possible.
And then not only is this a valuable archival resource
for us at the studio, it's a back door into the studio
with WireGuard as our server there.
And I know it hosts a bunch of personal stuff
in some of your media collection, which you probably
want if you're about to go on the road.
Not only that, but it's going to be an environment where
I can run this web top application that we're
about to talk about and have a remotely accessible machine
on the studio LAN.
And that, to me, is going to be extremely valuable when
I am in limited compute and limited mobility with LTE
connectivity.
Having a rock solid always on workstation
that can do a lot of my heavy lifting
was going to be a key part of my on the road strategy.
I think now I'm going to move that off to Linode
because I just can't count on this local server.
I'm just going to have to deploy this on Linode
and run it there.
And they're going to have plenty of compute
and plenty of networking.
But it's unfortunate it's going this way.
It's an old box, too.
We bought it from Unix Surplus used,
I think in 2017, 2018.
I can't remember exactly when.
So that means it's been through a couple of winters
and a couple of summers.
It's got an Intel Xeon L5640 24 core CPU.
So it's got quite a bit of cores for what we need.
And it's got 56 gigs of RAM.
I can't remember exactly how we got there.
But it's got 56 gigs of RAM in it.
And it's done a really great job for us.
But now it doesn't seem to be able to stay up more than 20,
25 minutes.
And I am legit going through an emotional process.
I am grieving the loss of our server right now,
especially because I'm six days out from the road trip.
So I can't even get anything to replace it,
even if I had the money to replace it right now.
There's just not the time to get it in place, no.
I mean, you really don't appreciate these things
and how reliable and how much you depend on them
until you start questioning it.
Yeah, when I realized what a rocket had been
and what it feels like now, it's like I'm
losing a friend.
But the road show goes on, in theory.
And our first meetup is scheduled for August 7,
which really is not that far away in Salt Lake City.
Our second meetup that is scheduled
is in Denver, August 20.
Plus, we will have the micro meetup link available,
where you can submit a request to me with,
I just have a few questions in there for you.
And we'll have a route with a live tracker.
Our own tracks installation is still up and running,
because that's up on a Linode box.
And so we'll have the live map that will give you
my location as we go around.
But we have a lot to get into today,
despite the state of my server.
So before we go any further, we've
got to bring in our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Hello, Chris.
Hello, everybody.
About 22 of you on the Mumble server today.
Linuxonplug.com slash Mumble, if you'd ever like to join us.
We have a quiet listening area and an on-air area.
It's a great way to just listen to the show in real time.
Talk about a low latency way to do it.
But the other thing that's just kind of cool
is it's all free software.
If you join like on a Linux box, or I suppose a PSD machine,
and run Mumble, we're running this entire stack
in the studio on Linux.
Mumble is free software.
So you can listen to the show in real time
with low latency, high quality Opus audio
when you connect in on Mumble.
And if you ever want to join us on air to jump in on something,
you can.
Like the Framework laptop, which is our first community news
item this week, we've all been waiting for the reviews
to land for this ultimate right to repair machine.
And it seems like overall, the reviews
have been a lot more positive than I think probably either
one of us expected.
Yeah, really.
I mean, the biggest negative that seems to have popped up,
and unfortunately, more than a few times at this point,
is the battery life.
But maybe we can take the Verge's review
as a bit of a case study.
They took a look at a model, came with let's see
the configuration here, display 13.5 inch 3-2 aspect ratio.
Yeah, 3 by 2 aspect ratio is kind of unique.
I like that.
It's your only option, but I like it.
Yeah, 2256 by 1504, and not a touch screen before you ask.
Comes with an Intel Core i5-1135G7,
and only 8 gigs of RAM on this model.
But don't worry, you can get more
if you're building this for yourself.
And that price, I think for configured,
as configured like that, is just under $1,000,
or basically $1,000 at $999.
But the notes about the battery struck me
as potentially solvable, because the whole idea
about the framework is that so many parts are replaceable,
swappable, and the battery is absolutely one of those.
And so if this thing was successful,
it'd be pretty easy for a third party
or for framework themselves to build a higher capacity
battery that you fit in there, assuming they could have
around the same form factor.
That's one of the weird things about talking
about this laptop is I think, especially at this point,
we're so used to just everything being soldered in
and having to optimize what am I buying right now,
because I can't change it and it has to last.
And it's a little bit of you have to unlearn that when
you're configuring this thing.
True.
And ByteBitten, it looks like there
may be a touch screen in the future, possibly.
Yes, so what some other channels showed
was there is on the motherboard a connector for touch screen.
So when you use it in the framework chassis,
because you can take out the motherboard
and create a small form factor design with it,
and you put then a touch screen on it, it's all possible.
Yeah, I'd love to see that kind of thing
take off where other people start building parts for it
too, but you'd really have to have some mass user adoption.
I think that's kind of the whole elephant
in the room about the framework laptop
is how it ends up playing out is going
to depend on how successful it is,
because they're not going to make
all of these additional modules, and there's not
going to be a bunch of upgrade components
and multiple iterations on the motherboard and CPU
that fit in the same chassis unless this thing sells
like crazy.
It seems like that's the other part of this
that has to be successful.
Yeah, I mean, I think, thankfully, it seems
like a decent laptop anyway.
So if it doesn't take off, it still
could be a fine machine to just get work done and run Linux on.
But you're right.
If it does take off, the value proposition
could really be a lot more.
You could easily get this thing repaired.
You could find spare parts.
You could swap things out, upgrade it as time went on,
change out the ports as things got fancier.
That would be pretty exciting.
If you look at the Venn diagram of customers
for the framework laptop, Linux user and write
to repair users, I think they overlap a lot in this diagram.
And depending on where you fall down on the write
to repair issue and how important to you
a machine like this is, I think pushes you over the edge
if you want to order this or not.
And it's been really interesting,
because I've gotten a lot of notes from people that
definitely fall into that.
I believe in write to repair.
And I want a system that can run Linux.
I like this idea.
And they're pulling the trigger.
And I know you've been on the fence, Wes.
And I think at the core of your indecision
is where you stand on write to repair.
And not so much as, of course, you want it to exist.
Everybody wants write to repair to be a thing.
But I'm curious how important you feel it is to you personally.
You know, that's a tough one.
I do think it's really important.
But I feel like I've been a little burned, skeptical,
just sort of, maybe it's just too pessimistic, honestly,
at the end of the day.
It's been hard to be able to engage
as a consumer who wants sort of the higher end of things.
You know, who really does care about computing,
likes nice computers, uses nice computers, not just for sport,
but for work and for getting stuff done.
And up until now, it's been hard.
You do have some of that stuff maybe in the ThinkPad line,
especially.
But basically, everywhere else, this
isn't really a choice you've gotten to make.
So unfortunately, it seems like there's
a bit of a barrier or an activation potential
for me emotionally to sort of be willing to believe
in this potential again, even though I really do want to.
Carl, it sounds like it does match up for you.
You ordered one.
Yes, sir.
I'm looking forward to getting it.
I'm going to be in batch two, which
is supposed to ship in August.
I'm guessing you probably went with the DIY edition,
so it's OS free.
Absolutely.
Yeah, I didn't get any storage RAM or OS for it.
So I'll handle those whenever I get it.
In fact, I just placed a new egg order for RAM and storage
today, and I placed the pre-order for the laptop
a week or two ago.
I miss the idea of just ordering the components
I want for my laptop from Newegg.
That's what a concept.
That's crazy, Carl.
Like, you can do that?
Wow.
Yeah, it's exciting.
What's going to be tricky, though, is what Linux
you decide to put on there, because you're
going to need something with a pretty new kernel.
Seems like 5.11, maybe the bare minimum, ideally kernel 5.12.
And so Jim Salter had a hard time getting Ubuntu 20.04
working on it, obviously, because it
has such an older kernel.
And even 21.04 wasn't perfect.
And I think if I'm just remembering off the top of my
head, I think 21.04 ships with 5.11.
You'd want a distro that ships with 5.11 or 5.12.
I've been looking on the framework laptop form,
and they actually have a whole Linux section, which
I'll link to in the show notes for just getting
Linux on the DIY edition.
And I would say probably what seems
to be the most popular distro reading through there
is Fedora, although there's a poll that
was conducted just two days ago.
Or no, no longer than that, but the last vote was two days ago.
And Ubuntu was the largest in the poll,
so people are also probably doing Ubuntu then
maybe with the kernel PPA backport, possibly.
That might work.
But if I were going to get a framework,
I would probably try to run Fedora or an Arch-based distro
on there, just that way you get all that new kernel goodness.
Because not only is it an 11th gen Intel,
but there's also just a lot of new components in there.
It's a lot of USB 3.0 stuff.
I would go with a newer kernel.
Yes, I mean, this is just not in the category
of off-the-shelf laptop in any way yet.
So if you're interested in this, you
should probably be prepared to do some tinkering.
Should we talk a little BSD in our Linux podcast, Wes?
Oh, it's been too long, but our friends over at FreeBSD
are working on some interesting stuff,
including a new installer.
Although this one has a bit of a twist.
This new experimental installer is web-based,
with the interface running from a web browser
either locally on the machine you're installing FreeBSD on,
or it can actually run on a remote system.
What a cool idea.
And I don't think this is absolutely the first time
I've ever seen this executed.
I feel like an early Debian installer prototype
did this too.
But the idea that the whole installer is web-based,
and you either just do it in a web browser on a live session
on the box, or you do it on a remote system,
seems actually kind of like a compelling idea for FreeBSD,
especially since most of them, probably a lot of them,
are being deployed headless.
What do you think of a web-based installer?
OK, it seems really practical, but the troll in me
just wants to say, this is one step away from an Electron
installer, right?
I mean, yeah.
Like, why not ship it as an Electron app on the desktop?
What's the difference at that point?
I mean, I don't know, though.
It could probably be a pretty simple, well, maybe not.
It could be a monster of a web application.
That could be its Achilles heel, I suppose,
is to create a competent web installer.
It may have to be an absolute monster,
especially because you're probably
going to want some abstraction in there at various levels.
And that's probably going to be tricky to even wrap your head
around.
They're also working on improvements
to their Linux compatibility layer, which I think
is based on Linux 5.7 right now.
And it looks like they're focusing a lot on AMD Radeon
and newer Intel GPU support to get those fancied up.
Also nice to see is that the Hello System project,
which we talked about a little bit ago on the show,
the freeBSD-powered desktop OS, well, that's
been steadily progressing.
They had a recent release, and they're making great progress
towards their next one.
Wes, that's the project being worked on by the App Image
founder, right?
Indeed it is.
Hello System is one to keep your eye on.
It's not for those of you who are offended by things that
try to look like Mac OS, because they're just
leaning hard into that whole UI paradigm and workflow
and just trying to create a BSD-based system.
Michael Larbel, though, has a pretty good write-up over
at Ferronix from the freeBSD community, so go check that out
if you like yourself the BSD news.
But we wanted to sneak in just a real quick deck update.
There's some interesting technical details
that we learned about the Steam Deck's Linux implementation.
Not only will the Steam Deck be using Wayland,
but it seems like once again they've
decided to take on the hard problem of building
their own compositor.
Building their own compositor, yes, that's right.
It appears Valve's Pierre-Lou Graffé has developed GameScope
as a follow-up to the Steam Comp Manager, which was previously
used for this role, on the original Debian-based Steam OS.
He tweeted a short video of a game
being played on the Deck, and it had a crosshair cursor,
which people noticed and then asked him about.
Nerds.
Yeah, exactly, right?
He replied, yes, this is Steam OS on the Deck,
and it uses GameScope.
The cursor is drawn by xWayland.
Huh.
GameScope is the new compositor, eh?
GameScope is the new compositor, and there's
some bits in there, too, that suggests maybe Steam OS 3.0 is
powered by Vulkan.
That wouldn't surprise me at all.
I think it would require Vulkan just for Proton
to work completely.
I noticed that Neil, who's not here today,
has submitted a proposal to create a spin of Fedora
targeted at the Steam Deck that would be Fedora for game
developers and players.
And you wonder, what would the advantage of that be?
But one advantage would be that then it
could be essentially a meta package of sorts
that you could DNF install and get all of that stuff
you need to create and develop games on Linux.
So that actually could be a pretty slick solution.
But right now, we're just going to wait and see.
We haven't seen the release of Steam OS 3.0,
and we're getting a trickle feed of information.
I'm hoping I'd love for one day to be
able to chat with somebody at Valve about the Linux
implementation, because we just love to geek out
about that kind of stuff.
We'll see.
Maybe one day.
If you're listening at Valve, linuxunplug.com slash contact.
Let us know.
We can come to you.
No problem.
That's right.
All right, well, one more community news item before we
go.
We deployed a matrix server.
It continues to grow.
The information is at linuxunplug.com.
And it's a project that we watch with a lot of interest.
And it seems that Element, the creators of the Element chat
client, and they also work on the core matrix protocol,
just raised a significant chunk of money.
Yeah, they've just raised $30 million of Series B funding
in order to further accelerate matrix development
and improve Element, the chat client.
It's a little confusing, because Element's
both the name of the client and the name of the startup.
Yeah, I wasn't really sure how to explain that.
You're right.
And they also work on the core matrix protocol as well.
They're like some of the core contributors.
The people that are throwing in the money this time
is led by Protocol Labs and MetaPlanet.
That's a fund that was established
by the co-founder of Skype and Kazaa.
And both Protocol Labs and MetaPlanet are big fans
and have publicly supported decentralized communication
in the past.
So it does seem likely that this is a great source of funding
that their visions of how they want to see communications
and where Element is taking things line up.
Because when you see funding like this,
you wonder, OK, well, what's their agenda?
But it seems, early days here, but it seems
like things are lining up.
It has led some folks to wonder that since Protocol Labs is
involved, might there be some overlap between IPFS
and matrix?
And at least in this initial announcement,
it sounds like, yeah, where the tech makes sense anyway,
the teams are looking to work more closely together.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in credit for 60 days on a new account,
and you support the show by going to linode.com slash
unplugged.
Linode is our hosting provider for everything
that we've built in the last couple of years,
and we just doubled down when we went independent.
I was using them for about two years
before we made the switch for the JB infrastructure.
When we got the keys back to the kingdom,
when we went independent again, we went this direction,
and we've just gone all in.
Their infrastructure is super solid.
It's flexible, and it's fast.
You can focus on your project and not your infrastructure.
And while I'm here right now dealing with a server
outage on our LAN, my first thought
is there's no way I can get a replacement server in six days
before I leave or get one set up.
I'm going to look through the services we're
running on our local host here, and I'm
going to spin them up on Linode.
And that's just going to be the quickest and most reliable
solution for a lot of this stuff.
They have 11 data centers to choose from,
so I'll probably pick something centralized
for where I'll be traveling.
Every service level they have is backed by the best customer
support in the business, and when that matters,
it really, really matters.
And what Linode has done is they have honed and crafted
a fine product.
They've been doing this for 18 years,
and they've really focused on just making it better
over all of those years, and they have remained independent
the entire time.
Wow.
I have so much respect for that.
Imagine the headwinds they were facing
when some of the larger hyperscalers launched,
like when AWS came around.
And then when VC funded competitors
came that could basically just burn money
and they just brought on another VC anytime
they needed more money.
They had to remain competitive, and they
had to make their product more appealing than people
that essentially had endless money on either side of them.
And they did it.
They made their product more competitive,
and I watched them do it.
I watched them, and they won me over.
I didn't have to choose Linode.
I chose to come over to Linode after watching
them respond to the market and build something better,
but stay true to their original vision
about making cloud computing accessible and affordable
for just darn near everybody.
Their prices are 30% to 50% less than other providers,
and their systems are just screamers.
They continually invest in the hardware.
They know what they have to do to remain competitive,
and they're all about it.
It's not like one of the many businesses that they run,
or it's not like one of the very, very many businesses
that their VC is funding.
It's not part of their business.
This is what they do.
It is totally all about the best experience
of running stuff on Linux.
And they got a ton of distros for you to choose from.
They've got bare metal machines in the works right now.
I just recently set up a box to just hold some data for me
up in the cloud, and I have a system here
where I select what datasets I want to go up,
and it uploads it up to a Linode box.
On the back end, I have my file system mounted
to their object storage, so it just expands as I need it.
It's so flexible, so powerful,
and now I am really appreciating how reliable it is.
But I'd love you to try it out.
Maybe it's part of a multi-cloud strategy.
Maybe you want to performance test your system,
or maybe you need a backup server like I do.
So go to linode.com slash unplug.
Get that $100 for your new account,
and just try this stuff out.
Go build something, or maybe learn something,
and you support the show while you're doing it.
There are a lot of ways and a lot of companies
that let you host stuff.
I mean, there's just an unbelievable amount now.
But none of them, none of them check all the boxes
like Linode.
When it comes to the performance,
when it comes to the customer support,
when it comes to the reliability, the clean dashboard,
the API, which I don't talk about enough,
the command line client, which I also don't talk about,
the whole picture with Linode.
And it's just one of those things
you have to experience for yourself.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
During our upcoming Jupiter Colony reunion road trip,
I suspect there will definitely be some moments
when bandwidth and resources are a little constrained.
But that can't stop the shows.
They must go on.
That's what led us on our quest
to build a powerful workstation in the cloud.
That could be our steady state, a system to rely on,
a system we can jump back onto anytime we need a lot
of compute, a lot of bandwidth, need
to download a lot of resources, and we don't want to use
maybe a constrained mobile connection
or whatever sketchy coffee shop Wi-Fi we can find at the time.
But we needed a way to do that, and ideally,
a full graphical workstation because some of our tools,
we might be rendering audio, we might be streaming something.
We don't want to be constrained just by a console.
And so we decided to give WebTop a try.
We had heard this lets you do this,
and we thought maybe eventually we
could turn this into like a remote rendering system.
Because when Wes and I do Linux action news on Sunday,
it's gotten to the point now where the export of our audio
is one to one almost with the length of the audio
because we're doing a new workflow where we're
doing the effects in a new way.
And it's a super cool learning experience,
and it's both really impressed Wes and I, I think,
with what you can do on Linux now with audio,
even when it requires like a Windows plug-in or something
like that.
But it also has cost us a lot in render time.
And so we thought after the road trip,
this is probably something we'd keep around.
I initially was thinking we could use the NAS here
in the studio because it has 24 cores we could use for rendering.
But then later, like 20 minutes ago, 15 minutes ago,
I started thinking maybe we want to do this
on like a big old powerful Linode.
And I know, Wes, you jumped in there last night
and tried to mess around with Reaper
and try to get it running.
Before we get into WebTop and all of that,
I'm just curious how far you're able to push it as a desktop.
I mean, pretty far.
I ultimately ran into some issues
getting some of the weirder wine apps to run.
But I suspect some of those issues
might have been the host system that I happened to pick.
I picked one of our servers running on Linode
to try this out.
Probably should have spun up at something dedicated,
but trying to be quick here.
And that was a pretty old kernel.
So I think some of the issues might have been related.
But besides the few kind of out there wine applications,
everything was working surprisingly well.
I mean, I got Reaper up and running.
I even re-streamed the Koda Radio live stream
yesterday with OBS running in WebTop on this server,
doing a video capture out of the browser.
And it worked.
That's impressive.
So the technology here is WebTop.
You get an Alpine or Ubuntu-based container
that has a full desktop environment.
And you access it using RDP.
They bundle it with Guacamole, which
is a XRDP web-embedded client.
So the end product, the way you consume it, is at a URL.
It just spins up a URL.
I think it's like port 3000.
You get a login prompt.
You provide the user credentials,
which is like ABC by default. And you're in.
You get a desktop, and you pick which kind you want.
I think by default, it's Alpine with Ubuntu
if you don't specify a tag.
But if you specify the tag, like we did,
you can get Ubuntu with Plasma.
And their version is based on Ubuntu 20.04,
which is pretty reasonable.
That's the LTS, makes a pretty good workstation.
But it is a little funky, like Wes just hinted at,
because it's a container.
It's not a VM.
It seems like a simple concept to wrap your noggin around
when I say it.
But when you're using it, you immediately forget
you're inside a container.
You really do.
Yeah, and you just don't have any clue,
until you do a uname.
And you see some weird kernel version
that doesn't ship in 20.04.
And that's when it all dawned on me.
Oh, yeah, right.
There's a host system under this.
So that would be a tip of mine.
And I think Wes's, it sounds like,
is maybe deploy this with a host OS that
has a more modern kernel.
So that way, any applications you
might need in the container that take advantage
of modern kernel features have that,
because we did run into that.
Yeah, it's like an upside and a downside,
I think, of easy containerization, right?
And this is one area where virtualization
and containerization can go hand in hand, really.
The whole setup process is really pretty straightforward
if you're using Docker Compose, right?
Oh, yeah.
I mean, this is a great release from Linux Server I.O.
Because they've just thought of a lot of stuff.
And they hit on it here.
They admit it kind of goes against the Docker grain,
because you're running a whole bunch of services
in a single container.
And as it's set up by default, you
should be aware that it's a weird kind of hodgepodge
in between the way a lot of the Docker tooling is meant to work.
But it's not really a VM.
But it's somewhere in the middle.
So by default, I think it's set up so everything in your home
directory stays.
But if you blow the container away and spin it back up,
well, you're going to have to reconfigure the operating
system.
The performance is surprisingly good.
Because like I mentioned, it's not using VNC or Spice.
It's using RDP.
And the XRDP project has actually
gotten some love in the last few years.
So it's stayed pretty performant.
And I experienced a totally usable session of Plasma.
I did turn the effects to instant
just because I wanted to, to make it maybe feel
a little faster.
We're trying to be generous here.
Yeah, and why waste the bandwidth
trying to transmit and render a fade-in and fade-out
of a menu when it can just be an instant pop-up?
So that was my thinking.
But I was able to use that kind of configuration of Plasma
on an iPad over LTE.
That was like my ultimate edge case,
is could I turn an iPad into a Linux desktop that
has its own dedicated connection so I'm not
stealing from my limited LAN bandwidth when I'm on the road.
And it worked.
It freaking worked.
And it was totally usable.
And they have this nice little menu that expands out
from the left-hand side.
They have a little arrow, and you tap that arrow or click it.
And a little drawer slides out.
And in there, they have the ability
to kick off a keyboard overlay if you need it.
They have a clipboard, so you can copy and paste
contents between your remote desktop and your local desktop.
Super handy.
So there, you can kind of copy out
whatever is in the clipboard.
And if you paste something in, that
becomes the new clipboard contents in the container.
That's so great.
And I needed that almost immediately.
So.
Yeah, exactly.
I was like, how do I?
Oh, my gosh.
I don't want to.
OK, honestly, the first time I just
used Netcat to get some data in there,
that was before I discovered the handy clipboard support.
Amazing.
And I love how you're playing like it was Netcat when you
and I both know it was Magic Wormhole.
I used both.
OK, I just got tired of having to hop onto the host
system to use Netcat.
So yeah, OK, Magic Wormhole's handy too.
Yeah, they're both good.
But it's just, there is something really
that sparks my fancy about this, because in my old IT days,
I deployed a lot of thin clients and terminal services.
I did Linux terminal services and Windows terminal services.
And you could just use this to really kind of accomplish
the same dang thing.
I mean, I think if I was going to use it
for a really extended period of time,
there's a few modifications I might like to make to it.
The whole thing right now is kind of based around the ABC
user.
And I think things get a little hairy
if you want to change that.
And I do not like that.
So that's something I'd want to spelunk into a little bit.
What are your thoughts on changing the username?
Because it looks like by their docs, they don't recommend it.
Yeah, they do mention that.
But they do have some decent docs
in here about for developers if you
want to build your own image.
So I think it's possible with a little consideration.
It is, ABC is not the best username.
And it would be nice to be able to customize this.
I think maybe, too, we might want a version based on Arch,
perhaps.
Maybe that would be kind of cool.
I could make 2004 work for a while, though.
It's not the end of the world.
As long as it's Plasma, that's the main thing.
Really, the whole idea is to have this system that's
running that you can reconnect to and disconnect.
And it has all the tools up and ready to go.
It's an always-on state.
And we experimented with this.
You can join and reattach to sessions
and leave things running from different web browsers,
from different IP addresses.
It's all based around the user credentials.
So that means that we can leave things.
Wes could stage something for me.
I could leave something staged for Wes.
He can pop in and finish it.
That kind of back-and-forth collaboration ability
while we're remote and on the go and with limited connectivity,
jeez, man, this is just going to be a lifesaver.
It's not as flexible as something like shells.com
that lets you run a whole bunch of different distros
and all that kind of stuff.
It's one distro, one desktop environment,
really meant for one user.
The way Wes and I are going to use it, it's really for two users.
And it's not really meant for a whole suite of users
and stuff like that.
But if you need something for yourself,
if you want a full desktop environment that
runs in your web browser with really good support
and pixel-perfect resolution rendering,
if you resize your web browser, your desktop environment
sees that as a screen resize and adjusts to accommodate it
pretty quickly.
Yeah, it really is impressive.
And I've got to just have a lot of respect
for the work, the folks behind this implementation.
It's relying on a lot of different open-source software.
But I think the Linux server folks
have really done a good job of taking it to the next level
and combining all of those pieces in a thoughtful way that
just works really nicely.
By default, one of the example compose files they have,
it actually even mounts the Docker socket in there.
Now, security-wise, you should be careful with this,
of course.
But if you're doing this in a controlled environment
where you want to use this as an admin machine
for the whole VM, now in your remote desktop,
you can launch up other containers on that server.
It's really cool the amount of possibilities that you have
and sort of serverizes and deploys
the power of the Linux desktop in a way that
might be a lot more difficult with a proprietary desktop.
But for us, it's just install Plasma in a Docker container.
Go for it.
Yep.
Yeah, that's such a great point.
ByteBit, and it sounds like you were thinking about doing this
with a Raspberry Pi.
Yeah, so I like working with a graphical user interface.
But with the Raspberry Pi, you want
to save as much resources as possible.
So I install the headless version, install Docker,
install WebTop.
And when I need a desktop, I launch WebTop.
When I'm done, I shut the container down
and put it up when I need it.
But I have the resources available to me
without a full desktop.
Yeah, and all of the packages it would
require to be installed on the host system
to support the desktop, even when you're not running it.
Oh, good point.
Yeah.
Nice little optimization right there.
Yeah, that's something I might want to try in the future.
I think that's the part that's nice about this,
is some of the extra flexibility, too.
One of the things we were highlighting
is running it on Linode, which is great because they
have super fast bandwidth.
And we can get fast processing and fast disk and connection
wherever we need.
But you might also want it, like you
were mentioning, on a server somewhere that's super beefy
or has local access to some data that you might need
to run experiments on or to do analysis on
or just to have a really powerful server
to offload some rendering to.
Yep, yep.
And something else you and I were talking about off air
for our use case, we have a system here
in the studio that records our shows.
And it also does tons of really great Jack audio routing
for remote hosts and guests and the Mumble Room
and brings it all together independently, digitally,
into our specific tracks in Reaper for us.
And it's just such an awesome machine.
I hate to even touch it, but it is old.
It's got eight gigs of RAM.
It's got super old processors, old disks.
It's in a bad way.
And I do want to replace it, but I
don't want to replace it with a $5,000 system, which
is what we would need to get enough CPU cores and memory
to do the rendering we want in a reasonable time.
And so my thought was is perhaps this
is an opportunity to offload this work to a server.
We do the core recording on this machine.
We stage everything.
We export the project out, load it up in this web top instance
up on Linode with a dedicated CPU machine,
and then we just let it go to town for a while.
And then we only have to deal with it just as a recorder.
And it keeps our costs down.
It keeps the noise of the machine
down here in the studio.
So that might be something we do,
or I may end up now having to replace
the server in the garage.
And maybe there we go with something
that has a lot of extra horsepower.
And we offload some of the processing job using web top.
We move the project file over.
We log into web top, fire up Reaper,
and begin rendering the project.
And what's so neat too is you've got both sides of it
in that if it's something you need to go in and futz with
in the UI, you have a graphical UI.
But in the same sense, it's just a Linux install.
So you can have SSH in there if you need,
or whatever back to our access to go in,
kick off the script that way or with automation,
and then check on it visually.
Yep, and like everything the Linux server IO guys put out,
it's really, really well done.
The Docker compose file is easy to read.
It's easy to understand.
And then they have some great documentation
that explains it all,
that we will have linked in the show notes
at linuxunplug.com slash 416.
Go check it out.
I think they've done a fantastic job.
And I'd love to know other ways
you particularly solve this problem.
Let us know at linuxunplug.com slash contact.
Linux.entropy.works, use promo code LUP13 and save 15%.
This is a member of our community
and I love watching them go.
They're an industry leading mobile
and web development studio based in the UK.
And Entropy has global clients,
including Mars Wrigley, Walmart, Mediacom,
the Financial Times.
They're trusted by some of the biggest names
in media content, but it's not just about the big names.
No, they wanna work with everybody.
They love working with smaller companies, startups,
people that are just getting into it.
They just love building mobile desktop
and web applications.
And because they're on our show,
probably not a huge surprise to you,
but I love seeing this,
Entropy runs on Linux.
They are open source hounds.
They have a team of distro hoppers
and Linux hardware nerds
and everything they do really goes back
to their love for the Linux community.
They're listeners of the show
and they thought, you know what,
like I preach often, let's spend locally.
And I think that's a great way to go.
And some of their key tools involve Ruby on Rails,
of course, that's huge,
but they're really moving into Flutter.
Flutter for mobile and desktop
and Flutter for the Linux desktop.
They've pioneered some of the most complex
Flutter apps ever built
with full machine learning integration.
They can rapidly build apps for iOS,
Android, Windows, Mac OS, and yes,
Linux, of course.
In fact, they can pretty much do it in no time.
That's how they've become
one of the global leaders in Flutter development
with dozens of deployments in the last year alone.
So if you're thinking about taking the plunge
into Flutter for the Linux desktop
or maybe another platform,
or maybe you're a small or large business,
maybe you're just an independent dude
or dudette trying to get into the app game,
well, Entropy is always ready to chat.
They'd love to discuss your ideas
and give you some opinions, some thoughts, some input,
regardless if you wanna move forward or not,
they just love to chat.
So get in touch, chat mobile, chat Flutter,
or discuss your favorite Linux podcasts
to help you get started
and to help incentivize you a little bit.
They're offering Linux Unplugged listeners
15% off their first project.
Mobile app, web app, maybe a Linux app.
If I could vote, build a Linux app
that makes recording PipeWire sources super easy
and build it around Flutter.
Go talk to Entropy about that.
I'd buy it.
So go to linux.entropy.works,
fill out their contact form, use promo code LUP13,
they'll get in touch, get you started.
There's never any pressure.
They're always happy just to chat
and discuss your project and help any way they can.
So that's linux.entropy.works and use promo code LUP13.
Well, I think it's time for some feedback.
What do you say, Chris?
Indeed, Mr. Payne, you wanna read us Nicholas's email?
Cause he's got something that,
well, it's one of those elephants in the room.
Hey guys, huge fan of the show.
I've been waiting the last couple of episodes
to hear what you think of this.
It's a tablet built for Linux.
Not sure if you've heard about it
or maybe you've had some skepticism,
but I hope you guys keep doing what you do either way.
And he's talking about here, the JingOS tablet.
Uh-huh, yeah, we haven't talked about this, have we?
No, it's been out there.
I mean, I think a lot of our audience out there
has probably seen it on Twitter
or been written about in some of the Linux news out there.
Nicholas tries to sweeten the pot a bit,
noting that the developer says it's not locked to JingOS,
the actual hardware he means.
You're supposed to be able to boot
any ARM Linux on the device.
Although of course, the hardware is coming with JingOS,
which is designed for the tablet experience.
I don't know though, the note about skepticism in here
rang true for me.
I mean, not just about Linux tablets,
but kind of non-iPad tablets at all, if I'm honest.
Yeah, that must be part of it.
I know the reason why we haven't talked about it
is because Wes and I are becoming
so skeptical about all of these types of things.
And this one seems particularly tricky
because you've got the JingPad, which is a hardware device,
and then you've got JingOS.
And the ask here from the Jing folks
is for us to believe that both of those things, the OS
and the hardware, will be in some kind of production state
that it's worth dropping $600 on.
And it's a great price when you consider it $600
and that includes the keyboard, which Apple charges like $300
just for the keyboard.
And then the tablet's like $1,000 on top of that.
Right.
But you're right.
It's not only are we just skeptical of these kinds
of devices now.
I was on late night Linux this week,
and we talked about grifters and open source and free software.
And we've just seen so many grifters now
that it is hard to believe anything's
going to actually succeed.
And so part of us just sits here and goes, well,
when you ship, we'll believe you.
Like the framework laptop.
I think that same skepticism was applied
to the framework laptop.
Yeah, really.
However, the downside to that is sometimes
we miss cool things really early in the stage.
It's like we've gotten old and bitter.
We're missing the new stuff.
We don't want to be that cynical, right?
We should still have hope.
I think that's essential.
And we want to support projects that have a reasonable chance
of working out.
Right, right.
However, I have seen some videos of the Jing Pad running Jing
OS.
And it's early days still, but it looks surprisingly good.
To say it's been heavily inspired by iPad OS
would be an understatement.
But it has taken a lot of the elements
that work well in iPad OS and applied them
to a Linux environment.
And this is once again offering that idea
that you could have something that works in a tablet mode
and also can be switched to a desktop mode
for greater productivity.
Convergence.
Yeah, convergence.
I've never heard that one before.
And these kinds of things, they just check a skepticism box.
So something that looks like iPad OS but isn't
means that it's never going to quite be as good as the thing
it's attempting to emulate.
Something that offers convergence but so new
and doesn't have super high-end hardware leaves me skeptical.
I think you're hitting on it right there,
is that it's not that they're not saying the right things.
It's not that these aren't good goals.
But we've seen so many folks have these goals.
And then it's not even that they didn't get part of the way.
But the claim and the competition on the market
is executed on such a level and with the amount of polish
that when you just sort of casually imply
that's what you're building to, and then it doesn't hold up,
you really start doubting, like, does our community even
get why people like these other proprietary solutions?
Yep, well said.
Now, it seems conceivable, Wes, that as time goes on,
technology improves, software projects
continue to get iterated on, hardware gets better and better,
display technology and CPUs in particular
have just really just gotten better and better.
I mean, maybe at some point, those things
converge in a way that makes it possible for a promise
like this to actually be met.
And we'll be over here on the skepticism sidelines,
thinking it's never going to happen.
And we've missed this convergence of timing and hardware
and software.
And something great does come from it.
But what we try to do is we try to talk about things
on the show that we know are likely going to produce.
And they're going to result in something.
And if we talk about it and you go spend your money,
you're not going to get scammed.
Because I'm still waiting on my damn Atari VCS.
And it was a lot of those types of things back in that era
that just sort of burned me out on this.
And now I want to see proof.
I want to see a product.
And I want to see it really starting to ship, at least
to reviewers, before we really go in on it.
But it's not to say we're not at least keeping our eye on it.
And I do wonder if maybe we missed the boat on this.
And maybe we should have talked about it earlier or not.
But I still stand by that core principle of,
I don't want the audience getting scammed.
That's one area maybe where some of the Pine stuff
has been a little more successful.
Or at least, they've had an approach
of not setting expectations too high.
That's where it really gets dangerous to my mind.
Right, is setting those expectations too high
and then being unable to ever really achieve
the initial promise.
Yeah.
Because I want us to play.
I want us to try these things.
But we just need to be honest if we're still
working out a lot of the kinks.
I like their progress.
I'm happy to see this landing in reviewers' hands.
And I think it's time to start taking it more seriously.
And I may end up having to re-evaluate my stance
on these types of projects.
If both the framework laptop and the JingPad
end up actually being really solid products that deliver
on their promises, well, then that
means it's time for Chris to reconsider this line
and figure out where that line should lie, I suspect.
Well, watch.
I actually do really hope that I have reason
to re-evaluate the skepticism that has brewed inside me.
We'll see.
Also, I'd like to make a call out on the podcast.
We're looking to chat with someone at Bedrock Linux.
Please email me, chris at jupiterbroadcasting.com.
It's on our minds, and we'd like to chat with you.
Well, like I mentioned, I was on Late Night Linux this week.
Go check out Late Night Linux for that.
We chatted about SyncThing, which my SyncThing install just
recently hit the two-year mark.
It's been running really solid.
And the guys had me on to chat about that,
grifters in the open source community,
and a little fedora silver blue.
So that was Late Night Linux episode 135,
where I joined the boys.
It was a good time.
Go check that out.
We'd love to have you join our Telegram group.
I posted the most adorable picture of Levi
in there this morning.
I don't do it often.
But every now and then, the really good ones,
I drop them in there at jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash Telegram.
And if you join while this podcast is out,
it's probably not too far back in there.
Or you could just look at all the photos, I suppose.
You can do that.
So jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Telegram.
And maybe as a bonus, there's a little bit of Linux chat
sometimes, but mostly dog pics.
That's not, it's mostly Linux chat.
It is, but I mean, you saw the picture.
It's very cute.
It was adorable.
Meetup.com slash jupiterbroadcasting,
and last but not least, we'd love to hear from you.
Linuxunplug.com slash contact.
That goes into an inbox that both Wes and I can check
and read, and we try to read every single one of them.
Even if we don't respond, and they don't all
make it into the show, we try to read every email every week.
That's linuxunplug.com slash contact.
I imagine I'll be worse at that practice
while I'm on the road, but when I get back,
I'll try to get that back in.
It's something I, it's a goal of mine recently
because I ask you to send the email in.
The least I could do is read it.
So it is actually a personal goal of mine
to read each one of them that comes in.
It may be a little sketchy while I'm on the road,
but we do try.
And last but absolutely not least, actually,
I need to mention the Luplug.
They get together every Sunday noon Pacific
in our Mumble Room at linuxunplug.com slash Mumble.
You can get the details, and then you join,
and you're good to go.
You hang out and chat with some like-minded folks.
Get the info, linuxunplug.com slash Mumble.
When we were fooling around with our cloud Linux desktop,
you came across a pretty neat trick.
Yeah, this is by a gentleman named Scotty Hardy on GitHub.
It's called Docker Wine, and it's a Docker image
that includes wine and wine tricks.
But not only that, it's pre-configured
with a handy little helper script
that's ready to set things up locally with X11 forwarding.
If you've got an X server running and just wanna run the app
in the container, or it's got RDP built in
if you wanna run this wine app on a remote server.
Which means it also supports audio redirection.
It'll play sounds through Pulse Audio on your Linux box
using this whole setup.
So Windows applications in a container
that you're connecting to over RDP with sound support.
And the name is cleverly Docker Wine.
We'll have a link to this in the show notes.
This is great.
This is so neat because you sometimes need to crap up
your system to get all of this wine stuff working.
Yeah, no one wants to install all these weird,
janky Windows programs, right?
That's the perfect use case for a container.
It really is.
Like, just go crap up a container,
and then when you're done with it, you throw it away.
And what's so nice about this project
is that as somebody who does weird things
with containers and plates with it,
there can be some arcane tricks between user permissions,
between mounting all the right Pulse and X11 stuff,
let alone configuring the RDP connection to be easy.
So it's just nice that a lot of that knowledge and trickery
is distilled in one handy little script you can run.
Well, I'm gonna check on the server.
It looks like it's still up, Wes.
Huh, I wonder why it would have crashed so soon
after last time, and this time it's remained up.
What's the difference, right?
Something tells me we're gonna stop pinging it
and stop paying attention to it after the show,
and then it's gonna crash immediately.
Oh boy, we gotta get this fixed.
This is gonna, I think job one really is while it's up,
offload as much config as I can, right?
That's job one.
Because the data's okay, I would rather honestly
have some hardware component on the motherboard
or the CPU fail than any of the disks fail.
Even though we've got them in a ZFS RAID,
at least all of the disks are fine.
We can ultimately move those.
Time to check our backups.
No kidding.
In the meantime, go follow the show on Twitter
for news announcements or schedule changes,
which I don't expect there will be,
or other kinds of things like that.
At Linux Unplugged, the whole network is at Jupiter Signal
because yes, there are an entire network,
a fantastic podcast, including the self-hosted podcasts,
Encoder Radio, and of course, the companion to this show,
Linux Action News, every Monday morning,
Wes and I break down everything that mattered
in the week of Linux and open source.
And you gotta catch that.
If you're not catching Linux Action News,
you're like missing half of this show practically,
but it's just the news segment,
just the news you need to know.
It's great too if you're in the industry.
In fact, if you know anybody in the industry
that should stay up to date on this stuff
as part of their job, send them a link
to your favorite episode of Linux Action News.
It's a great way for people in the industry to stay informed.
As for us, one more show in the studio before we head out.
It's literally the last thing I do before I hit the road.
So join us for that.
It'll be the last Linux Unplugged from the studio
for a while next Tuesday at noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
See you next week.
Same bat time, same bat station.
Indeed, links to everything we talked about today,
how to contact, how to join the Mumble Room,
the matrix server, all of it.
What we've done is put it all together
on a webpage at linuxunplugged.com.
I'd like you to check it out.
Also there, you'll find links to everything
we've talked about for previous episodes,
the entire bat catalog.
It's incredible.
We're still working on a Gopher version though.
It'll happen.
And maybe a Usenet version as well.
Great way to download the show.
Anyways, as for us, thanks for joining us
on this week's episode.
We'll see you back here next Tuesday!
Right!
And we'll see you next week.
Alright, go vote JBtitles.com.
We got through it.
It was rough.
I am off my game, you know, because I was already getting a little rough.
One of my data plans just got canceled on me, which has kind of sent me into a panic
about the road trip.
And then to have this server failure happening right now.
I think you're a one-legged stool right now.