This is Linux Unplugged, Episode 21 for December 31st, 2013.
Hi, everyone, and welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux podcast that's popping a
beer cap like it's a bottle of champagne. My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey, Matt. Here we are on the precipice of 2014, and our crystal balls have been shined
once again. We are joined by our virtual lug, our mumble room. They're going to throw in
some predictions. Plus, we just did a big batch of predictions, a huge episode, almost
like an hour, 50-minute episode on Sunday of the Linux action show, where we threw down
our predictions for 2014, and then immediately, one of the reasons we actually created this
show is because we get off air, and then I go, oh, crap. Oh, I should have mentioned
X. I should have mentioned Y. So, I got a few more predictions we got to get to. Plus,
there's been a couple of things that happened this week that also kind of just clicked,
and said, oh, man, this is actually going to play out big in 2014. So, we'll talk about
that. Plus, CES is moments away, and we have reason to believe that a couple of things
that we're going to talk about today in our predictions will bear fruit in CES just a
couple of weeks away. So, I'm looking forward. It's going to be a good way to end the year.
It's our last episode of 2013. So, I think it's going to be a good one, Matt.
Definitely.
All right. So, before we get to all of that, before we get to all of our crazy crystal
ball rubbing, I want to follow up with a couple of things that were sent into the show. There
was so much email to go through. I tried to kind of boil it down to just a few topics
because we recorded two episodes last week. So, it's actually been a couple of weeks or
one week since we sat down. And so, there was a lot to get through, but I tried to boil
it down to just a few things of follow up. So, to start with, I wanted to read the email
that Zach sent in because in last episode, we talked a lot about the Chromecast. And
in that conversation, XBMC came up, but I think it deserves a little extra attention
here, and so did Zach. So, here, I says, hey, guys, just wanted to respond to the Chromecast
XBMC talk. I use XBMC all the time, and I would love to see XBMC rise to the same popularity
as Chromecast and Plex. The only real problem with XBMC right now is the lack of out of
box functionality. Now, do you think, do you think Chromecast and Plex are already more
popular than XBMC, Matt?
Here's a simple rule to follow when in doubt with these things, and this is a rule I live
by and usually cheeses people off, but it's pretty accurate for the most part. If something's
easy to use, it's going to rise to the top. Not because it's better, that's interpretative,
but because people perceive it as easier to use and perceive it to be better. Plex being
a great example of that in Chromecast. Personally, I've been playing with the Chromecast, and
I do have thoughts on that.
Oh, really?
Yeah, as far as like, you know, because I think, like, XBMC and Chromecast are completely
different animals doing completely different things, but they definitely share different
levels of difficulty and or ease of use, depending on how you look at it. But yeah, XBMC I think
is awesome as Debian is awesome. That doesn't mean you're going to get grandma to use it
without some support there.
Yeah, and I, you know, I think part of the killer problem that Plex solved was that Roku
front end, because you can buy a Roku that even if at the end of the day Plex doesn't
work out for you and the family or whoever else has to use the TV, the Roku still does
a ton of other things. So you're not totally married to one solution, whereas if you go
to XBMC, you got to build a PC, you got to set all that up, you got to hook that up to
your or maybe a Raspberry Pi if you're geeky. But again, regular consumers aren't going
to do that.
Right.
Whereas Plex is is not quite consumer level, but it's getting pretty close, where you could
have somebody that ships a free like you could have an IX system that ships a free NAS box
with Plex preinstalled and says automatically streams to your Roku and they could just put
that on the box and essentially the consumer would only have to do startup Plex on the
Roku.
Oh, yeah. Well, and I still believe honestly, Raspberry Pi is the right kind of storage
attached to it. Slap a sticker on it. It's, you know, Billy Bob's media box. Yeah. Plug
it in. You're done. Yeah. I think there's a market for 60 bucks. Sure. Absolutely. So
he goes on to say, as things are, XBMC can do a lot of things, but sucks, sucks, such
functionality requires a researching how to do it and downloading the corresponding add-ons,
which usually aren't listed in the default add-ons. If XBMC would provide a more complete
and prettier add-on manager, they would have a way better off than they are right now.
New users won't want to connect to XBMC hub to get legally questionable add-ons. The add-on
system is a little awkward. Like we have, there's a Jupiter broadcasting app in XBMC
for Roku. Jeez. See, it's confusing to talk about. There's an app for XBMC for Jupiter
broadcasting, but you got to dig for it a little bit.
Exactly. And as far as, you know, people not being willing to dig for something that's
legally questionable, that's not entirely accurate, but I would say that it depends
how hard or easy it is to get to. Cause if a good homework assignment for everybody in
the audience is to go to the cord cutters subreddit and you're going to find people
that barely know how to work their Blu-ray players running Plex. I mean, these folks
are brand new to this stuff. So I think that there's absolutely, and of course they have
no problem how they get their media as long as they don't feel like they're going to
get pinched on it.
Well, and here's the other thing he points out is he says XBMC would do better off if
they could have official plugins from like Hulu and Netflix, right?
And I would think that would give them a real advantage. Yeah.
Because again, I go back to the Roku and Plex with Plex, I get all of my local content and
it's such a great setup. Plus the library is centralized. So if I have multiple Rokus,
they're all sharing the same metadata, the same, you know, watch played status, the resume
locations are all shared amongst all of the Rokus. Roku is great because it's tiny. It's
silent. It runs Linux. It's cheap ish. And, and, and then I can hit the home button and
I can launch the Netflix app. And that's a huge deal.
Yeah, you can get a, you can get an entry level Roku for 39 bucks. You can go up to
99 or up and higher if you want to. But I mean, you out of, out of the gate, you can
walk into it very comfortably. I think for like, it's an LTE for 39 bucks and that's
quite reasonable. And it comes with a remote. There's something to be said to that.
Yeah. Yeah. And the Roku 3 comes with a really cool remote with a, with a headphone connection,
which is great for a late night TV. And so that said, you know, I was just thinking about
the, the new studio that we'll be building in early 2014 or rebuilding, I guess you could
put it. And one of the things I'm going to have in there is TV service for clips for
unfilter. And I was thinking about how I'm going to be ingesting that media and how I'll
be displaying it. And one of the things that did cross my mind was, you know, maybe a TV
with all of the clips on there with XBMC sitting in front of that. And then I could
sit down on a TV and process all the clips on the TV using XBMC. I don't, I'm still
working through it.
That's interesting.
It made it, you know, there's, there's so many, it's almost, you know, you almost put
it really well when you sit and you can look at it like Debian because as Debian could
be used for a base, XBMC can be used for a base for, you know, display systems, for billboards,
for all, you know, home, home entertainment, all kinds of things. So XBMC totally has a
place and I like it a lot and it just depends on what use case. But you know, as far as
like spouse approval factor and really, I mean, to be totally frank, you know, my four-year-old
son and my two-year-old daughter can use the Roku, right? And they can't really use XBMC
and that really is kind of a big deal.
Well, we used to, we have a hacked Apple TV that we used to run XBMC on and it, the spouse
wasn't exactly enthused with it. She used it, she tolerated it, it was fine. Plex, on
the other hand, there's no comparison. So I think, I think you really nailed it. Once
you actually introduce non-geeks into the situation who are not on pedestals, chirping
the same old chirpy stuff and actually looking at it factually, Plex really is the easier
choice and it's great.
Even though it's a little uglier than XBMC, like, especially on the Roku, it's...
Oh, it's horribly ugly on a Roku, yeah. It's hideous. But it's really, really sexy on the
Android app or even on the, when you run it in your browser, it looks really great there.
Yeah, the Roku app needs a dire, dire, needs to be addressed in a big way.
I think that might be a limitation of the Roku SDK or something, but yeah, it's awful.
It might be, yeah.
Yeah. All right, well, we got a correction that came in from Mike from episode 20, so
two weeks back. He said, hey, unpluggers, at the beginning of episode 20, the topic
of licensing Ubuntu packages for the Mint project came up. He said, no one could think
of an example of any projects that rebuilt the source, but that is wrong. The Trisco
project often purges non-free packages from Ubuntu repos and then rebuilds some of those
packages and de-blobs them. These are mirrored and corrected packages are hosted on the FSF
mirror for Trisco to use. Just wanted to let you know. Thanks, guys.
Yeah, Mike, one of the things that was different and Popey made this point when he was on the
show last week or two weeks ago, was that Mint is pointing at Ubuntu repo. So they're
using Ubuntu servers, Ubuntu bandwidth, Ubuntu packages. They're not taking the packages,
rebuilding them all, sent to us or Trisco style and hosting them on their own servers.
So an analogy would be, so one group of people would be like hot linking to an image where
another group of people might be saving the image to their desktop and they're using it
on their own servers. That would be the difference there.
So I guess what Canonical is saying is, hey, you want a hot link, you need to have a license,
I guess.
Right. You're incurring cost to us.
To me, it didn't seem like a huge deal to Clem. It doesn't seem like a huge deal to
me, but it's something we'll keep an eye on. Yeah. Okay. One last bit of feedback before
we get into the balls here. This one came in from James and he had some thoughts on
the topic of Ubuntu as a rolling distro, which keeps coming up and Mark recently in an interview
suggested that maybe after 1504 you might see something a little more like a rolling
release from Ubuntu.
So this has got people thinking and James is one of them. He says, hey guys, happy new
year. I heard you talking about a number of times about the perceived issue with Ubuntu
because you can't always get the latest stuff. Well, I was a 15 year Slackware veteran until
I changed to Ubuntu in 2008. I tested and continue to test other distros, but I still
use Ubuntu because I think it's time for Linux to just work. And I find that Ubuntu
gives me that. And also I want to build up an experience to support others. That makes
sense. Yeah, definitely. However, I do want the latest packages. So I have run the dev
version since 11.10 was released. Canonical has a policy that the dev versions work every
day and it does. I get one failure each cycle when the X server is updated and I have to
upgrade my Nvidia driver, but that's it. It works flawlessly. It means I get the new stuff
and then when the new distros released, I already have experience if people need help.
If I upgrade as soon as the new repo is available, which means I'm on production releases for
only about one to two weeks at the start of each cycle, Ubuntu works great as a rolling
release. So what James is saying is my trick essentially is I run the production version
for a couple of weeks and then once it's back up and they're working on the beta version
again, I just upgrade my repos and I run the beta version. I was going to ask the mumble
room, does anybody in here ever do that with their distro where you run the stable version
for maybe a couple of weeks and then you jump to the beta version?
Yeah, I am running CrunchBang and I immediately went into Jesse because the stable of Debian
didn't have everything I wanted and then I launched into CID and I'm still experimenting
to see how it's going to go.
I did this myself for a period of time with the Ubuntu's where I would run the stable
version for a few weeks and then I would just switch. For a while what I would do is I would
wait until after the first beta release. That's what it was. It was more than a few weeks.
I would wait until after beta one was out for a couple of days and then I would switch
over to that and then I would ride that all the way to the finish line and I did that
for three or four releases in a row, like the same installation, just kept doing it
and it worked okay but what really I ran into constantly is a lot of instructions assume
a certain version of Ubuntu and they're already having a hard time, the instructions you find
online, you have a hard time finding anything that applies to the absolute latest version.
Usually it's one or two releases behind and then you just add an extra layer of anomaly
when you're running a rolling release that isn't even out yet and stuff is a different
version and stuff is in a different spot. So for me I just kept banging my head into
that. Did you ever try this Matt?
Not with, no, not in that exact thing but I have run into that when it comes to documentation
and things like that. It's always interesting to try and nail that down so for me it was
always a little bit different.
Yeah, yeah. And you know I've thought about trying it again actually with the Fedora release
and I tried it really briefly during our OpenSUSE 13.1 review. I switched over to their rolling
and it went fine but I only did it for a few days. So I kind of feel like if you're going
to go rolling you should go with a distro designed to be rolling.
Well that would be my thinking because otherwise you're essentially doing a work around. I
mean if Ubuntu really wants to make their distro the very best it can be they need to
address the PPA problem. The existing management tools for PPAs is pretty craptacular. It's
not that great. PPAs as an idea are great. Unfortunately what happens when one goes down
there's no system in place to alert people. Hey by the way this is dead. Put out an alert
that something's going to be done.
This is something the Mint project has addressed but it's not an Ubuntu proper.
No it's not and so I think that's something that they need to really look at because I
don't see them as really needing to go rolling release because it's not their target goal
but I do think that they need to address having more bleeding edge packages when it comes
to stuff like OpenShot, Firefox, various software types. I think that would really help out.
The backend stuff like lib this and lib that you know that's neither here nor there. That's
obviously a PPA kind of thing but yeah I don't know. It's going to be interesting to see
how they work it out but it's something that they're not addressing and I think they're
going to have to eventually.
Hopefully or maybe click packages will save us all.
That would be. Hey you remember click you know.
I do. I do. I do remember clicking.
That was not horrible.
I also remember clicking and running as it were.
Yes.
Old joke there for you all.
You have to be apt to get that.
Oh geez. Hey you know what I got to do before we make everybody tune out is I want to say
thank you to Ting.com who is sponsoring this episode of Linux Unplugged. Ting is my mobile
service provider and Matt's mobile service provider. Why? Why? It's easy. No contracts,
no early termination fees and the thing that really keeps me around is Ting is pay for
what you use. They don't have to worry about things like or I don't have to worry about
things like paying into a contract where I'm not using that fully.
So previously I had two phones on a smartphone plan $120 a month. Now I have two phones both
smartphones an HTC One and a Nexus 5 on Ting and I'm paying around $25-$30 a month it depends.
So what Ting does is they take your minutes, your messages and your megabytes and they
add those up at the end of the month and whatever bug that you fall into, whatever actual usage
you have, that's what you pay. It's brilliant. So some months I have 50 text messages. Some
months I have 200 text messages. Why would I have to pay a thousand text message plan
if I don't need it? It drives me crazy and Ting solves all of that.
Plus Ting has devices that are fresh and hot right now. There are some carriers that don't
even have like the HTC One yet. Ting is already supporting the Nexus 5. You can pick it up
from the Google Play Store. You buy it directly from Google. You bring it over to the Ting
network. Now you have a phone you fully own on a network that's paid for what you use
with no contracts or no early termination fees. Hot spot tethering built into your plan.
You just pay for your data usage. It makes a ton of sense.
So here's how you get started. You go to linux.ting.com. That's going to take $25 off your first device
or if you've already got a Sprint compatible device and you want to bring it over to Ting,
just check to make sure it's compatible with the Ting network and then they'll take $25
off your first month of service. That's a pretty awesome deal. They've got a savings
calculator. You can plug that in and see how much you'd save.
One of the things you'll notice when you're visiting the Ting site, go to linux.ting.com
to get started, is they are an awesome company. They have their blog where they're posting.
They're very transparent about their business, how they work, about future advances. They
talk about rolling out tri-band LTE and what devices on the Ting network like my Nexus
5 support tri-band LTE right now and what the benefits of something like that are. They
often will pick some of the best apps, some of my favorite ones on Android like BeyondPod.
They'll feature those on the blog. There's a lot of great stuff over here that you can
keep visiting and once you become a Ting customer, you'll appreciate this level of information
from your carrier and Ting has great customer service as well. If you call Ting at 1-855-846-4389,
any time between 8am or 8pm Eastern, a real personal answer to the phone and help you
out and you also have a fantastic dashboard that gives you the tools you need to control
your own account, you'll probably be surprised at the kind of functionality you can get in
there and how clear and easy a cell phone company can make your billing and information
like that. Once you see this stuff, you'll never be able to go back to anybody else.
It's just their stuff. Ting is so far ahead of everybody else. You got to check them out.
So go to linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. I
hear from people all the time who switched over to Ting and are totally thrilled and
you can be one of them. linux.ting.com. Thank you to Ting.
Actually I have a recent Ting story, real short one. Here recently I had it issued where
I did something dumb on my phone and I couldn't figure it out. You know, imagine that, right?
I mean do something foolish. I did something foolish. I was like, okay, well I'm gonna
give these guys a call and see what's going on. Half a ring, not even a full ring. A person
that, you know, actually is very well spoken, very easy to understand. I get up on the phone,
ask them a question. Within like, I don't know, three seconds, they gave me numbers
to start pressing into my phone. Pressed it in, boom, problem solved. That was the end
of the conversation. Asked me if anything else, happy holidays, blah, blah, blah. We
were done. I couldn't believe it. Someone values their time. It's the way to go.
Yeah, no kidding, right? And if you just get sick of dealing with customer service reps
and we sound like they're reading a script, this is such a...
Or they're trying to upsell you. God, that's my big pet peeve.
You know, Mail Hauler in the chat room says that he went from $100 a month to around $20
a month when he switched to Ting.
Wow.
Yeah.
Nice.
That's a nice savings and with the beginning of the new year, it's a better time than
now to get started and I think you'll see why I've been so happy with my Ting service.
All right, so I'm bringing in the mumble room here. I wanted to start, you know, one thing
I realized after this week's Linux action show, I made a huge mistake.
Get it out of here.
I completely, completely forgot to make a Wayland type prediction. And I know Ron's
in the chat room here has a Wayland prediction as well, but I want to lay mine out and then
we'll turn it over to him. So I think you're going to see in 2014, it's not, I don't know
if competition is the right word, but if you're a distro out there, Ubuntu isn't in this camp.
If you're a distro out there shipping this year, say the second round of releases in
2014 and you don't have decent, some decent Wayland implementation that people can try
out, even if it's sort of like what Fedora did this time around, that's going to be like
a check mark in the anti column in the reviews. Like the people are reviewing it, we'll look
at that and go, oh, well you can't even play with Wayland in this release. Like that's,
that's going to become like one of the competitive features for distributions to have in there.
Maybe not the first release of 2014, but their second release of 2014. Now, Ron's, I know
you had a Roins. I'm not sure if I'm saying that right. I'm sure I'm not saying that right,
but I know you had a Wayland prediction. What is it?
I believe that in maybe, as I said, the second term of releases, um, in 2014, we're going
to see possibly maybe gen two or the more bleeding edge distros to have such good Wayland
support. Um, maybe for arch, the arch build system that is simple as rebuilding the package
with Wayland support and getting, of course, Gnome and KDE support Wayland will have, so
you don't have to run X client soon. It'll be pure Western Wayland.
Do you think maybe like mid 2014, all of the gnome packages on my arch installation will
update with Wayland support. And then at that point, all's I have to do is go over to the
arch wiki, look at the article about switching over to Wayland and make the switch and I'm
ready to go.
Yeah.
That's bold. So you're thinking I could actually run my whole desktop in 2014. You think like,
what about like, what about like, uh, graphics drivers?
Well, if you're on Intel, um, the Western Wayland drivers have already, um, solid Intel
supports them. Um,
I was gonna say, what about the Radeon drivers on the open source drill?
Well, the open source drivers have, uh, of course going to adopt Wayland quicker than
the proprietary ones, but it really, maybe we could see the proprietary one supporting
Mia simply because steam, um, they want to support Ubuntu, but the open source drivers,
they will support standard, which is Wayland.
All right. Well, let me ask you guys this. Cause, uh, Corky in the chat room is saying
that Wayland. And I think he means in terms of performance will be better than X 11 by
December of 2014. I happen to disagree. I think at the, I think in December of 2014
we'll have the pharaonic benchmarks and they'll show that X still has on games, the lead,
but it's closer.
I would say it's closer. Yeah. I mean, cause you got to figure out what's excellence, what,
30 years, something like that. I mean, you know, it's got a little bit of a head start.
Right. I think all these games are going to be using some sort of, you know, X Wayland
compatibility and they're all going to be, I mean, for a long time, like years. So I
just, I think like, like you'll see like, uh, I don't know, maybe you'll see like the
window managers and the compositing, like all that kind of cleans up as a lot faster,
but the stuff people actually use where they really need high performance, like so window
draws will be faster, right? That'll be great. Menus and blurs and textures will be faster,
but like games that I installed from steam will not actually see any big benefit from
this in 2014.
I've got one, uh, I've got one Wayland prediction for 2014 and that is the monkey suit.
Oh yeah. No, that's going to happen. Yeah. That's hanging up in the closet right now,
actually.
I just like to expand on what you said. If you look at the way Wayland works, basically
it's a protocol. Western is its implementation. So if you want your fancy window managers
like, um, awesome to work in Wayland, you basically write a Western plugin for that.
I imagine Gnome and KDE, um, their compositors are Mutter and Kaywin, their window managers.
That's basically just a plugin for Wayland, um, or Western. That's all it is.
I think, um, I think in 2014 you're going to see a lot more apps, um, adding Wayland
support and then in 2015 it's going to be refinement time and then by 2016 and it's
going to be refined and you're going to start seeing a lot more people actually using Wayland
on distros.
So you think it's not until 2016 that we're going to have the sweet, sweet life of performance
and optimizations and all that kind of stuff?
Yeah, because there's still a lot of apps and, and, and applications that haven't, uh,
you know, added the support for Wayland yet. And I think that's going to be all, all during
2014 and then in 2015 it's just going to be refining those packages and then 2016 it's,
it's, it's going to be refined. It's going to be available and it's going to be easier
to use than ever. It's still going to have some flaws, but it'll be, it'll be pretty
good.
All right. I think this one's pretty easy to make. Uh, SteamOS doesn't go anywhere near
Wayland in 2014. All X all the time.
Yeah. Yeah. Why would they, they have no reason to, um, their, their goal is not to try and
push Wayland. Their goal is to get you to play video games. Right? Yeah, exactly. You
know, seems kind of obvious. Yeah. Yeah. Uh, yeah, go ahead.
Just like the, I don't, I'm not, um, I'm doubting anyone's knowledge here, but porting apps
over to Wayland isn't as difficult as it sounds. If the toolkit supports Wayland, getting your
programs for Wayland is not going to be too difficult.
It's just a matter of doing it right on a matter of motivation. Quite honestly, it'll
depend too. Like, so stuff that like stuff that really only uses cutie or GTK to get,
you know, what it needs on the screen, they're going to almost have the work done for them
by, by the upstream toolkit. But, uh, you know, things like video games, that's not
necessarily the same thing or, or certain things like I would think a Lightworks comes
to mind or blender. I'm not quite sure what the situation is there or anything that kind
of has some customizations where they've either written their own toolkit or they've made
changes to it. You know, those kinds of apps I'm thinking about where they just don't quite
look like any other Linux desktop app. I think those kinds of things will struggle in 2014
with Wayland. Yes. Well, the games, if OpenGL and SDL support Wayland and the games written
in SDL and OpenGL chances are that game's going to be able to be ported over fairly
simply. Yeah. I know that's what people say. And I still come back to the, everybody seems
to think that developers are thinking, Oh goodie, we get to port something over something
we didn't have to a month ago. No one cares. I mean, I don't think they really give a
rat's butt. They're just now porting everything over to Linux now and they're getting, they're
getting X support now and now they're gonna have to switch to Wayland. Well, if I'm them,
I'm going to take my sweet time. If they do it right and they write to the, the underlying
subsystems like OpenGL and all that kind of stuff. And then all you have to have is the
change made at that level. And then everything that uses that will then use the new technology.
But I think it's, I don't think it's as clear cut as that with some of this stuff. And I
think the motivation is really the key issue. You know, end users are looking forward to
this. Developers are thinking, God, I just got this work and leave me alone. Here's my
big hope for Wayland. It's not really a prediction, but I really hope that if they do eventually
get proprietary drivers, that a new version of Wayland doesn't necessarily break the proprietary
driver like it did in Xorg. I don't think so. Because you know, this is a, you know,
cause what they're going to have is protocol level support, right? So if you write to this
version of the protocol, you get this. And then they just have a new version of the protocol,
which gives you the new features. They shouldn't have to deprecate the old version. I wouldn't
think, but you know, I look at this and during the last live stream on Sunday, we played
this Intel video and the whole time and the whole video, Intel's talking about Wayland
and it's a very nice sort of like infograph meets YouTube. And, and really what they,
what they care about is digital signs, infotainment in cars, mobile devices. In fact, the Linux
desktop in this video, all about Wayland is not even mentioned once, not a single desktop
app, not anything about the Linux desktop at all. And so what I, what that to me means
is the corporate backing isn't going to be on the desktop side of things. There's not
going to be a lot of people spending a lot of money on moving over desktop applications
to support that. So that two things that means to me is X Wayland is going to be around for
a long time. That's pretty obvious. But the second thing that that I think unfortunately
means is maybe, unfortunately or not, is all our hopes are in the toolkits, the QT guys
and the GTK guys and what they do. And all hopes depend on them to do it right because
they're going to bring everything along with them that uses those toolkits. And I think,
oh, sorry. I think the proprietary drivers, you're probably going to see like an alpha
release for proprietary drivers in 2015 I'd say, cause these guys aren't really going
to jump on the bandwagon so quick. I mean, these companies, they're really slow.
Intel might, right? I mean, Intel might, but yeah.
If they can see a clear, clear cut benefit, absolutely. They'll jump all over it. Otherwise
they don't care.
I just, I mean, I've been burned so many times by Wayland predictions. Like if you go back
over the years, a few years in a row, I've made Wayland predictions that just didn't
pan out, but I kind of feel like this is the year that it does. And I, it's almost the
more dangerous thing to say famous last words, but I just, it feels like things are more
serious this time. There's more money behind it. There's more momentum and there's more
of a recognized need too.
I predict that we're going to keep predicting about Wayland for another three or four years.
Yeah, I agree with that. That's true.
What do you guys think about Mir?
Yeah, we should probably talk about Mir a little bit, huh? We should, yeah.
What do you think about that island out there in the sea?
Well, so now that we look at it, I think it's pretty clear that Mir is an Ubuntu specific
solution because just like we mentioned how QT and GTK and others will be building in
the backend support to move over to Wayland, Unity will have the backend hooks to talk
to Mir. And if you don't have something written to talk to Mir, you're not going to run on
top of Mir unless you do it through xMir.
And so it's going to be, it's almost hard to compare the two because Mir is only going
to be on Ubuntu and we know we're not really going to see much of it in 2014.
I think we're going to, I think it's probably going to keep pace with, I mean to a degree
with only Ubuntu specific monkey suits happening either way. But I think it's in an Ubuntu
specific sort of way, I think that it's going to be kind of like an upstart versus system
D situation to where they kind of run in tandem. They're running alongside of each other and
everybody's kind of doing their own thing, but I don't see explosive activity.
They're almost not in, you know, now that I look at it after we've had a few months,
actually half the year to sort of think about it, it's not in competition with Wayland.
Wayland is on its own track. It has its, you know, it's a wider industry proposition.
Mir's actual specific success is if it achieves exactly or even barely what they need for
Ubuntu. And if it accomplishes that, it is technically successful because it's not a
Wayland competitor.
Wayland is a solution for all of Linux and for multiple types of devices. Mir is a solution
for Ubuntu.
Yeah.
So basically, Microsoft is going to get less and less attention over the year 2014 and
Canonical is going to become more like Microsoft.
No, that's Google's job.
Oh!
No, it's going to be Google this, Google that. I mean, it's going to be Chromebooks and Android
devices in the tech news for the next, for 2014. It's going to dominate it. Just watch.
All right. Well, I got a couple of predictions along that line. Specifically, like the mobile
stuff. So is there any other thoughts on Mir or Wayland before we move to another?
Well, I was going to say, I'm kind of wondering if with there being XMir and XWayland, whether
developers won't just stick with X, so their applications can work on both. So we'll have
those better solutions, but not applications that actually take advantage of them.
Our desktop environments will speak directly to the display server and all the applications
we run on top of them will be using an X11 compatibility thing.
It's going to be a long time, guys.
Yeah. None of this happens. You're going to have to hold a stick up to see any of it move.
I think what you might start to see, if we're really lucky at the end of 2014, we'll see
that the XWayland stuff and the XMir stuff is able to take advantage of so many efficiencies
by replacing the display server underneath that maybe performance will be equal or even
better.
I mean, that'd be awesome. If we have such efficiencies in new code design, because everybody
knows Xorg is such a beast, that if by totally getting rid of all of that plumbing and having
a cleaner pipeline that goes directly from the desktop to the display driver to the kernel
to the hardware, et cetera, et cetera, that whole path is much more efficient.
Even though you're running something through emulation, just like we've all seen sometimes
when you run a wine game under Linux, it actually performs better than it does under Windows
in certain circumstances, maybe we'll see that same kind of thing happen with stuff
running under X emulation on these new display servers.
Yeah.
All right. Well, before we get to our next category of predictions, I got a little prediction
for all of you guys. This is going to be... Actually, I'm not even kidding. This is really going
to be the year where we all continue to build out our own cloud, and that's why I'm so happy
that DigitalOcean is a sponsor of Linux Unplugged, because they are going to enable this for
a lot of us. DigitalOcean is simple cloud hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way to spin up a cloud server, and you get root access to this thing when they
spin this up.
Now, check this out. Users can create a cloud server in 55 seconds, and pricing plans start
at only $5 per month, which gets you 512 megs of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, and a terabyte
of transfer. You think about all the different types of devices you can put Linux on. When
you put a Linux box out there with 512 megs of RAM and a 20 gig SSD, that thing can... As
a server, you will be amazed at the performance you can get out of a Linux box in these conditions.
I've got a box up there right now that's doing all kinds of backend. Frequently, I have it
recording a second backup copy of our live stream in case we have an outage. I have it
distributing files for the Unfilter show. Gigabytes. Gigabytes and gigabytes and gigabytes
of files now, like 20 gigabytes worth of files that it's constantly sending out and distributing
to our Unfilter supporters. I have all kinds of different tasks that I can spin up on it
really quick. When you're paying $5 a month, there's so many great advantages of productivity
and testing and just experimentation and training and self-learning that $5 is just an insane
value. DigitalOcean has data centers in New York, San Francisco, and Amsterdam. You can
distribute it out as you want. I've picked New York. That way, I have something on the
other side of the coast. Their interface is simple. They have an intuitive control panel.
Power users can even set up and replicate it on their own by using their straightforward
API. DigitalOcean also offers a vast collection of tutorials in their community section on
their site. Users who submit articles can get $50 per published piece. Here's a great
article. This hit our Linux action show subreddit this week. How to create a Beowulf cluster
using a.212.04 VPS instances on DigitalOcean.
Nice.
A Beowulf cluster, Matt.
Wow. Wow. They really went there. Okay, that's awesome.
I know. How cool is that? It really is, right? I'm pretty impressed by that. I don't know
if I'd be using that, but for the training aspect of it, it's actually kind of a great
opportunity. The way DigitalOcean pricing works is for $5, you get $5 a month, you get
a quantified cost, you get a machine you can always access. If you just want to do some
basic testing, they also offer hourly pricing. If you're working on an open source project
or I mean, gosh, maybe it's closed source.
It's negative in the freedom dimension.
You could upload it to DigitalOcean, use the hourly pricing, and have people all over the
world bang on it for a while, give you real world performance reports. You don't have
to worry about configuring your firewall. Look at these prices. I mean, it's unbeatable
what you can do. The great thing is the control panel is so nice you can, like what I've done,
I have an arch server, yes, I said arch, set up on DigitalOcean and I image that sucker
and when I want to deploy another one, I can just redeploy that image. It's ready to go.
It's super quick. You combine that with pay-as-you-go pricing, that's going to be really easy.
Here's how you get started. Go over to DigitalOcean.com. Check out what we've been talking about. If
you have a bad memory, just go to any recent episode of Linux Unplugged. Go down to the
show notes. We have a banner right there for DigitalOcean and if you use our promo code
Linux Unplugged December. Now, it's going to work for a little bit longer, but take
advantage of this while you can. Linux Unplugged December. You'll get a $10 credit. That'll
let you try out the $5 server for two months or you can get the $10 server for one month.
I've been using the $5 server for a few months now and it's awesome. It's great. I really
like it. Go to DigitalOcean.com, Linux Unplugged December to get that $10 credit and I think
you're going to be really impressed. This is really an awesome service and the performance
has been great. I just updated my Archbox last night and I just sit there and I watch
those download speeds as it writes those transactions to the SSD and I'm just like, oh gosh, yes.
And here's something I could see someone using it for too. Let's say you have an Arch install
and you're thinking, oh, you know, I want to actually try, I read mixed signals in this
one package and I'm not really sure if it's going to build right. I don't really want
to hose my system, but I want just kind of a test bed to test out different packages
that maybe have an iffy history. It's a great place to do that kind of stuff. You don't
have to be super geeky with it. You can use it as a tool just to try things out where
you don't want to do it on your main computer. And the snapshots make it easy to roll back.
Pirate Ghost. Pirate Ghost in our chat room, which is a great name, says, I have 11 VPSs
on DigitalOcean. Nice. How about that? They also are pretty cool about, he says, helping
him with working on open source projects. That's cool. Yeah. So big thanks to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. Okay. So this is kind of a spinoff of the prediction I made
on Sunday, but I want to revisit this in light of a story that came out and I didn't cover
it in last because it didn't really seem, at the time when I thought about it at first,
it didn't seem Linux specific enough to me to talk about it on the Linux Action Show.
But now that I think about the larger ramifications of this story, I actually think it's very
much going to become a Linux story. And what I'm talking about is these recent published
reports from Der Spiegel that the NSA is intercepting laptops and other hardware like routers and
firewalls purchased online and they can intercept the package when it leaves the company you
buy it from, say Dell, and they will install malware, in some cases hardware, in some cases
software, to do whatever the hell they want. The report indicates also, by the way, some
of the companies including this, let me see, I'll find it right here. Oh, here we go. Dell's
in there. Shocker! Yeah, I know, right? Western Digital, Seagate, Juniper Networks, MacStore,
Samsung, Hawaii, and Microsoft are included in companies in this report that says they
worked with. The report even indicates the NSA can even exploit air reports from Microsoft
Windows operating systems by intercepting the air reports and determining what is wrong
with the target's computer and then the NSA can attack it with Trojans or other malware.
That's just so sleazy. To gain physical access, the NSA reportedly worked with the CIA and
the FBI on sensitive missions that sometimes included flying NSA agents on FBI jets to
plant wiretaps that gets them to their destination at the right time so they can help disappear
again undetected after even as little of a half hour's work, the report notes. So what
you have here is machines, and here's an example of what they call a hardware implant. One
of the products the NSA appears to use, compromises target's computer, is codenamed Cottonmouth,
and it's been available since 2009. It's a USB hardware implant that secretly provides
the NSA with remote access to the compromised machine. Some of these, like you format the
machine, you wipe the master boot record, you delete the petition table, some of these
actually will reinstall themselves after you wipe. Now everything appears to be sort of
targeting Windows. You look at a lot of this stuff, and once again, it's requiring either
cooperation with the manufacturer or the fact that they can take advantage of zero-day exploits
or whatever it is. I read this and I think these NSA leaks, in 2014, what we'll see is
security becoming a sexy feature that companies are going to compete on. Linux and open source
will inherently be better suited to meet and increase demand there, and I think specifically
you're going to see a lot of new secure chat programs, file transfers will explode, secure
file transfers are going to explode in 2014. We're going to have our pick of our litter,
and some of them will be closed source, but a lot of them, because what's going to happen
is first you'll have a first round of stuff that's closed source. You've already seen
a few of these new chat programs that have come out that have been closed source, and
the first thing everybody now says is, well, it's not open source, how can I trust it?
Everybody's saying that now. So the next competitive step people are going to have to make in order
to check that box off and be competitive is they're going to have to go open source. So
as a result of trying to chase these sexy features they can sell to consumers, they'll
open source the software so that way they can say, well, here's the software, it's open
source, pay us for the service.
So I mean, here's the bigger thing that I see exploding with that, because all these
things are great, and unless you know how to audit code, and I sure as hell don't, open
source or closed source, that's awesome, but even if it starts out open source, you
get it on your system that's perhaps already infected with something that you don't know,
so you've taken benign software on an infected system that's got some weird hardware hack
thing going on.
Here's what I see being successful. Someone opens up a consultant firm that will actually
audit your hardware. That's what I want to see. I want to see someone that actually
that people can vet that can actually see what they're doing and actually have
a success record to look at. I think that's probably the only real defense against this,
because you can  otherwise, it's just peanuts and beer at that point. Peanuts make
you thirsty. You're going to have more beer. Or the security industry with the firewall
programs and various security programs you see in Windows.
You can see that, but you do have the advantage
I'm not buying it.
You have the advantage, like what happened with the  I mean, I see what you're saying
there. You and I would not really be able to check it, but you have the example of the
TrueCrypt project where enough in the community could get together and say, we're going
to audit this as a community.
Oh, yeah. It's great coming down to your computer, but what if  and again, look
how  I hate to be paranoid, but look what's already happening. What if you have a setup
on your computer you're not aware of that takes a benign program that's completely
safe and makes it unsafe on your computer? It becomes a mood issue.
This is more of a threat, I think, with Windows. What you have to do is you have to make best
efforts, your best rational effort that you can make. The first thing is if you're really
paranoid about security
Yeah, stop using Windows.
You do. You seriously have to consider, well, if I really care about this, I should probably
stop using Windows. It doesn't guarantee that some Linux box won't have something
on there that is monitoring you and maybe
But Windows is slow-hanging fruit, certainly.
Wouldn't it  what would really be scary is if some distro by default shipped it so
that everything you typed into the launcher was sent over the network that somebody could
capture. That would almost be insecure right out of the box and be really freaky, and if
that ever got popular, it would be a heyday for the NSA. But as long as nothing like that
happens.
Yeah, I think at this point, Linux is definitely low-hanging fruit, or Windows is low-hanging
fruit, and I think Linux is probably generally pretty safe at this point. That's not to
say that embedded programs and things might not be an issue later on.
Mumble  go ahead, Ryan.
Create a hardware test, call it the Snowden test.
There you go.
Yeah, yeah. You plug it in and it runs a Snowden audit.
Exactly.
Make a little humming sound.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think we just all need to learn how to build our own computers and make processors.
Oh, geez.
Absolutely. I got my clean room ready and I got my suit, so I'll get right on that.
Maybe open source hardware will become a more popular thing because you can audit the hardware.
What about something that sits on your network and is watching your machine?
That would be the most effective.
Like at the firewall level. Like this firewall includes packet inspection where we'll alert
you if it looks like something's leaking from your computer.
That would make the most sense to me because
Yeah.
AT&SA.
Yeah. I mean, it could be a marketing opportunity for PF Sense.
I mean, at the end of the day, as Heaven's Revenge points out in the chat room, it's
completely spot on. If someone wants to do something badly enough, they're going to
do it. I mean, that's just what it is. All you can do is minimize that damage by using
Linux.
That's right. Yeah, exactly. That's where I go back to you just have to make the rational
compromise. So you can't go tinfoil hat. You can't install a Faraday cage in your
house. But what you can do is  we could. But again, there's like diminishing returns,
right? But what you could do is use Linux. Use an open source email program. Use open
hardware if you can. And I think that just  that base fact will drive human behavior
towards open source and Linux. Not like  I don't know if it's going to be some sort
of mass hysteria, but when you have decision makers, people who are designing systems for
businesses that need to be secure, CEOs who are paranoid about corporate espionage and
things like this. Because all these things the NSA is doing, some private company could
do as well.
That's true.
In fact, in some cases, we have now documented evidence that the NSA has weakened industry
standards to make their job easier and other attackers could just take advantage of those
weaknesses too. Hello, RSA. Right? So it's one of these things where because the vulnerability
exists, it's not just the NSA that can take advantage of it. So there's like all of
these reasons that just stack up. And the rational person that really is concerned about
this would have to  I mean, I think the decision you come to is some sort of open
source system. Maybe it's not Linux. Maybe it's BSD.
Exactly.
But I think
The NSA uses Git for their software that exploits people.
It's probably all CVS.
Yeah, right. Microsoft Bob.
Yeah. Anybody else have any NSA-related predictions in the chat room?
I just want to say that you don't want to put tinfoil on your head because it will increase
the signal. You want to put a wet towel. That's all I got to say.
Good to know. Good to know. Good to know. All right. Well, any other predictions, Jerem?
I'm opening up the floor now.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
I've got a prediction about Canonical.
Oh, okay. Let's do it.
Yeah. And that is that I think by the end of next year, Canonical might announce that
they're going to make their own kernel.
So not a fork?
That is optimized for mirror.
It could be a fork, but I think that they're going to feel like they can't control Linux
and they want something that is custom-tailored to their needs for mirror and stuff.
So they'll have the Ubuntu kernel that's like a snapshot of like the semi-latest kernel
that was out at the time they make this decision?
Yes, exactly.
Can I interject?
Yeah.
If Popey was here, he would add the Ubuntu Canonical.
He is. He is here.
Well, I'm sure he's going to add that Ubuntu has no intentions or never will modest by
So we took our kernel and we connected it to our display server and then connected it
to our upstart in its system and then we just called it all one thing, the Ubuntu base.
So I think first of all, you need to clarify what BitPuffin was suggesting because what
I heard BitPuffin say and what Chris said were two different things.
Yeah.
No, I was just joking.
I heard and it sounds like he's trying to say that Canonical is going to turn Ubuntu
into their own system completely.
I can't see it.
It's too much.
Well, I think they would still like try to maintain some kind of Linux compatibility
like they do with Xmerve.
But BitPuffin, don't they have the best of both worlds right now?
They get one of the best kernels out there developed by a different team and then they
can pick the version they want to run and they can run that version for as long as they
want to run it and do whatever patches they need to do to keep it secure.
And so they can kind of do that now without having
That's exactly what we do.
Yeah.
We take a kernel and then we apply patches to it and that's our kernel.
That seems like path least resistance, yeah.
So I guess BitPuffin, for your prediction to work, you'd have to have some sort of decision
the kernel team was making that was inherently incompatible with Ubuntu's goals.
Yeah, something like that but also that they realize that Linux is a huge train that they
really don't have any control over and if they want to have their own stuff, they're
going to have to fork and stuff but then they can realize that Linux is like  it covers
so many stuff that they don't really need and bending Linux to be the way that they
would maybe need it to be would require it to
The herd kernel.
A lot of more work basically.
Yeah.
I don't think that's
So maybe they would feel better to start from scratch and implement things that  ways
that benefit them.
I don't think that they can make a kernel that anywhere compares to Linux kernel.
Maybe they could license the Microsoft kernel, 2014 Canonical Science License Agreement with
Microsoft.
I think you're kind of  yeah, it's kind of going like a ReactOS type of thing.
So we're going to see what, Ubuntu NT edition?
I would say if anyone is going to fork Linux, it's going to be the Mint guys because they
just like forking stuff.
No, it's going to be Google.
This just strikes me and I hear this a lot.
I don't want you to say this on IRC and it says this on podcast, this is  shock for
you, you're not the first person to suggest this.
I hear this a lot and it seems to be the natural exaggeration of well, Canonical will fork
X next or whatever X might be and it's just the natural most exaggerated, most ridiculous
thing you can possibly suggest.
It's the end point.
Yeah, but I've never made a fork.
Canonical is going to fork Atari, sure.
Now I want it to happen.
Now that we've recorded all of this and then BitPuff to emerge totally victorious.
I think it just comes down to practicality too.
Yeah, it's just more beneficial not to.
And
Adapt just need be.
Because if you look
Everything else has already been done.
There's already a fork of Firefox in Debian and there's already a fork of OpenOffice
as LibreOffice.
Everything has already been done.
So the one thing left to do that the only company that's so ridiculously outrageous
that would do it must be Canonical.
Well, okay.
I agree with you.
There won't be.
No, but I think that they would provide an experience which is like when they write the
display server, they kind of write it so that Unity works well with Mirror and Mirror works
well with Unity.
I would think that they would want to do something similar with the core system kernel stuff
too.
So the other direction would be
Kind of integrated.
Is you could take  So the Apple rationale was  Well, because you could look at it
from the Mac OS X standpoint.
They built their own display server.
They built their own kernel and then they have a BSD user land tools.
And so that's the extension of what you're saying is you'd have Canonical builds the
Ubuntu desktop to build the display server and then they have a Linux user land tool
base but it's an Ubuntu kernel.
Yeah, I just don't see that.
Not in 2014.
No.
Not at all.
I don't think there would be an announcement or something.
Oh, right.
Maybe the year after.
Maybe a couple of years.
Maybe 2020.
Now I see Mark Shuttleworth in a Buck Rogers thing twirling through space.
I mean it's going to be something like that.
No, it just practically doesn't make any sense.
The reason that I think they would never do that is because I mean they're not extremely
rich.
They're not billionaires.
I mean you have to take  if you're going to make your own kernel, you have to really
make sure everything works exactly like the Linux kernel was working before on Ubuntu
and they just  I don't think they have the resources for that.
I would imagine them working the GNU user land before they forked the kernel.
I mean look at Android.
And why fork that down?
Yeah, I can see that.
It's down deep, you know?
Yeah, if anybody's
Did I just give Popey an idea?
If anybody's going to fork  no, but seriously, if anybody's going to fork the Linux kernel,
it would be Google for Android, right?
Yeah.
And they could probably pull it off.
But even they aren't doing it necessarily.
I mean they are using certain things from it without going that deep into it.
They only fork what they have to.
Well, they don't want to make Linus swear at them.
I think it's
Yeah, exactly.
Well, they don't have to.
Yeah.
All right.
Monica loves the Linux kernel.
Last call for 2014 predictions.
Anybody have
Oh, sure.
If I may restate Ant's predictions for Ubuntu, no companies will use Ubuntu in one and a
half years.
Ubuntu in general will be dead in two years.
What?
Whoa.
Based on
This is not his predictions.
Not his, yeah.
Let me
They're Ant's.
I think it would probably be more accurate to say that these were the drunken ramblings
of Ant, which they could well be the drunken ramblings of anyone.
Yeah, there you go.
These podcasts are probably the drunken ramblings of us.
I'm not going to say anything negative regarding Ubuntu, but I am going to say that in the
year 2014, openSUSE is probably going to get even more popular than it did in 2013.
Okay.
All right.
Yeah, I know it is.
Ubuntu is going to be more popular in 2014 than it was in this previous year, which I
agree with.
They're all going to be more popular.
Yeah.
Look, I think at the end of the day, when I load Linux on someone's computer that doesn't
know Linux yet, I load Ubuntu on there no matter how I feel about it because it's going
to be easier for them.
Woo-hoo.
Got a woo-hoo of approval there.
I predict that Amazon is going to get tired of everybody using their affiliate system,
so they're going to make their own distro, make their own browsers, and their own search
engine.
Brilliant.
Yeah, right.
Hey, haven't they got their own distro on their Amazon Kindle Fire and their own affiliate
revenue system there?
Technically, yeah.
Yeah.
Actually, I think you're right.
I didn't think of it that way.
Now, here's a good question.
They're all Android forks, so technically, yeah.
What was different between the year affiliate system and the way it's integrated into the
Dash?
Product placement because they're actually advertising products, yeah, and not just shop
here.
So, okay, last call for predictions before...
I got one real quick.
Okay.
All right.
In education, Linux has always been really big, but I think it's going to become even
bigger with things like the Pi and the Chromebook becoming so cheap that schools realize that
the contracts they have with Microsoft are ridiculous and move from proprietary to open
source software.
Yeah.
I think schools have a lot...
They're also just reinvesting in existing hardware.
As XP goes away, that's going to be big for schools.
Oh, yeah.
And especially businesses, too, when XP goes away, where are they going to go with their
custom software?
Why not have somebody develop custom software for them on Linux rather than upgrading that
to Windows 7 or 8?
I would bet they're going to stay on XP until they have a massive just fallout from all
kinds of horrible things that they're going to be attacked because there's a lot of things
that if you notice, there's been some studies that said the hackers or the virus writers
are waiting for the thing to drop support so they can attack massively.
Yeah.
So probably about next year is when they'll realize that should change.
If I put my contracting hat on, I can already picture a client that's asking me to mitigate
the risk and not migrate the OS.
So they'll say, do what you can, firewall it, clock it down, protect it, let's monitor
it, put an antivirus on there, and we'll run the risk because it's in our land and we're
just going to keep it until it dies.
And I can see that happening.
So it's not going to be 2014 won't be like this, boom, everybody switched from XP.
It's going to be a slow thing that picks up momentum in 2014.
But I do think we're going to get lots of a blaster worm like alerts in the paper and
things like that.
You know, we're going to, I'm sure you guys remember that blaster worm thing that happened.
That's actually what my name is based on.
Really?
That's funny.
Yeah.
The patch was released the whole time.
That's what blew my mind.
It was out there the whole time and no one applied it.
Just like, really?
Yeah.
Don't banks and stuff have like custom software that they use for on Windows XP that they're
probably afraid to migrate to Windows 7 because it's got to be, you know, it's got to be changed.
Before it was on XP, it was on Scoboxes.
Like so they've had to move it before.
This has happened to them before, it'll happen again.
And in some ways you could make the argument, hey, if you move to Linux, this is just an
organic piece.
They'll just continue to exist.
It doesn't come to an end like some of these other products do.
It makes me kind of afraid that some of these banks might stay on XP.
They will.
Oh yeah.
There's banks on 2000k.
I mean, I'm seriously, at least that I've seen, at least as soon as a year ago.
A few years ago, I would walk into a Bank of America and they would have Mac Pluses
there from the 80s with text terminals, you know, and so they, yeah, they'll, that was
just the ATM.
Yeah.
There's only a few.
It wasn't recent, but it was a few years ago.
I'd just like to add a little bit you said about education.
Getting Linux, from my experience, getting Linux in the door for education is quite difficult
simply because there's not enough people who know about Linux to supply classes and stuff
like that.
Canada actually would prove that wrong.
I mean, it's based on the Canadians that I've known and the Canadians I've worked with and
also just reading news articles on it.
It seems like various provinces in Canada have actually had a lot of success.
Yeah, I think it depends on a local company who can work with the school district, you
know.
It depends where.
If you have a school district who has some big fatty IT contract with some company who
sucks off Microsoft's tip, they're going to come in there and they're going to sell more
Microsoft software.
But, you know, you get some local guy who maybe can help do some, you know, IT development
with the school district if they don't have a strong in-house IT and they like Linux,
it could happen.
Well, I went to a school who, the admins were very into Linux and they run Linux and all
the servers, anything that wasn't a desktop and the only reason they wouldn't run it on
the desktop is because teachers want their software.
They don't want to use LibreOffice or GIMP and for the purposes of teaching photo editing
or word processing, LibreOffice and GIMP are perfectly fine solutions, you don't need Photoshop.
Microsoft's going to solve that problem for us though.
With Windows 8, you don't have your own, I mean, you do technically, but the UI is going
to continue to change so much and, you know, these Metro applications are not up to snuff.
They're not what people want.
They're not Photoshop.
They're not, you know, they're not full replacements yet.
So that's going to help with that a little bit when you're faced with that stark of a
change anyways, then it's still a lot of change to switch to Linux, but you're already dealing
with so much change that it's not a huge leap, I would think.
I think another, what we're going to see coming up is, we saw some of this in 2013, but I
think GNOME 3 is going to even further just find its place as a desktop environment in
2014.
I could see that.
I think it's going to be a good year for GNOME.
Well, and I think schools will continue to do stuff.
I mean, like you have iTalk for classroom work, Moodle, which if you apply a theme to
it, it's actually not too terrible, but out of the box, Moodle is just painful to look
at.
I get that.
It's painful to use too.
I've actually run it a few times, but yeah, I think the tools are out there for schools.
It just takes time and it takes financial motivation sometimes.
Yeah.
And yeah, there's a lot of things at play.
So before we jump out of the Mumber Room, is it 2014 for anybody in here yet?
I know it is for Aviator Continuity in our chat room right now.
He's been there for seven hours.
He's been in 2014.
We are in 2014.
Oh, well, congratulations.
Welcome.
And hello from the past.
All right.
Poppy only has an hour left.
Yeah.
I thought BitPuffin was going to cross over during the show, but I can't remember.
Yeah, he did.
He did.
Five minutes ago.
Yay.
Well, happy 2014, Bit.
Okay, guys.
Well, before we go, I got to read a little email, so I'm going to get to that right now.
But it came from Tim, and he's calling us out, Matt.
Now we get these from time to time.
Last time it was about Debbie, and this time it's about Slackware.
He says, I rarely hear you guys mention Slackware.
I've been a Slackware user for many years and would love to see you guys do a Slackware
challenge.
I have a lot of people turned off by the fact that Slackware package managers not even handle
dependencies.
But I would like to think that you guys, as Arch users, would realize that there's a benefit
to knowing exactly what is on your system because you installed it.
These days, building and finding Slackware packages is as easy as ever with slackbuilds.org
and sbopkg.org.
He says most of Slackware's team keeps an up-to-date repository of commonly used pre-built
packages, and he gives a Wiki link to that, as a Linux user, Slackware user supporter,
and a huge fan of your shows.
I'd just like to see you guys give it some loveskis.
Now we did give it the love spotlight on last during our OpenSUSE review.
Yes.
So here's the thing about Slackware, Matt, is when we make these switches, these challenges,
I have to straight up use these for a while.
Right.
And here's the thing.
He mentioned a couple tools.
I've never really cared.
I played with Gentoo a little bit, okay, Portage, whatever, but Slackware I've never had a reason
to.
Now the tools he mentioned specifically regarding that, because he lost me at dependency stuff,
I will literally gargle glass shards before I chase down dependencies.
It's 2014, kids.
I'm not doing it.
Arch doesn't make me chase down that stuff.
It doesn't.
It's providing an effective experience for me.
I don't use it because it's geeky.
I use it because I'm lazy, and it appeals to me.
So that's okay.
There is a little bit of that.
That is part of my motivation to using Arch is I don't like tracking down the stuff and
everything I want in the repos.
I'm not totally opposed to trying Slackware, probably not in the immediate future, but
I do kind of feel like it's sort of like the thing I've just never really got into, and
I need to give it a fair go.
I've never had the motivation.
I just, I can't.
It's in the back of my mind.
I'm more likely to revisit Gentoo, honestly, as weird as that sounds, because I mean, Portage,
I've done this.
I mean, it's not like my ideal thing, but I can deal with it.
But I don't really get my, I don't really see the Slackware advantage, I guess is one
of them.
Knowing what's in my stuff, I don't care.
I love that it's there.
It's open source.
I'm going to, you know, at some level, the NSA is going to do what they're going to do,
whatever.
I'm just not that concerned about it.
I just want it to work.
The other thing, too, is I understand, I do kind of see what you're saying, you know exactly
what's on your system.
But that, to me, also isn't a huge requirement in the sense of library bloat or anything
like that.
So I don't want to put it down, because I respect anybody who chooses to use it.
But for myself, it's never quite resonated.
And I'm still going to give it some thought.
I might try it, maybe in the summer, I might give it a go.
I mean, if Arch burns me or something, or whatever variation of Arch I'm using happens
to burn me or something, yeah, then I might have an interest in actually pursuing it.
At this point, I need a motivation.
For me, I was, you know, burnt out on PPA, so I was just, it was just time to try something
new.
OpenSUSE was cool.
I had a lot of fun with that.
And I wanted to roll into something new.
But I'm kind of happy where I'm at.
I don't know.
Yeah.
I just don't know.
All right.
Well, as we wrap, one thing I wanted to mention is I think it's going to be an awesome year
for QT.
Yeah.
QT.
And I don't know what that'll mean for the GNOME desktop.
And I'd like to hear your guys' thoughts on that.
What do you think is QT's success going to come at the cost of quality GTK applications
on Linux?
Because, you know, when I sit there and I use the GNOME desktop, one of the things that
brings me back to KDE frequently is KWin's awesome, for one.
And number two is I feel like QT is the way of the future, and that slowly over the next
couple of years, my favorite applications are going to be replaced with QT versions,
and I should just get on the KDE bandwagon now.
So I'd like to hear your guys' thoughts on that.
That's my question for you out there in the audience.
You can go over to jupyterbroadcasting.com, pop the contact link, and leave your feedback.
And here's the other question, and this one I really want you to give some thought.
Does Groupthink, or maybe call it Management by Consensus, tamper open source innovation?
So does backlash to aggressive and sometimes new or risky ideas inhibit bold innovation
sometimes in open source?
Here's an example.
So Debian cannot get off the pot about their init system.
You know, they can't just choose systemd.
Even though choosing systemd, by the data I can tell, would only impact 0.8% of their
user base negatively.
That would be the ones that have a BSD derivative, and that's using voluntary stats.
0.8% of their user base would be affected by the switch to systemd, but the entire Linux
ecosystem could be benefited by it, not just Debian.
Yet they can't make the call because of this group, debate, groupthink, management by consensus
aspect that a lot of open source projects are driven by.
So I want to get people to email in.
You have any thoughts?
Well, here's the first thing that comes to mind, and it's adorable that people think
Debian does anything quickly.
I just find that just adorable.
It's Debian.
You know, they move at Debian pace.
But why is that?
Is that because of this groupthink, management by consensus, consortium?
That's part of it, but also because of the fact that they have what's working for them
now.
They like to take their time and really slog through everything at a snail's pace.
And I don't mean that in a negative way.
I mean, that's just how they operate.
I think you could look at a lot of things in the open source development where you could
see that the group debating really trivial stuff really slowed stuff down.
And then there's good examples where somebody comes along and Lenart says, boom, we're going
to do system D. And then all of a sudden, there's a bunch of energy behind system D.
Or Mark comes out and says, hey, you know what, we're going to build our own display
server.
And even though a lot of people can disagree, there is this declaration at the top, and
the focus is made, the commitment is made, and the team gets to work.
And you can see this play out in some commercial companies like Apple.
And then you have the other side where Microsoft, where they just can't seem to really execute
because they have all this middle management.
And I'm wondering if maybe the open source community suffers from a little bit middle
management.
You can't take it all out.
But I want to know what the audience thinks.
So go over to jupyterblogcasting.com, pop that contact link, choose Linux Unplugged from
the dropdown, send us your feedback for next week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
And we will read that during the top of the show next week on the show.
I think that'll be a good topic.
It's just something I've been kicking around as I've been watching the system D stuff and
Miren Wayland.
Let's put it out there.
See what people think.
Yeah.
All right, Matt.
Well, coming up on Sunday, I got kind of a surprise.
Oh yeah?
Yeah.
I'm not going to announce it yet because I'm not sure it's going to work out.
So we're going to cover it if it works out.
But I'll talk to you about it.
All right.
So we'd love to hear from you.
Don't forget.
You can join us live.
The Linux Unplugged show is live on the Tuesdays over at jblive.tv, 2pm Pacific.
Go to jupyterblogcasting.com, slash calendar to get that in your local neck of the woods.
We'll convert it for you.
All right, everyone.
Well, thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Matt, I'll see you on Sunday.
Okay?
Sounds good.
See you then.
All right, everyone.
Thank you so much.
Have a great week.