Gotta say happy birthday before we start the show to Debian.
Debian turned 23 today.
Happy birthday, Debian, and we'll be talking more about it later in the show.
They have a really cool timeline we'll be covering.
It is Debian Day.
Let's start the show, everybody.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 158 for August 16, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's celebrating Debian's 23rd
birthday.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
I am really looking forward to today's show.
We have a fun show lined up.
We got a bunch of really, really good updates from the community we're going to get into.
Mr. Sipes is here from, or formerly from, the Mycroft Project to give us an update on
what he's doing.
We have some really good Firefox news, which is the first time I've got to say that for
a while.
It warms my heart.
It does, doesn't it?
It feels really good.
And then I'm going to throw a challenge in Wes's face to see if he can get something
done by the end of the show.
Then later on in the show, we're going to celebrate Debian's birthday by talking about,
of course, what the future holds for Debian, and where Debian may be going, and where some
of the places it's come from.
And a little look at the Debian timeline, which is super fascinating.
Really some good stuff to share with you guys.
And then we'll wrap it all up and see how Wes does on the challenge.
So the question is going to be coming in pretty soon, because rumors have it that your friends
in Cupertino will be releasing a new MacBook soon.
Hey, oh, it's been about time.
Jeez, it is ridiculous.
And you know what's going to happen.
The current models, which are still perfectly usable, will go up on eBay, and people can
buy them for a reduced price.
And we have a pretty common question that comes into the show.
How do you install Linux on the MacBook?
Does it work?
What should I know about?
So this week-
Is it worth the amount of effort that might be required?
Have you ever done this before?
You know, I have, but it's been, oh boy, probably three years at least.
So this week-
Actually, I was installing Debian.
Really?
That's great.
I'm going to see if by the end of the show, Wes can get Arch Linux or maybe Fedora Linux,
where we'll see, running on a MacBook.
It's like a late 2013 model, I think.
And we'll kind of give you a report of what it's like to try it, if he can get the dedicated
graphics working, the wireless working, and we'll give you a review, so that way some
people out there, they just want that hardware.
And this is an old production rig that we have that's like, it's good.
I'd like to see if you could leave macOS on there, because I think a lot of people are
going to want to do that.
Based on the emails we've received, people want to do a boot, and I can understand that.
Yeah, absolutely.
And if you want to do more updates-
Wes, I officially am handing you this Linux-unplugged branded thumb drive, which contains the latest
official released Antigros image from last month.
Sure, it's signed with the JB signing.
Oh yeah, I checked it for sure.
Oh yeah, for sure.
Absolutely.
So there you go, Wes.
Good luck to you.
Thank you, sir.
There is a, it is already partitioned into two separate, well there's the OS 10 partition,
because I've played with Linux on there before, is like already shrunk down.
And so there is like a, there's like right now I just made it like fat or something for
you that you can mess around with.
So there you go, Wes.
The challenge is officially launched.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
Hey, before we go any further, let's bring in our virtual lug to dig through the community
updates.
Time appropriate.
Greetings, Mumble Room.
Greetings, program.
Greetings, how's it going?
Very good.
Hello.
I am excited to share this Firefox news story with you guys.
So we put it right here at the top of the community updates.
Firefox 49 for Linux is going to be gaining plugin free support for Netflix and Amazon
streaming.
This is super nice.
No more crazy workarounds, no more depending on Chrome.
I know a lot of Firefox users who have Chrome installed just so they can watch Netflix.
So this is cool.
And it's really another plugin biting the dust.
They're using that Widevine, how do you say that?
Widevine.
Widevine technology, which is created by Google, I believe, right?
But Google has released it freely.
And now Firefox will be integrating that and they specifically plan to publish support
for Linux users in September in Firefox 49.
That is great.
That's a big equalizer.
This and electrolysis is making Firefox look super attractive again.
Those days where you're just frustrated with Chrome for whatever reason and you're like,
oh, maybe I'll use something else.
Firefox is getting there.
For me, the story around how plugins and extensions have to be refactored to support electrolysis
might still be the final decision.
But I know both – have you – I know you've looked at Vivaldi before.
I was going to say both you and I have messed around with Vivaldi.
Yeah, I used it probably for a week or two.
Yeah, I've recently looked into it.
Mr. Tennell there in the Mumba room has been playing around with it.
Michael, has it been specifically – like, has it gotten to the point where it's specifically
ready to switch from Chrome and it solves some of your Chrome frustrations or is it – where
is Vivaldi at in your testing so far?
Well, I mean, actually, I don't like Chrome at all because it does a lot of things I don't
like and I prefer Firefox over everything.
However, everything that I didn't like about Chrome has been solved in some way in Vivaldi.
So the things that I – if I went from Firefox to Chrome, I would lose a lot of features,
but all – well, 99% of the features that I would lose are available in Vivaldi.
So the transition wouldn't be as bad for me to go from Vivaldi – go to Vivaldi, but
whereas Chrome would basically just not even remotely be an option for me.
Okay.
So the tab hibernation specifically is one of the most important things I've seen because
I set up a tab stack where you can put a bunch of tabs into one tab and then you can hibernate
that whole stack.
Oh, that is nice.
So you can take, like, 30 tabs and then hibernate them all so you only have, like, two active
and you can jump to them wherever you want to.
Oh, all right.
That's really nice.
I have heard – I've read about their – I just never really thought about using it in
that way.
That is a pretty compelling use case for me.
Vivaldi is going to switch to Feasible when they have a sync solution.
Web sync and bookmark sync is pretty critical.
Like if I'm upstairs and I'm working on a Google doc for a show today, I have a current
shows folder in my bookmark toolbar that all of my docs for the shows that week that I'm
working on, as I create that doc, I drag it down into this folder and that becomes available
on my machines here in the studio and my machines in my office.
Pretty important to me to have that feature and Firefox has pretty good sync now.
So that's one of the reasons I keep eyeing Firefox.
Michael, while you're kind of up and center right now, have you followed at all this theme
pack that makes GIMP look more like Photoshop?
It's something that's been around for a while but just recently got updated and it really
makes GIMP look and – work and look a lot like Photoshop.
And I don't know how I feel about it, but I'm wondering if you've tried it.
I tried it a long time ago.
I haven't tried the latest version, but it works in the sense that it brings the UI to
a more usable state and not the absurd every tool is like hidden at the bottom of the columns.
I like overall, but it's not really necessary because a lot of the things that it does is
not that much different.
Like it does a dual column tool set instead of a single column tool set.
That's cool, but I really don't care.
But the only thing that GIMP has a problem with in my opinion is the fact of where they
put the tools options section.
And this theme pack changes or whatever pack it's called, changes it and moves it to the
top right.
So it gives it a lot more prominence.
So that one feature, that one change is probably enough for me to use it.
Yeah.
So it uses some of the same icons, but really a big for probably a lot of switchers is it
uses some of the same keyboard shortcuts, which is –
Oh, and that's the most important part of me for me because I have a – I've used Photoshop
for so long that when I go to GIMP, I have to remember – I have to re-learn every single
time all the shortcuts.
Yeah.
Ryan, I kind of wanted to get your thoughts on dragging old design paradigms and ways
of using things from our proprietary days into open source projects.
Is this encumbering GIMP in a way that sort of prevents it from sort of branching out
into a different UI design even if it's bad by some people's comparison?
Is there maybe a downside to doing something like this to open source?
It seems like it doesn't feel like something that happens to proprietary commercial applications.
I don't think it's bad just because a lot of my friends who have moved from Photoshop
to GIMP oftentimes complain about things not being where they're accustomed to and that
it's a lot harder to continue using it.
So I tell them about these different things like GIMP Shop and I saw this the other day
and sent it over to my dad who used Photoshop for years and years and years before adopting
GIMP and he likes this type of stuff because it puts things in a place that he expects
it to be.
Yeah.
That makes sense.
For my mom who's been a graphic artist and literally lived inside the Adobe applications
for the last 25 years, this would be just – it's just simply a matter of like Rotten
was saying, Mr. Tunnell, that it is a mapping that's to your – it's like a muscle memory
mapping.
How's the challenge going there, Wes?
I noticed you're inserting the boot drive or the thumb drive for the first time.
Have you been doing research ahead of time?
I did a little bit of research.
I've got it booted.
I'm just – there's some –
Oh really?
Let's just say the word Broadcom is a factor.
Yes.
That is an issue.
Now, I wonder if we don't have an easy way to get you Ethernet either.
That's OK.
I'm working on a –
It wasn't at Apple's best wisdom to include an Ethernet adapter in their pro laptop.
You see, that's silly.
Those are so floppy drive.
I think I might even have a USB adapters in my bag but hopefully I won't need it.
I wonder if anybody in the Mamba Room is – moving on from GIMP.
I think we probably said our piece.
I wonder if anybody in the Mamba Room is an Internet of Things advocate or skeptic because
this next story is I think extremely good news for an actual manageable Internet of
Things world.
This is a big deal for Canonical.
They just struck a deal that is going to put Ubuntu on AdventX x86 based gateways and they're
going to be certified to fully support Ubuntu images.
Now these Internet of Things gateways I think are a pretty sound way to go because you have
your various janky, cheap endpoints that are distributed throughout your house that you're
probably going to be replacing every couple of years and you have all of that connect
back to a central gateway device that proxies – oh god, it's weird to hear a Mac sound
on the show.
Sounds terrible.
That is weird.
So –
I apologize everyone.
I got a little shook up there.
So it acts as sort of a central proxy to handle like you could manage a lot of these things
centrally from there on your land before it even has to go out to the Internet.
So for that particular device to be the sort of central communication point, to be running
something like an Ubuntu image that is supportable and updatable and likely more secure than
some sort of off-created embedded OS by some hardware manufacturer, I think this is a huge
win for that.
Oh, look at that.
I didn't even know I had that shot.
Well, that's pretty fancy.
So does anybody in the Mumba room have any thoughts on this, on the Internet of Things
in general and ways we could prevent a Armageddon where all mayhem has been unleashed on us
because these devices are out of date and unpatched?
I like the idea in general as long as I get to control what it runs.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, that's for sure.
Yeah, what it runs and how up to date it remains and how easy that process is are all pretty
key for me, I think.
Yeah, go ahead.
Yeah, yeah.
Very nice.
Sorry.
We all know that like a lot of this stuff right now, we set it and it never gets updated.
And so, I mean, that world in which some of these things actually run a legit like operating
system that's used in other products and actually gets updates, like that's a win regardless.
I'm delighted to see Mr. Pope here.
I'd be kind of curious to hear your thoughts, Pope, about this particular Git.
It seems like a pretty good position.
Just your personal thoughts on this market for Ubuntu as somebody who's watched the platform
for a long time and maybe the Internet of Things in general.
So hi, Pope.
Welcome back to the show.
Hello.
And your thoughts, sir.
Yeah, it's funny.
You know the old, there's no such thing as the cloud, just other people's computers.
Yeah.
I saw someone do a tweet earlier, I think yesterday, that said, there's no Internet
of Things.
It's just many unpatched, vulnerable, small computers on the Internet.
And that is so true.
And having a platform that is updated, you know, I worry that my home gateways, but not
just home stuff, corporate environment, there are devices on corporate networks of all kinds
which are not updated, not patched, not centrally managed.
And I think it's great that we're making inroads in companies that are making these devices
that allow them to be centrally managed and updated and secure and have apps via a store
installed on them.
I think it's great.
You know, but Google would tell us that we need something like Fuchsia to make this possible.
Yeah.
Can you tell me where I can download that?
Apparently in the future, that's where you can download that.
Okay.
I'll be waiting.
Wimpy, are you a bit of a skeptic on these particular device categories in general?
The only reason I don't mean to label you as a skeptic, but you and I have shared similar
thoughts on the past in regards to VR, which also seems to have the same kind of hype smell
to it.
I don't think Wimpy's there.
Yeah.
Oh, there you are.
Hello, sir.
Hi, Wimpy.
Oh, hello.
Hello.
Can you hear me?
Yep.
Hello.
I think you just have a delay.
Okay.
Yeah.
Oh, dear.
That's unfortunate.
Is this the alloy device you're referring to or something else?
It is.
I think it's actually a not-yet-released device by Advantech.
So it's basically a full-fledged x86 computer, and I don't think it's a shipping product
yet.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
Advantech Embedded Computing Group.
Now, Poppy, if you know anything different, you want to correct me, but I believe that's
the case.
I don't have an issue with these devices so long as they can actually run Linux of any
flavor because then you're able to put a Linux operating system on it after whatever platform
they've tried to build out of open source tools and things have sort of passed away.
It's when you get these things where their thing that runs Linux is like a heavily patched
version and they've never open sourced the patches back so you can't, you know, reutilize
the device fully without having to reverse engineer a load of stuff.
Or if they have like an image that they build once in a while, like they use Rootstock or
Rootstock NG or something, which builds a root file system that they deploy on the device
and then that's it, ships out with that and no one gets any updates unless there's some
kind of deep lead technical user who will go and download the latest image and flash
it on the device.
If it's got no internal way of updating itself, I don't want it on my network.
I would much rather have devices that can check in with a central server, get an update,
make sure I've got the latest version of apps, latest version of the core operating system,
whatever that might be.
And yeah, I agree with Martin.
If it ships with some form of Linux, then at some point I could potentially put some
other form of Linux that's more secure.
What an excellent point that is.
I think that's exactly it.
And maybe the meta story there is by enabling Ubuntu on this thing, it's opening up for
people like us to tinker if we wish, but also giving regular consumers that just use it
with the stock Ubuntu image a pretty fair shot at what seems so far to be a security
disaster.
So either way, it seems like a positive story for even non-Ubuntu users.
So I'm pretty excited about it.
I like that stuff.
And it always felt like it was like, okay, we're going to get Linux on these devices,
but it's not going to be a Linux we trust or a Linux we understand, so if this is real
Ubuntu, that'd be great.
Yeah, I know that.
And I know how to Google for things about Ubuntu, and I know how to read Stack Exchange,
and I can do things with this.
And it kind of goes back to my hesitations with FreeNAS.
I like the product, and here in my business I use it, but in my home, I kind of want something
I feel safe.
If I ever got the wild hair to tinker with, I want to be able to.
And I feel like with FreeNAS, I break it.
Yeah, with FreeNAS, I feel like I break it when I tinker it.
But if it's something that's Ubuntu-based, I grok that user space.
I know what I'm doing there.
Okay, so before we continue on, oh, you busted out a USB Ethernet adapter.
I did happen to have it in my bag.
Holy crap!
Respect!
So, okay, I'm guessing connectivity is a major issue, especially for something like Antigros,
which requires connectivity to install.
And I've noticed you've brought the thumbstick back to your Sputnik laptop.
What's going on?
Well, for some reason it's not booting now, so I'm checking the integrity really quick.
I'm also copying the Broadcom driver onto a second USB stick.
Oh, clever, sir.
So I will then hopefully be able to reboot, install that driver, and get it installed.
Okay, so Ethernet could be tricky.
That's what I assumed.
If we wanted to take out the wireless here at the JB1 Studios, you could go around the
corner and there is an exceptionally long Ethernet cord that powers our wireless that
you could bring it in here.
And I don't think it would take out any of our production systems because they're all
Ethernet.
So, hopefully we will all...
Yeah, by the way, I think if you're going to dive into the realm of Linux on the MacBook,
if you want to do that, go get yourself a USB Ethernet adapter because that's going
to come in super handy.
All right, so we have more updates to get into, and I want to do that, and Mr. Sipes
is here and we definitely want to talk to him.
So before we continue, let's mention our first sponsor.
And that's Ting, my mobile service provider, check them out.
Go over there right now to linux.ting.com and you'll save on your first device or if
you bring a compatible device, they'll give you $25 in credit for your first month.
Now, that's probably going to pay for your first month because the way Ting works is
you only pay for what you use and there's just a $6 fee for the line plus Uncle Sam's
cut like a mobster and then your usage, just your minutes, your messages, your megabytes.
In fact, they just recently lowered their data prices, which is phenomenal, makes them
incredibly competitive.
And they have a system where if you just want to use your device like a couple of times
a month for a few calls, you could save a ton of money.
But if you have a busy month where you're making tons and tons of calls, like for me,
in April, I'm on the phone every day, sometimes two hours a day.
And I have like one month on Ting that's like maybe, I don't even know, $55, $65, $75 depending
on if I'm also using quite a bit of data or something.
And then the other months, it's $24, $25, $26, $30, $35, $40 depending on my usage.
It averages out to be an incredible savings over two years over $2,000 and you can get
a feel for it too by using their savings calculator on their page.
It's really nice.
Unlocked devices, no contracts, no other termination fees.
You can get simple feature phones that just make great calls and have a week-long battery
life.
Or you can go get the Cadillac Android devices and everything in between.
You should check out some of their devices.
They all come unlocked.
You own that device.
They're not going to get in the way of updates.
They don't play that carrier game.
I love it.
And they're backed by two cows who have been around since the dot com boom.
Think about that.
Imagine that, making money on the internet since before the dot com boom and actually
doing it in a way that's great because you get great customer service with Ting.
Check them out at linux.ting.com.
It's a better way to do mobile.
I love it.
Thanks, Ting, for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
So Mr. Ryan Sipes is joining us, and you've heard him jumping in a few times.
And you may have also heard the news this week that he has departed from Mycroft, the
project that we have talked about a lot on this show, and I'm sure it must have piqued
the interest of a lot of our audience.
So Ryan, first of all, I just wanted to say thanks for coming on the show.
And how are you doing?
I'm doing great.
I have a bit more free time on my hands.
That's OK.
Good.
Well, we appreciate you spending some of that podcasting with us then.
So I imagine that you've probably gotten a lot of questions and seen a lot of different
discussions happening online.
Is there anything in particular you wanted to address or any particular feedback items
you wanted to touch on?
Mostly, I just wanted to assure everyone that Mycroft is licensed under the GPL version
3 and that as a result, regardless of my involvement, the project can continue and people should
feel just fine using it and implementing it into their projects.
And that's all I'm willing to say right now about it really specifically.
I think that if people are keeping up with me online, you have my blog post pulled up
there, to just stay tuned and I will kind of bring people into more of the mindset behind
that.
But I was really just ready to move on to other projects and this was the best time
to do it.
So Ryan, I kind of wanted to talk about you in a different context for a second.
Do you remember how long ago it was that the Mycroft funding campaign launched?
I mean, that was probably the first time I'd really heard your name.
How long ago was that, do you think?
It was September of last year.
Okay, so it's not even been a year yet.
Here's what's pretty damn astonishing about that.
A year ago, I wasn't thinking a lot about open source artificial intelligence personal
system devices.
It was obviously something the big guys were thinking about.
It wasn't really something on my radar, which I think was a mistake.
And then also, I had never heard the name Ryan Sipes before and I didn't know you from
Adam.
And now here we are less than a year later and artificial intelligence and voice recognition
and intent parsing are something that we talk about all the time.
And Ryan Sipes is a name that many people are all of a sudden familiar with.
And what I find to be extremely illuminating about this particular situation is, at least
in my view, it seems to demonstrate how quickly the open source community recognizes good
work and talent and how that really can propel you into the general discussion very quickly
just simply based on technical merits and a project that people are interested in.
And that is really one of the most, I think, interesting sort of side meta stories about
you and Mycroft is how quickly you've become sort of a common technology that we are discussing
simply because it sounds fascinating on its technical merits and what kind of that says
about our community.
And I'm kind of wondering, Ryan, if you reflect on sort of some of – if you could
reflect for a moment on what that process has been like going from nobody knew your
name really and maybe I'm wrong on that but I certainly really didn't to now you're
making videos on YouTube about Mycroft, you're going to System76 and you're getting interviewed
on podcasts, you're having to make blog posts when you quit a job and tweet about
it and then all the follow up that comes from that.
What the hell has that been like for you?
So I have been into open source software for a long time.
And so I was always watching and seeing people who I thought were much more technically talented
than I was shaping the conversations around the future of open source and kind of what
projects were rising to the top.
I think that the thing that happens is that after a while of being in this community,
you start to want to share your ideas and you start to want to contribute back to – I
had never used a server – I had never set up a server until somebody finally was like,
hey, check out Ubuntu in 2005 or whatever.
And when I started using the desktop Ubuntu, well then that opened my mind up to Linux
and at the time I remember I wanted to host a website and people were saying like, oh
you have to use this version of Windows Server and I just was able to get acquainted with
all this technology because of open source and so since then you want to pay it forward
and I got the opportunity to do so by introducing lots of people to a new technology that is
going to shape the future of computing in a lot of big ways.
Now before then, I actually was in the Mumble Room a couple of times before Mycroft ever
came around.
I talked about Kansas Linux Fest.
I think when I spoke for myself though, I'm really kind of meaning in the broader – like
Ryan Sipes as a name is probably not something – I don't think there's probably as many
people that were talking about you before something very technically interesting came
along that you were involved with.
Right.
Yeah, exactly.
But now because of my experience at Mycroft, I am very happy to be able to use kind of
the microphone that's given me to share other projects that I think that the open source
community should be gathering around and should be aware of.
One of these things is machine learning.
Absolutely.
That's an enormous opportunity.
It's an enormous – it's an enormous just space that's going to blow up and we should
be able to take advantage of that.
We'll need something there.
And the proprietary people are there now and will continue to be there so we need to be
there too.
Yeah.
And there are projects like TensorFlow from Google and Cafe from Yahoo and a few others
–
You mean Verizon.
– that are open source.
Yeah, exactly.
But I'm really excited to kind of go forward from here and continue to help shape maybe
like open source AI and personal assistance.
After a lot of self-reflection, I just found that I might have a better opportunity to
do that on my own at this point.
There are other projects that I hint at getting involved in in my blog post and I would love
to come back and talk about them and share some things.
I think that one of them the community will be familiar with and it's just a project
that hasn't gotten a lot of play that I think is really important.
And then there are some other ones that I'd like to talk about and see if we can't get
some collaboration.
But yeah, it's been a crazy wild ride.
I met a lot of people who I considered to be celebrities including you, Chris.
And it was kind of crazy when I posted the blog post to get calls from people who a year
ago if you said that they were going to give me a call out of the blue, I would have told
you that's just not possible, it's not going to happen.
And so it's been a wild ride and it's not over.
I think that there's so much more that I can do for the open source community.
I think that there's so much more that we as a larger community, the Jupyter Broadcasting
community, the Linux community can do and I'm excited to be a part of that.
Absolutely.
Yeah and you are always welcome to come and contribute to the shows because I always love
hearing your take on stuff and I know you reflect on this stuff quite a bit and I've
always sort of enjoyed following what you do and I'll continue to do so.
So thanks for joining us, Ryan.
And thanks for having me on.
Maybe some of you guys can help explain this next story to me.
Wes, I'm looking at you.
I know you're in the middle of a challenge right now.
But this sounds like a bad thing and I want you to talk me off the ledge, okay?
Fake Linus Torvalds keys have been found in the wild and we need to knock it off with
the short IDs ASAP.
Apparently it's well known that PGP is vulnerable to short ID collisions and many experiments
have been done to demonstrate that.
But what I didn't know is that keys, fake keys, fake PGP or maybe GPG keys I guess,
have been found for Linus, for Greg KH and other kernel developers in the wild recently.
Holy shit!
This seems bad to me.
This seems like NSA Russia kind of hacking China bad.
Well, it's really more just –
Talk me down, Wes.
You really shouldn't be using these short keys.
A project called Evil 32 to try to demonstrate this.
They took the web of trust, the usual one that you'll use if you are using PGP keys.
Right.
Yeah.
Say that five times fast.
Then they computed all of these brute force, you know, using GPUs and it looks like some
people have been taking their publicly available files and uploading them to some of the key
servers and so then people looking for them have found these.
So it does sound bad.
It is bad but we also know that these are not equivalent – they do not provide the
kind of identification, the kind of security that we expect from them.
PGP, GPG keys, don't do with the short IDs.
Anybody else in the moment have any takes on the story because this is kind of one of
those thick ones that it seems like something we know but probably the issue would be there's
stuff out there already that is signed with these short keys.
Short IDs, I guess.
And I don't know if anybody else has insights in the Momba Room but that's our take on
it.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
So I don't think this actually is bad for the normal users of Linux but more on people
that maintain distros and if they don't check it well then it's bad.
Oh, good point.
That is exactly who needs to be paying attention to this story.
Well said, Mr. Z.
Well said.
Thank you.
That is a really good point.
I wanted to mention something that I think was well said and started a conversation that
I think probably wasn't necessary but I wanted to give a shout out to Ninja Aaron who 23 hours
ago created a Linux action show subreddit post saying a quick comment about the ButterFs
coverage on the latest Linux action show and that's where we discussed the fact that the
official ButterFs project Twitter account recommended people use ZFS or ZFS.
That's pretty wild.
That was wild and our story was really about the reaction to that but you know he makes
a great point.
He says that ButterFs is definitely having its issues but he makes a couple of good use
case for ButterFs in this post and I guess I did want to mention like I'm not necessarily
opposed to the idea of people that want to use ButterFs on their laptop that has an SSD
drive.
I don't really think ButterFs is like the devil file system.
Really where I have an issue with the ButterFs advocacy, it really comes down to when people
try to advocate that it should be used in a business slash enterprise setting, however
you want to describe that.
I started in IT in the year 2000, about – well actually really – actually that's not
true.
1997 was when I actually officially got paid in IT when I was – I was at that time desktop
tech support.
But one of the things that I had to – there was – I had two challenges over my career
that were very much about data retention and then I had many challenges beyond that but
there were some that were very particular legally mandated, very, very, very carefully
audited use cases that I can't even really go into and in these scenarios, back then
we used very, very cutting edge file systems that were very risky, mostly because that
was all that was available at the time.
And so it's not that I'm also like some holier than thou soapboxer who says oh you
should never use ButterFs because you're a lunatic.
I mean I've been the guy that's been putting in a file system that's a little edgy in
production.
I have on a lot of my systems.
But there is sort of – I guess there is sort of this – it feels to me like there
is this failure to look within a bit to sort of self-analyze and say we've made a mistake
here.
And so I wanted to acknowledge that while I have been sort of anti-ButterFs in the last
few weeks as there's been more flaws, I also think there's many useful use cases
for it and I wanted to give a shout out to Mr. Ninja Aaron for kind of very well stating
that case and making me reflect on it a bit and go – I myself if I – actually for
this MacBook here, I would absolutely consider ButterFs on there.
You should have said that like two minutes ago.
No, it's fine.
What did you get?
You're getting the XT4 just because I figured you wouldn't mind if it was a safe and solid
choice.
I don't mind.
No.
So you're actually that far, huh?
So that means you got wireless working.
Oh yeah.
Ah.
Now that wireless fix – this is one of the interesting things though is that wireless
fix will not persist once you reboot into the main OS after it's been installed.
No.
But maybe I'll be smart enough to root into and install that preemptively.
Thank you for the reminder.
Damn it.
You know Wes, I'm actually pretty impressed that you got the Wi-Fi working without any
other connectivity.
So what did you do?
What did you do?
So this is going to be – the number one challenge is these MacBooks – any recent
MacBook doesn't have an Ethernet port.
And everybody that's going to be doing this is going to run into this problem where they're
not going to have Wi-Fi when they get in a live environment.
So what did you do to enable networking without having a connection?
Well I had conveniently – we're installing Antigros here and I had an Arch Linux little
laptop right here.
So I just ran make package, built the package, copied it on a USB drive, installed it, mod
probed the broad cam drivers and away we went.
Well played sir.
Which I was very pleased.
Everything worked perfectly.
Well played.
Network manager picked it right up.
We were on the network.
Damn.
And also I'm impressed that you remembered the Wi-Fi password too because I didn't tell
you what that was and you still – good job.
Anybody have thoughts on ButterFS in the mumble room before we move on to just a quick shout
out I have?
I'll just say I'm excited for BcacheFS.
We'll see when that's actually usable but –
Is that a B-tree kind of like RAM based?
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Tease me a little bit.
Let's see.
There's actually a Patreon for it.
Are you serious?
I mean maybe throw it.
Wimpy why are you looking forward to it?
Let's throw it right there.
Oh my god.
Okay.
Maybe that'll explain it better than I could probably.
Well Bcache is something that I've used to accelerate spinning drives by putting a Bcache
partition on solid state to effectively create sort of a level two cache.
This is great.
And the authors behind Bcache realized that they were very close to actually having a
full lock file system.
So they're going the next step to implement it as a copy on write file system.
They only have 38 patrons.
I feel like maybe we could bump that up a little bit for them.
So it's going to be a copyright on write file system like ZFS or Butterfess.
They aim for good performance.
They say significantly better than existing copy on write file systems comparable to the
performance of Extended 4 or XFS.
Hello.
See we really need this.
We're just embarrassing ourselves.
Oh wow.
Metadata and data checks on multiple devices including replication and other types of RAID,
caching, compression, encryption, snapshots and scalable.
It's been tested up to 50 terabytes and will eventually scale higher.
We'll be working on stable with a small community of users.
This is super exciting.
And what I really like about it is and this is where I was trying to get to in the conversation
on Sunday but I think I went off track is Butterfess when you look at the model almost
seems like this funding model makes a lot of sense.
It's just they would need way more support because it really is a full time job.
It is a lot of work to do this properly.
But this is this is great.
So Bcash I'll put a link to the Patreon in the in the show notes so that could be really
cool.
I'll check it out more after the show.
Has anybody tried it out?
Just watching it?
I have not now.
Hmm.
Wimpy what would be your use?
I've not tried it.
But one day.
One day.
Yeah.
As a principal file system on laptops for example.
Yes.
Oh could you imagine something like that.
The features of that if we had OK so here's why it's a big deal.
Here's why we need to get this right.
So one of the things that true OS is that out that they're changing the name of true
OS.
Is that a is that an official thing.
I hope I didn't anyways.
Is that a thing.
This is BSD unplugged.
So PC BSD has the Lumos desktop environment and they they've done a lot of work on their
file manager to integrate ZFS snapshots and backups and multiple versions into the file
manager and that is honestly the level that we need to get at with the Linux desktop.
And until we really kind of land on something until we really sort of solidify something
like this we're not going to have it integrated to the desktop level like that.
There's no way until it has mass adoption that's going to happen.
And definitely one of the advantages that the PC BSD guys has is if you're going to
go with it if you there they have one file system choice that supports all this stuff
and that's ZFS and they can plan for that and they can exactly and it's the same advantage
that once Apple gets off their ass and they finally get APFS working they'll do that and
they'll integrate into time machine.
And to be honest with you in some ways NTFS has been kicking our ass for a couple of years
with shadow copy.
I mean shadow volume copy has really saved my ass a couple of times when I was in IT
and I it's one of the reasons why I wanted to use ButterFS here on our server that runs
our VMs because it I mean it saved my ass a few times.
So there is one story I want to talk about before we go any further into the show because
last week I kind of offhandedly mentioned the Humble Bundle and was sort of like dismissive
with their only three games that supported Linux.
And then this week Humble Bundle 17 went live and all of the games all of the games in this
bundle support Linux so I just I wanted to follow up on that because I gave them kind
of a hard time last week and then they totally delivered this week with Humble Indie Bundle
17.
This is the Humble Indie Bundle and all the games freaking support Linux.
That is awesome.
Yeah if you pay more than ten dollars you get Nuclear Throne which is I think yeah I
think that's one of the games I wanted.
So we have a link.
Octodad nice always a classic.
I like that OMG Ubuntu has been writing about this too.
Yeah that's nice.
I think it is.
I like that they're posting more over there they kind of slow down for a while and it
seems like they've picked it back up and I think that's nice because it feels like there's
a lot going on these days.
It feels like things in some ways it's August and the news is slow but at the same time
there is a lot of really we're on the precipice of the interesting things really hitting us
and so that stuff is beginning to arrive and if you're watching closely like like that
terminal we talked about that there are things beginning to land.
It's like an incubation period right now and there's stuff happening it's kind of just
not visible and soon it'll be popping up.
And it feels like they're doing a decent job of percolating some of that stuff up and some
of the stuff like the GIMP theme or arc theme stuff like that it's also just kind of nice
as a daily driver it's nice to have that kind of stuff.
So hats off to Joey over there for seemingly picking it up recently and really doubling
down on content that I've been enjoying reading even as a non Ubuntu user I still find it
kind of interesting which is got to be kind of a challenge for a site called OMG Ubuntu
right.
Hey before we go any further I'll tell you about a challenge I have and that is every
time I need to do something it feels like I got to get a new computer well that's where
DigitalOcean came in I am able to spin up a server in less than a minute now and that
is a game changer for me when I want to try something out I spin up a droplet when I want
to put something in production I use a droplet and when I want something just for family
members I use a droplet.
DigitalOcean is simple cloud hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way
for you to spin up your own server on their kick ass infrastructure they have SSDs throughout
the entire thing they got data centers all over the world they have multiple data centers
in multiple cities they have private networking amongst your servers in certain areas which
is a really cool feature and I'm just going to put this out there I have not actually
done this yet but I'm going to admit Alan has been teasing me you could do a little
free NAS thing on that back end now that they've got block storage you've got ZFS you could
also do Ubuntu 16.04 with a little ZFS action and then do the back end block storage or
you know what if you want to go crazy you could probably there's probably I mean it's
block storage you could use butter fs2 yes you could you really could it's kind of fun
because it's a it's SSD backed and you just attach it as you need it's on demand their
pricing starts at five dollars a month and if you use our promo code and this is kind
of nice if you use our promo code do unplugged you get a ten dollar credit and then you can
try it out two months for free they have a really nice interface they have a super sweet
API that tons of open source codes already been written around and I got to tell you
now I've been using it I don't know a year and a half I'm not sure how long I've been
using digital ocean but almost every week I've spent up a droplet at least for a little
bit try something out and then destroy it and on occasion I keep it in production and
I've been I've been really sort of changing the way I think about computing like when
we wanted to start streaming on demand to a certain certain outlets that prefer you
only stream when you are actually live it made sense to just take an existing configuration
and sort of improve upon it and spin up a new droplet on demand using their API and
then we just pay for it while we're using it it really is like it's like infrastructure
on demand and it's it feels like 2016 you combine that now with their great tutorials
and the huge community around it and the fact that not only do they run Linux on their entire
infrastructure but they back a lot of the projects that we talked about in some capacity
or another and a lot of the folks that we talked to interact with digital ocean in a
way that I don't know if digital ocean really promotes properly because like there's been
projects that have come along them and been sort of desperate for hosting and digital
ocean has provided it to them for free and or worked out deals with it's not publicized
very widely and the other thing like when they decided to bring on core OS is one of
their distributions and and free BSD and those are just the two since they've been sponsors
that I've had like some information about and so I'm not sure what they did in the past
probably similar is they actually contact the upstream distribution and say we want
to work with you we don't we they don't just like go grab the ISO image and make it work
they're like we're gonna work with you on this let's get this going it's pretty cool
that's very cool so use our promo code do you unplugged and a big thank you to digital
ocean for sponsoring the program you know Chris if you didn't have a handy Arch Linux
laptop you could there are some scripts out there to convert your droplets to Linux you
could compile your you'd make do your make packages up there yeah that is something people
could look into because it's Paul I think it's mostly made possible because they're
kick-ass console yeah exactly so I want to talk about Debbie and today's its 23rd birthday
and maybe we could talk about the future of Debbie in a little bit I wanted to reflect
on something for a moment before we get any further this is from swampy over it does market
where a YouTube account it's a video of Linus at Deb comp 14 which was in Portland which
I think I think JB live stream to this I don't remember so I probably could have played from
my own clip archive but credit to swampy for that for this clip here I'll start with something
non-controversial no no I'm fine with controversial that's not usually my problem it's well known
around these parts that in 2007 you did an interview where you said that although you've
used many Linux distributions you had never used Debian because you found it difficult
to install yes have you tried it since no that was quick so I'm sure it's gotten much
easier to install it to me a distribution is I'm sorry you may want to close your ears
now a distribution is not very interesting I wanted to be easy to install so that I can
just get on with my life right which is mostly the kernel the closest I got to installing
Debian was there was one machine I forget which one it was it may have been the MacBook
Air that actually had trouble installing something and and Debian the installer would boot but
then it didn't install there either and eventually I figured out what was the problem with that
machine but but by then it was too late if there's a way to break installing an operating
system I've found it multiple times and if there isn't one you already know if I found
it and Debian last time super easy highly recommended trying maybe I should try I mean
one of the problems I have is I am not an MIS person I mean I may do kernels and people
think that that means that I'm technical but when it comes to actually maintaining machines
I am a complete disaster it makes me feel better right it's funny that he's like so
caught up making and well maintaining the kernel yeah you know the actually running
of the yeah not that interesting okay that's fine Debian is one of my first Linux eyes
it wasn't my first Linux eye but it was my mostly impressed it was the one I was most
impressed by and the one that saved the day for us the most when we first started using
Linux oh yeah and I so I don't know if it wasn't for Debian I don't know if if I would
be a Linux user today really yeah well maybe I mean it might have still happened but I
think it was definitely major seems to have been a rock-solid choice early on so that
kind of people could latch on to it yeah yeah so I boy I really I really am really thankful
to Debian because we had definitely tried it was old Red Hat it was way way before Fedora
it was way way long time ago like Red Hat four and five and we were trying some of this
stuff and when we were trying to do things like get the most current version of squid
and it's funny to even talk about Debian in the context and getting a more current version
but yeah literally our Red Hat distribution it shipped with a really ancient version of
squid and Debian with apt-get made squid setup and then the other thing that was really nice
about Debian is after after you installed a package via the internet which by the way
back in the 90s that was magic that was magic that was that was unbelievable and it also
still supported CDs which was great because we needed those and so to be able to install
squid but then the next thing after installing squid where it would bring up like an end
curses interface and ask me questions about what I want and and then to make it so easy
to do that and set up email server that and they setting up an email server on Debian
word nobody made it as easy and quick and then continued to keep it secure and up-to-date
like Debian did it was just you could rely on the fact that they were so slow and they
took so long to upgrade that you're gonna get a solid five years out of that machine
and and you with solid updates and probably longer and then when you did ask gonna run
and then when you did have to dist upgrade after five years or six years it was gonna
work and that was that was what that made Linux so a safe bet for me and it made it
it made it possible for us to fix major networking problems that we had so I I have a really
soft spot for Debian then obviously it's sort of the the proto distro that so many things
have so many things have come from and if you look at if you look at the success that
Ubuntu has had and the on the cloud and all of that and the fact that those origins come
from Debian it's really it's kind of incredible so I wanted to open up the mumble room and
say hey guys what are your thoughts on maybe where Debian as a project itself is gonna
go in the future where where does this where does the next five ten maybe even twenty years
where does Debian go and I wanted to give the mumble room time to ping me in the chat
room with their you know who wants to ever go so West while we while we give them time
to let us know where they and it could be quick or long have you reflected on this at
all since you know you and I were kind of chatting about this do you think Debian is
gonna continue to be a dominant player in this space is it gonna continue to just be
sort of the the foundation what's the next few years look like for Debian in your mind
I'm kind of uncertain I've played with Debian 8 I've used it to run like free switch for
example where there's some good like ansible recipes and other things that are freely available
and I mean I find it a relatively pleasant environment they've got system D now it seems
like you know it's pretty standard they have a huge amount of software available the Debian
8 release is still very current the software there is you know good for most needs they've
got their own PPA system in the works in the works I have not played with that or tried
any of that but you know it's coming you know what I haven't looked at it's like it's like
snap D that kind of thing that would be interesting as well but it does seem like a good place
to run software but I don't know what I what I don't know and what I'm curious to hear
from everyone else is what's the what's the enthusiasm like are people looking for it
is it like when you're just looking to run the Linux for some reason does Debian leap
to your mind should it leap to your mind well you know I'm gonna I see so Ryan's tagged
me but first I'm actually gonna I'm gonna jump it over to wimpy just for a second because
I have an idea where I feel like Debian is gonna grow a lot in the next five years and
that's Raspbian at the Raspberry Pi and I'm wondering what wimpy thinks about that is
you know because that's also a super popular trajectory for Ubuntu Mate it seems like a
likely a likely continued area of success for Debian what are your thoughts wimpy I
I think that's a little bit awkward actually because Raspbian isn't really part of the
Debian community and I think Raspbian would do well to more closely align itself with
Debian rather than sort of be an offshoot with its own repository sort of bolted on
top so this is not a Debian issue more a Raspbian issue I would definitely like to see Raspbian
become more closely aligned with Debian so maybe in the future there isn't a Raspbian
there is just a Debian and everything you need to power everything on the Pi is in Debian
proper rather than this sort of thing yeah and you know if you're absolutely right and
if I'm right that this is gonna be a continued area of success for Debian that is just gonna
get even more awkward that is really something that's a great point wimpy Ryan I want to
give you a chance to jump in what do you think do you think there's gonna be another distro
that will ever be surpassed as like the proto distro in this next few I mean this seems
to be a solid spot for Debian right now yeah I think that you're right I if I pull out
my crystal ball and I look at it though I think that we see we see like let's look at
Ubuntu for instance sure I right now everything's based on Debian I don't know how long that's
gonna last I think for the foreseeable future that's a for sure thing but the but I could
see them since they've gained so much prominence in in the cloud and and across you know when
you're deploying stuff there's so many people would just say yeah I deploy Ubuntu you know
and they don't even think twice they just use whatever configuration management tool
that they're gonna use on their cloud and just bang it's like spun up 20 machines yeah
all running a workload and what's crazy is you see more and more of those running you
know Docker images and like it it makes me wonder how long is it until until the until
the Ubuntu guys say like hey they want to go a different direction than we do why don't
we finally begin to break our reliance on them will snap be the press the thing that
pushes it over the edge there perhaps interesting I think it's possible yeah sweet Lou as a
user you say you don't really see a big difference between Debian and Ubuntu so do you just sort
of default go Ubuntu yeah I've tried some Debian base some other Debian based OS's before
and to me they just really didn't seem all that much different other than not you know
a usable place to install stuff from you know besides one that begins with an S there I
would say I would say yeah from a user usability perspective that's absolutely the case mini
Mac you make the point that you kind of view Debian as a having a special role in the open
source community yeah I see the Debian devs or the technical committee as somehow the
moral authority hmm you remember the set of s discussion or adaptation of system D yeah
I mean the work of Debian developers has still some impact yeah absolutely yeah you know
geez mini Mac good point if we reflect on the system D discussion it really seems like
there was a massive change in the discussion she's that bad thing I know there was a there
was a big pivot when Debian when Debian decided to go system D and then when Debian did some
of the legal legwork to make ZFS possible you immediately saw Ubuntu able to jump on
that and those are two huge huge technology issues and social issues quote unquote in
the Linux community that Debian was sort of the deciding authority on it's a great point
what it what an interesting position for them to be in and and you know it also makes me
think a little bit reflect a little bit on Ian Murdock and makes me miss him a little
bit so there you go that is boy if if you want to play with something kind of neat and
by the way mom or you still have a few chance a few minutes left or a minute left to jump
in if you want but if you want to look at something kind of neat and the history of
the Debian project we have timeline debian net linked in the show notes and you can scroll
through this and look at some of the major activity in the Debian project over the years
major milestones like Deb camps and huge bugs that were like news stories and first alphas
and then of course the final beta really final releases and the betas and all that kind of
stuff and also things like the the bug squashing parties in Cambridge and you kind of get a
sense for the Debian project at a larger scale it's pretty neat and sees that you can also
get a sense that there's still plenty of 2016 left to be filled out on that map and plenty
of the future for Debian goes way back this is I don't know what tech they're using to
generate this does it say it's really neat though yeah it's this tiny font down there
I can't quite read it it's at the bottom you see how small that font is at the bottom of
the page dang but somewhere down there probably tells you what they're using so happy birthday
to Debian guys it's it's really cool we're really happy to have something like you around
for so long so hats off and we give the as the special winners award to you yeah that's
for Debian right there just for you guys all right so I want to get to the how the challenge
is going and the reasons why this challenge was actually concocted in the first damn place
and while you'll probably be hearing more about it pretty soon if I were a little bit
of a crystal ball rubber what what did you what did you say crystal ball rubber Linux
Academy comm slash unplug that's where you go to learn more about Linux Academy and support
this show Linux Academy is a platform to learn the core fundamentals around Linux and then
the stack around although I built on top of it as your AWS open stack Docker Python that
all that stuff in that ecosystem that you hear about all the time that feels like our
big major nebulous topics that you're not really quite sure where you'd ever even get
started Linux Academy helps you put it in perspective and get it done Linux Academy
comm slash unplugged where you go to support this show try it out they'll put you in the
middle of a real world scenario so you walk away with experience they have instructor
mentoring when you need it they have customized learning plans that can adapt your availability
even when you're super ass busy and as somebody who owns his own business and as a father
of three children I can attest you can make Linux Academy work for you just get started
at Linux Academy comm slash unplug check out their great community look at their downloadable
comprehensive study guide there's real value there participate in their note card system
which is actually a pretty great experiment you might call it and enjoy their virtual
labs which spin up on demand when you need them and give you SSH access with distributions
you've chosen ahead of time Linux Academy comm slash unplugged if you're gonna get into
the world of certs this is a great resource Linux Academy comm slash unplugged in a big
thank you Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program looks Academy comm slash
unplugged okay Wes I heard you rebooting during that spot I heard you how's it going it's
installed now we're working on getting it to show up in the bootloader you have a preference
do you want refined do you not I don't know I don't know what's what's the difference
this is this is all new to me I mean you can get it to work with the native EFI bootloader
that seems good okay but you can also install refined which is kind of just a nice better
what would make it easier to get the Nvidia graphics working because that's that's part
of the question that's part of the question because I think that's like a kernel boot
parameter because otherwise I think it uses the Intel graphics by default I believe so
I want to talk about why this is happening because this is some crazy bull crap I mean
I actually I will be in full disclosure I will be honest with you the number one question
we have ever gotten into the Linux action show and Linux unplugged and I am literally
talking since episode one over a decade ago of Linux action show the number one question
we have gotten is how do I get Linux working on a MacBook and we answer it from time to
time but we never really fully go into it and so we're it's one of these things that
we're simply sick and tired of getting the question asked and so we just don't address
it a lot and I was I was I've been using the entryware Apollo as my daily driver at
home pretty much since my review and absolutely loving it and it is light right the battery
lasts for hours it's it's it's small enough that I can carry it and just bring it to work
when I need it not have to worry about bringing the power adapter and it's it is a very nice
machine and I have all my stickers all over it with I just I really enjoy it but then
No Man's Sky came out and that damn game I can't help but love it and it requires open
GL 4.5 support and SSE 4 I think and basically dedicated graphics and that's where the MacBook
came in yeah and I connected with okay so I sort of visualize myself as an audience
member I've either bought a used MacBook I've inherited a MacBook or I'm sick and tired
of Mac OS and Apple is not getting around updating this thing no and one of the things
that I know from previous testing experience is that Linux runs a hell of a lot faster
on the MacBook than OS 10 does so the fact that this is a 2013 is going to feel it's
going to feel I estimate under Linux probably going to feel like a brand new machine like
it's probably gonna feel very fast I mean it's got the PCI SSD in there it's got dedicated
said not about using f2FS or whatever yeah it's got dedicated Nvidia graphics it's it's
got a it's got a wonderful retina screen on it it's it's a really it's a pretty nice laptop
is a nice lap and people generally accept that the MacBook is built well so the question
has always been how reasonable would Linux be on the MacBook because my intention is
I know this sounds ridiculous is to then install wine and then install No Man's Sky I eventually
I plan to also put OBS on there and do some broadcasting from because it does have a four
core processor as well sure yeah that would work well yeah so that's where that was sort
of the impetus for myself to want to try Linux on the MacBook and then that sort of sent
us down the path of trying to figure out well what do you need to know before you put Linux
on a MacBook and it definitely seems to be one of the things you have to get your head
around is what model of MacBook do you have and this is somewhat not obvious since Apple
just calls everything MacBook and if you have Mac OS on your system you can actually entertain
this by going into the about back system and I have a screen I have a screenshot of this
in the show notes you go in there and it'll tell you like it's a late model something
something you Google MacBook Pro late model 2013 and it will tell you the specific like
model number is like it's 11 comma 2 or something like that right West of my yes I believe so
yeah and there's like other ones like older ones are like you know different so it's it's
it's a major model number comma minor model revision and you find that you can find like
arch wiki entries which for mine I've linked in the show notes that specifically tell you
about the little kind of esoteric tweaks you have to make to make it work on your particular
MacBook model and I as I look at this I think this could be a this could be a really great
Linux box if if all of this works out so I'm kind of really interested to see where it
goes I'll try the Thunderbolt out and then I can report back to the audience on on some
of my adventures with it I also was kind of wondering I was kind of wanted to pick Wimpy's
brain and ask him if he hears many people in the Ubuntu Mate community that are running
it on the MacBooks because that also crossed my mind as a possible distro if we couldn't
get arch working yeah it does crop up from time to time mostly in discussions in the
Ubuntu Mate community and if it's something that you're interested in doing then that
is the place to first search because it's a discourse so you can find the right discussions
easily and if your model hasn't been discussed then start a new thread and there are a few
people in there that can assist you with that it doesn't come up a lot it comes up a bit
but not not loads it's certainly not a major platform I'm seeing people use Ubuntu Mate
on I good I don't know I just don't at this point I don't know if I feel like recommending
it although maybe I'll feel differently after we try this I do see it as like it could so
a couple of things have changed recently first of all based on some of my reading the roadblocks
of getting the wireless working the Broadcom wireless have been significantly reduced but
the big change which is in the more recent kernels been around for a little while now
but if you depends on your distro there is built-in kernel level support with the synaptics
driver for the MacBook touchpad or trackpad or whatever you want to call it and that was
something that used to be a sticking point on my particular model have you had to do
anything to get the trackpad working or has it been working no it's just been working
I mean it's not quite as nice as the default one but I've got scrolling I've been impressed
the media keys have working even in live media what about the I can see the high dpc I support
gnome working nicely really you can see the tiny text on the console boot up and then
yeah once you've got to the login screen really did gnome just automatically go high
dpi mode yeah no way really yeah at least in the integration now what about the keyboard
backlight that's a great question is that working can you turn that on oh yeah and it
even has the like scrollable menu shut up really yeah wow that's actually pretty look
at gnome like kicking ass on that thing yeah so are you in the ins are you in the live
media right now are you in the installed meet ls well now I'm in the installed OS actually
I have to review how how it actually got here I was just kind of troubleshooting that but
I rebooted again and I expected it to go into Mac OS X but it went right into yours so this
is really going to be nice to be able to play no man's sky at home if you get this working
with pretty excited I did a after tech talk yesterday I did a let's play with I guess
that's what I would I guess that's what the kids call it I did a let's play with my son
Dylan who is a huge minecrafter and there's definitely minecraft elements in no man's
sky and so it was a lot of fun you know he's seven years old so he gets to experience some
of the stuff like kid does it's a lot of fun to experience it through a kid's eyes and
I think I'm going to post the let's play if you guys want to see it for the patrons at
patreon.com slash today yeah so before we get out of here anybody else have thoughts
about the Mac books or actually I know mr. to know they're in the mumble room wanted
to also say give a little bit of love towards the Zen books are you still in there I think
you had to know I think you laugh but he wanted to say if you're looking at Mac books you
should consider the Zen books I think I probably summarized what he was going to say he had
particular models in mind but okay he would say check out the Zen books so do you want
to continue on and we'll and then we'll just wrap up the show then we can cover in the
post-show how that sounds great okay all right so that brings 158 to a close Ryan thanks
a bunch for coming and man you are welcome to join us any week you have time is we're
always live at this time so it was good to hear from you and I definitely look forward
to what you're doing in the future where should people follow you if they want to kind of
stay tuned sure yeah they can follow me on Twitter at Ryan Lee Sipes R-Y-A-N-L-E-E-S-I-P-E-S
and thanks for having me on Chris I love it you bet man and why don't you link that in
the IRC so that way I can easily throw it in the show notes too so that way people can
lazy web that and sure they don't have to worry about spelling all right that brings
us to the end of this week's unplugged I tell you what Wes I'm damn impressed I think you
have so far essentially completed every damn ridiculous challenge I've thrown at you during
the show almost anyway coming close well I mean this is pretty much in there I think
the dedicated graphics is within your reach man hopefully I am okay all right if you'd
like to show up live it's a lot of fun join us over at jblive.tv go to Jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar to get converted to your local time zone don't forget to follow me at Chris
LS and at Jupiter signal for the network LinuxActionShow.reddit.com is where you go for feedback and we'll
see you right back here next Tuesday.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
All right JBtitles.com thank you everybody it was a fun show I really enjoyed that and
also sincerely happy birthday to Debian I really appreciate Debian I mean it's not only
has it been the basis of some of my most enjoyed and used OS's and continues to be the basis
for my favorite server platform Ubuntu but also I think it really was a big part of why
I got into Linux so thank you thank you Ubuntu thank you mumble room thank you chat room
now let's go boat all right so where you at with that thing I've got it booting I'm making
sure the bootloader is actually working and getting the Wi-Fi back up nice all right let's
see about that proprietary drivers JBtitles JBtitles so this is this is a MacBook with
an Nvidia chip in it yes yeah I think it's a 750 I think or a 760 and is this a new
computer or one no no it's a it's a it's one that I used back in like before I think even
before I hired Rekai for editing and then once Rekai came on board he had 50m ok 750m
he got the dedicated Mac and then this sort of became like every time I wanted to do a
comprehensive video editing project this is my machine I would go to and still do to some
degree but I've been transitioning to KDN live more and more so I've had this sitting
around and it's a late 2013 model that I and I actually think with an old Mac book you
have a better success rate with a slightly older model which is kind of bears out why
I think you'll probably see more of these showing up on eBay when the new model comes
out because it's literally been too long and so they'll probably people throw their old
models on eBay and you might have Linux users who want a particular build a quality of a
machine grabbing these and snapping these up perhaps so this is a pro 15 or some description
is it yes yeah it's a it's a late 2013 MacBook retina 15 inch with the 750m and the 1 terabyte
SSD PCI SSD and 16 gigabytes of RAM and West did you decide on a bootloader well right
yeah right now it's just using the built-in EFI so like when you hold down the option
key or whatever it is the that's what I'm working on confirming interesting but we might
just install refined yeah look at you look at you it would be interesting to compare
battery life between the systems no TLP installed and awesome that would really interest me
yeah I absolutely think this is not well optimized for the well I to be fair the cards are definitely
stacked against Linux however I was reading the arch wiki and it appears that LM sensors
now has some support but see I honestly the core issue I've never really been super compelled
to do this is the way Max are built they are Intel machines absolutely but they use a completely
different power management and cooling management architecture than a standard desktop PC and
honestly if I were Apple I would too because a CPI and all of that is just total shit so
what Apple did is they created the SMC controller and the absence SMC controller is both hardware
and software and the software component is only available in Mac OS 10 and there's no
open source equivalent to it because Apple holds all of the information and the SMC controller
is used by Mac OS 10 to escalate the fans with CPU usage so the OS is constantly monitoring
the demands and predicted demands the predicted demands if you can if you can even believe
that of the OS workload based on your average workload and it preemptively throttles the
thermal management of the Mac based on whatever metrics that Apple can has come up with with
their black magic and there's just literally no way to translate that to Linux or Windows
it's the same problem for boot camp users who decide to run Windows 7 to 10 on their
Mac hardware they have the same exact issue and in the past what I had done is I got a
program called SMC control and SMC control is a Mac OS program what you do is you can
use SMC control to hard set your fans to a certain RPM so that way at least there's
some thermal cooling because otherwise what happens is without the SMC controller kicking
in via software ignition then the thermal limits of the actual hardware are what did
take the fan usage.
Yeah that's what you want.
No so when you actually get to the full thermal limits of the Intel i7 processor that's when
the fans cool when you get to the thermal limits of the GPU that's when the fans kick
on so by using SMC controller in Mac OS 10 I could set the fans at a steady like 5500
RPM or 4000 RPM depending on my workload and then restart in the Linux.
If you shut down then the SMC controller reset and so if I booted from a cold boot right
into Linux I have no fan control but if I would first boot into Mac OS and then use
SMC control which is a third-party utility that only supports most Macs and then use
that to set the fan and then reboot from that into Linux I could have proper thermal management.
So one of the things that appears to have changed since I had to do that rigmarole was
LM sensors appears to have some capacity to control the thermals on the MacBook now and
so that could make a significant difference in battery life and it's absolutely an area
I'm gonna test versus Mac OS whatever the current release is.
So I was just looking on eBay in the UK at that spec and they still sell used for around
£1,200 which is about $1,500.
Isn't it amazing?
See I think Apple has always managed to have super good resale because they only at best
release a model a year it seems.
So you just if it's on it's sort of it's sort of like there's by their by their apparent
nonchalant attitude towards their hard Mac hardware customers they have created a very
robust aftermarket value for the MacBook but a but every time a new one comes out everything
shifts down a bracket.
So that I believe this MacBook will probably shift down to about $800 once the new MacBook
comes out in September and this a Core i7.
Is that still a current model even though it's been around for a few years?
No no no no but because but the current model will shift down a price range and because
this is a model or two below the current model it'll this is going to come down significantly
to about $800.
That's my estimation.
I could be totally wrong but that seems to be the history is because this is like two
models or three models behind this is going to be the this is going to be the real bottom
basement like still get an i7 still get Thunderbolt still get Retina still get PCIe storage but
under $1,000 easily will be this I believe that'll be the price of this machine and
at that price range it almost becomes reasonable to experiment with Linux on it and just see
well what the hell because I you know I it's a it's a six to eight hundred dollar MacBook
depending on spec and at well at the end of the day if it doesn't work I could just do
Mac OS 10 with Linux and VMware and so I think you're gonna have a lot of Linux users that
will pick this thing up because they the cult of hardware worship around the MacBook they'll
pick this thing up they'll try putting Linux on it and so I was like this is probably something
that I'm gonna get a whole new wave of emails about.
I'm kind of preemptively getting that yeah.
And you're only excited about Linux on Mac because the hardware is decent.
Well mostly what it's come down to is I want to start doing more remote broadcasts and
I need a pretty powerful system to run OBS because what I need to do is I need to bring
in I need to bring in a couple of RTMP streams I need to send out an RTMP stream and I need
to record so I'm probably gonna look at and so something that's for cores is probably
going to be necessary soon for me on the go and the problem is is OBS is available for
Mac OS 10 and if I'm not careful because of simple practical demand and need of production
I might accidentally use OBS on Mac OS I have to be careful it's like it's like somebody
who's an alcoholic I don't want to be around people that are I gotta I gotta make sure
that if we have Linux on this thing I just continue to use Linux so it's sort of preemptively
preparing for that it's also because I now want a Linux machine at home that has a dedicated
graphics card and that's kind of the big driver for me personally is all my Linux machines
at home are Intel graphics and that's been fine but now that I want to play No Man's
Sky at home it it's since I already have the hardware it's not like I'm buying the hardware
if I if this was me buying it I would never do it but because I already have the hardware
it seems like it's worth trying yeah definitely right and Linux does seem to run pretty damn
fast on it like it's it's it's a it's interesting you know Apple's gotten a really bad rap for
how long it's been since they've updated the Mac books and I've been one of the people
giving a hard time but this is the 2013 it still feels pretty damn fast it's once you
go SSDs and core i7 and all that it's a lot of but then it comes down to if you need things
like quicksync or other or or you know would be nice as a is a is a nicer graphics card
like a 980 or something yeah that would be nice yeah or even a 1080 yeah a 980 I'm in
my new intro where oh oh yeah how is the best you have the Athena don't you how has that
been going for you you it's epic yeah yeah honestly wimpy if I had the money if that
that would be my preferred route to go hands down absolutely see I feel like I can get
in with I can get within a stone's throw distance of something like the Athena with the MacBook
that I already own but I would yeah so are you running are you running a like a like
a like a like a multiple boot environment on this thing or is it just one distro I are
you game tell me all about it oh you can probably guess the name um I would I bet I bet I could
yeah yeah no it's just one destroyed yeah where's it's got it that's it yeah yeah no
it's um one distro so one one uh root disk which is an NVMe uh drive nice and then I
have uh two one terabyte um SSDs in there one is mounted as my home partition so just
for me and the other is mounted under a separate profile that I have just for Steam so when
I download the Steam games it goes to a separate disk and what that enables me to do is if
I want to re you know play on the desktop or something like that I can just rsync that
partition to the home directory of the Steam profile everywhere else so I don't have to
keep down because I'm on you know wireless internet that's a problem I have at home too
that's a great idea yeah so you don't have to do it with a separate disk you just have
a separate profile that you just use for Steam and then you know you can just rsync that
to your Steam profile Steam accounts you know on your other machines sorry do you log out
when you want it when you want to game do you log out yeah yeah when I'm when I want to game
I have a separate profile because I don't have any you know file sync services I have
a very minimal desktop configuration I have the Compton manager going rather than com
peers or something like that so it's it's specifically I am going to play a game right
now have you have you told with the idea I know you've probably seen there's tutorials
to have like a separate big picture mode instance of x running or you can have login you can
have user sessions that are only Steam big picture have you toyed with that idea yeah
if I ever make a box to like go in the front room then I would do something like that but
this is just on my machines I finished working I'm gonna play a game for half an hour log
out log into Steam and it auto starts you know the Steam client it doesn't go to big
picture automatically because you don't always want that but that's how I do it and it works
very well for me and it prevents me having to keep downloading gigabytes and gigabytes
of stuff over and over and over again is clever I think I might try that I also heard in the
Ubuntu podcast you're talking about it coming pretty handy at the snap sprint event yeah
yeah so I lugged it along so I took my Apollo and the Athena with me to the snappy sprint
event two very different laptops two very different laptops and the reason why is because
the power supply or rather the internal battery on the Athena is really a UPS that lasts long
enough for you to unplug the power in one location and walk to it's probably what two
hours two and a half hours yeah it's about yeah it's about two hours yeah so it's not
that but you know when you compare it to the Apollo yes I I can comfortably get you know
over seven hours I describe the Apollo battery life as I it's one of those laptops where
I open up the I open up the laptop and I don't even consider when was the last time I had
this on the power adapter that is such a feeling it's so nice yeah it makes it the perfect
go-to really quick at home laptop yeah and the new the new Apollo you can now get with
16 gigs of RAM as well which is quite tasty yeah yeah so yeah I was using the Athena for
building snaps because you can now build use snapcraft to build your snaps in Lexd containers
so you can have multiple snaps building at the same time so consequently I was working
on a snap start that building switch to a different workspace work on a different snap
start that building and at one point I had seven or eight snaps building because that's
great just had loads of loads of disk performance it's got 64 gigs of RAM it can do eight threads
it was just belting through that would be the perfect that's the perfect OBS remote
rig for me so down the road that might be where I go actually why while I'm picking
your brain so I've been looking at pod publish and I have a secret project in the works that
I think I want to use pod publish for and I wondered how hard do you think I'm thinking
about enlisting somebody in the community to make some changes and I wanted to bounce
it off you one of the things I would like to do is because I believe the pod publish
if I understand correctly one of the one of the files that it'll output is a like we've
talked about before is an MKV ready for YouTube that takes the audio track and then takes
a still image for that episode and repeats that still image that matches the length of
the audio track right yeah that's right what kind of changes do you think it they could
be major I don't know do you think it would take to make it possible to have it loop like
an mp4 what do you mean by loop an mp4 have a video that is just repeated through the
length of the thing yeah I imagine that'd be quite straightforward yeah that should
be quite straightforward I love the idea of pod publish and it seems like should I tell
you the thing I wanted to do yeah using ffmpeg there is a I'm not sure if they're called
filters but there is a way to generate animations based on audio waveforms wanted to be yes
was actually just have it you know a spectrograph you know waveform of the audio for the duration
of the I have been trying to solve this problem since I launched I mean I mean Rick I might
know we have tried we have tried video editing plugins that will try with it try to generate
this I have spent I have spent good money trying to solve this problem well I found
like half a dozen snippets of how to do this with ffmpeg and I couldn't achieve the exact
result I wanted to achieve but I did find some reference stuff so if there's somebody
out there who wants to have a go at solving that that would be kind of neat because what
you could do is have that overlaid on your still image you have your still image your
cover art yeah it superimposes all of the text for the you know the the episode and
title and all the rest of it and then you could have that you know spectrum going that
is so that is so badly what I want that I so badly wanted that I've given up on it and
I just I just I just assumed I'd have to I'd have to compromise with a mp4 loop because
that is the thing is is I YouTube is a viable publishing platform for a couple of reasons
first of all it works for a lot of people to get around certain restrictions it's also
has a huge built-in user base existing it's great for discovery just ask the chat room
a lot of them are in there because they found us on YouTube once and then decided to become
podcast listeners and then last but not least it may it is it is YouTube links are fundamentally
just more shareable than an mp3 file with a certain time index in the mp3 file and so
if you ever want to have your podcast shared with somebody else it kind of has to be up
on YouTube so people can pass the link around but I don't want them just I don't want to
publish something on YouTube and have people stare at a still image right yeah yeah I agree
so I would like to do the the audio is there's there could be several podcasts now that end
up using pod published from a snap and then if we make improvements to it like that it
could be some podcasts to get that I supply publish for those that don't know is is we've
talked about it just recently and I think last week show so check that out but it's
a tool that is currently installable as a snap so I have it installed on arch actually
a surprise surprise and you run it through there you give it you give it your podcast
that you've done and it can output the files you need for people to download but also can
create the WordPress post and what nots like that and has a I and I file where you specify
the different parameters and it then it it makes it very automated and for somebody who's
very busy but has a couple of really fun podcast ideas up his sleeve it makes it feel more
approachable you know a lot of that's just taken care of for you yeah so I'm really excited
so I've got a fix coming to pod published in next couple of specifically the snap of
pod publishing in the next couple of days I've had some feedback from running snaps
on different distros where there's an issue with locales and it can get its pants in a
twist so I've got a fix coming that will make that so after I install it from a snap it
doesn't show up in my path does it until I log out and log back in is that is that is
that how it does it should show it should show up what's the command I run then because
when I ran this is a implementation detail about snap yeah so if you have a snap for
say ffmpeg and there's only one binary that you're exposing from that snap called ffmpeg
it goes half under slash snap lash bin ffmpeg pod publish has four executables in the snap
so consequently the namespace for the binary is pod published dot and then the name of
the original executable so in your path you should have pod published dot publish underscore
podcast for example and pod published dot encode underscore podcast and there's a couple
of others specific to upload oh one one was specific to when I uploaded everything to
youtube for everything even to podcast had done which got us banned so that was the don't
use that because you can ban yourself you uploaded you know 250 break your account script
yeah yeah and there's another one that I forget what it does but the main to encode encode
and then publish so with snaps it's pod published dot encode underscore podcast okay and then
just path to config file and in your config file you tell it where all of the paths to
your assets are and stuff I'll send you a snippet of I'll redact some bits of the Ubuntu
podcast okay any file because what we do is like nine tenths of the config file is just
boilerplate yeah and we just have like six or seven things at the top of the file which
are the episode number and the markdown for that episode I love it links and then it automatically
drops all of those necessary markers into the rest of the configuration for you so you
don't have to do a full you know edit of a clean file every time you can start you know
with a template and just change the few things at the top and it makes you know turning the
publishing round very fast what I like recorded this evening Laura's already updated are any
files for our show notes so they're ready to go Mark's doing the edit this week which
he'll do tomorrow so we turn around the publishing very quickly now yeah wow well done and does
he edit an audacity because that's what I would that's what I'm I guess yeah we both
do yeah so on the Ubuntu podcast org website there's a page called about the show and most
of that page is actually how we produce the show and all the software we use including
the server stack and everything I encourage you to continue on pushing pod publish forward
because it's I haven't really been super interested in automating audio pub podcast
publishing for a long time and so I haven't really paid attention to it and Noah and I
and Rekai and West even get helped in a little bit recently have been really working on what
we are trying to create a way to bring video podcasting up to an entirely new level using
Linux and open source and we don't it's not an automated system but it will be a technology
stack that you use to create essentially super high quality I I think better than than anything
I've ever seen before video produced podcasts even with remote hosts and whatnot and so
I I like that you're sort of contributing at the audio end there which is still super
obviously relevant and something I'm just kind of getting back into and at the same
time we're kind of working on creating sort of a stack that people could deploy to also
make podcasting video wise under Linux super straightforward really high quality so at
both ends of both audio and video we're sort of working on automating and creating
the best product under Linux and I think that's going to be really cool for media content
producers who want to look at Linux and we may one day have these tools available to
them that give it a edge up over some of the other desktops and we'll make them lead
to proprietary OS's just to publish yeah because really if you can make it easy for
people to produce their content they'll go with whatever and if we can say this is
what you use on Linux to make your audio podcast or your video podcasting it you can make really
nice reproducible episodes it automates the process for you it follows these standard
conventions and this is this is I think something that the Mac has sort of gotten the default
nod to for a long time and maybe maybe maybe we'll make a little bit of a difference
you know what didn't make it into my Nvidia shield TV review because it didn't even
cross my mind to try this until I was just in my Google dashboard recently and I was
you know in Google dashboard you can go back and you can play back all of your dictation
so whenever you dictate to the keyboard you it'll Google actually keeps a recording of
that and you can play it back and it's kind of interesting because I play it back sometimes
and I hear my kids in the background and stuff like that it's like it's almost like a little
time capsule up on Google a creepy little time capsule and so I decided to play back
some of the recordings from the Nvidia shield TV and the audio is super super bad oh really
and I didn't you know I didn't think that I didn't think about this in the review because
it just didn't seem like something to eat it's not something you've had to think about
before how good is the microphone so that way you can do voice dictation because that's
a key way you interact with the Nvidia shield TV like all YouTube searches it kind of says
you know just hold this button down and talk to it and then it'll search and one of the
things I discovered and the reason why I realized there might be something going on is I noticed
that it started detecting Hadia's speech but not my so weird so I would give it to her
she could search for things but I couldn't search for things hon will you search for
me again it'll get old it is it is it is very embarrassing actually because it's like I
sit there and I'll try like three or four times and I start saying it very I try to
enunciate very clearly and then I have to give it to her and she's just says at once
and then it's fine so you don't even exist I was a certain pitch let's see that was about
I'm trying to figure out it doesn't tell me it doesn't really break it down by device
which devices I was doing that's funny looking at some of the things I've said is kind of
funny but what I discovered what I discovered is that the audio is really really scratchy
from the Nvidia shield remote it just has a really crappy crappy that is unfortunate
yeah it's interesting for Google to have like you know an evaluation of just like evaluating
these as they come in and giving you like yeah these device has a nice little break
colored meter or something yeah yeah exactly exactly I was trying to see if I could find
an example for you this might be it yeah Android TV so let's see this is me saying starbound
oh that's a dia having to say starbound because it wouldn't work for me she says it so well
yeah well as he came you could hear it wasn't very good but let's see sage brown it does
sound like sage brown doesn't it round and here it says it got total chaos see how you
can't you can't understand me you can't understand what I'm saying at all if the microphone is
just horrible and there you got THR roundtable and there because I think you hear it cut
out right there yeah yeah it's just so I and then here's me yeah I got that one clearly
okay Google yeah and that one's from my phone you hear much better that one is so that's
one thing I don't it's a it's a weird thing to amend to a review but I just kind of figured
out recently and either really it really depends on where you where you hold it too yeah and
okay yeah I was and I guess I also just revealed that I'm watching YouTube videos about starbound
I didn't I didn't mean for that all right I'm excited to announce that Wes is in the
market for a new switch that's right everyone I do networking switch at home and frames
they need to go places it's important that they get there quickly what do you what is
in your requirement list for a new switch quiet how important is quiet not that important
it's going in the closet look at you with the dedicated networking closet I mean it's
also there's a lot of other things in that closet but I mean there's gonna be a switch
in there by dedicated I mean the closet that's right so managed yes I would like a managed
V lands and all that shenanigans I don't I don't have like a huge need of a crazy number
of ports but I would like it is your base base amount of ports probably 16 but I could
get away with eight if it was a nice and and we're talking 100 megabits good absolutely
not because I need gigabit my upstream is gigabit I need gigabit internally oh yeah
you do so yeah you do that's really why I'm doing it it's like before everything I had
your firewall has gigabit networking on it not my current edge device but I'm gonna replace
that with a tower I have set up I just got a new Intel dual port Nick that I put in which
I have not set up yet but just sitting there I can see it in LS PCI but I feel like this
is it we might have an episode topic in the making because you're gonna do what straight
up Linux right mm-hmm that's the intention I'm gonna try seeing out seeing how if I can
just do that and how it work Wow so maybe I'll regret it maybe I'll convert it to a
PF sense box I could always spin that up if you remind me before you go I have a I have
a switch you could take a look at that you might want to consider it's a silent gigabit
switch of course you don't care about noise too much but boy have I learned my lesson
on that one and it's worked really well here in the studio for us oh that's good yeah I
will have to look at that it's fanless too which is super nice yeah actually that might
be what it is the anime the neck year GS 724 that might be exactly it in fact if somebody
would find that on Amazon and ping Angela with it that's she needs that too so also
I love the HP switches so shout out to Sonic 7-eleven in the chat room for mentioning the
HP 1910 16g I some of the best switches in my there was a moment in my IT career where
before HP switches and then there was a moment after HP switches and I'm being dead serious
like it it was a game changer for me professionally because I constantly was battling with clients
on the cost of switches they always wanted to lowball that particular component and HP
switches came along and offered a super competitive product like competitive with Cisco high-end
products for a much more reasonable price so what might be an $8,000 switch from Cisco
was a $3,000 switch from HP and now and that price scale has reduced even further now it's
it they make a good product so definitely love the HP's if you're if you're really looking
I mean so just as an example right I think Angela has like an eight-year-old HP gigabit
switch 24 port fully managed it's been running non-stop for all damn near as long as I can
think of I mean no can't it's it's got to be yeah eight years old and damn near eight
years old West and it's got to be one of the best switches to this day that I've ever owned
it's a really good one so big plug for HP switches but also I'll have to introduce you
to my switch that I have in the garage