Alexa, spell Linux.
Linux is spelled L-I-N-U-X.
That's not bad.
I'm not sure I could do that.
This is Linux Amplug episode 178 for January 3rd, 2017.
Welcome to It's Unplugged.
That's pretty close.
Your weekly Linux talk show that's celebrating the New Year's with robots.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
I think I could do a better job than the Echo there.
What do you think?
You have had more practice than she has though, so in fairness.
Hello everybody and welcome back and happy 2017.
This is really Linux Unplugged.
No, I'm not even sure what she said.
I don't even know if she...
Nope.
No idea.
But if you haven't guessed, later on in the show we'll be talking about securing the internet
of things and how open source might be able to solve this particular problem and take
something that's typically cloud-based and make it all local.
What?
Yeah.
That's later on in the show.
We'll be getting our 2017 predictions from our virtual lug, getting all prepped and ready
for this Sunday's Linux action show, the official predictions episode.
It's a big moment, Wes.
That's a huge moment.
This last week we put it off to review Solace.
I saw that.
Yeah, it's just like we had to go that way.
But I got a couple emails and I can't remember if it was a tweet or a telegram.
Somebody said, I really missed the predictions episode.
Now the anticipation is building.
And then the other guys, I got an email that said, I had a bet going on your predictions.
And then you didn't do it.
So we're going to get a little bit of that taken care of today.
Not all of them.
What's your appetite?
Yeah, we've got to make room for some great open source project updates.
I don't know.
Maybe some of these open source developers got a little time off for the holidays and
they banged out some code.
Come back fresh at it.
I know that's how I am.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So check it out, guys, because in a little bit we're going to have some great stories.
And what I think could be a great trend for 2017.
But first, let's bring in our virtual hug for the first time this year.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings.
Happy New Year.
Hello, everybody.
Hello.
It is good to see you.
And I want to start out, I want to start Jesus.
There's no way half this beer that you brought us could be hitting me that fast.
But I guess by the way, Mr. Mr. West over there really, really outdid himself this week.
He brought an Odin's gift.
It's a gift for you.
Which come on, how can you I can't ask for a better gift than Odin's gift.
And it's an amber ale brewed with juniper berries, which is sounds a lot like Jupiter
berries.
It sure does.
Yeah.
So you really you're just pushing all the buttons.
Is it local to us?
Is it is it a local brew?
Tequila, Washington.
Do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do.
Well done, sir.
Well done.
That is my pleasure.
So I've I've been talking about this since the beginning of last year.
Feels a little weird to say.
And I think I think, gosh, I just I don't mean to say I told you so.
But I think maybe I told you so I think you did.
There are more and more people these days that are looking for an alternative to Mac
OS, a special group of people.
I'm not going to sit here and pretend like it's millions of users not going to pretend
like Apple is going to fall apart because of how your average designer or art person
or whatever.
But there are there are those like the fellow over a bit cannon bit cannon dotnet wrote up
an awesome post.
And here's why I say it's awesome, because it's it feels like it's from the perspective
of an analytical engineer or somebody who's laying it all out there.
And it really breaks down the process from from the perspective of not not the Apple
user that we we Linux users like to portray that the hipster with the tight jeans and
and it's a concern about the image and the.
This is this is someone who is smart and rational like yourself that.
Chose a different path and is now using that same intellect that shows that path to evaluate
other paths.
And so he's right.
I've used Mac OS since the public beta.
I use it both at home and work.
I've also run various Linux distributions and BSD since around 2000.
So he's got some familiarity working with here, mostly using Ruby and has had some experience
with a PC that he built on the side.
It's got an Intel like I seven run at four gigahertz with lots of RAM and SSD and he
put arch on that.
But he mostly just SSH is into that from the Mac box to do Ruby development.
And it's way faster than the Mac box.
But recently he said there's been more and more appealing to a more and more appeal to
switching from, you know, switching away from the Mac.
He says, I spent a fair bit of time pondering the appeal of the switch.
These are some of the benefits as I see them access to a regularly updated pro hardware.
I'll give that a day.
Not restricted to Apple hardware that makes choices that I don't value, such as removing
the escape key, removing all legacy ports, the set, the set, the set, necessitating cheese,
the use of dongles for everything, though that may be our future regardless, I wonder
and prioritizing thinness and weight over everything else.
Also access to hardware that Apple doesn't make such as two in one laptops, getting comfortable
with alternatives before I'm forced to the ability to inspect and contribute to the OS
I use.
Oh, and using OS where developers are first class citizens.
Oh, also see stagnation of the Mac App Store.
Drawbacks of switching time required to find replacements of the software I use like Alfred
one pass and sketch the lack of access to the iOS SDK because he does maintain an app
in the iOS store.
Yeah, that's rough.
Yeah.
He evaluated a bunch of different alternatives from Anna Gross and arch and bida and elementary
really quite a good list.
Yeah.
This is on there.
I see honorary mentions give deep in and haiku and redox.
Here's kind of what he was looking for integrated consistent experience, good design, and simple
easy to use high dpi support, which is underscored and timely updates.
Top pick is fedora.
Actually really top pick he says all three top picks were known based fedora, arch straight
and elementary, which is not actually known three, which is his favorite right now says
elementary is what he's going with human interface guidelines, which are a plus in his opinion,
native programming language, or at least a primary focus, Vala, not Python.
And that's it.
That's what he says.
A model for funding ongoing development bug bounties, Patreon asking for payment with downloading.
That's an interesting thing.
I could see why that would absolutely from the professional developer angle, someone
who's used to you know, maybe he had paid for OS X updates back when that was the thing
could be a and you know, and there are a lot of like, if you have an app, especially
in that OS X ecosystem, a lot of really good apps you pay for, but you you know, you value
them.
Yeah, I just thinking about it, it really does matter to me that the Destro I'm using
maybe has a full time developer to on if I'm using a full on curated distro.
Let's get Ikey funded so we can do this full time is he doesn't think he does it full time.
That's a really good question.
Also designers as well as developers are on the team that he likes that they have a design
angle and then he just sort of wraps it up.
My ideal would be elementary on top of free BSD only your ideal man.
He says next I plan to resize the arch partition on my work PC and install elementary alongside
I'll aim to do all of my work duties on that machine and post how it goes.
So I have a link in his in the show notes if you want to follow the blog as he goes
along.
Now I reason I want to talk about this because we could we could sit here and we could talk
about Michael Dominic from Coder Radio or Leo Laporte or or or Bit Cannon.
I mean there's so many there's those are so many example.
Those are three examples of so many what I believe represent so many other people they're
doing the same evaluation and I'm not doing this to harp on the MacBook.
I don't really give a crap about that anymore.
It just I think it's I think this I think this I think there is a new reality and that
new reality is there is a there is an area of the market that Apple's decided it is no
longer worth their investment to target based on the overall importance of the Mac to the
Apple overall profitable ecosystem.
And those people that are realizing that are looking for something else and they don't
want to go to Windows.
They really don't at Windows 10.
The thing is is this is hitting I believe this is hitting when the Windows 10 hype train
is stopped right.
People at this point feel like it's a fine version of Windows.
Maybe it's one of the better ones.
But there are probably still a lot of Mac users especially who aren't ready to go back.
You know they left they probably left or they've been using it a long enough time.
Well here's the thing about Windows 10.
All the things used that drove you crazy about Windows still exist.
The crazy nightmare of downloading setup.exe to install your drivers.
The crazy high DPI support that is totally non-existent.
The mishmash of interfaces the 10 different ways to set your power management settings.
All of these the integration of market trend of the year when they release the OS.
That is so obnoxious.
Like the Cortana features.
Give me a break.
Well and I think there's a difference like the Windows can produce these sorts of Windows
power users.
I think we've talked a lot about switching to Linux in the past.
And they're the kind of people that know that right.
Like they understand that there's going to be three different menus to configure things.
They know how to go deep.
They know how to do the regedit.
That doesn't really exist in OSX to the same degree.
Whereas these people are looking at OSX as like a this was their functional computer.
I think it's interesting because I think I think a class of these people are probably
on MacBooks and using Mac OS because their taste which they would probably classify as
discerning would right would sort of compel them to go that direction.
There's not a lot except for some of the more popular newer distributions I think that might
that meet the level of quote unquote discerning tastes of a Mac user.
And I'm not trying to be combative but I think it conveys the image like there is a certain
standard they're going for in terms of quality and consistency and elementary OS is sort
of unique.
Solus is also pretty great in that way.
And Gnome 3 desktop in general is the best generally available desktop that I think I
honestly believe out of the box is the most consistent.
And there's something about that like I mean obviously we've talked a lot about Plasma
5 and how great it is but there's something about the simplicity of Gnome that matches
more with also bear in mind too that he's specifically requiring high DPI which sort
of focuses.
Plasma is good.
It's great actually.
Plasma is still slightly inconsistent high DPI compared to them three.
And that's really no three ballpark right now.
Yeah.
The GTK three GTK three.
So I think it's sort of a fascinating trend that is going to increase in 2017 and it's
why I just wanted to cover it at the top here because this is sort of what this episode
is about is these types of things.
Mr. Jude you have a point.
Yeah.
A lot of the people that I know that use Mac books it was not so much about the window
manager and stuff but the apps.
The apps and the fact that it has a shell right.
I need my email that's going to be reliable and I want my browser it's always going to
work.
Yeah.
You know both Chromium and Firefox under open source operating systems are some time
a bit not perfect whereas well especially previous versions of Mac OS you could rely
on the OS not to crash and your apps to work.
That's actually not as true anymore.
It's not just the hardware that Apple is falling down on but the fact that NFS and the latest
version of OS 10 will crash if you try to connect to things.
Right.
And you know to that point.
And also just people having troubles with even just the web browser and email not working
properly.
To that point there was a release of Mac OS where I can't remember what the reason was.
I think it was a licensing issue.
They just ripped out Samba and implemented their own.
Oh right.
That was pretty recently.
Yeah.
Their own SMB client and it just is absolute shit.
It's shit.
It's bad bad bad.
And it's gotten better now in previous in excessive releases because that's releases
but it's just was awful back then and it was just an example of something that just didn't
really care for pro users.
They wouldn't.
And it's another where you know maybe you have these skills you've used SIFs on other
servers and now maybe the Mac implementation is different for perhaps no good reason.
I think too and Alan I wonder if you agree do you think that some of it has to do with
just more people shifting workload into the web browser or do you think it's still more
about the native apps.
I think it's a little bit less about native apps now but I think what we need to look
at from this is actually getting back the idea of the reason any development happens
in open source is developers scratching their own itch.
So this might be the golden opportunity to get more developers back to using Linux or
BSD and refining that desktop experience to make it good enough for them whereas before
it was not quite good enough to drive them to get to go with the Mac instead.
Yeah sort of critical mass thing.
Before I go any further I should mention Alan reminded me I should plug it right now that
you can join Alan and I for our last TechSnap episode 300 this Thursday at one o'clock
JB time jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar and then the show goes on with Mr. West and
Dan.
So yeah I should mention that since Alan's here if you're listening you can join us for
that.
And thanks for joining us Alan.
Yeah Alan it's good to see you.
I just got back from the dentist and had nothing better to do.
So hang out with those Linux guys.
That's our audience folks.
Got it Alan.
I love it.
Well you just also happen to be talking about a topic that's been of interest to me lately
because I've seen a bunch of people I've known as hardcore Mac users for you know five or
ten years more being like well they took away my escape key so I bought a Lenovo.
Yeah right.
Yeah we just had somebody in the chat room that just said that basically.
In fact he said, who was it, I just yeah DeBill are you in the Mumba room DeBill?
No I don't see him in the Mumba room.
DeBill said that he replaced his Macbook at work for a three year old Lenovo with Linux
because he got tired of it crashing and all those kind of shit.
And I think that's the main reason so many Linux and BSD developers went with a Mac is
because they were having these consistency and polish problems on the open source OS
and a lot of that has gotten better although a lot of it is not.
The thing that we haven't really caught up on is the lightness of the hardware although
like the X1 carbon from Lenovo is nice and light and is getting there but you know reliable
suspend resume and battery life.
The Mac has always been way ahead there but maybe this will be the push to actually make
people spend time on making that happen.
Yeah exactly.
Yeah and I noticed I think specifically Solus and maybe elementary OS too have done something
to make standby really fast and reliable on those distros because like it's with those
distros my benchmark is is this is the password prompt on my screen by the time I finished
lifting the lid.
There you go.
Yeah.
And those meet that benchmark and that's as fast as I could possibly ask for.
But then there's other desktops where it does.
So what line before.
OK so West has closed his laptop.
What log in manager are you using on that you know GDM.
OK.
All right.
So I think that seems to make a difference.
Fire it up.
All right.
Not quite about a half second after after the screen was up which is usable.
It was usable but it's not as fast as a MacBook.
Which is cool.
Yeah.
You have to see what the Mac is cheating by not doing things like erasing the full disk
encryption password program.
Right.
We covered that in last week's tech snap.
It turns out that it's just sitting there in plain text in the RAM just hanging out
just chilling the password.
And if you plug into Thunderbolt you can DMA and yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah just so
just wait.
So plug into the Thunderbolt port lift the Mac lid grab the RAM contents.
There's the password.
You don't have to.
You don't have to crack nothing.
That's this.
And there's little devices you know.
You just the Thunderbolt stuff is going to be and USBC is that's what's going to be crazy
about them.
We should move on.
But with the MacBook specifically with those USBC ports being Thunderbolt in reality and
that's right there on the bus.
I wonder if that's going to become a security issue.
It's going to have to be a Solus is using LightDM.
Well damn.
I don't know.
I don't know what to tell you.
Although I don't know if LightDM is specifically specifically fast or slower.
I just have a lot of experience with GDM.
Getting a Solus just really quick since we just put out our review.
They have an update.
We reviewed them on Sunday and that afternoon they put out an update and just thought I'd
mention it really quick because it's sort of the distribution that I'm all excited about
at the moment because that's what I just installed on my machine.
I still have it sitting right here and I just checked and I got all the updates installed.
Nice.
Yeah.
So there's just a few general improvements including a bump to the Nvidia driver.
The new version of software center version 15 has gone out which includes updates and
new apps that I probably would have mentioned in our review if they were in there at the
time.
And I guess they now are – this is like the last version of the Budgie desktop that's
going out before they focus on Budgie 11 which is what a lot of the users are excited about.
Also I should mention the Mate edition has been updated and it's got the new Brisk menu
in it which we covered in like two weeks ago I think it was.
That's going to be exciting to watch.
It shipped.
The first version of the Brisk menu is – gosh that was fast.
That was really fast.
It feels like we were just like – it was just kind of a dream.
Yeah.
It was on the pipeline.
Now it's here.
Now we just start the clock to see how long it shows up in other distributions because
that thing is going to take off.
That's for sure.
Just as a quick comment like just looking at that little snapshot overview like you
said like they do snapshots pretty regularly but like there is a lot of stuff in there.
It's so clear how much is going on in this project.
I know.
I don't – I feel conflicted because I feel like I could take up a half hour covering
it actually to be honest with you but I don't feel like that probably would be the best
use of all of the audience this time but –
If you're interested go check it out.
Go try it.
But there is a lot.
There is a lot in there for just a quick update.
Yeah.
So the momentum – the momentum is high with this one.
Keep it up guys.
Also it looks like kernel 4.8.15 as well as 13.02 OpenGL.
I don't even – I didn't even – wow.
I don't follow OpenGL at all anymore.
I care – what I honestly was more curious and watch closer is the NVIDIA driver versions
because I do like to have the later versions of that.
So good job to the Solus project.
So Wes you and I were chatting about this before the show today.
This is kind of a nice thing for Nexus 5 phone owners.
Now the Google has stopped updating it right?
Didn't they stop updating it?
Yes they did.
No 7 for us.
And then I think this year the 6P and the 5X lose support.
They will.
They still get security updates though.
Oh.
The new hotness.
Okay.
Yep.
Boy that's pretty.
I mean they almost feel still new.
Yeah.
I guess security updates is not the end of the world.
No.
Yeah.
How long do they get the security updates for?
Do you know?
I want to say like a full year.
Okay.
So you get like two years probably from now if you have a 5X or a 6P.
That's reasonable.
Exactly.
I feel like the 6P should get another year of –
Yeah.
It does feel like it was – that was an expensive phone.
It was the last phone.
Yeah.
Nexus 6?
It's –
Yeah.
Do you not get update 7 and so on?
No it shouldn't be.
I have the 7 update pending.
I just have to press the button.
Do you not get 7.1?
I have no idea.
You might not get 7.1.
That would be –
Yeah.
That would be some real shit.
Put you on the –
Yeah.
But you don't get the thing where we ironed out the –
That's the worst.
I just don't know about that.
And of course so this is a real thing.
This is a real problem.
And this is where I think things like Lineage or Ubuntu Touch have some real promise.
The Nexus 5 is now fully working with Ubuntu Phone.
So if you've got a Nexus 5, you can go all in.
We've talked about Maurice's cool software that he created in the past that allows you
to flash these devices super easy.
So he's been working on it.
He's also got an unofficial port for the Fairphone 2, which is becoming fully working, which
is awesome.
Hey, cool.
The GPS still is not working, but otherwise it's fully working.
Wow.
Nexus 5, though.
All in.
It looks like it's working also on the 1 Plus 1 Ubuntu Touch port.
Still some stabilization improvements that need to happen there, though.
But wow.
In fact, the developer, Maurice, is using a Nexus 5 running Ubuntu Touch as his daily
driver.
He even connects it to HDMI and gets the convergent stuff.
Wow.
That's neat.
So it's full-on Nexus 5 with convergence, while Google's not even updating it anymore.
Nope.
That kind of makes me curious.
I have one kicking around still, so I'll definitely try it on there.
My mom's using a Nexus 5 still, and it makes me like, maybe I'm better off just flashing
it with Ubuntu.
She doesn't need a whole bunch of Android apps, so would that be a more secure, maintainable
thing?
I think it would.
It would be really interesting to see that type of user's perspective.
Also, if you check the show notes, you can get the link to the article, but you could
also just go to ubports.com and learn more, which interestingly enough is powered by a
DigitalOcean.
Oh, digitalocean.com is our first sponsor this week.
You know, DigitalOcean's awesome like that.
It's not just that open source project they're hooking up, Ubiports is one of them.
I think they also do support for elementary OS's back end.
They're watching elementary OS's back end, yeah, you bet they're not.
Oh yeah, you bet it.
You bet it.
You betta believe it.
They know the movers and shakers.
There's a few different distributions out there they're supplying infrastructure for,
and remember that time Wimpy was on the show working on his releasing a version of Ubuntu
Mate.
He was running on DigitalOcean service.
That's right.
There's a reason why everybody's picking this as their infrastructure.
It is so, so easy to get started, so quick to get started, and it's damn reliable.
And it's super fast.
Digitalocean.com.
Use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, one word, you apply it to your account, you get a ten
dollar credit.
Now what's great about DigitalOcean is this super simple interface.
It is like, if you were gonna ask for the best interface to manage virtual machines
and data centers all over the world that use KVM for the virtualizer, Linux for the backend,
and SSD for storage, and then you want to do like templates and snapshots and have an
API and multiple distributions including FreeBSD to choose from, you honestly would not come
up with a better idea.
In fact, it's the gold standard.
And you know, you've probably used some of those other cloud providers interfaces.
Oh, I'm sorry.
We have to configure like five or six things before you've even spun up a VM.
That is not how it works at DO.
Those are like designed in the 90s.
I swear.
Or they just scream enterprise throughout the whole thing.
I swear to Linus.
Those were created in the 90s.
This is modern stuff.
But what I think is truly awesome about DigitalOcean is I've been sitting here raving about that
UI.
I think that whole UI runs on their API.
That's why the API is so good.
It's super great.
They did it right.
And it also explains why it's simple and straightforward because they got to work with it themselves.
I don't want to paint the answer right now.
It's awesome.
They got 40 gigabit connections into the hypervisors.
They got data centers all over the world.
They have team accounts.
They have hourly pricing.
You can run fantastic rigs with two gigs of RAM, two core processor, 40 gigabyte SSD,
three terabytes of transfer for three cents an hour.
What?
Yeah, three cents an hour.
I know.
Develop locally and then deploy globally.
This is a really, really slick system because you could spin up a rig when you need it.
So you could be working in a Docker container.
You could be working in a VM.
You could be working in a jail for all I care.
I don't care what you're doing.
Maybe you're just running the directory in your opt folder.
I'm not going to judge because when you're ready, you publish it up to DigitalOcean.
You start testing on it.
You get a bunch of users banging on it.
It's so easy to manage the DNS, set up your SSH keys.
You're going to be doing it at a boss level.
DigitalOcean.com.
Be like Ubiports.com and become a DigitalOcean customer.
Just use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
the Unplugged program and happy 2017 to DigitalOcean.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
So Wes, do you have any interest in the Firefox inaugural consensus results?
Oh yeah, that sounds interesting actually.
I'm kind of curious who finds themselves a Firefox user these days.
And I didn't even know they did this.
I didn't know that either.
But it makes sense when you, I mean you probably need that to help grow in the right direction.
So from the fire, here we go.
This is making me concerned from the Firefox department of whimsy.
We get this report.
This could be a bad, you know, I'm going to save it.
You know what?
I'll save judgment.
Let's see what's happening.
Because I was about to talk about having too much money and people sitting around with
time on their hands.
But no, I'm not going to get in there.
So let's keep going.
I mean you need at least two people making up department names, Chris.
That's how any organization works.
That's true.
All right.
You're right.
So a lot of their survey takers were between 18 and 34 years old or 55 plus.
80% use a PC, 12% use a Mac, and 6.8% use GNU slash Linux, GNU slash Linux.
However, a bunch of the Linux users bitched that I actually also run Windows a lot.
So I sort of voted Windows, but I still have a Linux machine I run.
So you should have had multi OS.
Don't peg me.
That's that was in there.
I don't know.
I don't know what that means.
Next time just pick Linux.
Just pick.
Yeah.
I know.
That's what I was thinking when I read that.
That's not that hard of a choice.
They even they even said, by the way, anyway, I won't go into what they talk about.
Speaking of our Linux folk, we found they tend to speak more languages than other OS
users.
58% of Linux users speak more than one language compared to 38% for Mac and Windows users.
So more mold.
That makes sense.
Linux is, you know, those it feels like Mac OS and Windows developed for English first
and then right and then.
But there's other places in the world where the people are developing their own native
language for open source.
So and they can just run it on their desktop.
A couple other things I thought were interesting.
Likes for Firefox users cooking.
At least 66% of good cooks, even if they don't like doing it.
Fall is the favorite season by 32% and 16% for winter.
And Star Wars beat Star Trek.
It was a close call.
Star Wars got fifty four point six percent.
Star Wars on this article.
Yeah.
Forty five point four percent.
I know.
It's true for us.
Dislikes.
Most actors who have played Spider-Man.
Fifty six percent chose no over Tobey Maguire.
Bungee jumping.
Sixty seven percent haven't been bungee jumping.
Twenty six say they never would.
Online dating they don't like.
Seventy nine percent have never tried it.
Nine percent said yes, they've tried it.
But it's a horror show.
Firefox sends their condolences.
The world.
Here's another thing Firefox users dislike.
The word jowls.
Fifty one percent said it's their least favorite word over synergy, fluid, and moist.
That's a common one.
Moist.
Fluid though.
Come on.
Fluid's a fun word and concept.
If people didn't mind me swearing on this show, I would be swearing about this.
This is what they spend their time and money on.
I mean they probably didn't spend a lot of time and money on it, but still.
I was hoping for like fifty six percent of Firefox users want multiprocessing.
Ten percent of Firefox users know what sandbox tabs are.
That's what I was hoping for.
The things that people are excited about.
I mean like I've been using Firefox at work and I'm always pleasantly surprised that when
I have a tab open and I try to open a new tab to go to that same URL, it just pops me
back to my current tab.
These are things that I like about Firefox, but I don't, this survey does not tell me
about that.
Oh man.
Oh too bad Alan had to go because this next one would be such a good update for him.
I should pick up the pace.
I think we're dragging.
Should I pick up the pace?
Let's do it.
All right.
So we'll just go through this really quick.
Huge, huge, huge, huge, huge story everybody.
Linux.com.
How Facebook uses Linux and ButterFS.
Oh man.
Whoa.
This is going to be great.
Finally.
We've been waiting for this.
That pro argument that all ButterFS users always throw in my face when I say ButterFS
is garbage and we should abandon it.
But Chris.
Chris.
Facebook.
Facebook uses it on their servers Chris.
Chris.
Are you better than Facebook Chris?
Actually Chris.
Actually.
Well actually.
Well actually Chris.
Facebook uses ButterFS.
That's what I get.
Every time I get that.
You've seen it.
Oh yeah.
Okay.
All right.
So we have an interview.
Actually.
Yeah.
Thank you.
We have an interview with not just somebody who works at Facebook in the server department
turns out to also be a lead developer of ButterFS.
So this guy pretty familiar with the product.
So let's go with what he says.
So we're going to get.
Now this whole article is framed around how Facebook uses ButterFS but in reality I love
you Swampy but it's only two questions in an entire article.
It's not about this at all.
But so Swampy asks, ButterFS has been in development for a long time.
Is it ready for prime time?
I know some distributions are using it as a default file system while others don't.
So the question is, is ButterFS ready for prime time?
It's right there.
Is it ready?
The direct quote is, is it ready for prime time?
Chris Mason's answer, it's certainly the default in Soos.
Pretty strong answer there.
And then he goes on talking about Soos and how Soos uses it.
And then he says, Red Hat hasn't picked it up in the same way.
Okay.
Next question.
What are the areas where ButterFS makes more sense?
If I'm not wrong, Facebook also uses ButterFS?
Here's all of the millions of deployments that Facebook has.
It just has a couple of qualifiers.
Inside of Facebook, again, we pick targeted places where we think the features of ButterFS
are really beneficial to the workloads at hand.
The big areas we're trying to focus on are system management tasks, the snapshotting
type of things.
In other words, they run it on a tiny fraction of their systems where that specific workload
makes sense for ButterFS.
So when you hear Facebook runs ButterFS, they run it on some of their servers.
And then it's for things like, okay, well, you have snapshots for your root file system,
you can do rollbacks, that kind of thing, but it's not their giant storage cluster.
He also goes on to say that they use Gluster and XFS, and that they're all pretty much
Linux, and that they don't really use ButterFS outside of management tasks around distributing
around operating systems and updates by snapshotting features.
And they like checks on the features.
So they think ButterFS, and I agree, has some snapshots, checksums, copy-on-write, all things
I would love, sub-volumes, all things I would love to see.
Those are legitimate uses.
And it's not that I don't like ButterFS, actually that's not true.
I don't like ButterFS.
It's a bad product, it's got a bad brand, nobody's deploying it seriously.
And unfortunately, it's a jalopy, everybody knows it, unfortunately.
I wish it wasn't.
Because the world needs ButterFS, because ZFS isn't GPL.
And I really think that's why XFS has been getting a ton of development in the last year
and a half.
Like the development pace on XFS is skyrocketing.
And I think it really is, like they're talking about adding copy-on-write support to XFS.
I really think XFS is trying to now fill that hole a little bit.
And I think it kind of illustrates as well, like I know some of the things people in the
XFS camp have talked about, you know, is ButterFS really wasn't designed in the way where, you
know, stability, production, runnableness came first, where it wasn't going to lose
your data.
But I think it kind of highlights the siloed nature sometimes of kernel development, where
we do have this like thriving XFS community, where it's very much trusted in production,
and they're going to add some features, but they're going to do it in a way where they
ensure they don't break compatibility.
They're not going to break your file system.
Will, go ahead.
So just, it looks like in here, from what he said, pretty much all Linux, the places
we're targeting is ButterFS and really management around tasks and distributing the operating
system.
This pretty much means if we have a server, the operating system is going to be installed
on ButterFS.
I didn't read it that way.
I do get that.
I see what you're saying.
But see what he says, when he says here, where they have targeted specific work environments,
that to me means that's not all of their systems.
You will want the operating system to be using ButterFS and have Snapshotty and all that
kind of stuff, but you don't need all of the application that they have on top, which is
Facebook or whatever the database is or whatever it's the program, needs to be on the same
file system because that will actually make sense.
It's not needed for that.
It's targeted of environment, doesn't mean the whole environment doesn't actually compensate
or encompasses that part.
All right.
Okay.
Fine.
All right.
So William, when usually we're talking about file systems, this is usually what I like
to check in with you because you always tantalize me with... I can't remember the name of it
right now.
But it's-
BcashFS, I think.
Yes.
Thank you.
Yes, it is.
It is.
Can we get a little BcashFS update?
How's it going?
So development's still progressing at a pretty smooth pace.
Encryption still hasn't landed, but there's a branch for it.
A lot of work has been focusing on performance and stability recently in just the feature
set that is there so far.
Those are good things.
Unfortunately, we don't have snapshotting yet, but checksumming works, and he's also
working on multi-tiering and replication and those sorts of multi-device type features.
Now, is... Okay.
Is there no work being done right now on Extended 5?
Is that a thing?
I guess that's...
I think that's a pipe dream.
Yeah.
All right.
Also, I don't really see why you would want to port the X4 code base forward to add those
type of features because it's a mess.
Right.
It's easier to do that kind of clean room implementation.
Super quick mention, because I said I wanted to pick up the base, Kodi.
Love it.
Hey.
One of our favorites.
Seventeen is just around the corner.
RC2 is out as we record this.
Not much of a difference between RC2 and RC1, so if you're on RC1, don't worry.
But I just wanted to give it a quick mention because it is coming down the pipe soon, and
if you have a Kodi box you can test on, they could probably use the help because this is
a huge release.
The new theme is really what the headline feature is, the new default theme, which does
look super good.
You see that?
It does look really nice.
That looks really slick.
But tons of new backend stuff, new way... I mean like everything from the PVR stuff to
the video decoding stuff, add-on manager changes, all of that is worth talking... Is Mr. Tennell
still in there?
Mr. Tennell?
Rotten.
Michael, do you have any Kodi thoughts before... You're usually following Kodi pretty closely.
Do you have any Kodi 17 thoughts?
Is there somebody who has a few add-ons on 16, are there things maybe I'll have to worry
about for 17?
Do you know any of the... Are you hip to any of that?
Yeah, there's a lot of differences in 16 and 17.
They're mostly appearance things, like the Krypton changes a lot of stuff for the way
the theme is going to change, so it's actually changing a lot of the way the interfaces for
all the different applicant add-ons work.
So it's mostly transparent, you don't have to do that much, but there are some add-ons
that require rewrites, but overall it's not a bad thing, it's more like they got a lot
of extra features they can utilize.
What I think is great is the LibreOffice, not LibreOffice, why did I say that, LibreELEC.
The fork of LibreELEC is really fast-paced development with Kodi.
So Krypton's not even out, and LibreELEC already has builds for the Krypton version, so the
alpha builds and the beta builds are already there, whereas OpenELEC doesn't even have
one yet.
So it's really something I would suggest people look at if they're looking at using Kodi.
So I'm going to put a link to this in the show notes if you guys want it.
It's LibreELEC.tv, and their tagline is Just Enough OS for Kodi.
So this is something you install, it gets you a base Kodi box, like an appliance-level
OS that gets fairly close, that tracks the Kodi development fairly closely.
So that's pretty cool, LibreELEC over OpenELEC, I'm going to check that out.
Thank you, sir.
That's cool, I'm dropping that in the show notes right now.
17 is...
I can't wait till it airs.
Oh, I know.
I can't wait till it gets out.
I've been just continuously impressed with Kodi.
I'm using it on...
All the places you can use it.
I'm using it on the Android TV.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
I'm using it on the...
I have not tried it on Android yet.
Super good.
It's super, super...
I can't...
It's got to be one of the best Android applications ever.
It's just so...
Wow.
It's like everything you want from Kodi in an app.
It's so...
I mean, like, I'm sitting there browsing Zomboshare's on an Android app.
It's just totally mind-blowing.
Without having to go tab out to some other app or any of that.
That's so great.
Wow.
And it can browse my local file system, too, which is good because I've got a hard drive
in that thing.
Ah, I tell you what.
I just...
I really love it on there.
And it's such a...
It's such a true appliance at that level.
Like, we just unplug it from the wall sometimes, and it's just no big deal.
It's so awesome.
That's...
That's amazing.
Mm-hmm.
I did an episode on it of the Linux Action Show for you guys.
Here.
Thunderbird development.
So this is a question that came in from Kapi in the subreddit, and he asked, has anyone
tried out Zimbr Desktop as a replacement for Thunderbird because he's worried about it
dropping off?
Yep.
And Zimbr Desktop...
Or...
Well, if you like Outlook, you'll like Zimbr Desktop.
That's kind of being harsh.
It's better than Outlook, I guess, but...
What does that even say?
I want to check in with you.
Are you still using LASN1 as your email client?
I've kind of fallen off with LASN1.
Oh!
Yeah.
I was using it for a while, and I was enjoying it, and I liked it, but I didn't find myself
using any of the pro features.
I don't really...
I mean, I send emails, right?
I receive emails mostly, but I don't need enough.
At work, we have 365, so I end up using the web interface for that anyway, so it was enough
to kind of keep things in the web interface.
That said, I still think it's a good project.
I'm excited for what they've done.
I like the way they develop things.
I just don't know if I have enough of a use case.
If anybody in the mobile room has thoughts on their favorite awesome mail client, tag
me in the chat room.
Actually, I'm still using N1.
What are your thoughts?
It's become invaluable.
Wow.
Not like I'd have to have it, but I definitely...
Like when I installed Solace, I was like, oh my God, can I get N1?
Oh, I can.
What I really like about it is two things.
I super like the fact that I can snooze emails, and I can say, alert me about this email tomorrow
at 6 PM.
That is such a nice feature, because it helps me get away from leaving the mark as unread,
because like...
That gets messy so fast.
Oh my God, dude.
I wonder if it says on my phone, if I pull up the mail icon, does it say how much freaking
mail I have?
It is an unbelievable amount of unread mail I have at this very moment, and so using what
used to be a great horrible system, I suppose, of just leaving messages as unread, and then
if it was unread, then I knew I needed to follow up on it.
That doesn't work.
You can't do that.
Not when you have like a ton of email to get to.
So being able to set a reminder like that is super useful, because then it goes out
of my inbox.
It clears out.
So it looks like it's been cleared out of my inbox.
Anything that can reduce the complexity of what you have to do, and it can make it easy
at a glance to just be like, this is what I need to deal with now, later, I will check
again and deal with what needs to be dealt with then.
But the other thing I really like about it is this creepy feature that it has.
Talking about the read notifications?
Yeah, which is like read receipts on a whole new level.
Do you have any idea how they're doing it?
I assume they're shipping like a little pixel or element inside there.
There's something in the email, but it seems to work even with plain text emails.
But I don't know if that's true.
I guess maybe everybody I email uses HTML mail, but it would have to be damn near everybody
I email.
So here's what it does, and it even integrates them with Gnome's notifications.
So it's so fun.
So I send off an email to somebody, and when they read it, instead of getting like the
traditional read receipt email that you get in your email box, I get a push notification
to the email client, which shows up as a Gnome notification that Wes has read my email.
And I get that every time Wes opens up my emails, and it turns out, and this is really
valuable for me because I like to dive into email and then get out for a while.
And so I can tell if I'm having an active conversation with somebody because I can see
that they're reading my emails, and then I know if I need to stay present.
The other thing that's really great is if I leave n1 minimize in the background or running
on like my second desktop and I'm on my main desktop, I will often see like Wes has opened
up your email, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Because what everybody seems to do in the entire world is instead of, when they go to
email somebody, they just open up the last email from them, hit reply, clear out the
subject line, put a new subject line in, clear out the body, put a new body in, and send
the email.
And so everybody opens up my old emails before they send me a new email, at least a lot of
people, not everybody.
So I end up getting a notification in like five, ten minutes that, hey, you're about
to get an email from Wes.
So I keep an eye out.
And without fail, it always happens.
Wow, actually that's pretty handy.
It is very handy because otherwise, once I'm out, I'm done.
It might be days until I open up my email again.
You could have like, you know, you could have solved that thing or come to a resolution
with a question you had right there.
So that turns out to be a very super creepy, great feature.
Well, maybe I'll have to give it another try.
So that combined with the delay, the way you can snooze emails, and the overall UI is nice.
I mean, it's an Electron app, but it's probably one of the best Electron apps I've ever used.
I never found it to be slow or anything like that.
And I don't mind that it has a pay structure.
I'm glad the company's going to be around.
And they still allow you to host your own server, which works fine on DigitalOcean.
So I'm happy.
Yeah.
I don't disagree with that.
I never want that feature ever, ever, ever.
The creepy tracking?
Yes.
Please.
No.
If I want to have that type of knowledge about people being about to text me, I would use
an instance messaging service.
There's plenty out there already.
I'll make another one if you're listening to this, by the way.
I should also say it has pretty great GPG integration, too.
It beats even Enigma or whatever.
What's the Thunderbird extension?
Yeah.
Enigma.
There's also the...
Well, Enigma...
Yeah.
It's good.
It's fine.
Yeah, it is.
I like Enigma a lot, so I'm not trying to disparage it, because I also like that it
has good key management.
Made it easy, and it came out quickly on the time that FSF was trying to cash on the fears
because of the revelations and stuff.
It kind of does work.
But you know what?
Yes.
So I just wanted to get it out there for Kipi, because N1 might be something, if you're willing
to host your own server or willing to let them host it for you, because it does require
that server-side component.
Right.
And that's how the tracking works, but also sending notifications to your desktop.
The other thing that's really great about it is that intermediary server seems...
It just gets really shitty when you get a lot of email, and sometimes red status doesn't
get synced correctly through IMAP and stuff like that.
It's just a pain in the butt, and the N1 client doesn't seem to have those issues.
So I like that a lot about it, too.
So there you go, Kipi.
That's my answer to your Thunderbird question.
Now, before we go any further in the show, we really got to get to the predictions.
We got to get to the predictions.
That's the whole point of the show.
That's got to be where we're going.
So let's talk about Ting.
That's our next sponsor here on the Unplugged program, and Ting is mobile service that's
perfect for our audience, because it's really quite simple.
If you just think about how you use your phone a little bit, you can save a ton of money.
Honestly, it's not really all that bad.
One of the things I've done is we have a nanny for the kids, and she has an iPhone on Ting.
And I don't go like, Jenny, don't use data.
Don't make phone calls.
She just uses it however she wants.
I don't really bother.
I am the weirdo that enjoys hacking the system.
I like looking at my bill and going, three phones, and I've only spent 35 bucks.
That's crazy.
I like that, because I know how to use Wi-Fi for phone calls and downloading podcasts.
And you can get the thrill of optimization there.
Yeah, I know.
That's great.
It's like, hey, I won a little bit.
I cheated the system.
That's right.
I do deserve this cheeseburger.
That's a good way to think about it.
I do deserve a cheeseburger.
You do.
Right now.
You sure do.
Freak eye.
Yeah.
He deserves a cheeseburger, too.
So here's what's great about Ting is your average monthly bill is like 23 bucks.
That's your average device cost, like six bucks for your line, and then your usage will
generally work out to about 23 bucks.
It's amazing.
And if you start with our URL, linux.ting.com, you get $25 in service credit, so it'll pay
for more than your first month.
Now, if you don't have a device, you can go get one with that $25, and that's also a great
way to go.
They have fantastic customer service.
They have CDMA and GSM networks to choose from, no contracts, no early termination fee,
and they have, guess what, a really great control panel, a legit, a lit, as the YouTubers
say.
They have a lit control panel.
Did you know that?
I did not.
Lit.
Which I thought at first was like you're lit up.
Yeah.
Right.
Sure.
Getting lit.
Yeah.
Or you're getting wasted, getting lit.
I guess that's another term, getting lit, right?
This is quite the overloaded operator we've got here.
But no, now it's legit.
Too lit to quit.
Legit.
Shouldn't it be le?
That's le.
Ting is le.
It really is.
I'm going on almost like what, three years with Ting?
That's le.
Let me tell you, that's le.
That's longer than a lot of relationships.
Look at you guys.
Also that's le.
Congratulations.
I know.
Me and Ting, you know what?
I think it's really Kyra that makes it all work.
I think Kyra behind the scenes, she's pushing all the buttons and making it possible.
Without Kyra, I don't know what would be going on.
Who else would explain to us how Ting works?
We can't do it.
We need her.
No.
Ting keeps rates simple.
We don't make you pick a plan.
Instead, you just use your phone as you normally would.
How much you use determines how much you pay each month.
You can have as many devices as you want on one account.
That's good because when you use more, you pay less per minute, message, or megabyte
of data.
Your usage plus $6 per active device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill.
Simple.
That's what we mean when we say mobile.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
Go check out their lit control panel, too, and I got an app, too, which is really nice.
Sim cards for like $9.
Put them in a device, security system, anything like that.
I think you know what?
I just got a really interesting idea.
I would love to be able to check the battery status of LadyJuice remotely.
I wonder if there's a little way I could hook up an Arduino or a Raspberry Pi and a little
Ting.
I'm sure you could.
It wouldn't be great if I could SSH into something and get the battery level.
Yes.
That would be great.
Maybe turn the car on remotely.
Yeah.
All right.
You know what I can do?
Let me try this.
I'm not sure if this is the right command.
Alexa, ask automatic how much gas I have.
Your Ford Super Duty F53 motor home is 80% full.
Your RAM 1500 is 72% full.
Isn't that great?
Wow.
Yeah.
We're going to get into that more later.
Let's start with our 2017 predictions.
I don't know what it is this year.
This year, I feel like it's going to be the year of more of the same.
What do I get excited about if it's more momentum in the right direction?
We're going to have some fights.
We're going to have some missteps, but overall, we're going to do pretty good.
Maybe that means for all the negative 2016 comments, maybe it really wasn't a bad year
for Linux at all.
Yeah.
I don't know about that.
I don't know.
No.
Freck Labs is not saying it's 1500% full.
There's two different vehicles listed there, one motor home, one truck.
So I want to defer to the virtual lug.
Maybe they can get us going.
Maybe they can get us.
Do you have a quick one off the tip of your tongue?
Well, we kind of already talked about it.
I was just thinking at the end, we'll see BcashFS.
I think by the end of 2017, that's going to be something that we will be talking about
more.
Interesting.
I wonder if he just told Williams.
All right.
Sweetloo, what is your...
Go ahead.
You'll get first.
Go.
Well, I still hold on to my prediction about Ubuntu and Microsoft merging when Ubuntu reaches
the end of the alphabet on this coming April.
I'm going to keep track of this.
So Sweetloo's prediction is really what you're...are you really saying that Microsoft buys Canonical?
Is that what you're saying?
Yeah, either that or merges with...
Yeah, it's going to be an acquisition, right?
Not happening.
All right.
So and then...
Hold on.
I got to write this down.
So that's not...
Microsoft...
Okay, go ahead.
May make a deal with Canonical or actually more likely with Suze to be honest, though,
because it's the previous deal.
To have them help them support a Linux kernel, I don't believe they will acquire Canonical.
Is it like an Ubuntu...
Not now.
It's like an Ubuntu blast kernel running on Azure?
Not just that, but also because remember my prediction, we're ever closer to the year
of my prediction of Microsoft running with Linux kernel and a Windows desktop environment
on top that is proprietary.
God, I would love that.
Yeah, but I just think they're so allergic to the GPL.
I think they're...
They're not, though.
They're not.
This is the thing that they've been realizing is that it's actually useful to have other
people maintain your stuff and you will not ever have the issue of not having people to
hire to fix your stuff because everybody knows it.
That's logical and very cognizant, but do you think they've actually made that big of
a change?
Yeah.
Yes.
Because look at the companies, I just can't not look at the fact that they've been acquiring
talent more with the acquisitions of the apps companies and so on.
They're not acquiring just the companies, they're acquiring talent that knows how to
work in this platform without telling the world that they're doing so.
Right now, if you want to look at the prospects of any business in IT and you want to know
what they're up to, there's two ways.
You can ask them and they might say about it or you can look at what they're hiring
because they can't lie about the hiring because otherwise they'll not get the right people.
So do you want to go on record and say that you're going to see Microsoft products running
on an Ubuntu kernel or do you want to actually say Windows because I could actually get behind
the first one.
I don't know if I could get behind Windows in 2017.
I'm not sure if it will be in 2017, but until 2018, I'm pretty sure there will be a Linux
kernel with a Windows desktop environment.
I think-
That was my prediction.
It was a five-year span.
They're three years in.
They already have a Linux distribution on the server and Azure and all the stuff.
They love Linux now.
Here's what I'm going to say.
I'm going to kind of hijack your prediction a bit and I'm going to say in 2017, Microsoft
makes a deal with Canonical to run a product on an Ubuntu blessed kernel.
And it might be like the more like the slimmed down Ubuntu stuff, like Ubuntu core.
I could totally see that.
I could see them doing that on the cloud.
I could even see them doing that in like a product.
I really could see that happening, but running their core Windows desktop, I've always thought
eventually to go on a VM, but I figured it'd be because it'd be replaced with another Microsoft
product.
Right.
And it seems like I could see them doing that on a BSD or something, but I feel like they're
always going to want to withhold that to be able to have their new proprietary drivers,
their new custom kernel integration that lets them have the one new feature or the HoloLens
support or something where they have a competitive edge in the business.
And I don't think, I think there are still enough things at the OS level for the desktop
world that they wouldn't be willing to share that.
On the cloud server angle, yes, I think that's a different ball game for them.
I think you're on the same page.
To be honest, it won't matter that much the feature of Microsoft and like in general what
OS you're running because they're really moving to the assistant world, want to give you Windows
10 for free.
Why?
Because it doesn't matter.
You're going to profit on having you talk with Cortana.
This is the thing that actually is dragging people still to Windows 10 and try and they
were excited about the experimentation.
You can run Cortana everywhere, even in your Android phone.
Alexa, what do you think of Cortana?
I like all AIs.
Yeah.
She's pretty nice.
Fires.
Yeah.
So producer Michael, I would love to hear your predictions.
You wanted to jump in.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
One of my predictions is I think SNAPs will make a big leap forward ahead of everything
else.
Oh, yeah.
So it's the year of SNAPs, huh?
Yeah.
I think the SNAPs are already on the track record of becoming the more standardized way
of deployment, but I think this year they're going to set themselves apart way farther
than 5X or App Images could be close to catching up.
I think that won't happen until the end of the year, but I think it'll happen.
I think 1710 will probably offer a Unity 8 by default.
Oh.
Okay.
All right.
So that's two right there.
I'm going to mark you down for it.
So 1710, Unity by default.
Unity.
You mean, you mean Unity 8 by default.
Unity 8.
Yeah.
I meant Unity 8.
Okay.
QT switch and stuff.
Ooh.
Oh.
All right.
All right, Double.
You got two predictions for us.
Go.
I do.
One is we're finally getting a proper KMS support as well as the right Wayland support.
Okay.
I'm down with that.
The second is Solus is going to become more popular and will eventually come out with
a AUR type solution similar to Arch where you can, you know, the community can maintain
build scripts for separate packages.
I get to see that.
So it's like a Solus AUR equivalent.
I'm going to vote for, I'm going to, my prediction is that doesn't happen.
Yeah.
Okay.
Here's the thing.
Solus is anti AUR, anti other people's packages.
Yeah.
I've already tried to make my own packages with them and they've already told me nah-uh.
So I've done this too with Solus and the thing is if you go to install an application that
doesn't support Solus, like you don't have the advantage of a dev or an RPM install.
So you go into EO package and you copy a couple make files, you create a script, it starts
downloading the source and you go through this rigmarole to get one thing installed.
What people are doing is posting those to the Wiki.
So the Wiki is starting to contain more and more of this third party and I think as they
gain popularity, they're not going to be able to keep up and so they're going to have the
ability for you to actually compile them, but it's not going to be part of the main
repo.
Yeah.
I think that this is the possibility of happening, but I don't think it'll be Solus back.
Solus will not like endorse it or anything.
There won't be an SUR and my main reason is because I'm an official maintainer of a package
for like the official upstream and they still wouldn't let me control the package in the
thing.
Yeah, but you just named it, dude.
The SUR is good.
I like that.
That's good.
You're welcome, sir.
Yeah.
I think there's something wrong with that.
I don't know so much about NVIDIA getting Wayland support this year.
I would say maybe beta support.
I don't know about, I don't know.
Oh, sorry, Wes.
I was stepping on your pedal, Wes.
At the end of the year maybe, you know, you start seeing the, yeah, some of the, like
if you install some of the beta drivers or something that starts working.
Yes, exactly.
That's what I was thinking.
But it's not like the default, it's not shipped in the...
Yeah.
And it won't be like the unbelievably great performance that we want or something yet.
But I don't know.
But maybe you're right, Double.
Maybe they'll, they should, right?
Here's the thing.
It's not like they haven't seen it coming.
We've been, Wayland has got to be the slowest moving train coming at you and it's like there's,
if you don't see the Wayland train coming, then you're not looking.
You are not looking.
You've had like, what?
Like four years now of gradual buildup?
Yeah.
That's ridiculous.
All right.
Anybody else in there want to toss into the mix a prediction for Linux in 2017?
Hmm.
Really?
Nobody else has anything else?
No?
Nobody else?
It's not going to be the year of the desktop.
No?
Linux desktop.
Is there ever going to be a year?
I'm not surprised at that at all.
Will there ever be?
I don't think so.
Yeah.
It depends on your perspective.
If you want to talk about Linux in general, Chrome OS already kind of did that.
A little birdie tells me from the Solus project that there's no way in hell the AUR is happening.
I'm not going to, no, no, they say, no, no AUR free, no SUR, which is too bad.
Can we make wishes too?
I do agree that Solus will become even more popular than it has been before.
Yeah.
I think so too.
So the predictions, can we make wishes?
Oh, I'd love to hear it.
Yeah.
I just, I just wish that we have one either in a Google play store, like it's something
that is just across all OSs.
It actually is able to, if the app has compatibility with your multiple OSs, install it, please.
Yeah.
Rekai says, if you're looking for crazy predictions, maybe 2017 will finally be the year KDE cleans
up its mess of settings.
Ouch.
Wow.
I don't know.
How dare you, sir.
But then how, where, what will we have that the windows users will be comfortable with?
Wait, where's the refuge?
Yeah.
I still feel like I don't have like, I don't have my like succinct prediction.
I feel like I have good commentary on other people's predictions.
Go ahead, Delby.
You can jump in again.
So I wonder if at the end of 2017, we'll look back at the 2016 MacBook Pro release and basically
realize that a lot of developers have switched over to Linux and the wish and the wonder
is going to be what gains we see on the Linux desktop from that.
Do you think it's possible Apple could hustle and crap out another MacBook in like June
that is 32 gigs of RAM?
Do you think that could happen?
Or are they just like, or do you think they're up there in their Johnny Ive white towers
going, I don't know what the problem is.
This is a really powerful machine.
It's great.
They just need to figure it out.
I don't think that's going to happen now that they rely on common people to just get their
stuff.
They don't care anymore to make it really high tech.
Mass consumer.
Yeah.
I was about to say, I don't think they're worried about like, what's the problem.
I think they're like, there's no problem.
Yeah.
I wonder if that ties into that, their IBM partnership and stuff, because it seems like
some enterprises make Mac works, but it also is particularly a pain point.
So maybe this is a sphere they exit.
You know, you think, you know, you think that they, they think that you think it's a problem,
you know, or whatever.
A lot of people think it's a problem, but remember, they think different.
Oh boy.
I think, you know, what's weird is my, my thoughts around Linux in 2017, oddly a Microsoft,
the name Microsoft keeps popping up.
I keep there.
It's, which feels strange.
It's weird.
And it's, I wonder if it's, I mean, if they continue that trend, that's, that'll be, that'll
be noteworthy for sure.
And it's, I think it's going to be, I think I'm going to, I'll wait.
I guess I'll wait for last.
But I think, I think we're going to be surprised by Microsoft in 2017.
And I think, I think we're, we're probably all sort of settled on the fact that distributions
like Solace and those others are getting more important than ever, but there's other distributions
over 2016 that I think turned it around.
And I don't know if that gets enough attention either.
And I think OpenSUSE is one of them to a degree.
I think it turned it around from a distribution.
I don't know if it's still, it's not quite, I don't know if it's gotten there yet, but
I, I guess it feels like it's not quite yet a distribution that's changing the conversation,
that's influencing the conversation, quote unquote, but it's one that's getting a whole
new tidal wave of excited users.
Like, so they're doing things right as a project that's appealing to a lot of, a lot more people
than they were, say, at the beginning of 2016.
Right.
And they're kind of on the, that like starting point of the curve where it's like they're
doing a lot of cool things.
They have some good, interesting ideas.
And so yeah, maybe 2017 will be the year where we see like, do people flock there?
No, we don't know.
But it could be a great, 2017 might end up being a great year for OpenSUSE.
Yeah.
The 2015 was when they first announced, it was like November, 2015 when they started
doing this whole new thing.
So there's only been a year of this massive change.
So I think there hasn't been enough time for them to actually like kind of develop the
curve completely yet.
And now, now I think you're right, that 2017 will be a much, much more OpenSUSE friendly.
Unless they screw it up.
I mean, I think they're pretty much, they're pretty positionable to do well.
Wecom, you want to jump in with a.NET one.
All right, go for it.
I could see.NET becoming a native.NET support for the desktop.
Oh really?
For Linux.
Why do you say that?
I think Microsoft has enough third party applications that if programmers could use their.NET languages
and just port them to Linux, you would see a lot more, people wouldn't be threatening
to move to different applications or different programming languages, which is a big problem
for them.
So if they could install a.NET application on a Linux desktop, it solves the migration
of.NET programmers away from Visual Studio.
You mean it helps Windows desktop become a reality on Linux.
I get it.
I don't know if it helps Windows desktop, but I think what it helps is Windows applications,
Outlook per se, or business applications where people want to run them natively.
Yeah.
Or third party developers.
People that write in.NET, they can now run it in Linux.
Yeah, Daredevil, they could use that for the.NET, they could release the.NET VM bridge
from your Linux desktop to the Windows VM.
That's good ones guys.
So here's what I got.
So Sweetloot says that Microsoft will make a deal or buy Canonical, Daredevil says that
Microsoft makes a deal to run a product on Ubuntu blessed kernel or maybe even Windows
in 2018, which we probably would start hearing about in 2017.
I'm going to actually, mine is, I have a similar prediction along the same lines, just a little
more, a little more less ambitious.
Rotten says it's going to be the year of snaps, they're just basically going to pull ahead
by a pretty good margin.
And at 1710, Unity by default, Mr. Double says that NVIDIA gets Wayland support and
Solus will have an SUR equivalent.
And Monkeycom says.NET becomes a mainstream Linux language.
I got one last thing to throw in there.
Throw it in there, Mr. West.
Doesn't make me happy to say, but I feel like at least, I think we're going to be talking
about Linux Mint in a less than positive way at least one time this year.
You know, interesting.
I don't know if that'll be another security breach or just relevance issues.
It's not that I don't like the project.
I just think that seems like something on the horizon.
It feels like there is some direction and momentum that way.
And over the holiday break, I was seeing a lot of threads, and I don't think anybody
in the Mumble Room saw this, I've seen a lot of threads about potentially Linux Mint was
compromised again.
Did you see that?
No, I didn't.
Did you see any of this?
I saw someone asking the question about it, but it wasn't really.
In a few Reddits, yeah.
Well, what happened was, is somebody posted and slash pwned, hey, I just owned Linux Mint
again.
And then in all the other subreddits, people were asking if it was true or not.
Trying to validate, yeah.
Yeah.
So no word there, though.
Second time I have seen something like that since the initial break-in, though.
And I hope that prediction is wrong, honestly.
I really do.
But we'll see.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Well, I mean, I just want Mint to stop doing the terrible decisions they do.
I can give you one example that they should stop right now.
Lay it on me, brah.
Which is incredibly stupid.
Brah, lay it on me.
The priority structure that they make their repo higher priority than PPAs.
Yeah.
They need to stop that.
If it's FUD, if it's FUD, why is this happening?
What kind of FUD is this?
And who's behind it?
You're telling me that just somebody-
Canonical might be behind it.
Come on.
Joking.
Do I have to have my conspiracy bacon clip here?
It spread pretty fast on Reddit.
So maybe that's the part that's-
Because I think the reason-
That particular thing.
Although the problem that they had was so easily avoidable that they should have never
had the problem in the first place.
True.
And it meant that anything can happen at this point.
Like who's to say that they realized their problem the first time and like because they
should have never had that problem because what they claimed was the whole meant that
they didn't update their WordPress for three years.
That's just stupid.
That's literally painting a target on your back.
Exactly.
And it's also an easy target because there's a plethora of holes for it.
That has got to be the-
That is-
Yeah.
You know, it is Reddit.
Who knows?
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, that part, yeah.
I mean, the current one is totally probably-
I mean, I don't know.
Could be.
Could be not.
I mean, I don't know.
It seems to be garbage.
Probably.
Like just not true at all.
I don't like it.
It just makes me the whole-
So that is a thought-provoking prediction to end on there, Wes.
I like that one.
You know what else is thought-provoking?
Getting an education, linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
Go there, sign up for a seven-day free trial, and try out Linux Academy, a platform built
by Linux enthusiasts and educators and developers that came together to create the Linux Academy.
They wanted to create content that Linux users could zoom to learn more, to spread Linux
and to help you get a job, get a raise.
In fact, a lot of new features they've launched to the platform really enable these goals,
like public profiles to show your accomplishments, core schedulers to match a busy workday, mobile
apps for iOS and Android so that way you can practice on the go, which would be so awesome
like on the bus or on the train or sitting on the turlet.
Up your skill game while you're just wasting time otherwise.
I had an uncle that would seriously take a two-hour crap, really.
And I tell you what, if I had Linux Academy on my tablet-
You would too.
That would be a very productive two hours, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
One of the things I think is really great about Linux Academy, it sets them apart from
everybody else, is instructor mentoring.
Because these topics, they're not fixing the sink.
They're not something where they could have somebody with a cell phone on call when you
have a question like that.
These are dedicated staff members that have to really understand this stuff.
It's a business.
They know what they're doing.
You know, they've been really good at adding new content and updating old content too.
And that is also something else that sets them apart.
Plus they have these labs, these hands-on scenarios where you get real world experience.
If you just need to get some certs, they've got great courseware for that.
They have study tools that you can download, comprehensive guides that you can look and
print out and listen to for audio.
Seriously people listen in the shower, I can't even believe it.
I mean, actually, shower thoughts are real, man.
That's a real thing.
So why not, if I can have brilliant shower thoughts, maybe it is the perfect time to
learn actually.
I think about it.
It's shower thought time.
You can check it out.
Also, just a real quick thing.
If you've already subscribed to Linux Academy, you've got like just a couple of days left.
We were on break so I couldn't mention this sooner.
But if you're listening live or you're downloading like day after the next day, they're giving
away a pixel.
What?
Yeah.
It ends on January 5th.
They'll do this from time to time.
So it's just good for you to watch.
They have a blog where you can watch these things.
You just got to log into your account and help spread the word.
Well, they got it all on their blog.
They just go to their Linux Academy blog and learn, but you got a couple of days left to
get a pixel.
And Wes, would you recommend it now?
How many?
What are you like, what, one month?
Two months into it?
What do you want?
Yeah.
Probably like two, almost three months probably.
Are you loving it?
Hating it?
Caveat.
I'm not a person who, my whole life is not on my phone.
I mean, I do a lot with my phone.
Obviously I need it.
It's a great, it's a great phone.
If you just need like a consistent phone, latest Android.
That sounds perfect.
Yeah, exactly.
It's perfect for that.
Sounds like an iPhone.
Yeah.
It's exactly the kind of like, I'm not, I don't have a lot of complaints.
I don't have a lot of like, I don't need to do anything with it.
It just works.
How's the camera?
Lovely.
Really?
Oh yeah.
I'm loving it.
Yeah.
I could, maybe one day.
Maybe one day.
And you know what?
If I could get, if I could get.
Linux Academy dot com slash unplug.
Go there.
Get a seven day free trial.
Learn more about the platform.
And while you're there, I mean, you'd probably be eligible to get a seven day free trial.
I'm just saying.
Go to Linux Academy dot com slash unplug.
Sign up.
Try to get a Google Pixel.
And you're off.
Boy, if you get it, tweet me at Chris LAS.
I seriously want to know about that.
That would be.
Oh man.
If a JB member can get, ugh.
Yeah.
All right.
So are you ready to, are you ready to talk about securing the internet of things and
smart devices?
I mean, I'm quaking in my boots over here because you said IOT and smart devices in
the same sentence.
I know, right.
But.
Can I put it another?
Yes.
Let's talk about it.
Cyber.
Ugh.
Ah.
Well, OK.
How about this for a sentence?
You ready for this?
Wes, are you concerned about cyber threats against your smart devices?
Internet of things?
Huh?
See, I got cyber threats in there, Wes.
Isn't that good?
Can I, is there like a thing I can do with my body that just, I'm like a hundred percent,
a thousand percent yes?
Yeah.
You know, so I got to just make a huge disclaimer if we go any further because I got to imagine
I probably should have said this way earlier in the show now.
Now that I think about it.
Yeah, that's true.
A lot of you are listening going, Chris, what the AF are you doing?
Why do you have a privatized spying device in your studio right now, literally listening
to every word you say?
Spied on the whole show.
Yeah.
Are you crazy?
Are you ridiculous?
Are you nuts?
Have you lost it?
Don't you care about open source and Linux?
My God, Chris, what about Mycroft?
Before you go down that route, I encourage you to go check out how I use the Amazon Echo
Dot to automate my studio.
It's a vlog I posted this morning, just posted a couple of hours ago, and it goes over how
we use the Echo Dot in the studio, why we got them, how I've isolated them off on a
separate network, and what our intention is behind all of that.
So just so you know, if you're concerned about that, go watch that episode.
It's all covered in there, how we're using it, all of that stuff.
It would be a whole episode to talk about that, so that video is in the show notes.
Now, I want to talk about the big concern.
The big concern everybody listening has is cloud services, cloud monitoring, things like
that.
Well, it turns out I've done a little digging, and there's some interesting things that those
of you who are considering getting a device like this might want to look at.
Now, I'm not like Mr. Expert on any of these devices yet.
I've got three of them at this point for the studio, because the Echo Dot was $40, and
what I decided to do was, well, I should get one for myself to learn with it.
So that's upstairs in my office, and then I wanted one in the studio because I checked
this out.
Now, actually, we have video, so if you're watching the video feed, Alexa, turn on JB1.
OK.
Oh, that's so cool.
Look at that.
Yeah.
Alexa, turn off JB1.
OK.
And we're back.
So everything in the studio was sort of in place, and then I can do things like, Alexa,
turn on studio ambient lights.
Oh, I didn't say it fast enough.
Sorry for those of you at home, by the way.
I'll get over this.
I won't do this.
Just give them like two months, maybe?
No, give me like two more minutes in this episode, and then you just, there's a mute
button on there.
Alexa, turn on studio ambient lights.
OK.
Oh, that's lovely.
Yeah, isn't that great?
Alexa, turn on studio accent lights.
OK.
Alexa, ask for a fart.
Just to prove a point.
So the studio was kind of out of the box just over the years, ready to be integrated, but
we needed, you really kind of need something to centralize the control because this product's
made by Hughes, this product's made by Belkin, this product over here is made by TP-Link.
They all support some weird subset of the same protocol, but, or maybe not.
And I want them all isolated off on their own LAN, so that way they're not talking to
any of my other devices, they're not monitoring any of my other traffic, because I don't trust
these things.
I don't trust these things at all.
And so I wanted them off on their own LAN, but in order to actually access them, you'd
have to take your device and put it on that LAN to talk to them.
Well what kind of stupid idea is that?
That is not feasible in a lot of cases.
That only is that a pain in the butt and breaks whatever I'm doing on my device, but it also
then exposes that device to the very thing I'm trying to avoid.
It's like the stupidest workaround ever.
And so this device, this Echo, is in that LAN.
And so it's my bridge, essentially.
So I talk to it, and it talks to them.
So that's kind of interesting.
But I wanted to make this even better.
So I'm not here yet, but I've begun looking into two different products that look like
they could essentially act as the command and control of the cloud for a device like
this.
The first is Home Assistant at home-assistant.io.
It's a Python app, I think.
Yeah, Python 3.
Home Assistant is an open source home automation platform for running on Python 3.
Open source, did you say?
Mm-hmm.
See where I'm going with this.
You see where I'm going with this.
And the other one, and this is maybe the one I'm more likely to look into, OpenHAB, OpenHAB.
It's a vendor and technology agnostic open source automation software for your home.
And my understanding is, the Echo, I'm trying not to say the hot word, the Echo could actually
talk to it over Bluetooth.
And OpenHAB could run on something as simple as a Raspberry Pi.
So it's like-
Which is even cheaper than the dot.
Yeah, right.
Exactly.
Fully open source, developed in Java.
Yeah.
It's got a web UI, it's got Android and iOS apps, and a web, of course, works on the desktop,
so that's already built in.
It's got notification support, all of these things.
And I've seen some indication that there is a way to tie the device into OpenHAB.
So that way, instead of going to the Echo Cloud, or the Amazon AWS hosted services,
it goes to OpenHAB.
Oh, wow, really?
I'm not sure yet.
I don't know what you're looking into there.
So it's kind of a fascinating path I've gotten.
And I really kind of think, one of the reasons I want to wrap my head around it now is they
sold a ton of these over the holidays.
Oh, yes.
And I had so many non-tech people in my life asking about them, or if I tried them.
I was astounded.
And I thought I understood how this all worked.
I thought I kind of had it all conceptually figured out, until I actually had to set all
of this up, and create smart groups, and do all of these things, and I have such a deeper
understanding of it now.
It's like AWS Lite.
Yeah.
It is like an entire thing.
You really have to learn.
There's a command structure, and all of this stuff.
So it's been fascinating.
And I do kind of feel like it's an interesting thing to know, just the general consumer platform.
But man, I can't wait until something like Mycroft comes along.
And then that's really going to be where it gets interesting.
And that's a space that we need to have open source stuff.
What's that?
The API of the Echo is pretty good, too.
Oh, yeah?
Yeah.
There's a lot of integrations for... You can write your own integrations and commands
for the Echo to do a lot of things that aren't necessarily intended to do.
They have integrations built into a lot of things, but you can pretty much write your
own for whatever you want.
It's not really open, but the API itself is very extensive.
That's interesting.
So I got a dot for the beard to do some experimental development with, too.
Ooh.
Yeah.
I was thinking, maybe we could tie it in with J-Bot.
Wouldn't it be great if I could execute... So we control different things in the studio
now with J-Bot.
Wouldn't it be cool if I could get some of those... If I could bark that at the Echo?
Yeah.
How many times at the end of the show are you like, oh, I want to stop the YouTube stream?
You can just yell at the Echo.
It's been interesting to just see how many little scattered devices I had around the
studio that were controlled with it.
It's a fun experiment so far.
But I think OpenHAB is probably my path.
So this is sort of my call out to the audience.
I heard from an individual this morning, which is really awesome, who might be pretty well
informed on it, but I've also just put the call out there.
At Chris Elias on Twitter, if you've got something set up and maybe you could give me some advice
on how I could compare it with my Echo Dot.
And if it's feasible, I'd love to be able to have one here at the studio, an OpenHAB
set up, and one maybe like running at the RV, too.
Oh, yeah.
And do I even need the dot?
I have all these questions.
Yeah.
You don't need the dot for OpenHAB.
You can put the software on other devices.
And then like, so I wouldn't get the voice stuff, but I would have like one app that
controls all?
Yeah.
You can have it.
I've actually played with OpenHAB myself, but I haven't spent a ton of time on it.
But I have dug into it a little bit, and it has ability to use pretty much any device
you want.
And it just, depending on what hardware you give it, what features it has.
So you can, you can, if you, you can't really like replace the dots or the Echo's like software.
But if you have something that's similar to it and you put OpenHAB on it, you can use
it to facilitate most of it.
Wow.
But you can also make it where OpenHAB and the Echo connect to each other, too.
That would be great.
That sounds interesting, because I think, I mean, here's where, here's where I feel
like this is gone.
And as people where we talk about specs, and often we think about open source and community
solutions, we sometimes, I think we fail to see when the market has decided on something.
I wonder if this holiday season, if the Echo didn't tip over to a mass consumer product
and it sort of won.
Boy, didn't Google Home try to push hard on the ads, though.
Yeah.
But I don't know that actually translated.
Can you name a, can you name a single Google direct product that's done well in the mass
consumer market?
Is there any reason to think that Google's good at doing that kind of product?
Yeah.
Whereas like Amazon at this point has really got, like there are, there is a, there is
a lot of, there is a lot of different functionality built into Alexa, like they have not slowed
down from the moment they released it.
There is almost stuff daily they're doing on this thing, like they are very passionate
about this thing.
It's a huge thing for them.
Have you ordered any packages or other things with it?
No.
I think it is the number one reason why Alexa, why the Echo will always, it's hard, well
I think will, it is a, it is a, it is a core business interest of Amazon to have this thing
in your home because they don't have physical stores.
They need to have this in your home.
This is super important to their business.
This is their like easy way to interact with you.
Right.
For Google, this is another metric.
This is another metric collection device.
It's important, but it's no more important than your Chromecast or your Android TV or
your tablet or your Google Docs account or your YouTube account.
Those are actually probably great, especially your Gmail account is a much richer, greater
source of metrics than a Google Home will ever be because there is a certain line they
just can't cross.
They can't, if they could always monitor, if they could listen to every dumb thing you
say and every time you masturbate and every time you cook dinner and every time you watch
TV, if they could listen to all of that, that would be extremely useful for them and that
would also destroy their business.
It would fundamentally undermine their business.
So I think we're, I just don't think it's, I don't think it's as critically important
to Microsoft, to Apple, to, or to Google as it is to Amazon.
I think it's, it's fundamental to Amazon and here I will disagree.
I think the reason Google does not need to make such a big effort is because they already
have the phone.
I actually, you can, there is a page you can visit in Google and listen to all of the recordings
of you saying, okay, Google, and basically see all of you said, I'll record it.
You can have access to it, but they already have that and the reason, and the fact that,
but they're not, but you know what I'm saying, like they're not always listening, you have
to trigger it.
Actually, it does.
It is always listening to the point that you go to the recordings page, it includes the
part that you said, okay, Google, so it meant that it's recording all the time.
It is always listening.
I can set it up where it's not paying attention to me.
Like right now you said it a bunch of times where my phone's right next to my speaker
and it didn't do anything because it's not listening.
Well, but in the case of the home, it is, and same with the Echo, it is always listening
because there's no other way to hear the command word.
Like if I just say the A word in casual conversation, it triggers her immediately.
I don't have to say it like Captain Picard talking to the computer.
If I just say, you know, Wes, today I tried the Alexa and it's working pretty great, it'll
just pick it up and start running like crazy and the Google Home is the same way.
However, it's just getting, what it does is it just has like a quick buffer.
It has like a 10 second buffer where it's, yeah, because honestly, if you think about
it, it would be like a constant 800 kilobit stream up if it was uploading everything you
always said to the cloud.
It would.
Of course it doesn't need to always upload, but this is the thing.
When people saying that, you know, we're moving to these assistant oriented world where your
device doesn't need to be a massive computer, have massive computational power, just get
all of the data from fast connection and basically have a huge battery and this is just the device.
And when you include that alongside having self driving cars, Google actually is working
on.
Right.
I don't feel that that's why they don't need to make a huge effort on us because they don't
care about it.
So today at CES, Amazon announced the Alexa everywhere strategy.
So they're building, cancel, they're building it into watches, dish, whirlpool devices.
Volvo is going to do a series of speakers with it built in.
And there's probably other devices.
I think that goes right back to what you're talking about, where like, here are these
companies where suddenly the incentive to work with Amazon on this is huge because they
want to sell them.
They know that, you know, you want to get your refills, you're like, hey, washing machine.
Amazon gives preferential placement to devices that work with Echo.
You've seen it if you've gone on Amazon ever.
You see it.
And so imagine now that one of the biggest, the Walmart of the internet is now going to
feature devices that come with Echo built in and you've got dish enabling Alexa voice
control on its hopper, cancel.
You've got whirlpool connected, whirlpool devices, whirlpool freaking appliances.
Imagine that, cancel.
Imagine being able to bark at that thing to start the dishwasher or just get an update
on how much longer the dishwasher has.
I feel like also for these companies, Amazon is less risky.
Because not only do they get preferential placement, but when you partner up with Apple
or when you partner up with Google, you generally get taken to the washer.
Like, it generally…
And they have their own agenda.
I mean, not that Amazon doesn't, but Amazon agenda you can understand in a much clearer
way.
And the Amazon one is going to sell you more devices.
So that was sort of, I just sort of, in a long-winded way, which was much more eloquently
stated in my vlog video, explained part of why I got one.
And so I feel like right now I'm in the phase of wrap my head around how this damn thing
works with all these devices and figure out like all of the limitations and all the little
like boxes you've got to check.
And then it's like, okay, now that I understand how this consumer product works, how it integrates
with these other consumer products, what their risks are.
Oh, and if you want to know like the monitoring and capturing we're going to do, also check
out that vlog.
Because we're going to be like packet capturing and all that stuff.
Once I get my head around that, then it's time to roll out OpenHAB.
Then it's time to like really like, now it's, I've lived that, I've walked that walk.
Right.
What's the state of the art if you don't care about the compromises?
If you want to build your own secure LAN, don't want to go out to the net, don't want
to worry about all of that stuff, is it possible at all?
Is it ever possible with a device like this?
Is it ever going to be possible?
Is that so possible?
You know what, just one last thing before we move on.
I am shocked at how quickly my son Dylan, who's almost 8 years old, picked up the Echo.
Like he's up in my office right now as we're recording this and he's just sitting there
playing Minecraft and he just casually barks over to the Echo to turn off the fan.
Or play a fart sound.
Yeah, definitely that one.
There is something for, there's sort of like a, there's like a, it lowers the barrier.
Like I had all these devices before that I had control from my phone that I would trigger,
that nobody else had access to, and that's not actually a good thing.
Because now people around me can turn off the lights and stuff like that.
That lets you delegate.
Well, it just lets them get, like when they're up there too, it lets them get control over
their environment a little bit.
Anyways.
And it's a great controlling device.
It is also, yeah, because there's a Simon Says feature and you can just have it, that's
where the magic happens.
So you can Simon Says that thing all day long and it'll repeat it back to you.
There's also, you can have it connect to your phone.
So that's particularly handy too.
It'll connect like a Bluetooth, as a Bluetooth speaker, which is kind of cool.
Wow.
Anyways, playing around with it and I would love to hear the audience's thoughts on it.
So LinuxAction.reddit.com or tweet me at ChrisLAS.
I personally think this conversation's over.
I personally think Echo's running away with it.
It's a solid product and it's one of those products too that people that got it are still
excited about it.
So I think that's all in all.
The barrier to entry is great with a dot.
Yeah, right.
It was 40 bucks.
I think it's still 40 bucks and that's safe experimental levels.
Yeah, that's right.
Something you can easily play with.
Yeah.
Uh-oh.
I think Dylan's in here trolling us.
This is the problem.
I can't find the answer to the question I heard.
Alexa, Simon says, Dylan, don't interrupt the show.
Let's see if she says that.
Dylan, don't interrupt the show.
Dylan, come over here real quick.
Come here real quick.
Come over here and sit on my lap.
You got a couple of seconds to tell people.
Dylan, what's your quick review of the Amazon Echo?
Do you like it?
Yeah.
And what's your favorite thing to ask it?
Alexa, ask for farts.
That's your favorite thing?
Yeah.
I'm not sure what you meant by that question.
Jesus, too bad.
Alexa, ask for farts.
There we go.
This is something that Dylan and I were trying earlier.
Let me do it, okay?
Okay, I'm going to show them.
Alexa, what is the largest state in the United States of America?
The largest U.S. state in the United States is Alaska.
Alexa, how many people live there?
The population of Alaska is about 686,000.
That contextual awareness is pretty powerful.
We've been able to go about three or four deep, I think.
Oh, nice.
Yeah.
Do you have one more thing you want to add before we go?
We're about to wrap up the show.
Did you want to say something?
All right, get in there.
Say it.
Bye.
All right.
It's Dylan's last day of winter break, so he's joining me in this studio.
Well, that's great.
That's actually really cool.
All right, so that brings us to the end of this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
If you've got any advice or thoughts on securing the crazy wild west of Internet of Things,
let me know if you've got any experience with it, too.
What are you doing to lock it down and any open source projects that are helping you
make it more secure?
LinuxActionShow.reddit.com.
It's also where you go to submit other project updates you think we should talk about.
At least do.
And we'd love to have you join us live next week.
We'll do episode 179 on Tuesday.
Go to jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone.
And don't forget jblive.tv is the URL you put in there, where our chat room is, where
you get information about our virtual lug and hang out with us.
We love having all of that.
You can also send us emails at jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact.
And one last reminder, episode 300 of TechSnap, the last Alan and Chris episode, and then
the new fresh Bigger and Better Blood comes in.
See you next Tuesday.
Thanks for joining us and have a great week and Happy New Year!
Oh, you know what we should have mentioned?
The Patch Your Shit shirts have relaunched.
Oh yeah!
Ahhhh!
You know what, Wes?
This is what I get.
This is what I get for not being a salesman.
If I was a good salesman, I would have thought of this.
Yeah, you sure would have.
Teespring.com slash Patch Your Shit.
Check it out.
Spread the word.
I guess we should have said something.
I can't find the answer to the question I heard.
She doesn't ever find anything for me.
Alexa, buy me some shirts!
No, don't do that, Alexa.
Alright, jbtitles.com, jbtitles.com.
Thank you, Mumble Room.
You guys are great.
Yeah, great suggestions.
Really appreciate it.
You're welcome.
We didn't actually, we didn't address one thing that's very important.
I can't find the answer to the question I heard.
What?
What is that?
What did we address?
What's very important about the Echo?
What?
Perverting free software.
Oh, that's true.
Sorry, I didn't understand the question I heard.
She doesn't understand it.
She doesn't understand about free software.
No, she doesn't.
I kind of felt like the reason why we didn't really address the free software angle of
it is because that's kind of a foregone conclusion.
Oh yeah, it's totally not ever going to be.
Yeah, no.
And I think really we've got to wait for the Mycroft.
Yeah, that's probably true.
But Mycroft is still using Google on the back end.
Well, no, it uses whatever you tell it to use.
You can tell it not to use Google.
You can tell it to use Alexa, if you want.
What I meant for the speech recognition.
Remember that time I hooked Alexa up to the Big Sur?
Yes, I do.
They built their own speech recognition as well.
I don't think so.
Just because, yes.
I think they're still using the web service through Google.
Nope.
They built their own.
Alexa cancels 2017.
That's one title.
Dude, this is not duct tape.
This is gaffer's tape.
This is what we use in the studio.
They're working on their own infrastructure so that you don't have to use Google and you
can use whatever you want.
And you can actually self-host their own protocol and their structure.
Chris goes IoT.
Chrysler minivans will run Linux.
Alexa predict cancer.
Cancel.
Farting in 2017 with Alexa.
That's good.
That is good.
Ooh, Alexa engage 2017.
I like the Alexa prediction cancel.
Are you guys still recording?
Yeah.
We're still doing our show.
Oh.
Yeah.
I know.
We do these shows forever, huh?
Oh, yeah.
I told you we'd be done at 3.30, didn't I?
Yeah.
Jeez, well.
You know, it's Wes.
He just talks so much.
You just can't get me to shut up.
Oh, Simon says the spiders are coming.
I don't have you hooked up to it.
Richard Stalmazan.
That's a pretty good pizza, dude.
I like it.
He won't like it.
No.
What does he like?
Emacs, mostly?
Yeah.
That's the first one I was gonna say.
Don't say the A word.
That's pretty good.
I like that, too.
Dot the cloud of things.
Chris has gone full retard.
Fair.
Big sister is watching you.
That's pretty good, too.
Yeah, that is pretty good.
Big sister.
I like that.
Dylan, unplugged.
Boy, I feel like this is the hardest year to do predictions ever, and it's not because
I know, I know, I'm a horrible person.
Aren't we all?
That's what we've learned in 2017.
Alexa, cancel 2017.
2016 is proving that anything can happen, so we're just like, okay.
Yeah, I suppose so.
I don't know.
Do you like Big Sister is Watching You?
I mean, it might not be the best title.
Should it just be Big Sister is Watching?
Oh, maybe.
Alexa, you're big sister.
I can't find that skill.
To find skills, go to the skills section of the Alexa app.
Oh, they actually got a skill, too.
Interesting.
Ask for cards.
Sorry, I didn't understand the question I heard.
What's great is you can turn that skill off.
That's great.
Ask for cards.
Sorry, I didn't understand the question I heard.
He is determined to get a fart.
Yep.
I mean, we've all been in that position.
Ask for farts.
I found a few matches.
Do you mean for a fart?
Fart sound jokes.
Or fart detective.
Ooh, what's that last one?
Alexa, fart sound jokes.
What is that?
I can't find that skill.
Alexa, what is a fart detective?
Sorry, I didn't understand the question I heard.
Gotta control your laughter there.
Alexa, ask for farts.
I'm not sure what you meant by that question.
What is a fart detective?
Find who dealt it?
Is that what it is?
I like how calm she is, though.
I'm going to start, hmm, I don't know what the answer to that is.
Not that I should know.
There you go.
You got it.
Yeah, that's the Alexa.
Don't you want one now?
Yeah.
Can I give one to Wes?
You gave a fart to Wes?
No, let's give...
Give a dot to Wes?
Wes, you should get a dot.
I should get a dot.
You know, one thing the Google thing has going for it, I will say, is Google Home.
If they could connect all of the...
If OK Googs and Google Home and Google Assistant were all connected...
Yes, that would be powerful.
Yeah.
Assistant is, I think.
Because then you have it with you.
Because this thing, you know, the Echo is only...
If you're with it.
Yeah, if I could have my home then do all the assistant stuff, yeah, that would be nice.
So big sister is watching is now the number one.
They just made an Echo Alexa thing for your phone.
Well, they do have them for watches.
I wonder why they don't make an app.
Yeah.
Oh, speaking of which, you know, earlier you asked for what is a product that Google
made that isn't a failure?
Yeah.
Chromecast.
OK.
I don't know if it's super mass consumer, but it's definitely the biggest hit they've
ever had.
The $35 price point doesn't hurt.
Doesn't hurt.
Yeah, that's a good point.
What is the home selling for?
Like $100 or something?
Or $220.
$120 or $130.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's already back in stock.
It was out of stock in our local Best Buy.
It's the same price as the regular Echo, except Amazon made three versions of the Echo.
So people who don't want to spend the money that would be comparing to the home can get
a cheaper version, and also people who don't want it to constantly listen and get another
version which costs a little more.
So I think that's probably a really good strategy on Amazon's part.
But you know what?
I'll tell you.
The Google Home did sell out, but the Echo, everywhere.
So I had a couple days off before Christmas, and I wanted to get them in the studio.
And I literally called every store, everything from Best Buy to Sears to Bed Bath and Beyond
to Kmart and Fred Meyer and Home Depot, I called all of them, and they were all sold
out.
They sold out everywhere.
Five months ago?
I mean, yeah, we talked about it a little bit, but it didn't feel this hot.
Well, Amazon sure pushes it.
Every box comes with Echo stuff all over it.
It's all over the front page.
The stickers, the packaging.
And so I think people have been really aware of it.
So when it dropped from like $130 something to $40, that's a gift.
That's a casual buy it for yourself with no thinking.
Sort of like what they did with the Kindle.
Yeah, right.
If it's like $70, you're like, okay, yeah, fine, I want one.