This is Linux Unplugged episode 164 for September 27, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's changing up the format a little bit.
By throwing your usual hosts out, and taking over by taking calls.
The phone lines are open to be a part of the program. It's a free call, 1-877-347-0011.
The number again is 1-877-347-0011.
So this is a special edition of the Linux Unplugged program.
Typically we meet as a virtual Lug, a virtual Linux group that comes together to discuss Linux.
This week we're going to be changing it up a little bit.
If you listen to our new show User Era, that's a show hosted by Chris, myself, and Rekai the Beard.
We talk about everything. We talk about life, and technology, and Linux.
Last week we were having a discussion about how we could improve the network.
One of the things that came up is, for the longest time Chris has wanted to host, or at least have the network host, a call-in program.
One of my long-time passions for a long, long time has been, I want to help people get started with Linux.
You see, back in 2009, December of 2009, that was a big year for me.
Les Brown, the Breitmotivator said, people change when they say, I've had it.
I had one of those moments. I had one of those, I've had it moments.
I reached my lifetime limit of how much Windows I could take. I couldn't install one more driver to a Windows box.
I couldn't add one more Windows computer to a domain controller.
I reached December of 2009. I said, I'm done. I'm done working on Windows.
A lot of people said, you're an idiot.
There are practical reasons why Windows needs to remain in the workplace.
If you think you're going to go out and start a company and service only Linux machines and recommend to people that they only install Linux and that they don't ever use Windows on the bare metal, you're ridiculous.
That can't be done.
In fact, the number one hindrance I had to switching myself to Linux and starting a company in Linux is people telling me that it couldn't be done.
People kept saying, you're arrogant.
A couple of years in, it started to work out.
Then people said, you treat Linux like a religion.
You need to be more practical. You need to be more reasonable.
You can't treat operating systems like that.
I think part of me just realized, and it's really in the last couple of years, that that's why AltaSpeed has never lost a customer since 2009.
Because when clients switch to us, they know that we understand it's not just an operating system.
That's where the pictures of your kids live.
That's where the video of your children's birth lives.
That's how some of you make a living.
That's how some of you have entertainment after you get home from a long, hard day of work.
You don't want to fight with your computer.
There are some people that live out in the middle of nowhere, and the computer is their lifeline.
It's their emergency communication.
After years of people telling me you can't start a business on Linux, and after years of people telling me that you're too arrogant and you're too single-minded, you need to be more reasonable.
Now people are asking, how'd you do that?
How are you making so much money installing Linux and switching people to Linux?
How are you doing that?
And so this hour of the Linux Unplugged program, we're not going to have our typical discussion format.
We're going to be taking questions.
You can ask a question by calling 1-877-347-0011, and I'm going to try and answer those questions.
Now, those questions can be general questions about computers.
They can be Linux-specific questions.
They can be business questions.
Anything that's on your mind as it tangentially relates to Linux and open source and business, we'll throw that in there, you can ask.
And if I can't answer the question, if I don't know the answer, we have standing by our Linux Mumble Room, which are the people that usually meet here every week to have a discussion.
So I'll say, hello, guys.
How are you?
Hello.
It's the Mumble Room.
It's good to have you guys here.
Thank you so much for being part of this inaugural program.
Glad to be here.
I'm hoping you guys can help me.
Now, one small little technical issue I'm juggling is that the machine that the phone machine is connected to is actually the same machine that the Mumble Machine is on.
And so I have to bounce between the Mumble Room and our phone lines.
And so hopefully the Mumble Room will be a little patient with me as I make those jugglings.
But yeah, I'm encouraging everyone to call and ask a question or tell us about your experience on Linux or, you know, something that's worked out with, you know, worked out very well for you.
So joining us, starting off is Ben from Louisville, Kentucky, and he has a question about Awesome Window Manager in Arch Linux.
Hi, how are you, Ben?
Hi, how are you, Noah?
Hey, good.
Thanks for taking time to be here with us today.
So tell me a little bit about Awesome Window Manager.
You've been trying that out, I take it.
Yes, and I sent you a pic on Telegram of the error I'm facing.
It's based around Lua, which is a stripping language of sorts.
Yes.
And I have been trying to get this particular theme that I showed you the crash on to work.
I downloaded it from GitHub.
I did a git clone, et cetera, the past main and whatnot.
And when I load up, I keep getting that error over and over and over again.
I contacted the developer of the theme.
He is a heavy as heck user of Awesome.
And he wrote the theme, and I said, you know, dude, can you take a look at this for me?
And he did.
He was stumped as to what was going on.
I was like, oh, okay.
So I was like, okay.
He most likely said it's the piano bar stuff in the theme.
And I opened up the config file, took a look at it, and I was like, okay, what the heck is this?
So, yeah, I'm not sure exactly how to fix it.
So I kind of called in today to see what your suggestion would be.
Sure.
Or Chris's or whoever is hosting with us.
Because truthfully, you know, I looked at that theme over and over again,
and even my friend Jamie tried to come by and look at it, and he didn't know what to do.
So I was like, I don't know if I should look at another theme or, you know,
I just wanted to ask my question because, you know, I haven't dabbled much with Awesome,
and I'm sure you guys haven't either.
But I just wanted, you know, to get your advice and, you know, to see what could possibly be done.
Sure.
And that's what I did because, you know, I just – I've been dabbling with this for weeks,
and I just couldn't figure out, you know, what in the world to do because how – I just, you know –
Yeah, no worries.
Let me ask you this.
Do you have a copy of that script that you could send it – you said you sent it to me on Telegram?
I sent you the picture, yes, but I can send you the GitHub link to it as well.
That's fine.
Yeah, that would be great.
And actually what I might do is I might throw that up into our –
Yeah, are you communicating with me on Telegram or are you in the chat room?
I can send it to you on Telegram.
Give me just one second.
Yeah, no worries.
And what I'll do is I will throw that into the chat room, and I'll have our chat room and our
mumble room take a look at that script, and somebody there might be able to dig in.
You got it?
Yeah, sure.
Not a problem.
Well, I've got you on Telegram, so –
Okay, perfect.
Let me get that over to you, and I'll see what they tell us.
Sounds good.
Well, what I will do is I will – obviously that's going to be a script-specific question, so what
I'll do is I'll throw that in the chat room and see if somebody there can't help you out with that,
and if they find an answer for you, then I will respond to that in Telegram, and of course we'll
post that answer in the show notes of this week's episode.
So thank you very much.
I thank you for the call.
We really appreciate having you.
1-877-347-0011.
That's the number to call.
We're going to answer your Linux questions.
Linux questions, technology questions, or business questions.
All of the above work.
And joining us now is – who do we have here?
We have – we have Roller?
Am I pronouncing that right?
Roller?
Yeah, and I'm Paulson Pfeiffer in the IRC.
Oh, cool.
Well, thanks for being here with us.
How can we help today?
So I'm just calling to see if anyone's using Mageia.
I switched to Mageia when Mandriva died, and that was sad for me because Mandriva was the
Linux that I knew – I grew up on.
So is Mageia still good for Linux?
Let me ask you this.
What are you trying to do with it?
So I was just actually using it as a desktop just to do my office and just documents and
just normal stuff on.
Let me ask you this.
What led you to Mageia to begin with?
So when I was way younger, before I even knew anything about computers, my oldest brother
came from Portland, Oregon, where he was doing his – he was getting his PhD.
So he ran the computer lab up there just voluntarily, and he learned all these different cool tricks
about Linux, and he had a LAN party with Mandriva in Utah, and we had tons of people show up
from, like, Idaho and all over the place.
They showed up at his office, like, his practice for his chiropractor stuff, and they all came
and it was really cool to see everybody, like, not really know very much, and he just showed
up here.
Here's, like, six different DVDs, and we're going to start installing them and see what's
going on and, you know, work through strange issues.
Sounds like a man after my own heart.
So you're basically looking for a general office use kind of a Linux distro.
Yeah, and by using it for general office stuff, I ended up deciding that, you know, I really
want to know what's going on behind the scenes, but I never really had a chance to learn that
before, so when I tried to dig into it, I found FreeBSD and, you know, forked off that
way.
Gotcha.
Well, I'll tell you what I would start with.
I might start taking a look at Ubuntu Mate.
Have you ever used Ubuntu Mate or played with it?
No.
I've just been, I went straight from Mageia to FreeBSD.
Okay.
So I'll start with this.
If you're looking for a general office distro, I might stick with something like Ubuntu Mate
because it's going to be a really nice, stable, clean, very polished operating system based
on Linux, and you're going to be able to do a lot with that, and I'll tell you why I would
choose a Linux distro over a BSD distro.
You know, the BSD guys, they're great guys, and they have a really great competitive product
out there, and I think that there is something to be said about the community, the BSD community,
because they don't bicker as much as a lot of the Linux guys do.
I think they have a much more cohesive product, but a lot of the day-to-day stuff, the reason
it works on BSD is because it's using a lot of the tools that we built on Linux, and then
they're just kind of importing those, and so you kind of shorthand yourself from a desktop
perspective if you're trying to do a lot of day-to-day things on BSD, and I use BSD all
the time in data centers when it comes to things like FreeNAS.
I think it's a great choice there.
As far as a desktop distro, I might look at something like Ubuntu Mate.
Now, if you want to dig in a little bit deeper, if you don't just want to stick the flash
drive in, install, and be done, if you want to dig a little deeper, what you might consider
doing is playing with something like Arch, but Arch can be a little rough to get started
with, and so what I would recommend is taking a look at a distro called Antragos.
Have you heard of Antragos?
Uh-uh.
Okay, so Antragos is a distro of Linux that is – it is essentially Arch.
Arch is basically you build everything yourself.
You choose what the web browser is.
You choose what the file manager is.
You choose what the mail client is.
It doesn't assume anything, and that's great for learning how things work because
you really have to dig in, and you – I remember the first time I used Arch, I had
to load the application that I needed to read a fat file system, and it was just – it
was a very enlightening thing because it was a sobering thing because it was just something
I had taken for granted.
When I stick my SD card in there, I can read files off of it.
Now I have to go – I had to learn about what program specifically allowed me to read
that.
Now the nice thing about Antragos is it holds your hand a little bit.
When you first boot into the installer, it will ask you.
It will say, which of these web browsers would you like?
Would you like Chrome?
Would you like Firefox?
Would you like Thunderbird?
Would you – and yeah, and it kind of walks you through, but it has enough pain that you
have to – it forces you to learn a little bit at a time.
Right.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah.
That's great.
That's what I stuck with BSD for was because I started to find where they were hiding all
the documentation.
Obviously, they have a handbook, so they're not really hiding it, but once I started finding
where they were putting it all, I was like, oh, wow.
Someone's taken a lot of time to write this all down.
I should read it.
Exactly.
Well, yeah.
I would suggest you give Antragos a try.
Take a look at that and see how that works for you.
If you don't mind, if we ever do this again, I'd love to hear back from you.
Either you write in or give us a call back, like I said, if we do the episode again because
I'd love to hear how that works out for you.
Now, on Sunday on the Linux Action Show, we talked about a story from Lenovo.
The story, if you hadn't heard, Lenovo – well, what we reported on Sunday and what actually
happened, there was a little bit of clarity that has now come to light.
That clarity is that Lenovo – as far as the story went on Sunday, Lenovo made a computer
and just basically intentionally decided for it not to run Linux.
I'm assuming that Ryan from Lawrence, Kansas, that is what – I'm assuming that's the
premise of your call, right?
Correct.
Hey, no.
Hey.
Nice to talk to you.
Yeah.
Great to talk to you.
What were your first thoughts when you first heard about the Lenovo story?
Well, first off, I'm a little bit biased.
People should know me from the show.
It's me, Ryan, from System76, but it did really bother me when I considered what the
implications of that Lenovo story were because people started coming out and saying, well,
it's not really Lenovo's fault, it's Intel's fault, and so we shouldn't be raising our
pitchforks and going after Lenovo.
But that story struck me totally different because it means that not a single person
over there gave enough of a shit about Linux users to be like, hey, we should test another
operating system on this.
So let me give you some – let me give you some clarification, see if this changes your
opinion at all.
What was reported on Sunday was that Lenovo made a computer that simply didn't work
with Linux.
In fact, what it actually is, Microsoft came to Lenovo and said, we want you to custom
build us a laptop that meets these specifications.
We want better battery life.
We want better performance.
We want better cooling.
We want software RAID.
We want all these things.
And Lenovo said, okay, and took one of their existing model computers that you can buy
at Best Buy and install Linux on and it will work fine, and they took that model and they
called it the Signature Series and customized it for Microsoft, gave it to Microsoft, and
then Microsoft sold it through the Microsoft online store.
That specific computer has AHC turned off by default and so you can't install Linux
on it.
So my question is – my question back to you is, is that really what we're that upset
about is that a computer custom built specifically for Microsoft and sold only in the Microsoft
store and an alternative that is the exact same model computer but is more widely available
and that one is available to install Linux, do we really have that much ground to be upset
about?
I think that my feeling on it is pretty straightforward.
This is only a problem because people who wanted to run Linux bought a computer and
they just assumed, you know, Lenovo is a good brand, in the past I've been able to install
Linux on their machines fairly easily and so I'm going to buy it.
I see where you're coming from.
It does kind of bother me though that there's a – I guess if it's made to run Windows,
well that's – I guess that's perfectly fine, you know, it just – since the revelation
I would hope that it's updated to say, you know, something along the lines of somewhere
in the documentation will not run a Linux operating system.
Yeah, I mean I think that buyers have the right to be informed for sure and I definitely
I thank you for the call.
I think that they have the right to be informed.
I just – I question if – and I'm the first person to say that everything should
run Linux.
If I bought a computer it's running Linux or I'm not buying it but I think when you
go so far out of your way to make such a niche system for such a niche purpose, I feel like
there is just – I just have a hard time getting completely bent out of shape and maybe
that's just me.
Maybe I need somebody to switch me more to Linux, make me more hardcore than I already
am.
Frank is with us from Stanford, Connecticut.
Hi Frank, how are you?
I'm good now.
What's up?
Hey, thanks for calling in today.
How can we help?
So sort of two questions but different.
First one, so over the years I've collected enough hearts to sort of want to build a storage
server.
Got the easy part done.
A bunch of hard drives.
Kind of need a controller for them and I know that's the tricky part especially if you're
looking at CSS.
So I'm trying to figure out how to pick the right, you know, hard drive controller,
host host controller for about eight spinning disks, pair each like they're western digitals
but yeah.
Sure.
So you're looking to build an entire file server?
Yeah and I've sort of got it in my head that quite possibly it may end up serving duty
also doing VM work but main purpose is file server.
So I already have a chassis and hard drives.
So the chassis already had a motherboard but it's still old so I'm going to replace it
anyway.
Sure.
But my big one is like well I've got eight drives and how the heck do I get them, you
know, talking to the motherboard and patch experiences, you know, get a dedicated card,
you know, something that hopefully doesn't do RAID or at least presents the drives to
a problem with ZFS so it presents all the drives to ZFS and it can do its, you know,
wonderful magic.
Well I'll tell you what I did, Frank, is I had a, I just, I actually just got that building
a file server in December and what I ended up doing was I bought a case that actually
had a hard drive controller built in.
Now as you pointed out, that backplane that connects all the drives then reports as individual
SATA drives to the motherboard so there's a little PCI card that goes in the motherboard
and that connects to this backplane and then those drives go in and then they're reported.
Now there's a couple of nice things about that setup specifically.
One is when I was looking for a motherboard I could just shop for the best possible motherboard
and as long as it had a PCI slot I didn't have to count SATA ports.
The second thing that's really nice about it is because all of the hard drive controlling
mechanisms are handled on the chassis itself and on the controller itself on the case,
I can do things like hot swaps.
I can pull the drive out, put another drive in and let it rebuild, that kind of thing.
And I will find, I can find a link for you and throw that in this week's episode show
notes.
Would that help?
That would be great.
Yeah, cool.
Well thank you very much and I thank you for the call.
Really appreciate having you.
The number again, 1-877-347-0011, you give us a call and we will talk about Linux or
business or computers or all three.
We love chatting and this is a super fun program.
Like I said, something a little different but I think it's fun.
I think it's going well.
We're going to have to make some changes to the audio setup I think because of the call
quality and people, as I'm moving on from calls, people are thinking I'm hanging up
on them and of course it's difficult to patch both the mumble room and the callers.
My good friend Sean from Washington is calling.
Hi Sean, how are you?
Hi Noah, how are you doing today?
Excellent.
Thanks for taking the time to call in today.
How can we help?
So I have some friends back in Phoenix and they're starting a company and they're building
a web application.
It's going to be on Linux, use open source like Django and Ansible.
My question would be what kind of business or technology advice would you want to give
them like small business just starting up that you wish you could have given yourself
when you were first starting Alterspade?
I'll tell you the first thing I would tell myself is grow slowly.
I actually – I probably erred – at first I erred too far on the side of growing too
fast and then I erred I think a little bit on the opposite of that of growing too slow.
So I'd say just take it one step at a time.
The practical ramifications of starting a business are pretty simple.
You can open up a checking account in your own name using your own social security number
and you simply open the checking account with letters DBA, that means doing business as
and then the name of whatever you want to call your company.
What you do is every time you do work or any time profit comes or any time money comes
in from that business, in this case web application, you put the money into that checking account
and the only checks that – and all the money from the business goes into that checking
account and only business expenses, only things that are directly payable from the business
come out of that account.
Then at the end of the month what you have left by definition is profit and so you can
take that money home.
You set aside a quarter of that to pay your taxes with and now you have money to spend.
That's the practical tactical part of getting the business up and running.
Now as far as advice like big picture type advice, one is I would stay away from any
sort of debt.
Debt in business is super, super risky.
Business going into business, small business in and of itself is risky and so going into
debt while you're going into business is all the more risky.
The second thing I would say is the more you can increase your profit margin, the more
you can get the spread up, the better the business is going to be.
One of the ways that I have found to make AltaSpeed remarkably successful and why our
profit margins are larger than many of our competitors is because we leverage very cost
effective technologies and so instead of buying a $10,000 Cisco IP phone system, we are running
free PBX and we have inexpensive SIP compatible standard phones that I bought used off of
eBay and open source and Linux is a really great way to increase that spread, to increase
that profit margin, you can gain a lot of traction if you leverage that software that's
available to you.
Another way we do it is we don't buy Microsoft Office.
We don't own a single copy of Microsoft Office.
We don't own a single copy of Windows 10 and so every computer that we issue to an employee,
we're not paying that license fee.
We're not paying that yearly fee to Microsoft.
We're using LibreOffice because it can do all of the things that Microsoft Office, whether
or not people want to admit that and so we do and all those things together have added
up to a significant spread in our profit margin so we're fundamentally able to make more
money and the third thing, if there's only one piece of advice that anyone would listen
to me from business, it would be make sure that you're putting a tremendous focus on
integrity because if customers see you serving them well, they are more than happy to write
you a check for appreciation.
If you go into it with the heart of I just want to make a lot of money, I just want to
do a lot of things to make a lot of money, that's where I see a lot of people get themselves
into a hurt because you start to lose sight of what's really important, that is you want
to be helping and serving other people well.
Does that answer your question?
I think I'll…
Absolutely, that was really helpful.
Cool.
And thanks again for calling in.
It's really great to talk to you.
Sean and I met actually in a hotel at like three in the morning.
It was at Linux Fest Northwest a couple of years ago and we just started talking about
Linux and Sean is a great guy and has a very successful career in Linux and we've been
friends ever since and so it's really good to be able to chat with him for a little bit
if you caught the familiarity there.
Who do we have here?
Frank from Canada.
Hi, Frank.
How are you?
Oh, hey.
This will be our first international call.
How can we help today?
Okay.
I bought a new computer finally about a year ago, an i5 with a 970 Strix Asus video card.
In short, when I install NVIDIA drivers, the reboot goes from about 15 seconds to about
three minutes.
I've tried this on Kubuntu 16.04, Mate and Neon.
Does it sound familiar at all?
It does.
It sounds very familiar.
I'll tell you what.
I have not had any luck shorting the boot time with Ubuntu.
I had a very nice, very powerful Linux laptop and I had the stock driver, just regular driver,
and that thing booted in like four seconds flat.
I mean, it was incredible and I think part of that was it had an M.2 drive in it.
I loaded the NVIDIA driver on that thing and it slowed down to probably, I mean, at least
30 seconds, if not more, from a cold boot.
I mean, it was absolutely unbearable.
Part of it is I didn't care a whole lot because I'm not one of those people that shuts his
laptop down.
I just close the lid, let it go to standby, and then I bring it back up.
Lately, actually, with 16.04, there's actually a new bug.
If you have a Skylake machine, there's a bug with the NVIDIA driver where if you try to
encrypt the hard drive, you can't use the NVIDIA driver, it just won't boot.
It gets to the desktop and then it just, you get that little brrm and then you try and
log in and then it just goes back to the brrm and you can't log in.
The only luck I've had with getting faster boot times and using the NVIDIA driver is
using Antragos.
Have you ever heard of Antragos or played with it?
Yeah.
No, never played with it though.
Okay, so...
Is this exclusive to 16.04?
As far as I know...
I've got a 14.10 machine and it reboots like, quickly split.
Yeah, I don't have any 14.10 machines.
I have a 14.04 machine, that same thing, it's very fast.
As far as I'm aware, it's a 16.04.
Here's another thing you might try.
A lot of the issues that I've had in 16.04, namely wireless, because we all know that
wireless doesn't work in 16.04, have been actually fixed by Ubuntu Mate.
You might try Ubuntu Mate and see if that doesn't fix the NVIDIA driver problem.
I don't actually have...
Most of my Mate desktops are machines that are a little underpowered and so that's why
I'm using the Mate desktop to begin with.
I don't have any NVIDIA cards that are installed in any Mate boxes, but I would give that a
shot.
I would give Ubuntu Mate a shot and see if that doesn't fix your problem.
If that doesn't fix your problem, then I would start looking at Antragos.
As I was explaining to a guy earlier today, Antragos is basically as easy to use as Ubuntu,
but has all of the power and stability and flexibility of Arch.
Does that help you?
So you're using YUM instead of APT?
You're using actually Packer, P-A-C-K-E-R, instead of APT or YUM.
The command line syntax is a little bit different because there are flags.
For example, when you go to install, like if you're installing on Ubuntu, it would be
apt-get install Firefox.
In Antragos, you would type something like packer-s and then you would search for something
like Firefox.
I'm sorry, small s, capital S will search, just a small s will install.
You can actually...
I have a cheat sheet.
If you head over to jupiterbroadcasting.com, click on the contact link up at the top bar,
and click on Ask Noah and shoot me your contact information so I can get in contact with you.
I actually have a little cheat sheet that I use when I first started using Antragos
on the how do I get commands going, how do I get things started, how do I install things,
how do I remove things, those things.
I'd be happy to send that over to you if it helps you.
Okay.
So I just find that on the Jupiter Broadcasting website?
Yep.
jupiterbroadcasting.com, up at the top, click on contact and then Ask Noah.
Now he brought up something kind of interesting.
We were talking a little bit ago about 16.04 and computers that don't run stock, aren't
designed to run Linux, and so they've had all of these little weird things.
One of the things that I should have asked Ryan about this while he was there because
he works for System76 is they have some pretty amazing machines that just work right off
the bat with Linux.
And so they actually, my Oryx, even though 16.04 is problematic, they were actually able
to fix a lot of that, and it is super appreciated, and that's not even a sponsor spot.
That's just how cool they are.
They just do that thing all on their own, and it's amazing.
Okay.
Let's see here.
Who do we have here?
Next, we have Eric from Indianapolis.
Eric, welcome to Linux Unplugged.
Hello, Noah.
Great to talk to you.
Great to talk to you, too, sir.
How can we help?
So I'm a fellow podcaster myself, and I want to start starting it back up, and I want to
do some interviews, kind of like what you guys have been doing, and I've heard great
things about podcasters, so I want to give that a shot, but I also wondered if there's
an easy way to share my desktop with the person I'm interviewing so that we could like go
over some websites or some programming code, and if Meet.jitsi might be a good fit for
that.
Yeah, actually, Meet.jitsi has a screen sharing app, so there's a couple different ways you
can tackle this.
The first way is a lot of people use Hangouts.
Now, they've discontinued Hangouts on Air, but to the best of my knowledge, that regular
Hangouts is still a thing, and there's a disproportionate amount of people that are doing internet communication,
voice communication, video conferencing over Hangouts, and that is perfectly accepted.
Basically, what Chris does, you have to understand something about Chris, guys.
Chris goes and finds whatever everyone else is doing, and he says, how can we do it just
a little bit better?
How can we get our video quality a little bit higher?
How can we get the audio quality a little bit higher?
It's that little bit of extra silver lining, which is why Jupiter Broadcasting remains one
of the largest, best networks out there, and I'm just getting messages, yes, regular Hangouts
is still a go, so that's one way you can do it.
The second thing you can do is Meet.jitsi, which does have a screen sharing ability.
Now, I've not tried it myself, but everything else in Meet.jitsi has worked so well that
I'm going to go ahead and stick my neck out for them and say that I bet it will work just
fine.
The third thing you can do, and how we do it at Jupiter Broadcasting, is there are these
small little USB devices that you can buy from a company called Madwell, M-A-G-E-W-E-L-L.
They're about $300, and they're on Amazon, and basically what it is is an HDMI capture
card that plugs into USB natively compatible with Linux.
It actually presents itself to the system the same way a webcam would, a video for a
Linux device, V4L, and the nice thing about that is you can pull it into any piece of
software you want.
You can pull it into OBS if you're doing podcasting, you can pull it into VLC and record,
you can pull it into, I mean, you name it, if Linux can see it, you can pull that device
in.
One of the things that I have done is if I am conferencing with somebody, I will take
my laptop, which has an HDMI out, plug the HDMI out into the Madwell in, plug the Madwell
back into my laptop, and now one of my second display, quote-unquote, becomes a captured
thing that I can send out of a Skype window or through OBS or through Hangouts or whatever.
It just becomes another video input.
So that might be something you could take a look with.
Any one of those three sound like they might work for you?
Yeah, definitely.
I think the Meet.Jitsi one might be the simplest.
I think my question was I would have to make sure that they're on mute on Meet.Jitsi so
that Zencastr doesn't have a conflict with that, right?
Yeah, both of them you can shut off, various parts of it, so you can disconnect, you can
turn off your camera, you can turn off your microphone or whatever, so you can kind of
pick and choose which parts you want to pull from various services, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, I think I'll try that first, but then if that doesn't work out, I like the idea
of having the hardware capture device, and my primary device for recording it would
be a laptop that's ironically a Lenovo ThinkPad even after all the crazy crap that's happened
with Lenovo lately.
But it's been a rock-solid laptop for recording.
I was able to take it to a conference and did some interviews there on site with a lot
of the equipment that you guys have recommended, like the Electrovoice microphone, the PreSonus
USB mixer.
It's been really well done, so thank you guys for recommending such great hardware.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'd appreciate it.
Thank you very much for the call.
I appreciate having you.
I tell you what, those PreSonus stuff, that's what I'm using right now.
I have a RE20 and I have a PreSonus audio interface, and that thing is sweet, absolutely
sweet and works very, very well and is actually pretty cost-effective, all things considered.
We've gotten to a point where you can get a pretty decent audio setup in almost no time
at all.
One of the things I was doing was a couple of days ago, I was on Facebook, and this guy
is challenging me to switch him to Linux.
He's kind of like taunting me.
And eventually, it got to a point where I said, listen, I drove all the way to West
Virginia and that guy was already switching to Linux.
And so if you think I won't come to wherever he is, I won't tell you where he is, but if
you don't think I'll come to, and then I said his location, then you're dead wrong.
And joining us right now is Chris from West Virginia.
Hey, Chris, welcome back.
Hey, Noah.
How you doing?
Long time, no talk.
How have you been?
How's that school going?
How are those kids working out?
All those kids are surprising me every day, how fast they take to it, what they've done
with it.
And the high school has already purchased, well, they've already got the purchase order
going to purchase the machine so that we can start doing it there.
That's awesome.
So I'm really excited to see what those high school kids can do because they are just,
what they do with what they've got, if you recall, seeing what they had.
They do amazing things with what they have.
When they get OBS and Linux going, they're going to knock the socks off of me, I'm sure.
That is definitely awesome and thank you very much for what you're doing.
How can we help today?
Well, I actually have two questions.
The first one is really small, if you don't mind.
From a business standpoint, you know that I'm trying to start my own and that seems
to be moving right along.
How well does Simple help scale when you're talking large number of computers, say multiple
thousands?
Do you have that many?
Have you seen that?
I have not used it at the scale of thousands.
I will tell you that their sales team seems to have no concerns selling it as a large
scale solution.
So I certainly wouldn't be hesitant.
I'll tell you, if I was really worried about it, if I had like 10,000 people and I absolutely
had to have control of all those computers, at some point it does make sense to go and
take another look at TeamViewer.
Neither of them are open source.
I don't think you're really giving up a whole lot one way or the other.
My memory serves, the way that TeamViewer licenses is per technician.
So I think it's kind of expensive, it's like $1,500 or $2,000 or something like that.
But you could install, theoretically, and at least my understanding is you could install
all 10,000 computers on TeamViewer, you would just be the only one to control it.
So the cost goes up as you have more technicians, not necessarily as you have more clients.
Does that make sense?
Yes.
To toot my own horn and say I'm going to have thousands, that's, yeah, I'm shooting for
the moon there.
I don't know about that.
But I think that as you get into it, I think you're going to find that if you go out there
with the right attitude and you serve people well, and you're willing to charge a fair
price and do good, honest work, I think you're going to have people flock into you.
I would not be surprised if you have a thousand people that you're going to need to support.
Well, I do support somewhere in the neighborhood of 7,000 computers in the county school system.
Exactly.
We have a proprietary Microsoft thing.
The second question, from your standpoint, how do you convince a business owner, let's
say you've taken on a new client and he's a small business owner, I don't know, say
five machines.
And from your perspective, how do you convince him that Linux is a better a better fix for
his business?
I mean, you and I, and most of the people listening obviously, know that it's probably
the better choice.
Sure.
But if I'm a small business owner and I've been using Microsoft and QuickBooks for five
plus years and it's just working for me, and you present this to me in my eyes, oh my goodness,
I've never heard of this, this could possibly destroy my business, I don't know what makes
that sale.
So what I do is I approach every client with the assumption that the client is smarter
than I am and they know better how their business works than I do.
And then based on that, what I do is I make my sale catered around what is going to benefit
them and what is going to be in their best interest.
Now, I'll stop and tell you, I don't waste a whole lot of time trying to, my grandma
used to say those who are, what's the phrase, those who are convinced against themselves
remain of the same opinion still, something like that.
You can't, if somebody is dead set against something, sometimes you're just not going
to convince that person.
They want to be stuck in the mud, they want to be ignorant, and sometimes you're just
not, there's just not much you can do for those kind of people.
And when we do initial consultations, consultations, seems like that sometimes, when we do initial
consultations, one of the things that we mandate from our clients, and I've turned clients
down for this, is they have to be willing to allow us to make technical decisions where
we feel strongly see it fit.
And you know, if I am not, I am not going to be someone's paid monkey hands.
If you want somebody to walk in there and just do the work that you want, you want done,
there are plenty of companies that'll do that.
That's not us.
We craft solutions for people.
We craft cost-effective solutions without compromising quality.
That's what, if you call our 1-800 number, that's the message that we'll read.
It'll say we provide innovative solutions without compromising quality.
We take the same quality that you would get from a Wirecast machine with a $4,000 Mac,
and we will build the exact same quality machine.
It might look a little different, might behave a little different, but you're going to
get the same result, except we're going to do it with Linux, and we're going to do it
for a tenth of the price.
And if you don't want that kind of solution crafting, we are not the right fit for you.
So to some degree, you have to decide as a business owner, how do I want to sell myself
and what kind of clients do I want to work for?
And then once you have that decided, then you go in and you start looking at the advantages
to them.
So I'll give you an example.
We had a church that was broadcasting using a, it wasn't Wirecast, it was an alternative
software, and basically we went in and said, hey, listen, you're doing this wedding.
This is coming up in a couple months, and you're going to be using this software.
And the problem is, this really isn't up to being able to switch cameras.
It didn't have enough horsepower to handle the amount of video inputs we wanted.
So, you know, we can throw together a box for you for a tenth of what you paid for that,
and we'll be able to stream that out.
You'll be able to stream 1080p because they were using standard definition.
You'll be able to use USB cameras if you want like a camera angle of the drummer, you want
a camera angle of the worship team or something like that.
It's going to be really cheap to get additional camera angles.
Plus, we can take your existing video camera if you want to use it, it's SD, but we can
apply it, we can use a converter and pull that in because that lens shot all the way
down the sanctuary and hit the podium, and they spent a lot of money on it even though
it wasn't HD.
Really, people aren't watching to get high video quality, right?
They just want to see the service.
In this case, it was these people were getting married and they wanted their family to be
able to watch from the East Coast.
And so we said, we can do all that in a much more cost-effective way, and we will increase
your ability to grow and expand.
And that resonated with them because then they saw and they said, oh, we could spend
less money and we could get more, and that's something that any business owner is going
to understand.
And you have to remember, for the most part, businesses are actually easier to switch than
people are to Linux.
They really are.
And the reason is because businesses have a common denominator, and that is their bottom
line.
At the end of the day, they just want to make money.
I have yet to meet a CEO, I have yet to meet a president, I have yet to meet a general
manager that really cares what software is running on his computer.
What he does care about is that that stupid thing stays running 24-7, that those employees
know how to use that computer system, that somebody is going to be available to him when
something goes down and get it right back up, and that that machine is going to function
in their environment.
And if it meets those four or five criteria, I have yet to meet a business owner or a business
manager that really cares one way or the other.
And so, we actually just got done doing some kiosks, actually, and this might be a Runs
Linux this coming week, for an amusement park that needs to sign these liability waivers.
It was an easy sell for Linux because the cost of buying an actual computer with a Windows
license and site kiosk on top of that was going to be $700, $800, and to be able to
do that with Ubuntu Mate, a Firefox in kiosk mode, and Intel Nux was a tenth of the price.
So my suggestion is, and I thank you very much for the call, my suggestion is look at
what the business is going to benefit from, what things, if you were that business owner,
the whole moccasin thing works really well here.
Take a look at if you were in their moccasins, if you ran that business, what would make
you want to switch to Linux, and is Linux appropriate for those people?
Because sometimes, you might run into a place where you say, listen, they're an all-Windows
shop, Microsoft, for example, people that work on Microsoft Office, if they came to
me as a client and said we wanted to switch to Linux, we want to use Linux, we want to
see what Alterspeed could provide for you, I would tell them we're probably not the technical
solution provider for them.
I'd be honest with them.
If your job is to support or run Microsoft Office, you're probably not going to be very
happy when I set you down with LibreOffice, nor are you going to be very effective to
your clients.
And so, you know, there are just some situations where people are just stuck in, I want to
do XYZ and I'm going to do XYZ.
Now, don't confuse that with Microsoft couldn't run Linux.
It's not that Microsoft couldn't get word processing and spreadsheet calculations and
PowerPoints done in Linux.
They absolutely could.
They just choose not to do that.
And they make choices that make it necessary for them to run Windows.
But I've yet to ever meet a business that if they wanted to run Linux, that it wouldn't
save them money or save them resources.
Now, somebody I haven't talked to in a while, this name popped up and this is really cool.
Elijah from Idaho.
Hey, Elijah.
How are you?
Hey, no, I'm doing pretty good.
How about you?
I'm doing excellent.
Thanks a lot for calling in today.
How can we help?
Awesome.
Okay, so I've got a couple questions and they're really similar to each other.
On my home network, right now we're just running a super cheap $20 Linksys router that I want
to replace.
Now, I'm wondering, would there be any real difference between putting in a PF Sense based
router or one of those Ubiquiti Aero S routers?
Is there any real difference between like the firewall and that kind of stuff?
So they're targeted at kind of different markets.
PF Sense is a really great solution if you have a very large enterprise and you need
a very large, powerful level or layer three device, edge device that's going to do something
for you.
In those cases, PF Sense make a lot of sense.
I have a couple of concerns with PF Sense.
The first is I try to stay away from computers when I can, as weird as that sounds.
But traditional x86 computers that aren't appliances, like actual computers that are
just being purposed for something, even if it's by a company, I've never had an appliance
like device fail.
I've never had a router fail, never had an access point fail.
I'm sure they do, but at the scale that we work at, I've just never seen it.
I have, however, had servers fail all the time, especially if those servers have spinning
disks in them.
I've seen them fail a lot.
In fact, you basically count on it.
We actually swap all of our spinning disks.
And so the idea that I would take my entire network and base it on a single device that
I know is, especially if it has a spinning disk, I know is going to go out in a couple
of years, that has always made me very nervous.
The second thing is that you can't buy a PF Sense for more than a handful of manufacturers.
So a lot of people just end up building them themselves.
That's not a bad way to go.
And I have a file server that I built myself and put FreeNAS on, so I suppose in that regard
it's kind of the same thing.
But you have to remember, when your edge device goes down, you have taken a lot of stuff out.
So then that brings us to Ubiquiti.
Now, Ubiquiti makes great stuff, and we have a ton of Ubiquiti stuff, and I love Ubiquiti.
I can't say enough good things about Ubiquiti.
It's amazing.
All that said, the things that I like about Ubiquiti are that they are heavily centrally
managed and controlled, which when you're managing a lot of sites is very, very helpful.
When I think about my edge device, I mean, everything that passes through my network
is eventually, if it's leaving, the network is going through that edge device.
And so I become very, very picky at what device I'm going to essentially trust to keep my
network safe from outside intrusions and allow any of my personal traffic, encrypted or otherwise,
to leave through it.
And so a device that is centrally managed and a device that goes up to this controller
and stuff, that has always made me a little bit nervous.
Now, I understand that the newer versions of the edge routers, they can function completely
autonomously.
I can play with one, I think, itself.
And it's just a little web interface and you can control it and do everything that way.
And so it's definitely not a bad way to go.
Personally, I have invested so much time and effort into Microtech that I have a hard time
dragging myself away from those.
You can get RouterOS as a standalone distro and play with it and learn it.
And then you can go buy a $35 router that has all of the features that the enterprise
grade ones do, and then some.
And then when you decide you need to move up and you've learned that interface and you've
learned the web interface or you've learned the command line interface or however it is
you want to manage it and you want to move up from that.
Now you can go buy a $10,000 Microtech or whatever the largest one is, as a 4U monster,
and that is more like a computer thing, and you can go put that in some large business.
But guess what?
You're still using the same web interface that you used on the $35 one, the same web
interface, the same CLI interface that you used on the distro that you just loaded into
VirtualBox.
And that is very compelling to me.
I don't know if either of those, I don't know if I made a very good case for it or not,
but does that kind of answer your question or does that give you some insight or some
things to think about?
It does.
That's great.
Thank you.
And one other real question that's pretty similar is a local business hired me on as
their tech guy, and it's a local small business and they need to make sure that their network
for that business is secure.
And along with that, the guy wants to become PCI, I think it is, or PCI compliant.
And so would a microchip router that you're talking about, would that do that for them?
It would.
Basically what they're looking for when they talk about PCI compliance is you essentially
want to have two networks.
You want to have a public network that is giving Wi-Fi to people or whatever it is,
and then you need an admin network that is just for the business.
So we run into PCI compliance issues all the time at hotels.
They have a single network and then they just let their guests go on their Wi-Fi network.
You can't do it that way.
Now there's a couple different schools of thought.
I personally totally separate the networks.
I come in at the CABA modem.
I go into what I call a WAN switch, and so I just plug the CABA modem straight into a
WAN switch.
I take two feeds out of that and I go to two entirely separate edge devices.
I have two microtechs.
I have an admin microtech and I have a guest microtech.
And then from there, those networks are entirely different, are configured entirely differently.
And the thing is, the guest network sits physically outside of the firewall.
So there is no, oops, I had them on separate VLANs, but I accidentally tagged this port
and now they're joined together.
There is no, oops, I had a firewall rule separating these two networks, but I accidentally disabled
it or deleted it because I was troubleshooting.
No, they're two physically separate devices that sit physically apart from one another.
And then the downside is, of course, one is they are paying for two routers.
And the second disadvantage, of course, is that we're managing two devices.
But in the long run, I think that's a way better way to go.
The only downside to doing it that way, or the only problem with doing it that way that
I've run into is every once in a while you run into an ISP that won't assign you more
than one dynamically generated address.
And so then they have to pay for statics.
Typically that's not the end of the world because if you're doing anything remote, you're
going to want static assigned addresses to those edge devices anyway, because if you
ever need to make a change to them, it's really nice, especially in your case where you live
out in the boonies and you're commuting into work, very, very nice to be able to just SSH
into those things and restart them or make changes to them versus having to actually
drive out there.
But most of the ISPs that I've worked with, if you just put in a switch to the cable modem
and it will split out those two connections and give you a dedicated guest side and a
dedicated admin side.
Hey, great question.
Thanks a lot for calling in.
A couple minutes left in the show if you want to call in 1-877-347-0011.
That's the number to call.
And we're talking about Linux and technology and of course, personal life and business.
Now, hey, Ashley from Ottawa, Canada is joining us.
Hi, Ashley, how are you?
Not too bad.
Hey, Nolan, long time listener, first time caller.
All right.
How can we help today?
I'm not sure if it's Linux Unplugged or Linux Action Show.
You guys mentioned that if you know most of what, not obviously as much as you or your
co-worker know, but if you know most of what you guys are talking about, they should be
working with Linux.
I just got accepted to college for CompTIA certification and stuff like that.
They're trying to push Windows and I really just want to work with Linux.
Do you suggest just going to Linux Academy or getting in material and stuff like that
and studying for your certs as a way of getting into Linux itself, like the industry?
Sure.
I think that anytime you look at spending any kind of money, especially something like
college, you have to look at it as an investment.
What you look at anytime we do an investment is we want to look at the return on our investment.
If I buy a laptop for my business, if AltaSpeed writes a check for my laptop, we look at the
return on investment for that laptop.
If we spend $1,000 on that laptop, will it fundamentally enable me to make more money
than it costs thus by returning on its investment?
The answer unequivocally is yes.
The more places I can get work done, the more efficient I am, the more money this place
makes.
That's just the way it works.
We want to look at the return on investment.
If you look at college as a return on investment, you say, how much money am I spending?
I'm spending $30,000.
I'm spending $50,000.
What am I getting for that $50,000?
Well, a couple of things.
If you want to work in large corporate environments, a lot of those places, you want to get your
foot through the door if you don't have a degree.
They'll just ask you, they'll say, what's your after high school experience?
If you don't have something to put on those lines, they don't even look at your resume.
The second thing we can get from college though is real skills that are applicable in the
workplace that will fundamentally make you better at what you do.
I have a degree.
I went to school.
I learned things in school, both on the business side that let me sit down and look at our
books and I can instantly get a picture of what my company is doing, as well as on the
technical side, I learned networking things and subnetting and stuff like that.
When I went into the industry, I could walk in and I already had an understanding of how
some of those things work.
Is that saying that you have to go to college to work in IT?
No, no, it is not saying that at all.
In fact, arguably more people are hired and the preference in this industry is on certifications
and being current because one of the big things that I see that drives people out of the industry
or that doesn't get them hired is people will walk into a job interview, but they'll walk
into a place that they want to work at and they'll sit down there at their, their, their
resume and they'll say, yeah, I learned Red Hat five.
Okay, great.
So we're using Red Hat seven soon to be eight.
What do you know about Red Hat eight?
Well, I don't know anything about Red Hat eight, but I know Red Hat five that's useless.
That's useless to me as me as an employer.
That's a useless thing to me.
I would much rather have somebody sit down at my desk and say, listen, I don't have any
formal education.
What I do have is a passion to learn and I have gone to Linux Academy and I have studied
the material that's there and I am very comfortable in making things happen.
I am very comfortable in achieving the goals that Linux Academy has set up and if you give
me a production environment, I can go out there and I can do the kind of work that you
need me to do and you let me work for a couple of weeks free and I'll show you, I can make
you more money than I cost.
I'll hire that guy in a heartbeat.
In a heartbeat I'd hire that guy.
I can't speak so much for Canada.
I would assume it's similar to the US, but in the US most people are not working for
large corporate firms.
Most people are working for small business and small business cares way more about can
you get the job done than they do about what your formal education is.
So what I would encourage you to do is I would sit down with a guidance counselor at the
school or I would look through some of that material or the courseware and I would say,
is any of this material valuable to me in the workplace and is it something that I can't
get other ways and if the answer to that question is yes and if the answer to that question
is I need to know Cisco networking so that I can go get this job making $70,000 a year
and so if I spend $30,000 I can make $70,000, well that would be a good return on investment.
If you go to college and you say I want to go learn about Linux server administration
or maybe you go and learn about Windows system administration because that's where the next
job is and that's how you put food on the table while you work towards the goal.
Taking a step back so that you can take a step forward in the future, that's an okay
way to go too.
Is that something like because you're a huge Linux enthusiast and I'm the same way but
would you suggest doing that like actually taking the time to learn the Microsoft stuff
just to put food on the table until you can get into Linux industry?
No I guess I wouldn't suggest, I mean I'll say this, I will do whatever it takes to feed
my family before I let them starve so if I mean I'll work at McDonald's before I let
my family starve.
Whatever, that said I think that the paradigm that you have to either work for a company
that uses Windows or use Microsoft products or you won't have a job, I think that's a
false paradigm because so many people are hiring Linux people right now.
In fact we have people from Linux Academy that are coming and saying we want to hire
people from your audience because your audience is smart and talented and we have other employers.
There was a guy just wrote in I think three weeks ago, four weeks ago he wrote into the
Linux action show and he said I am looking to hire some Linux guys and we're dry.
We cannot find Linux guys so can you give me some contact information for some Linux
guys and so I made a plug in here and people that wrote in their resumes I forwarded off
to him.
I remember that show yeah.
Yeah so I mean there are very much people looking to hire Linux guys and they're so
desperate to hire Linux guys they'll even hire them remotely.
They don't even care if you move they just want Linux guys so I think you can easily
make $70,000, $80,000, $90,000 a year working in a Linux career but I guess what I was saying
was if you have to take a step back, if you take one step back so that you can take a
step forward that's an okay thing to do.
You just want to make sure that you're moving in a direction that you're comfortable with
because if you're like me and you don't want to be working on Windows for the rest of your
life and I started working on Linux, I started working on Windows in a help desk and it about
drove me crazy and you don't want to be that guy.
You don't want to be myself 10 years because you about want to kill yourself.
So yeah but does that answer your question?
Yeah it does and yeah you guys are like rock stars to me so keep up the good work.
Awesome.
I enjoy listening to your show.
Well thanks we really appreciate having you and thank you very much for the call.
Just a couple minutes left if you want to get in 1-877-347-0011 let's see here who
do we have here.
I'll tell you let's just stop here and talk about Linux Academy right.
Linux Academy is interesting in 2016 that I would get that call.
I would get the call where somebody is talking and I have to think about it to give them
an answer mind you where I'm asking do you want to spend $15 a month or do you want to
spend $30,000 a year?
And if you spend the $15 a month in about 6 months you have a reasonable chance of obtaining
the same skill set as somebody who spends $30,000 and goes to a liberal arts education
system.
Of course you're not going to be liberally arts educated you're not going to take basket
weaving and music therapy and whatever other classes you got to take to actually get a
whatever else you have to take to get you know the degree but you're going to learn
the same skills and those skills are valuable in the marketplace.
And it gets even cheaper if you are a Linux unplugged listener because we have a code.
If you go to Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged they're going to knock a couple bucks off.
And I have done all of my education in the last two years strictly through Linux Academy
and I'm comparing that to doing actual like Red Hat classes.
I've done both and I know which one I like better.
I like being able to sit in my skippies at night drinking a Coke watching the Linux action
show but that's a self-serving I don't watch myself but watching TechSnap and doing
Linux Academy on my computer in their you know bite-sized pieces.
It's a really valuable way to get an education and I said it on last and somebody was bringing
it up here.
You don't have an excuse not to have a good Linux job.
You don't have an excuse not to be doing what you love.
That's an old quote right you do what you love and you'll never work a day in your life.
Honestly I swear to God I don't feel like I work guys.
I don't feel like I work at all.
I feel like I wake up every morning and I get to go out and play with Linux all day
every day and part of that is because I have the skill set to do it and part of having
the skill set is going to Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged.
And while we're talking about advertisers I'll just tell you something.
It makes me so irritated and sick when I see people that complain about advertisers.
I was listening to a radio show I recently got back into Sirius XM and I'm really following
the political election and in this election or in this show this guy is talking and he
makes this beautiful point about the Constitution this absolutely stellar pinpoint perfect point
about how we need to we need to get to a point where we all agree on the rules to which we're
going to govern society and it just is a beautiful point I just I was so interested in the show
and I was so interested I'm like that's a great point and then he goes have you upgraded
your underwear lately and I went say what you know I did one of those one of those you
know German Shepherd cockeyed you know the tilt the head thing what and I'm like what
what did he just say underwear have you upgraded your underwear lately let me tell you about
underwear blah blah blah and then he goes into this ad and all I could think about was
my god that man just took X amount of dollars and then talked about underwear on his political
show because somebody paid him to do it that is such a weird thing and it is so jarring
and weird that I don't even want to listen to the rest of the program because he's talking
about underwear and it has nothing to do with the program and frankly I don't really want
underwear advice from a guy I'm listening politics which just doesn't make any sense
right if you guys could see I mean you know how valuable Chris's hair is and he pulls
half of it out stressing over which advertisers is he going to take on the network he is he
is anal retentive when it comes to who he will allow to advertise on the network and
it is it is so the process the way that Jupiter broadcasting is does advertisers is so much
different from every other show I have listened to it is unbelievable it is absolutely truly
unbelievable and the way that it works is he goes and finds products and services that
serve him well and that he's been using for years and have provided him great value and
then he goes and says you know be really great if I could go tell the audience that wants
to hear my opinion on technology because let's face it the man is pretty well versed in technology
he spends every waking minute researching reading or trying technology says I'm gonna
go share those opinions with people and because he's not an idiot he capitalizes the heck
out of it because you would do that right if you have an educated formed opinion that
is a positive you know reflection of a business and you're going to go give that that opinion
on air you might as well get paid for it you just that's just that is a that is a basic
fundamental function of business is when you're good at something you don't do it for free
and the fact that people find a way to complain about that is unfreaking believable to me
it is unfreaking believable that people have the audacity to complain about it what's
further unbelievable is that the same people that complain about the ad reads are not the
people that are on the patreon contributing to patreon if you want to not hear ad reads
on the shows then the patreon should be like double or triple of what it is because this
network has to be funded somehow and right now those advertisers are funding that network
and by the way those advertisers are providing an extraordinarily valuable service that you're
lucky to know about I was before I got on this before I walked up those stairs down
this hallway and sat down in this chair to do this show today I was in the middle of
troubleshooting when I've had the worst week of my life this week as far as all to speed
troubleshooting goes because we've had a ton of like nitty-gritty problems that I had that
require my attention and I don't like to do that I like to I like to be the the you know
the manager I like to sit and have the text go out and do the work and then I just kind
of check things off make sure that things are going smoothly occasionally I poke my
head in something that I find fun this week it hit we've been so busy I've had to devote
my energy to fixing dumb little problems that I don't want to be fixing and just before
I got up these stairs and sat down to do this program I had just finished setting up a new
phone server for someone and I didn't have time I didn't have time to go provision an
actual box and set it up coordinate all that stuff and so I took a snapshot of a of a stock
phone system that I have set up with generic extensions and I used their imaging thing
to create a droplet from that image and I had a phone system up and running from start
to finish with the trunks configured the whole nine yards in like 30 minutes I mean it was
absolutely unbelievable and using the code do unplugged you're going to get ten dollars
off your Linux rig so in this case is a five dollar rig I'm gonna get two months of that
file server for free or I'm sorry phone server for free I won't even pay for it the fact
that I'm telling that the fact that we have to explain why this is valuable to you that
you can I'm charging that client by the way seventy five dollars an hour and we build
based on a templated thing so if it to set up a phone system from scratch I don't know
what exactly it comes out to be but whatever that is whatever that time thing is that's
what we build the client and then when we go back if I can find a way to shorthand that
and shorten that up a little bit guess what maximizes my profit maximizes my spread and
I make more money doing that I'm doing and all of those innovations are happening because
of digital ocean not because of anything I'm doing it's because of what they're doing
and I'm able to resell absolutely incredible just absolutely unbelievable so there there's
my rant for for advertising I'll tell you something else too but just before I'm done
I'm almost done but before I'm done my phone I am leaving for I'm leaving for a for an
international trip I'm gonna take my ting sim out I'm gonna put go buy an international
sim I'm gonna put it in my phone and then I'm gonna have phone service wherever I am
because that's going to be because I because ting doesn't charge you for what you don't
use and so you can go to you the the ability to just pay for what you're using the ability
to own your own device is unbelievable and it's the same appeal as Linux it's the same
appeal as being able to own my own computer and doing what I want with it now I've extended
that to my phone I just I it is it just it makes my brain hurt to think about like why
this is controversial why we have to explain this to people why that's not like painfully
obvious that this is like an amazing thing but if you think if you're one of the people
out there that say oh they just do those ad reads because they they pay the network you
are a hundred percent wrong it has that that is that is a very small fraction of what contributes
the it's the complete other way around we serve people by providing them with valuable
information and we happen to find a way to capitalize on that and I'm not done yet I'm
almost done but not quite done yet one last thing the other day I was driving out to my
buddy's house and I were having a conversation about phones and he's talking about how he
bought this phone on on his whatever network and now he wanted to get a different phone
but he wasn't sure if he wanted to stick with the same service provider and he's like well
I'm trying to decide what service provider so I can decide what phone to get and I'm
like that doesn't make any sense dude just buy the phone you want and then put it on
whatever service provider you want you know I'm used to ting he says no I can't do that
this one only activates here this one only activates there and I'm like listen dude here's
what you do you go to eBay and we bought him a Nexus 5 and he got it for like $85 and he
activated that sucker on ting now what I do is I actually keep ting sim cards on me at
all times so I can give them out to people so I end up ting sim card we activate it and
he went over to linux.ting.com and that got him the promo code he was able to activate
his phone on the ting network now the great thing about that is because I know that he's
going to end up sticking with ting because the fastest way to decide to stay with ting
is to go try somebody else and then you realize how much more you pay or how crappy the service
is and then you come back so I if he wants to leave though he's not locked into ting
he can go over to AT&T or he can go to T-Mobile or he can go to you know name a GSM provider
you can go to those those places and then when he either gets sick of paying $190 a
month for his phone service or he doesn't have reception anywhere then he'll decide
to come back to ting so linux.ting.com you'll save a couple bucks and you will own your
device you will own your service you'll only use for what you pay you go on a trip out
of the country you don't use your phone for a couple of days then you don't pay for
those couple of days only pay for what you use linux.ting.com that's all I have to
say about that okay Zachy was on hold but you got you got dropped there and you have
a question about setting up your wireless yes so I'm about to purchase a Toyota motor
home that I'm gonna strip out and redo and I want to make it smart I travel up and down
the coast from Oregon down to Arizona and what I want to do is make it so I can park
like you know like in a Walmart or wherever and hook up to their wireless network but
not have to hook my devices up directly have my own like separate wireless internet inside
the vehicle okay the audio cut out of the last can you give me that last little bit
again okay what I want to do is set up a wireless basically have Wi-Fi boosters on the outside
of the mobile home gotcha so that way I can have my own network on the inside and don't
have to hook my devices directly up to their system or go into the building it gotcha there's
a great device for doing something like that called the cradle point and basically what
the cradle point is is it is a hardware device that connects to a wireless network and then
has its own router built in and then its own access point built in and so basically you
can connect it via hardline or via Wi-Fi to any network you want and all of your devices
connect to it and then it becomes your router and edge device and all that stuff and then
your connection to the internet it can be either wireless or wired it connected whatever
you want so if you're you know you're mooching off the neighbors that would work Chris for
example uses the cradle point in his RV so when he travels from RV park to RV park he
connects the cradle point then to whatever the wireless system is there or if he's parked
at JB then he plugs in but all of his devices inside just talk to that cradle point would
that ends would that would that help you yeah that would help me quite a bit and I just
want to let you know thanks for all you guys do I ended up finding a computer in the dump
and I switched it over to Linux that was like my first step I had an expired Windows card
and then I went and purchased a couple elite books and they're running Linux mint beautifully
so I just want to thank you for all that you do and keep up the good work cool well we
really thank you for the call and I appreciate having you it it is a lot of fun I can honestly
say this might be one of the most fun things I have ever done on on the network is doing
these calls hanging out I love I love answering questions and the thing is people are asking
me for my opinion today and I have to tell you I am an expert on my opinion I I know
everything there is to know about my own opinion it's it's kind of incredible but but this
has been a lot of fun and I really appreciate you guys taking the time to call in and hopefully
we were able to provide some meaningful answers to you I'm gonna take a couple more calls
I'm gonna go to is it Goffin from Chicago no Gorin Gorin hi Gorin how can we help hi
nice to meet you finally over the phone long time listen the first time call I do shoot
you guys an email every once in a while I hope I'm not bothering you too much no no
I don't have a question so I do run a small I think consulting I support local small businesses
use Linux distros made mainly for phone systems and file servers and stuff so I do wonder
what can you recommend is like customer database it doesn't have to be fully open source it
doesn't have to be fully free I'm fine with the you know a small monthly charge so I can
keep track of all my customers and then all the hardware that I have installed at their
network a lot of credentials for servers for searches access points and stuff like that
sure so what you're looking for is is what's known as a CRM or customer relation management
CRM and there's a couple of them out there there's there's also ERPs that are out there
I actually am just it's funny you asked this it really is because I actually was just taking
some time to investigate this for myself basically we have we have breached the end of what I
think we can reliably provide for our for a meaningfully provide for our customers I
think we are serving them as as good as we can possibly serve them they don't have a
need that goes unmet there we have a we have a 120 minute response time and so things are
going great and so my next thing is now I want to help more people I want to expand
out I want to do more remote management I want to I want to do Wi-Fi more hotels and
part of that is going to involve provisioning if you will a sales team I need people that
will go out and sell these products in addition to me because I need to spend my time working
on the actual business and so I need people to continue sales and continue to move the
business forward but I also need to because I'm a control freak whatever you want to
call it I like to keep track of all these things and I like to have a I like to wake
up and sit down in my office and I like to have an idea of at least an idea of what all
of the people that work for this place are doing because after all my name's on the
building I want to know and so I have looked for a CRM and basically what I've come down
to is ZURMO it is an it is an open source CRM that is completely web-based so you could
spin this up on something like DigitalOcean and it would cost you practically nothing
and this will allow you to track your customers track your sales and and so basically what
we are going to use it for is we are going to use it to focus on customers because one
thing you have to you one thing you have to get right there's a difference between serving
somebody and annoying the heck out of them if you if we go into a hotel and they have
crappy Wi-Fi and so they are losing hundreds of dollars a month or thousands of dollars
a month because these days Wi-Fi is just as critical as hot water and we go into that
place and we say for five thousand dollars we will go through and we will increase your
revenue by two thousand dollars a month because you're gonna have that many more guests because
your guests demand Wi-Fi if we can do that that is not bothering somebody that is not
selling the that is not the that you know the the the the stereotype of selling somebody
something it is it's serving somebody and we are taking we guess we're gonna get paid
for our efforts and but we are going to make you more money than than we cost you there's
a difference between doing that and then just cold calling places and saying hi I'm Noah
with all the speed and I want you to buy my Wi-Fi you know that that is not a that is
not helping that just annoying somebody and so there are little things you can do for
example you know you you when you go in and talk to somebody you say well how do I you
know can we follow up can we follow up in a couple of days can I give you a call if
they say yes then you're that does not bothering somebody's not harassing somebody to call
them back two days like you said you were going to do and follow up with them and if
they say we're not interested then you know you move on but we need a way to track who
has been called who hasn't been called because sometimes you walk into a place and you say
I'll do X Y Z and it'll cost you X Y Z and they say yeah that's great and now they're
waiting for you to come in and do the thing that you promised to do and so you need a
way to track that and so that's kind of what we're doing at the CM does that sound kind
of similar to what you're looking for yes I was hoping that I see a web-based CRM would
be the solution I tried some of them and VMs on my VM host at home like the VTiger sugar
CRM and some others but most of them look like way over complicated for for my basic
needs at the moment so yeah I haven't came across dermal but I'll be definitely installing
it tonight and I'll check it out sure yeah check out check out Zermal I think you'll
find that's that's a pretty decent one to go to and it's definitely the one that Alta
speed is going to look at and I will follow up as either an app pick or as maybe a show
episode idea about that later hey if you haven't heard we do this show every week or Chris
and Wes do the show every week this week they're out on location filming interviews so they're
not here so that's why I'm filling in and we would like your I would like your opinion
I would like to know how you thought this show went if you like this segment if you
want us to do this kind of episode again Chris and I are talking about spinning this off
as its own show it would be a call-in show I assume that I've done an okay job hosting
it and that he would let that continue but that's basically what we're looking forward
to and we need to know so head over to Jupiter broadcasting comm click on the contact link
choose Linux unplugged from the drop-down menu and let us know what you think mostly
just as this is a show this is not going to replace unplugged we I sorely sorely apologize
to our mobile room for the I was told early on in the episode that basically they can't
hear what's going on from the from the calls there's no way to tie those in so I need to
have a bigger mixer to make that happen and but we we very much value your contribution
and you guys taking time out of your day to be here and the show will return to its regular
format next week but if this is something that was fun if you had as much fun with it
as I did or you didn't get quite in didn't get to ask your question would like to do
that in the future then drop a contact link and let us know because we would love to do
that I'm the co-host of the Linux action show that's every Sunday mornings at noon on Sundays
that's Pacific time a special thank you to Rekai our video editor Michael tunnel our
producer and everyone in Jupiter broadcasting who makes this show and every other show on
the network possible and we'll see you back here next week.
All right now that that is over I am let's hear to do I didn't here's the thing if I
would have seen somebody from Germany anyone that's calling especially from Germany I would
have taken idea to do here we go Jay hold up let's see what's up Jay Jay from Germany
do I have you me hi I'm sorry I'm glad you said something in the chat room I the thing
is it doesn't tell me I have to I it the way that it works it doesn't go in in any specific
order just kind of goes in the order that people called in and I've got like 15 calls
in 15 calls that I haven't gotten to but we're like we're literally 40 minutes over what
the show is and Rekai still has to edit this thing and get it out so I had to wrap it up
but I will answer your question now that we're now that we're off and I'm done recording
how can we help okay thanks I just wanted to ask how much pain is it changing from one
main Linux distro to another so are you locked in like with Microsoft or is it harder or
less hard because I fear I'm currently locked into the Ubuntu system yes so I you know it's
funny it's it's really interesting you ask that because I have actually just gone through
that this week I have switched from an Ubuntu based distro over to enter goes and what I
have found was that it actually isn't that bad most especially when you go from a very
well-supported Linux distro to another very well-supported Linux distro you don't run
into a lot of pain it you know anything that's available in Ubuntu is pretty much available
enter goes now where it wouldn't be so smooth is if you went from something like Ubuntu
to Fedora I love Fedora I think Fedora is a great operating system I think Red Hat is
the best Linux company out there and if that's not clear let me say that again I think Red
Hat is the best Linux company out there but I don't think that they're I don't think that
they have a desktop offering that that fits exactly what I'm looking for these days and
that is that a rock-solid desktop operating system that's designed for a business class
system that I don't have to do anything with for a couple of years but even knowing that
even knowing that how much I love Red Hat the company and I've been a Fedora user since
version one there are some things that I just never could get to work right in Fedora GNS3
which is a network simulator when I was doing my networking certification would not run
in Fedora so I had to run Ubuntu in a virtual box inside of Fedora to run GNS3 yeah I know
it's ridiculous right that might change now but KVM yeah yeah but five years ago six years
ago that was the case GNS3 would not run Harupad the to the rest of my knowledge it there is
no precompiled binary for there's no there's no RPM or it's not in any repo you have to
extract and and you know and run the the actual binary so if you go to an uns you know a less
supported less used Linux distro you might run into some of that but yeah if you stick
with main distros I don't think you're gonna have a problem at all so no problem switching
to arch not at all now I think you're gonna be fine in fact I think you're going I think
you're gonna find that your your experience is a lot smoother on arch so it's just going
to be a reinstall and copy files or could I do this even in a more or less hot like
state where I install the new system onto the old one well I don't know that you can
cop you know if it's just a folder full of binaries it would it'll probably run and if
you copy over something like your home folder you might keep your bookmarks and stuff like
that in general I would probably expect to have to reinstall your programs and reconfigure
things I don't know that you're going to be able to quite that seamlessly smooth over
but what I guess what I mean is all your programs are going to be available if you have any
database files or or personal files you'd be able to back those up and restore them
without any problem things like your Firefox bookmarks or Chrome bookmarks or something
like that yeah you could move a home folder over that wouldn't be a problem but yeah I
don't think you're just going to be it is possible Google actually swapped their Red
Hat servers for Ubuntu without ever even turning them off they literally swap like one file
at a time yeah yeah and they made a presentation about it and it was wicked cool so it I'm
not saying it can't be done it is definitely possible it's probably ten times more work
than it would be just to back your stuff up and reinstall but I don't think you're going
to find that to be overly burdensome.