We came across a little tool called Sokae, which we will have linked in the show notes,
that looks at your bash history, goes through everything you've been doing on your box,
and generates a pie chart or a bar graph, whatever you like, you have some options,
of your most frequently used commands.
And we thought, this probably reveals a lot about how we use our boxes.
So we're going to run it on our systems here.
We'll have a link to it if you want to try it on yours.
And we're going to reveal our top used commands on our Linux systems.
Do you want to go first, Wes?
Yeah, okay, you can definitely tell that I'm just using the terminal as a file manager,
because my top three are ls, cd, vim, and then followed by cat.
After that, though, there's git and docker-compose, so it gets a little more interesting.
Oh, man, mine are so embarrassing compared to yours.
Okay, all right, well, you can definitely tell I'm into my arch,
because my number one command by like a lot is yay, the package manager.
Well, you have to run it like what, six, 10 times a day to be sure?
You got it.
And then YouTube DL, which is what I use for clips, and then SSH,
which is just me logging into everything else.
This is embarrassing.
Hello, friends, and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
I like the tactical gear, color matched and everything.
This episode is brought to you by the all new aCloud Guru, the leader in learning for the cloud,
Linux and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses, thousands of hands-on labs, get certified, get hired, get learning
at aCloudGuru.com.
Well, coming up on this week's episode, it's our worst idea yet.
I don't know what we're thinking.
We thought we'd have some fun, I guess.
We're going to hand out the login info to one of our servers to our chat room.
And then whoever owns the box first gets a prize.
We're going to have more details later on in the show.
We're going to call it the unplugged hacker games just because we're having fun as we
approach episode 400.
So we have the hacker games coming up.
We have some community news to get into, including how the heck does archive.org actually
run and manage to archive the entire internet and some feedback.
But before we get to any of that, I have one line of duty that I must carry out before
we proceed any further.
And that is to say time-appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, Virtual Lug.
Well, nice to have you all in there.
So I wanted to get into something before we get into the news, and that is just maybe
a call out, a request to the audience, perhaps, as we approach episode 400.
Stay a while and listen.
If you know us, you know that we like to do something to celebrate the milestones like
400.
We don't do it all the time, but every now and then we like to get we like to have some
fun.
And we thought, what could be some ways that we could really enjoy ourselves leading up
to episode 400?
And there's one topic that Wes and I have always wanted to do on the show.
We've talked about it 100 different times, but we've never really found the right partner
to work with, if you will, quote unquote, using that term loosely.
But we've always wanted to do an episode on Linux and brewing beer.
We'd really love to go hands on, if possible.
We'd love to make some episode 400 beer that we drink later on at some point and use
Linux to make it happen.
It's not required that we go hands on, but it sure would be fun.
And we're looking for somebody who's actively brewing beer.
I mean, I've heard from people who have brewed beer, but we're looking for somebody who's
actually doing it right now.
Maybe even has a brewery.
Maybe not.
But somebody we could engage with, learn from, and then maybe share their story on the show.
And if we could end up with episode 400 series beer, too, boy, that'd be a lot of fun.
So we got we got five weeks.
May not be impossible if you or someone you know is actively brewing beer and uses Linux
to make it possible.
Get in touch with us at linuxunplug.com contact or hit us up on Telegram or Twitter.
Or, Wes, I should also mention, if anybody knows how the hell to use the brewery, that
that automated brewing machine, also let us know.
Oh, the brewery.
Yeah, we have it sitting out in the garage.
Technically runs Android, which is kind of Linux.
I've heard that's Linux.
Yeah, it's kind of Linux, right?
Kind of.
So anyways, let us know linuxunplug.com contact or Telegram or the Twitters would be fine
as well.
But looking ahead at something that's also coming just a few weeks out, that's GNOME
Shell 40 and one of the things they're launching in GNOME Shell is fully realized gesture support.
And I thought maybe we'd just zoom in on this one feature for this episode with the gesture
support in 40, you can manage running apps, you can change your workspace, you can bring
up the overview.
It's they've taken the gesture support that GNOME Shell has had for a while and they've
really rounded it out and completed it.
And assuming you're all into that kind of thing, which a lot of people are, there is
one major problem.
It does not work on X11.
There are technical reasons, but it is a reminder of why X11 just needs to go.
Get that out of here.
Get it out of here.
But one clever developer figured out a way to bring these touch gestures to the X11 version
of GNOME Shell and it really opens up the desktop to a quick and efficient way to navigate
the UI.
And so I've decided as I'm kind of prepping my space right now.
I am I am making way for GNOME Shell 40 because I have been a plasma head for a while and
I want to switch over to Shell 40 when it lands.
So what I have done is I have dusted off and I'm charging it right now an old Apple Magic
trackpad because I guess these work pretty well now.
Oh, look at you.
I know, right?
I'm thinking I'm going to do to I'm going to do the two mouse setup.
I'm going to have a regular mouse on my right and then I'll have my trackpad on my left.
It's a setup I've used in the past for video editing and also kind of helps with RSI because
I use my right hand less this way and I can manipulate the UI with my left hand and I can
click and point with my right hand.
So you kind of get the best of both worlds.
How well that Apple Magic trackpad is supported.
That's what I'm kind of wondering if anybody in the Mumble room has tried these before
with Linux.
Yes, I have indeed.
So the trackpad one works pretty well.
Number one.
OK, yeah, I've done pretty well.
What about the new Magic trackpad two?
I haven't tried it yet.
Yeah, but the one works well.
The only thing I have from time to time, it does not auto connect.
So you will have to manually connect it via Bluetooth.
So I was thinking I do wired.
I was thinking because I did read that some people get it working with Bluetooth but get
disconnect issues, but it seems to work 100 percent of the time wired.
I'm fine with that.
This is a desktop.
So that's, you know, and this is I just want to try this out.
And I've recently realized that I am very much a desktop guy.
I really like desktops.
And so I thought about it.
It's like, well, maybe I could just do a few things to take what I like about the laptop
experience and bring it to the desktop and make it even better.
So now I have like a full desktop keyboard and mouse, but I also will have the trackpad
gestures and all of that.
Does that mean you're going to buy like a really bad webcam to add on there, too?
Nice.
I have like a Logitech C920 hooked up, but it is starting to feel old, but they really
haven't surpassed it much.
But you know what I mean, Wes?
Like I'm preparing the way, like I'm getting myself all set up.
I got my monitors arranged the way I'm going to want them for GNOME Shell.
Getting myself ready.
My body is prepared.
My workspace is prepared.
I don't know if this is like a I mean, obviously, there's a lot of really good stuff.
It seems like GNOME 40 has a lot of nice things.
But does this speak a little bit to the GNOME, you know, riding the edge of GNOME experience
that either have to be upset by it or like you're doing, choose to really embrace it
and plan ahead?
Yeah, I'm wondering, Carl, if your thoughts have evolved at all on the horizontal workspace
layout and some of the recent things that the GNOME project like Alan Day made a post
saying where they're they're going to commit to multi monitor support and they're going
to continue to work on that.
Have you have your thoughts on GNOME 40 and and if you're going to stick with the more
traditional layout stuff, is that evolved at all?
I haven't read through all of the updates yet.
I'm still a little skeptical.
I mean, I know they're going to try and work towards it and they're they're listening to
the feedback, at least.
I'll definitely give it a shot when it comes out.
But we time will tell if it's something I can actually get used to or not with the different
different things.
What I've noticed is that every time I bring up, you know, the spatial relationship of
the desktop, they like that they're focusing on the spatial relationship between elements
on the desktop, like the app drawer and the workspace switcher.
But I've been more focused on the spatial relationship between different workspaces.
And those aren't the same thing.
Hello, Poby.
Good to see you.
I don't think I've gotten your take on the GNOME 40 shell changes.
We've been chatting about them on the show, kind of preparing ourselves for it.
I was just talking about how I'm setting up a rig to get ready for it and I'm going to
jump in and try out the new layouts.
What are your takes on it?
Is this is this the time when the Linux desktop is passing you by or are you on board to try
out the new the new changes?
Well, I'm on Ubuntu, so it's a bit difficult to try it out unless I nuke and pave and go
with some other distro right now.
What are your thoughts on that?
So I could give it a go on one of my other machines.
But what I don't think that will help me because what I really need to do is play with it
on my primary machine where I have multiple monitors.
Because like Carl, you know, I need to feel what it feels like using it on a daily basis.
And I'm not there yet because I need to use this as a functioning machine.
I can't really use pre-release software on this right now.
Yep.
I thought about doing the pre-release thing myself, been tempted a couple of times.
We did load it up at one point to just kind of get an idea of what was coming so we could
talk about it.
But I didn't want to I didn't really want to base my whole opinion on it yet.
Well, kind of in this same realm, talking about this this hardware, believe it or not,
in kind of a fixing the barn doors after the cow comes home, traditional open source style,
the Apple Touch Bar on MacBooks may actually see at least a glimmer of hope of getting
upstreamed in 2021.
It's actually happening that that that little touch bar, even though I think now it's rumored
it's going away, we may have at least some basic functionality soon.
Released out on Saturday by independent developer Ronald Sklar was the latest reverse engineered
open source driver code that gets the touch bar and the Apple light sensor support working
for MacBook Pro 13 inch 14 inch and 15 inch models.
Yeah, light support light sensor support is particularly interesting because that's part
of the solution that macOS uses to adjust the screen brightness.
Now the Apple iBridge that T one security trip driver is also needed for interfacing
with the eyesight web camera and the light sensor and the fingerprint sensor.
At the moment, the Linux driver coverage is focused on the touch bar and the light sensor.
Yeah, so no webcam and no touch ID.
But the driver is coming along.
And while it's a slow pace, it means that people who are transitioning to preserving
or archiving these machines or rebuilding and repurposing these machines are going to
have support.
And that I think is kind of nice because as these are sort of probably being taken out
of production with the M one over time now, and it won't be all at once, Linux will be
ready to support the systems that want to stay around and stay relevant.
That's I love seeing that kind of thing.
And unfortunately, that seems to be about where our MacBook support is shining best
these days.
Not so bad, though, really, you know, because if you buy a Mac, you're buying a Mac to run
macOS.
But if you're buying a used Mac, it's really nice to be able to run Linux on it.
It's not an ideal situation.
Obviously, it'd be great if hell, it'd be great if Apple upstream drivers for heck's
sake, Wes.
But you know, as far as a number two, being able to run these machines years after Apple
abandoned them, I think is hugely not only useful from just like an economic standpoint,
but also just from preventing environmental waste.
Now, it'd be very, very entertaining to me if there was somehow a touch bar revolution
on the Linux side of things after the Apple ecosystem wasn't so fond.
Linode.com slash unplugged go there to get a $100 for 60 days on a new account.
That's, that's really remarkable.
$100 in credit will really let you try out Linode and see what it can do.
That's what's great is that kind of shows some confidence by Linode.
And one of the things I think is great about Linode is all of the distributions they support
in a, in a moment, we're going to open up one of our boxes for the chat room to log
into.
And we're confident that we'll have the performance necessary to actually make that possible
because every machine has super fast SSDs, 40 gigabit connections to the internet, and
one of 11 choice data center locations to choose from.
And one of the great things about Linode beyond just the fact that I trust them with our infrastructure
is I trust where they're going long term.
They're independently owned.
They have been since 2003.
That's a big deal if you're going to rely on them for your business or for even your
personal stuff.
And they've really honed in what they do well.
They focused on it and they make it just right.
They do it right.
They do the best virtualized Linux computing out there.
You can try it too and see it, see it for yourself, see how them being in this game
for so long has given them a certain head over everyone else.
Get out at linode.com slash unplugged and get that $100, 60 day credit.
They're independently owned and they're founded on a love for Linux.
And I love that about them.
And we run a ton of our infrastructure on there.
So I can recommend if you need to build a website or set up a backend for a chat system
or maybe run a real time chat app like mumble, Linode is going to work for you.
But even a static website might be the way to go, maybe for a blog or maybe for a resume.
I will toss a link in our show notes at linux unplugged dot com slash 395 to a really well
done write up in the Linode documentation area on choosing the right static website
for you and kind of the pros and cons, the theme options for the different ones and then
a comparison of things like Jekyll and Hugo and well a bunch of other ones and then how
to use them so you can get an idea of what the flavor would be managing it and what front
ends they have to even manage them if they have them.
It's all just kind of outlined for you beautifully and then of course like one click to get these
things going on Linode and with our hundred dollar credit you could try each one of them.
Why not?
I actually one of the first ways I started using Linode and one of the ways I knew I
was going to be using Linode for a long time was I tried out every different combination
of WordPress just boom, boom, boom, boom, boom on Linode tested each one of them, built
each one of them up.
Not only was it a great way to refresh myself on how to use WordPress because it had been
a while but I really got a sense of what performed the best for me and I just kept that Linode.
It was great.
You can do the same thing.
Go to linode.com slash unplugged get that $100 60-day credit and of course support the
show.
We all love archive.org.
It's one of the greatest resources on the internet and it's the home of the internet
way back machine.
It's also a content distribution network of sorts.
You got to imagine it is quite the infrastructure and you've probably imagined if you didn't
know it's running Linux you would be correct on both counts.
I mean don't all the best things run Linux?
It's true.
That's true.
Jonah Edwards is the infrastructure manager at archive.org.
He joined in the fall of 2016 and this is in his bio quote escaping from the world of
online attention optimization to the peace and safety of a techno utopia librarianship
which is incredible and he gave a presentation to the internet archive staff about the infrastructure
you know just to kind of tell the employees how things work and like the awesome people
they are they made the whole thing public and Wes and I watched it and we grabbed a
couple of moments to just kind of tell you how they use Linux and how the archive.org
actually works.
So why don't we do this?
Let's start with an introduction from Jonah himself.
Hey everybody for those of you who don't know me or I haven't had the pleasure of meeting
yet.
My name is Jonah Edwards.
I run the core infrastructure team here at the Internet Archive.
Yeah and you probably suspected but may not have known that they run all of their own
infrastructure.
There is no cloud.
So there's no cloud.
It's just someone else's computer.
Most of us have probably heard this sentiment in some form or another but here at the Internet
Archive that's really really there's no cloud.
It's just our computers in our buildings run by our people.
And he gives us a rundown of what those computers are.
We have around 750 operational servers right now.
We run these things way longer than anyone else does.
The oldest systems in our fleet are from back in 2012.
More than a thousand VMs across the fleet which is probably what those of you who interface
with us directly mostly interface with.
Tens of thousands of storage devices from high performance NVMe flash, SSDs, the spinning
disks underlying the operating systems on the servers, and over 20,000 spinning disks
in paired storage which is the redundant storage layer underlying the Internet Archive's corpus
totaling nearly 200 petabytes of raw storage capacity in the Internet Archive.
200 petabytes.
I mean I knew it'd be a lot.
I knew it'd be a lot.
But you can imagine the growth rate too is a hell of a thing just to even manage.
We're currently growing the Internet Archive by over a quarter of its size per year.
Per year Wes?
Per year?
What?
Imagine what that's like to manage from like a server standpoint, a disk standpoint, a
network standpoint.
And they've recently seen a large jump in traffic in general.
We've had a huge explosion in outbound traffic over the last year with the pandemic, lockdown.
You can see there in March and April of 2020 how we really flatlined just because demand
increased so quickly and so dramatically much faster than we anticipated.
Yeah.
So the pandemic and people at home led to increased use of Archive.org which is interesting
because it led to a big decrease in actual library use but the Archive.org Internet library
saw a huge uptick.
Yeah.
Well it's the safest library out there.
That's true.
And no mask required.
Then he gave us a bit of an overview of the network traffic they see.
This is hard to actually put in this talk because this was an area where he gave some
visual examples and did an overview that was like put up on maps and whatnot.
So we will link to the video so you can see the entire thing.
It's not that long and it's interesting the entire time.
I think it's one of the best virtual talks I've watched this last pandemic year.
And so if you want to check out the whole thing I would encourage you but here's a little
taste of the network infrastructure and even kind of where they're going with it.
We're pushing 60 something gigabits out most of the time right now.
We're currently working on expanding that capacity.
My expectation is that flow will be probably in the 80 gigabit range once we kind of clear
everything out here and then just more from there.
So the inner site links that we do are kind of our current bottleneck.
We run those with a technology called dense wave division multiplexing.
I'm not going to get too into this.
I just think it's super cool.
So I tell people about it whenever it comes up.
We use fiber optics to connect our sites and just like with a prism, if you shine the fiber
optic in different colors, you can prism it together into a single beam of light and deprism
it back at the other end.
Super cool technology.
Anyway, that's my little aside.
What we're moving towards now is actually going to be a full fiber ring between our
sites.
We're going to have 100 gigabit links between all the sites.
We are going to be able to utilize both directions of the fiber ring simultaneously, giving us
kind of 200 gigabits of bandwidth in both directions.
Of course, if we use the whole thing, then we're not going to get quite the redundancy
of the fiber ring and that's the reason I'm really excited about it.
It's been kind of one of the biggest causes of outages for us, especially long term outages.
I know watching the networking details was your favorite part of the talk with.
Oh my gosh.
I just love the amount of openness here, which I guess sort of makes sense given it's archive.org,
but tons of nitty gritty, tons of nice actual pictures of their somewhat messy networking
stacks.
You actually get to see some of how this really happens.
Right.
It's not so much like the PR photos you see from AWS or Google Cloud, but like their actual
infrastructure, the real stuff, kind of like we're going to get to a little bit later
in the show.
Real infrastructure sometimes has issues, but what I appreciated about this talk was
you could tell the staff understood the value that this infrastructure brings an electronic
archive and Brewster Kahle, the founder of the Internet Archive, wrapped it up with a
real nice moment, actually, where he acknowledged Linux's role in all of this.
And of course, how awesome his team has been at implementing open source technologies to
solve these problems.
We're all built on on Linux and the wonder of open source.
And it's just what a sharing awesome, amazing environment, the whole Linux Ubuntu free and
open source software, the sharing that's been going on.
And then we built the Petabox infrastructure on top of that, mostly in PHP and Python,
to go and offer our services to the world.
It is a really impressive thing that this group has been able to pull off.
Yeah, that was Brewster Kahle.
That's pretty great.
And it's nice to see them acknowledge Linux's role in that.
Yeah, really nicely put.
And with that, we'll just say thank you to Archive.org for everything they do.
And a big, like, love from the show to them because they helped Jupiter Broadcasting do
some of their early distribution.
And I love, love, love the Wayback Machine, some serious nostalgia, but also just great
to go back and see how things have evolved over time.
Well, yeah, I mean, I think especially as we rapidly evolve what happens on the Internet,
that's documenting the culture that exists or doesn't exist anymore.
All right, Wes, grab your Swiffer.
Time for a spot of housekeeping around here.
I did this last week.
It's your turn.
No, we're going to both do it.
We both have the broom.
You know, it's shared.
Gosh, I tell you what, I mean, I don't know where you found this dual handled broom, but
OK.
Wait, wait.
Oh, you missed a spot there, Wes.
Yeah, right there.
Yeah.
Come on now.
Get that.
He's going to get upset with me.
So you go to Jupiter Broadcasting dot com slash Telegram if you want to join the J.B.
Telegram group.
All kinds of reasons.
Not only do you see behind the scenes discussion, but you follow up with us directly.
Additionally, show announcements and when events are happening, you'll generally get
info about them in their Jupiter Broadcasting dot com slash Telegram.
Every single Sunday, our virtual get together outside the show just to hang out and talk.
Sometimes some of the sessions are recorded.
Sometimes it's just to hang out and talk about things you love about Linux or things you
do with Linux or ways to use Linux or learn.
It's a pretty cool community and it's self-organizing.
Every Sunday in our Mumble Room, we'll have the calendar event at Jupiter Broadcasting
dot com slash calendar.
And I encourage you to get Mumble set up because then you can join our virtual lug during the
show.
And I was just I was just thinking it's funny how the clubhouse social network thing has
gotten so popular.
It's really Mumble.
The club, what Clubhouse is doing, it's Mumble.
And it's not as good as Mumble and it's not free software.
But the idea, the idea is sound so you can join the lug and hang out in there every Sunday.
And while you're over at Jupiter Broadcasting dot com, why not grab the all shows feed?
When we launch new content, you get it there.
But additionally, in that feed, along with this show, you get Koda radio, self-hosted
and Linux action news where Wes and I are breaking down all of the important Linux news
every single week.
That's all Jupiter Broadcasting dot com.
Go get some.
That should be the new slogan, you know, Jupiter Broadcasting dot com.
That'd be really obnoxious.
Although obnoxious is kind of the name of the game because we wanted to be a little
tongue in cheek, have some fun with this because, you know, it's the hacker games.
What's even crazier than letting anyone join a virtual lug and speak on our podcast live
on the air?
How about sharing the login information to one of our application servers with our chat
room?
We've set up an application server with one major misconfiguration.
If you find it, you can own the box.
Whoever gets root first claims the yet to be announced 400 swag.
One box, one hacker, one exclusive prize.
It's the Unplugged Hacker Game.
Oops, we misconfigured one of our systems.
An actual misconfiguration that I've seen in production.
The first who pops root on the box and leaves their name in an email and their email address
in a text file in the slash root home folder wins lup 400 swag.
Also the first who posts a link to the super secret file in the slash root home folder
also will win the swag.
So that's what we're doing today.
We have this accidental configuration and it's on a server at rust.rodeo and the login
is backup.
And what was the password, Wes?
Unplugged.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
So the user account is backup.
The password is unplugged.
Rust.rodeo.
Go log in.
If you can pop the root first, you win.
And if you can find the misconfiguration that we did.
But this user account backup doesn't normally have a shell.
A lot of systems like Ubuntu or Debian, this is a Debian box, will have a backup user pre-added.
And I actually have seen in production when the client needed for some reason the backup
account to actually like log in and do something over SSH, I can't even remember what the circumstances
was back then, but it was something to do with backup PC.
And they set a shell for their backup account and set a really basic password.
And that is actually how I got access to the box.
And so we're kind of replicating that setup, but with a modern twist because this is an
application server that we have deployed.
And so it's running amongst other things, container software, and it has net data installed
for monitoring.
It's a common system, pretty minimal install, running on Debian that you'd see with one
or two mistakes that I've actually witnessed in production that have been made here.
Maybe it's not the newest Debian, you know?
Yeah, maybe there's a couple of old packages on there.
So go log in to rust.rodeo with the user account backup and the password unplugged.
And whoever gets there first, put your name and email in a text file in slash roots home
folder and then let us know.
And then in the meantime, what we thought we would do is tell you about kind of like
a cheat way that won't work on this box, right, Wes?
This isn't going to work.
Like, we're not going to...
I don't know if I want to tell them about it yet because then they could use it, but
I don't think it'll work.
No, I mean, it might work, yeah.
You think?
You think it might?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
That'd be cheating.
You know?
But I'm going to tell you about...
I'm going to tell you like a cheat code way you can do it.
It's something that kind of inspired this segment.
We're curious to see how long it takes somebody to get access because my thinking here is,
oh, I'm actually seeing a little bit of usage tick up on it too.
Interesting.
I'm watching the system here.
My thinking on it is quite simply, oh, oh, we have some definite...
People are...
Wow.
Excellent.
It's funny to watch what people are doing.
So we have somebody who is spinning up Docker.
We have somebody who's running Nano on the sudoers file right now.
Look at you guys, you deviants.
What are you doing to our box right now?
This poor innocent box.
Boy, there's a lot of things happening right now.
Ideally, install some Rust on there because it's got a great domain name, but I don't
think we put anything that was Rust powered on it yet.
This is our Rust application development server, rust.rodeo.
So while people are...
I'm going to tell you a way you can get root, but if you use this, you don't qualify for
the prize.
But this is what kind of inspired the segment.
It's like, you know in Mario when you get the star and then you're invincible?
That's what this is.
You can automatically exploit any low-hanging fruit to pop a root shell in Linux with this
app.
And I thought it'd be fun to tell you guys about it because if you wanted to test your
systems and see how they stand up, we actually ran this against a couple of boxes, some of
which it could not exploit and some of which it could.
And it's called Traitor, and we'll have a link to it in the show notes.
It's obviously up on GitHub, like seemingly everything is these days.
And you run this Go app on your system as a regular user, and it will automatically
check for all of the known likely vulnerabilities on a box and then pop you a shell using one
of them.
Oh, Neil, you got it.
You got it already.
Yep.
I didn't remember exactly what you said I should do, so I just went ahead and dropped
a file in slash root on the host file system.
That's great.
I found the super secret file.
I also decided, you know what?
Just whatever.
I'll just drop something in there, too.
I've owned everything.
I access stuff.
You want me to install something?
I can.
I can upgrade the system to Debian 10 and break everything if you'd like.
Well, that only took a few minutes.
Well done, sir.
So walk people through how you got root.
Tell us what you found and what was misconfigured.
I don't know if this was the misconfiguration you were going for, but here's the one that
I found.
Docker PS worked.
And that was enough for me to realize this is a Debian system, so this is probably going
to be busted in all kinds of fun ways.
So by default, on most of the non-Red Hat family, and I think this is actually kind
of fixed in the SUSE family now, but at least in the Debian Ubuntu family, if you have the
ability to access the Docker socket and you have a Docker service daemon, you're actually
able to bypass every single protection if you don't have, you know, SE Linux working
on it, for example.
And so what I did was I just docker run dactechrm space-it-v slash to slash host and opened
up fedora-latest, and that gave me a root of S with a mount point with read-write access
to the host file system, and everything was there.
And I just poked around and did stuff, and it's like, oh, well, you know, whatever.
Man, Chris, you're bad at this.
You just wanted to say that you used Fedora to own Debian.
That's pretty great, yeah.
But I think what's great is it's two issues that you compounded.
So number one is you got access to the box.
Maybe in this scenario, somebody has a backup account on a server, and they're using a really
basic password that you're able to dictionary attack, or for whatever reason, you get shell
on a box.
But you didn't get root shell.
You just got user shell.
He wasn't in the sudoers file or anything like that.
But then you leverage an extremely common docker misconfiguration to own the rest of
the box.
And that was actually exactly the route we thought somebody might take.
So congratulations.
Well done, sir.
Well done.
You will get the yet-to-be-announced swag item.
And I think that the point we were trying to make with this is it is actually pretty
exceptionally easy to have zero knowledge or experience with a box, and if you just
have an understanding of how these fundamentals work, you can get access.
And that was exactly the point we were trying to demonstrate, ah, PyCrash was going that
route too.
I almost made it, man.
You almost made it.
I left a little treat on slash root if you want to go look, Chris.
Technically nobody has posted a link to the super secret file yet, PyCrash.
So you could technically still do that and post a link to it in the IRC room, which means
you have to get it uploaded somewhere.
And then you would still qualify for the yet-to-be-announced swag item.
Ah, Gamma was looking at set UID binaries.
Yeah, that's a good idea.
Yeah, this was a conversation that I think I had to really convince Wes we should do.
The other thing we did, although it's not super obvious, is we decided to go with kind
of an easy root password.
It does have letters and numbers, so it's not super crazy easy, but it would probably
be guessable.
Definitely, yeah, dictionary attackable.
Yeah.
It's not really, everybody knows important passwords, but I just think that it's funny
to reach into a past life where I actually saw this scenario and it was using not a super
simple password, but a password for this backup account, back with this client.
It was using a password that was in several scripts that multiple people had access to.
So there was many scenarios where you would have an opportunity to see the password, like
if you're on the LAN or something like that.
And it was a dictionary word and you could just log in to any boxes backup with that
password because they set it up on every single rig for the backups to work.
And then all it really takes, right, is someone's trying to backup something, maybe they're
trying to backup a container.
So they add that user to the Docker group or they fuss with permissions on the Docker
socket and suddenly your castle comes crashing down.
Congratulations Neil, you are the winner of the first Unplugged Hacker Games.
I also have been thinking about a version we could do where we leave a box running and
then see if somebody can own it that is in the download audience.
So you don't have to be here live for that too.
Oh, IRC update.
Yeah, it looks like someone's got the super secret prize linked.
There you go.
So that's two people now.
Good.
I was tempted to do both, but I figured, well, one, it's kind of a pain to copy the file
out.
We got you with laziness.
Yep.
And of course, because this is how it works on the Unplugged program, the super secret
file was an adorable picture of Levi playing in the snow.
It was cool.
I loved it.
With his baby tongue out.
You got a little baby tongue sticking out there in the snow.
You need more of those.
I like Levi.
Levi is, yeah.
I mean, he is the prize.
So put your, okay, yeah, good, Carl, you got, Carl, you got your, all right, great.
Nicely done.
Carl got in there too.
Ha ha.
Carl, which route did you take to get root?
I did the same thing that Neil did.
I knew that there was a way to do that.
I'd seen it blogged about before, but I couldn't remember the exact flags and it was the volume
mounting the root file system inside the container.
Thor leaves his mark.
Thor was here also.
Very nice.
Nicely done.
I think we'll do this again.
I really enjoyed that.
But next time, next time it won't be a Docker misconfiguration, but it does show you the
importance of things not running as root, doesn't it?
Right.
And also this is why I use Podman because this kind of stuff isn't actually the default
setup.
Right.
That's what stuck with me here is like, you know, honestly, I mean, we probably wouldn't
have used exactly this box, but this is not that far off from just sort of a lazy default
setup of, oh, I just need to run some containers.
I've installed Docker.
I'm setting things up really quickly.
And I mean, the tool we were talking about, Trader, it's able to do this too.
You know, you just have that Docker socket open for it and away it goes.
And Trader is just out there.
Anybody can grab it.
It's not, you don't, you know, you just, she just listened to some silly Linux podcast
and you know about it.
This has been your Unplugged PSA.
Also I want to say thank you to our Unplugged Core contributors at unpluggedcore.com, keeping
the show independent, helping us reduce the ad load needed.
And also when you become a core contributor, you get access to two different feeds, a limited
ad version of the feed, same full production, just no ads, or you get the full raw live
stream, all our screw ups, all the stuff that never makes it into the show, the full pre
and post show that's basically an extra show that never gets released.
All of that is available to our members.
And we do that as a thank you because it really makes a huge difference and we immensely appreciate
it.
And let's do a little bit of feedback before we get out of here because I really ran my
mouth off a lot at the end of the last episode.
But before we get to that, Thor of Norway, I wonder if it's the same Thor, writes in
about Minecraft Bedrock Bridge.
I was recently listening to the segment on Flatpak and the Flatpak packages for Minecraft
Bedrock Edition that I mentioned last week.
He said, I started looking at a main list of differences and capabilities and I came
across a proxy bridge that bridges Minecraft Bedrock Edition and Minecraft Java Edition.
I was linked to this in the Jupiter broadcasting telegram today as well.
It's at geysermc.org.
Geyser MC.
And it is a middle layer that allows Bedrock at Java Edition to play with each other.
It does the translations in real time.
That's remarkable.
What an incredible bit of engineering and we'll put a link to it in the show notes because
if you have this drugs like I have, then you know what a big deal this is.
And so thank you for everybody who sent that along.
I will definitely take a look into that.
It also gives me another excuse to spin up a Linode.
So there's that too.
I always like that.
All right.
Well, moving on to our next piece of feedback from Kai asking about audio hardware.
A long time listener, first time caller, I was wondering if you could talk about your
audio hardware setup in the show.
I'm in the process of building a new PC and was looking for a sound card.
It seems that there's no sound card with official vendor support anymore, at least for Linux
and lots of, well, use kernel XYZ and this firmware and well, maybe it works, at least
that's the comments I see on Reddit.
So do you guys have any ideas?
Regards, Kai.
I think it's safe to say that we're everybody on the team is a really big advocate of just
getting a USB audio interface for anything that where audio quality matters.
Yeah, so much so that it's been years and years that I've actually had like an internal
sound card.
Yeah, I use one upstairs on my desktop for my speakers, but I would never capture audio
that way.
And additionally, I have just found it super solid.
The way this has just worked 100% rock solid for me every time is a name brand USB audio
interface.
They can be a wide range of prices.
We have a couple that we like.
Maybe West, you could mention those here a sec.
But what I wanted, the tip I wanted to give you is whichever one you end up getting, you
can go into pulse audio, any of the pulse audio control panels like Poova control and
disable the HDMI audio out, disable the built in, in and out, just disable all of those
and leave the only audio interface enabled that you actually use.
For me, it's USB devices.
And then you're never really going to have any problems with like zoom meetings, picking
the wrong audio interface or an application launching and not playing audio right.
If you disable the sound cards, you don't use improve a control solves the problem.
Yeah, that definitely makes it simpler to sort of disable anything that you don't actually
want to show up to actually be an option.
And probably control sure is pretty handy, even if it's not the not the prettiest.
People are sending broadcast messages on the owned machine.
Do you have any audio interfaces off the top of your head that we recommend besides like
the M audio, you 21 or 22, whatever it is, right?
Yeah, the M audio one, they're not.
It sort of depends on if you like them or not.
But lexicon has some ones like the alpha, I think also the omega line that works just
fine with Linux.
I know there's been some mixed reports on the on the focus right Scarlett's of the newest
Yeah, line maybe which I've not personally tried.
But all their older stuff has always worked really nicely.
That's what I'm talking to you on right now is a two i four, but the two i two works great
too.
So my top tip is get a used two i two or two i four Scarlett perhaps a focus right um,
I have tried the newer ones and I don't I haven't really had any problems but I have
had multiple people tell me that the older ones are slightly better with Linux support.
In general, though USB audio devices just even the cheap crappy little tiny ones you
buy off of Amazon are better, especially on a laptop than the built in audio interface.
There's just a lot of electronics in a small space and it just kind of makes them sucky.
And so that's why we always always break it out.
All right, so let's get into the arch stuff because I had a lot to say in the post show
and Eric writes in this is first of all love the show.
But I wanted to respond to the concern about people making fun of arch users.
I don't like abusing folks for their choice in well, pretty much anything.
But you know, it might help the arch case if so many arch users didn't take to Reddit,
the managerial forms and etc.
And question why people use anything but arch.
It just kind of begs for teasing regards, Eric, he's kind of right like this all I think
started as a Reddit meme.
Yeah, and there are you know, I think it's safe to say arch tracks some strong opinions,
I guess on both sides, but but you know, people who discover it and use it and sort of evangelize
it and I think it is fair to point out that there are times where that's not really appropriate
or where the message isn't appropriately nuanced with clarifications around you know, this
is why it works well for me, but everyone skips that first part and it's more like well,
this is why it's the best.
Indeed, indeed.
All right.
We got one more that kind of gets to the philosophical side of the arch discussion.
Indeed it does from Mr. Ders.
I just had to write in on love 394s after show arch discussion.
I have a degree in computer engineering, so I get computers, but I don't do anything with
Linux as a career.
I've only ever heard about the toxic environment in open source but never experienced it.
Part of that is how I approach life and human human interaction.
But I honestly think the vast majority of the community are honest, kind, hardworking,
real people.
A person's self esteem is often wrapped up in their life's work, their value system choices
and preferences.
It can be difficult to hear that another user doesn't appreciate the same things we do,
especially if we are a creator or contributor.
For example, Neil commented that he had failed with all of his hard work on fedora if it
didn't do what Chris needed it to do.
I do love Neil's commitment to creating better and better software, but he is far from a
failure.
We only fail when we fail to appreciate the wonderful diversity and how open source tools
can be used and everyone's individual rights to choose for whatever reason that is.
For me, I choose PopOS, Ubuntu Server, Arch, Endeavor.
Sometimes it's my perception is the best tool for the job.
Sometimes it just feels good and it looks good and it sounds good.
But at the end of the day, it gets the job done.
There are so many car analogies I could make, but I've already said too much.
Thank you for the show, Mr. Ders.
Good point, Mr. Ders.
And Carl and I were having a conversation in matrix and Neil and I were having a conversation
in matrix after the show.
And kind of what I realized too is part of the factor here is, especially when it comes
to Linux distributions, is how much does community interaction matter to you and what community
does that best for you?
And for me, I realized afterwards, I don't think I have an Arch user form account.
I don't think I've ever posted over there.
I've never tried to submit something to an Arch maintainer for fixing.
I've never done any level of community engagement.
In fact, I think I've even commented to you off air that one of the things I've liked
about Arch is I am 100% ignorant for the most part to any politics going on.
I know there's some from time to time, but I'm mostly ignorant compared to what I know
about what's going on with all the other distributions.
And I kind of find that to be a respite.
But others engage fully with the community and have had a different experience.
And so that has factored into one of many factors of choosing a distribution.
And I think that was probably what was missing from our conversation last week.
Yeah, we all have sort of different experiences and interactions with even if it's the same
organization, the same project, but you can use that, explore that and interact with the
community in totally different ways.
I'm just waiting for WSOS, you know, with the pain command line that's all like customized
and looks really cool.
And the pain window manager, the pain programming language.
Then you're just going to come to me for support.
I don't want that.
You can find our sponsor Cloud Guru on social media.
They're at just slash a cloud guru just about everywhere online, Twitter, Facebook, YouTube.
It's just slash a cloud guru.
If you do the Twitter thing, you can follow this here show for announcements at Linux
Unplugged.
The network for all kinds of news is at Jupiter Signal.
And of course, I'm at Chris Last.
Wes, I think you got a Twitter account, too.
At Wes Payne.
Look at that.
That's so easy.
It's actually simpler than what mine is.
It's just my name.
Yeah, that's a lot easier.
The entire Jupiter Broadcasting Network of shows, fantastic shows, the best shows, JupiterBroadcasting.com.
And if you work in the tech industry, don't miss Linux Action News.
Every Monday morning, Wes and I break down everything that matters in the world of Linux.
You're not going to want to miss that.
LinuxActionNews.com.
See you next week.
Same bat time, same bat station.
And do keep the Linux rolling.
Tuesdays, join us live, 12 p.m. Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
That's a heck of a lot of Linux.
But is it enough Linux?
Only you can determine that.
Links to everything we talked about today and how to contact us, the Mumble server info,
our Matrix server info, all of it, all of it, LinuxUnplugged.com.
It's that simple.
People are still owning our box right now.
I'm seeing the messages come in.
Oh, man.
The poor little machine.
Deviants.
All right, everyone, thanks so much for tuning into this week's episode of the Unplugged
program as we build towards 400.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
JBtitles.com, everybody go boat.
I think our Rust application server has turned into a chat server for everyone who has owned
it.
They're just chatting back and forth using broadcast now.
It's our own JB intranet.
Yeah, really, it is.
Look at all these people.
So how many people are now logged into it?
Okay, we've got 11 users currently active, a little bit less than during the show.
I just killed a lot of sessions.
Oh, did you?
Thank you very much.
He yanked everyone.
Yeah, he has thrown me out, but I'm back in now.
So there was 20 people by the time he yanked everything, and I'm not counting the four
separate sessions I was running multiplex through Docker.
Oh, good.
I think the next one we'll try to do something that runs overnight or for a couple of days
to give people a couple of chances.
I think this is so much fun.
All right, we'll do it even bigger and better next time.
It was fun.
Look, Chris, you're bad at security.