I don't think any of us had this in our predictions,
and that was just last week,
but Canonical has a job posting up on their careers page
for a quote, Linux desktop gaming product manager.
And the description reads,
we're excited to create the role
of desktop gaming product manager
to make Ubuntu the best Linux desktop for gaming.
We will work with partners in the Silicon world
to ensure the latest graphic drivers and tweaks
are built in for optimal frame rates and latency,
as well as with partners in the gaming industry
to ensure that mechanisms such as anti-cheat capabilities
are available to ensure fairness and product availability.
Where is this coming from, first of all?
And second of all, what strikes me about this
is I was just thinking,
we're getting awfully close to the deck
and no major game has announced anti-cheat compatibility.
Does this feel like a response
to the deck being arch, you think?
Oh, I don't know.
Response seems like maybe a lot.
You know, you'd think there'd have to be a little more
going on behind the scenes than just that,
but it certainly feels like maybe it's pulling into
more of these machinations we don't quite see
behind the various curtains.
It is weird the way this job post is written.
Like, you know, half of it's talking about
some of those like this graphic stuff
and software development,
but then there's also a lot of the phrase go-to markets.
How do you find someone who's software development
experience, really interested in open source of that,
and then also has an MBA?
I guess that's what you need.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris. My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent. Hello, gentlemen.
Welcome to our first Sunday episode.
We're here together.
It's nice to see your smiling faces.
Coming up on the show today, we've been waiting all summer.
It's a new year and it's time for a new server
with some essential help from our community.
We are starting off on a major migration.
We're going to tell you more about it.
You know some of it.
We're going to tell you the complete picture in this episode.
We've got two servers, new networking,
a totally new balls to the walls,
don't do as we do kind of setup.
So you're joining us today mid-gallop into a migration,
and we'll give you our first major progress report.
Then we'll round out the show with the emails and the pics.
You know, we've gone through and done our pre-show discussion
on what would be the right pic.
I think I have one that's going to be good for the timing.
So I'm vouching for this week's pic.
Oh, wow. Okay.
I mean, the first pic of a new year is serious business.
Yeah. Yeah.
So before we go any further,
we've got to do the business of the show.
We've got to say hello to our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, virtual lug.
Hello, hello.
Hello.
Good evening.
Namaskaram.
Sunday.
Hello.
Welcome to the Sunday episode.
We're trying out the old jitzy today.
Should be interesting to see how that goes.
Nice to see some of their faces.
They're like real people.
It is, wow.
And I mean, they did not bat an eye
at following us right over here.
Yeah, well, it helped that we kept dropping
our connection to Mumble.
That didn't change it.
As you probably guessed, I'm out of the woods.
Made it out of the woods.
Yeah, you didn't die.
Yeah. A nicey death. Good work.
So if you didn't catch last week's episode,
I got stranded out in the woods
after the Pacific Northwest got slammed
with an unusually cold winter storm
and didn't have enough fuel, didn't have enough propane,
didn't have enough water, tanks were full.
I was freezing my, you know what's off.
And our ideal scenario is we were gonna get out of there
after last week's show on Tuesday.
We didn't make it out till Thursday.
Ooh.
Yeah.
Now, the nice thing was is the longer we stayed out
in the woods, the more we kind of learned to live out there.
Still real hard on the rig.
And there has been damage to our water system.
But what happened is a bunch of ice formed
on top of our slides, like thick ice,
much thicker than I realized.
And it must've been a combination of just melt
and then refreezing that just made this thing huge over time.
And so it was hours per slide to get that ice out.
Wow.
Took forever.
Of course, I tried to not do it and just saw it,
see, well, maybe it'll break when it comes in.
No, no, you could drive a car on this ice.
So it was like that thick.
So we had to like chip each slide.
It took hours and you know, it's 20 degrees,
15 degrees outside.
There's only so many, and it's right at winter solstice too.
So there's only so many hours of daylight.
You've got a few hours of daylight
to do the work out there.
You can only be out in the cold for so long.
We're making no solar, right?
It was just worst case scenario.
And so we didn't actually make it out till Thursday.
And then that evening, another huge snowstorm came in.
If we hadn't made it out that day,
we would have been trapped again that evening.
It was like down to the wire.
Yeah, you probably would have just gotten out now.
Yeah, maybe, yeah.
Cause it's just now gone,
for the first time since Christmas,
it's gone above freezing.
So yeah.
But then, you know, fast forward,
like we're here at the studio Saturday,
last night, day after New Year's,
even though Wes has friends in town,
he still came, spent the day up here,
brought Brent up.
Brent's in from town.
Wait, Brent's in from out of town.
Nice to have Brent here.
Out of country.
Right, right.
And you had quite the experience.
I had a saga.
I think it's a podcast length story in itself
that I won't go into details,
but it took me, let's say two days to get here.
Yeah, you had to end up crossing the border
a total of five times.
Yeah, yeah, I did.
Customs got to know me really well.
And that's not usually a good thing.
Also, you learned almost the hard way
that if you buy something in the duty-free store
and then bring it back into your own country,
there's like a 200% fee for that.
Yeah, it turns out they don't tell you that
when you buy these things.
I guess it's an edge case.
Yeah, so just be aware of that, listener.
Brent'll save you some money there.
So before we get into our service stuff today,
I just wanna mention that we do have a meetup
on the 30th planned at the studio here
in the Seattle area, it's up in the town of Arlington.
So it's about 45, 50 minutes North of Seattle.
And we're gonna do phase two of the server launch.
We're gonna have a get together potluck here,
just have a good old time, do a live lup
and hang out at the JB studio,
assuming that it's safe to do so.
You know, we just will watch all that,
but so we'll have more information on that soon.
But if you're in the Pacific Northwest area,
start making your plans for that.
But all right, let's talk about server stuff
because you guys know that if you've been listening
to the show for a while,
we have this really super reliable, super micro box
that has been around forever.
We bought it used.
It's really done good work for us, right?
I mean- Sure has.
In the bedrock of the studio for a few years now.
And it's lived through some real hot summers
because it's a garage that has an exposed roof
and it's also where the afternoon sun is.
So it gets really hot in there, even for the Seattle area.
You know, it could be over a hundred and something degrees
in there in the summer.
Survived multiple OS transitions, many Arch updates.
Yeah, it started life as a FreeNAS box,
then it became a Fedora box,
and then it became an Arch box.
And there are legacy artifacts of that
going all the way back to the FreeNAS installation.
It's pretty funny.
And Alan Jude set up our original ZFS setup on FreeNAS.
And so that has been carried forward
through all those installs as well,
which is something we're gonna kind of finally modernize
and update on, which we'll get into that in a little bit.
But I mean, it really has served us well.
It's loud, it takes a ton of power,
and it's been through a lot of seasons.
And this last summer,
it started hard locking on us a few times.
Probably the most fatal one
was during the final few weeks of the road trip
when we were all AFK and it went down
and I had like some backup infrastructure on Linode
because we knew it was sketch.
And that was the only thing
that kind of saved the day on that.
So we realized goal number one
when we go for a new server is stability.
We gotta make sure this thing's not locking up on us.
We wanna have remote management.
We wanna be able to figure out what's happening
even when we're not in the studio.
And along with that,
we wanna build like a cooling box for it in the spring
and all that kind of stuff.
That was like, and probably, obviously,
something that's just will last us a few more years too.
It's not just reliability,
it's also sustainability for a few more years.
Yeah, right, we're kind of getting some work in now
to forestall having to do this again sometime soon.
Yeah, I love getting four or five years
out of something like this if we can't even longer,
which we definitely did with this last box.
So that's like 50% of our goals right there.
The other 50% of our goal
is to increase the available storage that we have.
We archive FLAC versions of our show productions on there.
We archive special projects on there.
Anytime we go to a community event,
if we record audio or we film it,
we archive all the source material on there.
There's also a media collection
for people in the studio that's on there.
I have some family stuff on there,
like videos and things like that.
There's a ton of our archives
from the object storage up in Linode.
You guys, we've talked about this before,
but just as a recap,
we run Nextcloud up on Linode.
Object storage is the backend.
And then to prevent excessive growth,
we just carve off every few months some of that
and we throw it on the physical server here in the studio
that has this.
And that way we keep what's in object storage
to like three or four months.
And then anything older than that lives in an archive storage
kind of like a cold storage here at the studio.
Then we run Nextcloud on each of them
and it helps us manage that and it's really nice.
And so we need to be able to grow that as well.
So right now the current system has two terabytes free.
It's running Arch.
We haven't updated it since the last time
we updated it on the show.
That's been a few months.
It's like, it's definitely due for some updates.
Yeah, I think so.
Let's just see here.
How many?
You think, you know,
it'd be really dumb to do one more update
just because we're in the middle of a migration.
Yeah, no, we don't need to update it.
But boy, I tell you what, there was a second there.
I'm like, let's do it.
Let's kick off the millionaire.
Let's update this sucker.
But no, no, this is not that time.
So we wanted to move over to something
that gave us additional capacity,
some runway for storage.
Ideally, although this is a long shot,
ideally something that gets us through the rest of the year
because buying high capacity SAS hard drives right now
is like buying them made out of gold or Bitcoin even.
It's ridiculous.
We were looking at prices last night
for even just, you know, maybe two terabytes.
Some of the drives are going for nearly $800 right now.
It's just not happening.
Too much.
So we wanted to try to get as much storage runway
as possible with this migration.
And did you get the updates there, the number there?
Oh, yeah.
Oh, you know, hey, net upgrade size only 24 megs,
but 229 packages, three gigs of updates.
Three gigs of updates and a 24 megabyte net size.
That just makes me smile.
You know, that's just so damn impressive.
We'll miss you, Arch.
Mm-hmm.
So it really was a matter of getting new hardware,
trying to get the right price to performance ratio,
and then finding time to set it up
and finding a new physical spot to put it
that we could build a box around later.
You know, as with a lot of these things,
it's an exercise in engineering compromises, right?
Like, we have the resources we have entirely, you know,
thanks to the amazing community that we have.
And we're trying to figure out, like,
for our particular needs, which, you know,
it's kind of an odd combination of things.
And it's not necessarily,
it's not the thing hosting the shows.
It's not the stuff, you know, if something happens
or we need to do some work on it, that's okay.
But it is still, you know, important to the studio.
Yeah, it's not in the pipeline of production,
but it's in the support area of, like, infrastructure,
which is, like, a second tier of infrastructure.
So it works kind of good for this sort of thing.
It's definitely, and it's something
we definitely have in production,
so if it breaks it, you know, we feel it.
When I was looking at buying something, you know,
I was looking at, like, a $1,000, $2,000 rig, you know.
I was, you know, looking at something budget-friendly
because I knew I was gonna have to put
a bunch of money into storage.
But, like Wes said, like,
we have a f****** amazing community.
It's, like, you can't put it down as an asset
on a balance sheet, but it has gotta be
one of the strongest assets of this company
because we had two different individuals step up
and hook us up with incredible hardware
that is really, it changed the focus
from, like, how the hell are we gonna afford this
to, like, let's get some storage and focus on the setup.
Both of these servers that were donated to us
are nicer than I would have bought.
Right? No kidding.
Like, you know, we could have got something decent,
but not this.
Yeah, and both servers, one came with no disk
and one came with disk, but both servers
ended up having 48 terabytes of total storage available.
Ironically, like, they both,
that's where it worked out to be, is 48 terabytes.
Which is interesting because right now
we have about 20 terabytes, and we have two terabytes free
in our current system.
One is a set of spinning disks that I picked up
from two different vendors on eBay,
and the other came with 24 low-right threshold SSDs.
But they're all SSDs, and man, is that a thing of beauty.
So when we saw this, what we saw was a real opportunity
here for us to play with disaster recovery
and failover setups over time.
Especially, not maybe so much from, like,
an OS hot standby standpoint,
but more, like, from a data recovery.
For some of these really big, you know,
archived files of productions and stuff
that right now they're just not properly backed up
because it's difficult to do so.
Yeah, it's a lot of storage.
So how do you do that?
And especially when you have a Comcast connection
that has, like, a kind of crappy upload speed
and stuff like that.
So we're gonna talk more about that.
That's more down the road.
What we're gonna focus on today is the box
that has 24 SSDs in it.
And that's gonna be the first box we deploy in this
because it's got some great CPUs in it.
It has got a couple of Intel E5-2667 Xeons,
clocked at 3.6 gigahertz.
And these are just beautiful CPUs.
And there's 16 cores total here.
And it has 755 gigabytes of usable RAM.
It's just, we're using, like, something like 0.4% right now
just in the base setup, it's insane.
Yeah, we're talking RAM disk here.
We're gonna be getting there.
So it's a Dell R730 XD, and it's a hell of a box,
but it was a little bit above my pay grade.
Yeah, I gotta say, our community once again stepped up.
And joining us this Saturday, we had a listener
who helped gave the hardware a once over
and get things rolling.
Just don't confuse them with old Wes.
My name's Wesley.
I'll go by that, just we're not confusing me with Wes Payne.
But yeah, so I'm kind of local here to the Seattle area.
And when I heard Chris say that he would love
to have some extra help, I was like,
I'm a guy who lives in Seattle, the Seattle area,
and I would love to help you guys.
So yeah, I'll come on down and see what I can do.
I actually told new Wes, don't come.
I said, don't show up.
The roads are frozen.
It's a two hour drive from where you're at.
Plus we're having to get together on the 30th.
That's just too much work, that's crazy.
Don't come.
It's no, it's just not, we're not worth it.
But he didn't listen to me.
He headed out and he really, really knows this particular
line of Dell hardware in and out.
So that worked out like perfectly
because it's what he deals with his day job.
No kidding, he could not ask for anything better.
Now, Seuss on the other hand,
well, we're all kind of on the same page there.
Yeah, I knew it was a distro
and that's about the level that I had.
Yeah.
We had some fun moments.
I think that's how we feel sometimes too.
We're slowly learning.
The net install had some learning curves for us.
Yeah.
We also chatted about how much of a great deal
you can get from used server hardware.
I think that is really the gold point here
is everything we got is used.
And yet it's still amazing for what we need to use it for.
And maybe something people should consider more often.
Absolutely, it's very affordable
because you got companies who, you know,
they go through their stock,
a third of their servers at a time, they do upgrades.
And they'll go for like 700 bucks, 800 bucks.
Yeah, and they're ridiculously powerful for that too.
Yeah, they also have a nice feature
that I think we're excited about, IPMI, right?
But NUEST wanted to warn us and tell us to be careful.
Oh yeah, IPMI is great.
It's easily one of the best things
about sort of enterprise hardware.
There is a downside though, of course, as with everything.
There's a major security component there
because it's its own separate board before
the rest of the motherboard.
That's how you can turn the server on while it's off.
It's because it's its own own board
that has the ability to control the server remotely.
And so when you expose this over IP, right,
which is how you want to for convenience,
now you've got this huge attack surface
that has the ability to control your entire box.
That's definitely something we'll have to keep in mind.
Definitely.
Because I think a big part of this for us was IPMI,
getting some kind of remote management.
You can really think of it as a computer inside your server.
And so I think what we'll probably do is lock down
what IPs can connect to it and that kind of stuff.
But it also was why we did this.
Because if I had IPMI while I was on that road trip,
I could have rebooted the server
and got it back up and running again.
And it wouldn't have been out for a few weeks.
So just, I mean, a huge thank you to NUEST
for making it all the way up here
and helping us get the ball rolling on this.
We really kind of needed that
because I ended up way behind on getting this going
because I got stuck out in the woods
for a week longer than I intended to.
So all the time after Christmas,
between Christmas and New Year's,
was when I was gonna be working on it.
And I was stuck.
And there were a lot of different moving pieces,
which is why it's having extra hands around too, right?
Because like, okay, there was the physical setup
in the studio, getting that wired up,
plugged into the network, up and going.
Then there was actually getting the OS installed.
And we still needed to figure out like disk layouts
and operating system configuration,
and all kinds of things.
Even just having his knowledge there on the BIOS,
because he knew those BIOSes in and out
and what we wanted to do with it.
Yeah, that could have been a rabbit hole.
We wasted way too much time on it.
Right.
And also a big thank you to those of you
who donated the hardware.
Real Zombie Geek hooked us up
with one of these awesome servers.
That's the one we'll be telling you more about soon.
We had anonymous listener give us the one with the SSDs
that we put into production now.
And it's great for us because it allows us
to just get to work and get back to making the shows
and learning this stuff
and be able to relay that to you guys.
So let's talk about what we're excited about
with this server.
It's definitely IPMI.
That's a big game changer for us,
but there's a ton in this box.
A lot of it we haven't even told you about.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Boy, have I really just gained a whole new appreciation
for Linode this week.
I don't want to do any more of these.
Setting up an actual physical server is a lot of work.
Yeah, no kidding, right?
Just even the physical aspects of it.
Rather than just clicking a button in a web UI, perhaps.
And I honestly wouldn't be surprised
if the power draw of that server
is probably about the cost of a base Linode, right?
But then that base Linode is gonna be in their data center
with their screaming fast connections
and their awesome hardware
and also 11 data centers I could pick from.
Plus they can handle the backups if you want.
Yeah, I mean, it's really just a whole other ball game.
And it's honestly why we have 98% of our infrastructure
up on Linode.
That's how we really deploy everything.
Anything that the team uses,
anything that our listeners interface with,
that's what we use Linode for.
But I hear from so many of you out there
that have tried it out for something like Nextcloud
or replaced Zoom with Jitsi
or have decided to migrate to GitLab
and you put that on Linode.
You're just having that peace of mind
that you've got the root password.
You can make a backup when you want it.
You can get your data when you need it.
You can have full control over that setup.
I think that's worth a lot.
It's a kind of peace of mind
or almost a stress that gets lifted off your shoulders
when you move to that kind of setup.
And then the great thing about Linode
is they give you all the tools to manage that
in a way that's not super complicated.
It's not gonna be overwhelming.
So if you wanna take steps in this direction,
but you've never done it before,
you're not gonna get scared by their horrible interface
or their complicated UI.
Like I picture something like the big hyperscalers,
that is its own ecosystem, right?
That is its own language.
That's its own tooling.
There are people that can become specialists
in those hyperscalers that can't do anything else.
It's not necessarily a good or bad thing.
It's just not where I wanna invest my time.
It's not where I wanna develop my skillset.
And it's also, it's not gonna enable me
to use multiple cloud providers should I ever need to.
And Linode then has all these great tools
like APIs and command line tools you can use as well
or integrate with Kubernetes or Terraform.
So it's just like, it's sort of sitting in this perfect spot
for people that really are advanced
with their infrastructure management
or for people that just need a $5 Linode.
And their pricing is 30 to 50% less
than the major hyperscalers.
So go try it out, get $100 and really kick the tires.
And you support the show.
It's linode.com slash unplugged.
You go there, you get $100 in 60 day credit
and you support the show.
What a great way to start the year.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Well, after new West put in a lot of hard work
getting us all set up and configure,
you know, the OS was installed.
Then we realized, oh right,
I've got to set up this new disk array.
And we hadn't really gotten quite that far in our planning.
Yeah, this was tricky too
because we had to make a couple of decisions.
And one of the things we seriously gave consideration to
was doing everything in ButterFS.
Traditionally, we have the root file system in ButterFS
and then we have the data pool in ZFS.
And we thought this time,
perhaps we just ButterFS the entire thing.
And we didn't really have like a hard line
on like requirements.
So we had to actually hash out,
well, what do we actually want to do?
How much storage do we actually want available?
And by having that conversation,
we kind of whittled it down to ultimately,
well, we're going to actually end up using ZFS.
You know, it was interesting though.
It was a fun discussion and thought experience
in some sense, you know,
it kind of showed what things, you know,
what parts worked well in a world
where it was all in on ButterFS
and kind of unified some of the tooling we could have used.
But, you know, it came down to just the available features
and the amount of the pool we could actually use
because at the end of the day,
if we just had the same amount of space,
that's still an improvement,
but we were kind of running into issues
down the road in 2022
that we would just have to immediately address.
Yeah, I wouldn't be surprised
if we wouldn't have made it more than three months
with what we have available on the current system.
And with the price of storage right now,
I just can't really see us being able to
replace a bunch of those disks right away.
Right, and so if we, you know,
if we had kind of copied a similar setup,
the current array was set up by Alan back in the day,
and it's set up with a bunch of mirrors in the pool.
Probably a sensible way to do it.
Totally, yeah, you know, Alan and Jim over the years
have shared a lot of great stuff.
There's some good wisdom on how you might want to set up CFS,
in particular, what kind of use case you've got
and, you know, what uptime reliability
and how much data protection you need.
But with mirrors, you know, you're making a copy there.
You're mirroring that data over,
and that means that you're only gonna get 50% utilization.
So we ended up with exactly the amount of free space
our current system has.
Yeah, and you, when we told you that,
you looked over at the calculator,
and you weren't exactly happy.
I'm like, we just can't do this.
Like, we should, especially because these are-
We kept reading all the arguments, you know,
we went and looked up all these kind of guides,
I'm like, how do I think about
setting up your CFS storage and stuff,
and be like, yeah, okay, yeah, I mean, that argument,
I can't say that's not good reasoning.
Right, I like PMed Neil on Matrix last night,
I'm like, Neil, what do you think about this too?
Cause we were in this, we were all sitting here
in the studio trying to decide what to do about it.
And, you know, you throw out a couple of options
we could use to try to get some available storage
out of a ButterFS setup, which was very helpful.
Thank you for taking the time to do that.
When we were talking about it, it was,
the main constraint you had was,
you didn't foresee expanding your physical topology
within this year, right?
That was the constraint that you ultimately put down to me.
And I said, the main concern you should make sure
you think about is avoiding a topology
which can lead to cascade disk failure.
Because if you're relying, for example, on parity rate
and you say, all right, I'm okay with accepting
two disks failing, you have to make sure
your rate configuration is set up
so that you reduce the likelihood
that two disks will fail at the same time, right?
And because you can't replace the disks
and you can't afford and you can't figure out
whether those disks were bought at the same time
or if they're different times,
you have to go with the worst case assumption
that they're all bought at the same time.
And that means that they will all fail at the same time
when they get to failing.
I expect that to be the case.
You're right.
So expect that to be the case and design it accordingly.
Like I recommended, for everyone else,
if you're doing Butterfess, I recommend using a RAID 10
and using Z standard compression
to increase the available space
to be somewhere closer to what you would get
with the RAID 6 arraignment
because the RAID 10 configuration
is less punishing to disks than the other options.
With ZFS, you can do an equivalent configuration
with you putting mirrors
and then striping the mirrors on top
because that's essentially what a RAID 10 is.
It's a striped mirror.
But don't do RAID Z or parity RAID
because with the higher density disks that exist today,
the likelihood of cascade disk failure goes up.
I have personally experienced this at work
and in my home setups.
And I basically don't use parity RAID
unless I absolutely have to.
So don't, if you can avoid it.
Yeah.
And to make it more poignant,
these are low right SSDs to begin with.
So they have a lower life cycle than an average SSD.
So they will fail sooner than an average SSD as well.
Right.
And so like, this is where if you're using Butterfess
and like what I told Chris,
and I'll say it repeated again for everyone else,
is make a separate Butterfess pool
for your data with your disks
and configure it differently
than how you would set up your OS pool
so that it's optimized for those characteristics.
So for example, set it up so that discard is async,
set it up so you use Z standard compression,
probably at a higher compression level
because you're willing to eat more CPU cycles
in return for less IO on disk,
set it up with RAID 10,
make sure that you've got proper monitoring and alerting
to catch the warning signs quick, those kinds of things.
Thank you.
Thank you for taking the time.
That's some great advice.
And that is exactly the kind of rational setup
everyone should follow.
And I wanna be clear,
what we ended up with is nowhere as good as that.
And it is better than what we had on the whiteboard
for quite a while, which was simply YOLO.
And it was just a JBOD with no RAID at all,
which we ultimately decided against.
But what we chose seems a little more rational
when you consider we considered no RAID at all.
But I will also remind you that we have a server
with the identical amount of storage
that we have as a failover box.
So that ultimately played a role in our decision.
So we decided to go with ButterFS on the root,
which is a hardware RAID one using the Dell RAID controller.
It's got these two drive slots in the arse of the box
back where the ports are.
There's two disks in there that run the OS.
Then we've got 24 solid state disks
that are getting passed through on the controller.
And we're going with ZFS.
And because you should never do like what we do,
we are doing RAID Z2.
And like you should never do like we do,
we're doing one big VDEV, which you should never do,
especially with 24 disks, right?
So don't do that.
We basically tried to read all the advice we could get
and then not do it.
I mean, it seems pretty rational, right?
I mean, no one-
But you liked the number when we said you could get,
we had like 82.5% capacity.
That was the number you liked, I think, right?
That's what it came down to, right?
Is this migration just doesn't happen
if we don't have more storage.
So ultimately we wanted as much storage
available as possible.
So we went with a parity RAID,
which we're really gonna be screwed
if we have a couple of more than two disks fail
at any point in time.
And it's extra screwy because the time it's gonna take
to get a replacement disk will probably be
about the amount of time it takes for a third disk to fail.
So we're really kind of going down to the wire
with the idea being that we have the second box
that will have an identical copy of everything
that we could do like a ZFS send to recover should we need.
The IRC thinks we hate our data.
They might be right.
I mean, we did almost YOLO this whole thing, right?
You know what's been fascinating to me
watching all of these discussions happen, Chris,
is just your, the difference in your capacity
to accept risk.
And it was basically Wes for a few hours
just trying to bring you back from those cliffs there.
So-
You know, I'm not trying to,
it's more just to make sure we presented the facts
as they may be.
I appreciate it.
So one of the things you kind of workshopped
on your laptop was we were curious,
like what happens if you just do a big ass
ButterFest volume with 24 disks
and a couple of those disks pop off,
like how does ButterFest handle that?
So Wes kind of replicated that on a smaller scale
on his laptop.
Tell us what you did.
Oh yeah, it was just fun playing around with ButterFest
and ZFS and you can set up some loopback devices,
you know, just make some raw files you treat as disks
with the loopback system in Linux,
which is super handy to play with.
You know, it's the Mount-O-Loop option
you may be familiar with.
And then yeah, you can set them up
and then play with whatever type of raid configuration
you might want, right?
Great way to start learning on ButterFest or ZFS tooling
without necessarily touching your real disks.
Yeah, and no big loss
if one of those loopback devices disappears
and you want to see how the system reacts.
Yeah, right, that's also, so yeah, exactly.
And then you can sort of modify things.
You can just write arbitrarily to it without worry
or take it offline entirely and see what happens.
And you know, ButterFest, it did degrade,
but we would have had to do like a full restore from backup,
which, you know, isn't, we should be able to do.
That's the point of having the backup,
but ultimately we decided that probably wasn't reasonable.
So why only one VDEV?
Because we did actually,
didn't we initially do four VDEV, six sticks?
Well, so it was basically just trying to figure out
what storage, right?
It ended up being the storage capacity metric.
Yes, right.
And so if we were splitting it up,
that just meant there were more total parity disks.
More parity disks, so there's less available space.
But with the amount of disks we have,
it actually would make a lot of sense
to split it up into multiple VDEVs
because then it kind of isolates
like the rebuild degradations to that VDEV
and doesn't screw with the entire.
Yeah, you can find some tips out there
for just how many you should stick to
for the various rate levels
and how to take your total desists
and place them up into VDEVs that'll perform nicely.
And then there's also of course concerns around
if you're trying to optimize for IOPS and stuff like that.
That wasn't our concern in this case,
but it gets complicated
and you definitely shouldn't do like we're doing.
Don't do it like we're doing.
Now here's something that you might wanna consider
and we're gonna just be honest with you
on how this part goes.
And we kind of have a luxury
because the old server hasn't crashed recently.
Doesn't mean we wanna take our time doing this,
but it means instead of just like whole hog
picking up the Docker environment
and dropping it on the new server,
which was what plan A was,
now we're thinking because they're both running,
why don't we do a application migration to Podman?
So we'll go from Docker in this migration
to Podman running on the openSUSE Tumbleweed
in the new setup.
We thought we didn't have enough to learn
with a new server operating system,
so why not introduce something new into the mix?
You know, really we've been, you know, I've been playing
with Podman a little bit on the side.
I think you have too, and it's come a long way.
It's been exciting to watch its development.
There's a lot of stuff to like about it,
especially with the mixed sort of changes
that the Docker test top world has been seeing lately.
So kind of felt like maybe this was just the excuse
we needed to really see.
You know, it's not, again, as we said,
like there's some stuff that needs to run,
but it's not exactly business critical day to day.
So we can have a little time here to try to figure out
and learn, frankly, learn a lot more about Podman
is also what we need to do here.
And then we have the luxury
that the production implementation is still running.
So we're gonna start with like a simple applications
and then kind of work our way up.
Eventually we get to a bunch of applications
that are all kind of intertwined
with a whole bunch of storage and all that kind of stuff.
And that's where we're gonna have to just move
like three or four things at a time.
But I think, although we haven't actually,
have we tried this yet?
I don't know, cause you might've been plugging away
at this before the show started,
but we're thinking because we were using
the Docker ZFS driver on Arch,
we have a sub volume for each Docker container.
Yeah, we've got, there's a lot of sub volumes.
So there's both the layer of, there's the volume layer
and a lot of ours are set up on that setup.
And then there's the sort of container storage layer
for the images and the current setup,
those are both on ZFS.
And so should we just be able to ZFS
send those to the new box?
Yeah, so the application data we can just do.
Yeah, that's gonna be nice.
And then it'll be a matter of starting the app in Podman
and just connecting it to its moved data, hopefully.
I mean, Podman's come a long way
in some of the Docker compatibility
and I have not really used it in anger or in production.
I don't think either of us have.
So that's, I think that's gonna be what's interesting
is to figure out what pieces move easily
because we've tested a few simple apps in the new setup
and they seem to be working just fine,
but nothing with complicated interdependencies
and networking and a whole bunch of state
that we're trying to migrate.
Yeah, yeah, it's gonna be interesting,
but I think it'll be good to learn and try something new.
No, I'll also be learning the Tumbleweed tooling
along at the same time.
So there's quite a bit actually,
there's a lot of moving parts to it.
It has been neat to see some of that integration though.
You know, like for instance, Podman has its EFS driver,
but it also has a ButterFS driver
and Tumbleweed has that set up for you out of the box.
Yeah, well, of course.
And so it's just been interesting
since we've kind of been, you know,
like we hacked on Snapper to our Arch setup.
And so it's one thing I'm excited to explore
in this new world is just some of those pieces
in a system that someone else has been thinking about
how to compose those pieces and work with ButterFS
and not just the stuff that we've come up with.
Then phase two-ish, I suppose,
after we get everything migrated
is going to be attacking this DR box.
We have a couple of routes we could go there.
We could do another Tumbleweed box
and just kind of keep them in sync,
or we could Proxmox that machine
and allocate a VM to be like a backup server
and do like some cron jobs to ZFS send.
I don't know if we have a complete picture
of how we wanna do that yet.
Like one thing we're considering is like sync it up here
and then Wes takes to his house
and it runs there as an actual legit
for realsies offsite backup.
What an idea!
That would be a big step up for that data.
There is like some stuff that we've just decided
like if a disaster strikes,
I guess we're just gonna lose this
because I mean, where do you wanna pay
for 20 terabytes of backup storage?
And we're adding to it every single episode.
Like it just gets crazy, right?
So this is a real solution for us now.
So if you have ideas or suggestions,
nicksonplug.com slash contact for that.
Oh yeah, I'm sure you guys have some very clever ideas.
Now that being said,
that seems like a pretty performant box
to just be doing backups.
Wes, do you think you'll have other plans for this thing?
Yeah, we got it right.
Something tells me we'll find some use cases.
That's kind of why I was thinking Proxmox
because you could have a lot of the storage
and like a tumbleweed VM
and then you slice off like the other stuff
because the other box that we're not using,
it has four Xeons in it.
And another like 700 gigs of RAM or something,
just a crazy amount of RAM.
Something tells me it doesn't need all of those
for copying bytes off the network.
Especially when they're gonna become one
over at Comcast connection.
So it does make me think like,
one of the things Wes and I were talking about
is offloading the CPU video encoding
that we do in the cloud right now to one of those boxes.
They also, these Dells let you set power caps,
which is fascinating.
So you can say, just don't let the system
use more than 600 Watts or something.
That's pretty nice.
Maybe you don't always want that,
but it's cool to have some of these more,
you know, customizable options down at the firmware level.
I noticed an option in there while we were playing
to cap it by BTUs as well,
which I thought was really fascinating.
Yeah, I gotta say the SSD box is quite enough
that you could have it on your desk
when it's not under load.
That's been pretty surprising too, yeah.
It's also big enough to be your desk.
That's true.
It is a monster and they're heavy.
That is a thing, but it's up and running.
The migration is in progress.
We're starting with like network test pinging applications,
stuff that just as really simple,
but has obvious application data history
so we can verify that the migration worked correctly.
And then we'll start moving over
the more integrated tooling,
things like NextCloud and our production tools
and workflow things and media stuff.
And I imagine we'll have it probably done
within a couple of weeks.
I mean, we're not in a rush,
but once you get one or two of them going,
it's just sort of rinse and repeat.
Yeah, definitely.
All right then, how about just a spot of housekeeping.
Thank you to our members, unpluggedcore.com
and our network members at jupyter.party.
It's now 100% ad free feed or the live feed,
which has a lot more show.
You want more Westpain?
That's where you get it.
Right there, right there.
So thank you to our members.
You get all our screw ups.
So you're welcome.
If you have feedback or ideas, segment ideas for the show,
then it's unplugged.com slash contact.
You can join our growing matrix community
at linuxunplugged.com slash matrix.
Our matrix server is colony.jupyterbroadcasting.com.
And you know, if matrix isn't your thing,
we have a telegram group.
It's always going, jupyterbroadcasting.com slash telegram.
We'd love to have you there.
And don't forget our virtual lug meets on Sundays
before the show.
And we're going to be meeting on Tuesdays
at the old showtime too.
So go get your mumble set up, which is actually jitzy.
This is practice, practice both, right?
You know, get mumble installed.
Maybe get your mic working.
For goodness sake, it's 2022.
Probably also install an audio editor,
something you can record your mic
and then listen back to and make sure you sound all right.
Yeah, Audacity.
There you go.
It's free.
Try it out.
Goodness sake, it's 2022.
Goodness sake.
We've gotten a lot of great feedback.
Here's a quick one that we can get into.
Bedrick wrote in, he says, dear Linux Unplugged,
you've talked about monetizing Linux desktop apps
in Linux Unplugged 4.3.8.
I would like to pay for applications I use,
but I personally dislike the feeling of being forced to.
My new year's resolution is yet again
to go over the open source projects I use
and set up donations.
What I would personally like to see
is a tool that makes it easier to donate
without the hassle with individual project payment details.
I imagine a GNOME software welcome screen
to set up credit card details
as a flat hub account or something similar
and an autopay option with an opt out possibility.
This autopay option would be default,
regularly pay the recommended price
for all apps installed on my system
that satisfy a few defined conditions.
One, the app is already installed
for some minimum amount of time,
so longer than a trial period, for instance,
and is used frequently enough to be useful,
like at least once a year or something.
Some additional configuration would be appreciated,
like global and per app configuration for the price
as an absolute value or a factor of the recommended price,
configuration of the trial period and usage frequency
and some payment breakdowns.
I feel like the Linux desktop community
needs to feel in control and not be forced to.
You know, I think we've seen various takes
on some pieces of that.
Nothing that's quite got all of it
but more so really seems to have taken off.
Yeah, open collective comes to mind,
but it doesn't quite do it at this level.
The days of what, Flatter, was it?
Yeah, yeah, right.
There's a few out there,
and I don't think I'd want something,
much like he doesn't want to feel forced to pay.
I don't know if I agree with that take,
but I understand the sentiment.
I wouldn't really want this to be a GNOME software solution.
Try as I might, I still struggle to use GNOME software,
and I wouldn't want it to be something
that only could be done in GNOME software.
Now, Chris, you and I this morning
were throwing around ideas around podcast networks
and how they could monetize shows.
Do you see any of that being applicable in this case?
So next week, Dave Jones is gonna join us on the show,
and Dave works with the Podcast Index
and Podcasting 2.0 Initiatives.
And one of the things Dave's gonna talk to us about
is how they use the Bitcoin Lightning Network
to pay content creators.
And the idea is roughly,
he's gonna tell us more about it,
but from my rough understanding,
you say you have a podcast app, an open source podcast app,
and it's got a Bitcoin wallet in there.
And what you do is you throw like 30 bucks of Satoshis
in that wallet that's built into the podcast catcher.
And then you go in there and you say,
you send this amount to Jupiter Broadcasting,
you send this amount to name your favorite podcast,
and kind of like you might with a Patreon
where you can kind of subscribe at different tiers.
And then what the app does is it uses the Lightning Network
to kind of stream Satoshis to the creator as you listen.
So you set a threshold and you set a total amount,
and then based on your listening,
it funds the creators you're actively listening to,
which I think is a really interesting thing
because it's part of what they call a value for value model.
And it could be applied to free software as well,
I would think.
I don't know if people wanna pay
by their hour usage of software,
but there could be something in there that says,
hey, you used this editor for eight hours this week,
or this month, or this year.
Or you launched it 28 times this month,
something like that.
Would you like to send the average amount?
Yeah, ways to lower that barrier in a practical way.
Because then yeah, many of us mean well, right?
But even when you are intentional enough
to maybe think like, oh yeah, year-end things,
I wanna donate and such,
you might think about nonprofits in years,
but how often are you also thinking of software?
It just doesn't always easily happen
if you don't actively do it.
I like this idea of the Bitcoin wallet in the podcast app
using the Lightning Network,
because it's all free software, the entire stack,
even the payment system is free software, all of it.
And yeah, there's scammers out there
that use this same stuff,
but that's true for cash and everything else.
And so there's something interesting there
about monetizing free software
with a free software currency
that tends to grow in value over time.
And doing it in a way that is transparent
because everything on the blockchain is transparent.
And so the project by the very use
of a blockchain payment system is held accountable,
or a podcast network is held accountable, right?
Because it's all of the accounting
is there on the blockchain.
And there's something about free currency,
free software, and a public ledger
that seems like there's probably some kind of,
as they would say, synergy
that we just haven't really fully explored yet.
Do you feel like these tools are ready
for prime time action, like the Lightning Network and?
Oh, sure, yeah.
Oh, yeah.
So well-tested and totally ready
for us to take it on full speed?
Yeah, I mean, like with the podcasting index,
like that monetization system's
been in practice for a bit now.
Nice.
Yeah, so maybe.
Yeah, you never know.
We could see something there or nothing, absolutely.
It all happens and we still struggle
to pay free software developers.
Yeah, I mean, I think you're just trying to lobby
to get people to implement your prediction.
That's what's going on here.
Oh, yeah, that's right, right.
Although I didn't work NFTs, you see, that was, yeah.
All right, so I have a pick that I feel like is
the kind of pick you only really do on the show
right after the holidays
where people may have gotten a Kindle.
So what I wanted to link in the show notes,
and I know it's not for everybody,
but it's a Kindle comic converter.
It'll take like a JPEG or a PNG or a PDF
of your comic that you might be reading,
probably a Star Trek comic,
and then it will convert it to a format that is readable
on your new Kindle that you got
without having to go through like some Kindle Cloud
or Amazon authorization.
And it's simply called Kindle Comic Converter.
We'll have a link to the website
or we'll have a link to the Flat Hub as well.
Isn't the Kindle just one of those things,
like so many of those that were,
I'm sure there's plenty of open source behind it
and the device works pretty nicely.
I have one, I use it, I like eBooks,
but it's just, I'm so grateful for open source things
like this that can put you a little bit more in control
because otherwise it's really very much feels
like a locked-in ecosystem.
I wonder if I could find our old
Linux Action Show Kindle review.
That was pretty rough.
Linux Action Show is the very first Kindle.
Yep, there it is, 13 years ago, there's us.
I'm gonna put a link to this into the show notes.
Wow, it's only two minutes long.
I think it was an outtake, so it's not the full review,
but it's pretty bad.
I'll put a link to that in the show notes.
Oh boy, I don't think I've seen this one.
12 years ago, we were talking about
the very first Kindle on the Linux Action Show.
Season two.
Yeah, that was just after we started calling it Seasons,
which I think was around 100 episodes, I think.
I don't remember for sure.
So it was like 100 episodes in when we started.
The whole thing is...
Definitely a system that makes sense.
Very foggy, it's very, very foggy.
I have to be honest with you.
Well, thankfully you documented it,
so you can review it later.
I look back and I go, who are those people?
Who are they?
What are they talking about?
And every now and then I find myself agreeing
with my past self and I realize,
oh, I'm just like a robot.
If you give me the same input,
I pretty much give you the same output.
Is that a good sign or a bad sign?
I guess you're consistent.
Yeah, I suppose on some things.
Although you can find some reviews of me
really dogging on Butterfess and Fedora,
so some things do change.
And more recent ones about Seuss,
now that I think about it.
If you'd like more show,
remember that we do have a log
that gets together every Sunday
and now on Tuesdays at noon Pacific.
If you're in the tech industry,
make sure you're not missing linuxactionnews.com.
There's a lot going on there
that doesn't make it into this show.
But now we have a new Same Bat Time.
It's Sundays now at noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
See you next week.
Same Bat Time, Same Bat Station.
There you have it.
Of course, the show will just kind of come out
like a little bit earlier in the feed,
so for most of you out there, just a little bit sooner.
Linux Action News will be towards the end of your week now,
so make sure you're at linuxactionnews.com
slash subscribe for that.
Links to the things that we talked about,
which is not much, not much,
because it's, you know, it's a special episode.
But we'll have those at linuxunplug.com slash 439.
Yeah, anything else, gentlemen?
No.
It's been good.
Good work, guys.
Well, thank you.
We got ourselves a new server.
Yeah, and a new day.
A new year.
All right, everybody, thanks so much for joining us
on this week's episode of the Unplugged program.
See you right back here next Sunday.
We'll be right back with another episode of Unplugged.
All right, jbtitles.com, let's go vote, everybody.
Go pick your title.
You got something there, Bryn?
What you got?
Throughout all this discussion, I got really curious.
Two things, I think.
Okay.
Maybe I'll throw them at you one at a time.
Go for it, go for it.
Okay, number one, what's gonna happen to the old server?
Well, we've had someone who's requested it,
so we might donate it to a listener.
Oh, well, that's nice.
It's like a full circle kind of thing.
I like that.
Yeah, so that's sort of plan A,
although if they don't want it,
then I haven't really figured out plan B yet.
But that's plan A.
Okay, I like plan A.
All right, let's question two.
Okay, question number two.
It's a good question.
How's Arch been?
What's the debrief?
Like, are you feeling like it did what it needed to?
We should have done an Arch exit interview.
Yeah, really.
We should have done that,
because I think it worked better than we expected.
And we thought it'd be okay,
but I think it was solid as hell,
and it's not going out of production
because of any Arch issue.
It's because the hardware's dying.
Yeah, really, right.
We could have kept this train rolling.
The will of the community in our vote.
Yeah, and stepping up and saying,
yes, you're gonna go this direction in the polls,
so we're doing it,
even though the lizards may have conspired
to make sure the poll went their direction.
I will say, you know, it was one of the,
I've had a few personal Arch servers
or similar type things in the past,
but I think this was the lowest touch of those,
which is not generally necessarily
maybe what you think of in the Arch setup.
So it was kind of a test of that kind of stability as well,
because it was maybe monthly
or maybe sometimes a little less on those updates
that we did.
Someone can do the math.
But yeah, I think that worked pretty well too.
I mean, I think just to recap,
what made it work well was,
we say it all the time,
but put our FS on the route and not ZFS,
because when the ZFS module a couple of,
maybe three times on us,
failed to build or install correctly,
we could still boot the system.
That could have been catastrophic otherwise.
You fixed a little timing issue,
so that way ZFS got mounted before the containers start.
Oh yeah, just to make sure
that was gonna play nicely together, yeah.
Because, you know, that's the thing about Arch,
is like, there's no distro maintainer,
like, you know, kind of making sure that works.
Like we had to figure that out on our own,
because sometimes the Docker containers would start
and the pool wouldn't be available,
and they'd be like, where's my storage?
And then things would be broken,
but the applications would be running,
so it's not immediately available or obvious.
Yeah, but like, you know, we tweaked that ages ago.
Yeah, it just stayed.
It just worked.
It was never a problem again.
And then I think the LTS kernel helped.
We weren't taking advantage
of the cutting edge kernel features.
Not in that box.
It got updated more than I expected,
but it was point updates.
And then I think, obviously,
having our applications in containers
and not like installed from the AUR or the Arch repository
meant that the OS could pretty much roll independently
and not affect the applications.
And so we didn't have things like AUR installs breaking
that no longer updated or anything like that.
And I think that also contributed
to being a successful Arch box.
Are we gonna do some occasional like zipper live updates?
Oh yeah, I think we should,
because I mean, the whole thing is holding it accountable.
And if it, you know, and not sugarcoating if it breaks
and not hiding if it's been a big success
and if it's been really great and, you know,
we have to own that, then we own it.
Either way, I think we do it publicly
as a, you know, as sort of an example
of how to run something so you don't have to, right?
It's sort of how I always looked at it.
Like we'll try this and we'll try it with something
that really matters to us.
So that way you listening can do it the right way
and don't do like we do.
And I think there's some value in that.
We've gotten quite a bit of feedback
in the last several months of people saying,
oh yeah, I remember, you know,
when I first caught some Linux unplugged
and the thing that really grabbed me
was you guys doing live Arch updates.
We've gotten that so many times
and it feels like it's both memorable
and really valuable, perhaps.
We'll see.
Hopefully it's also fun and valuable with the SUSE setup.
And I actually, I could imagine if it, you know,
if it actually failed on us,
it would like wreck the rest of the show.
Like, what are we gonna do?
Just keep on doing the show?
That's a bummer, yeah.
Yeah, we're bummed out.
Like at worst, like we stop the show and fix the server
and at best we keep going knowing the server's busted
and we got a big job after the show.
Wes will just do like his tap dance routine
to fill the extra waves that we gotta fill for the show.
You know, we should probably just set up a mic
in the garage directly already.
One of us just moves out there.
You better get your finger on the beat button.
All right.