We've been kind of scratching our heads like what is a great task match application because we've been trying to do this
but that's not open source and task warrior is
Complicated. I don't know why task warrior is disqualified and it just doesn't work to sort of manually sync paper notes between us all and matrix
Every morning like that's not gonna cut it. Yeah, but if there's like one
Universal law that seems to be just more and more true these days in free software. You're always
Three solutions away from next cloud, you know, it's like you start talking about a problem
two
Or three other applications get mentioned and then you always inevitably end up on next cloud
Of course, we were looking at next cloud tasks, which is one of their featured apps
And I'm kind of impressed if you look at it
It's got a great UI and then it supports caldev export
So when you schedule your tasks, you could you know evolution Thunderbird?
ICAO, I don't know what you use but anything that supports caldev. You could just import the dates
From your task app and next cloud into your calendar
That's kind of slick
but you know, I sort of feel like next cloud is going through this transition and I'm curious if you guys agree, but
next cloud just recently announced next cloud hub 3 and
It is like a collaboration suite to the extreme next cloud
Chat is more like slack now and you could share documents and preview widgets in there
It's like this whole team style collaboration that has its own file system behind it, too
And then they have these task systems with group collaboration
They have a new mail app a new mail 2.0 app. That is a lot more advanced for a mail application
It kind of feels like they're trying to build
The next version of exchange but the free software version like they're really going for a collaboration suite
I just found here in the apps library. There's a SharePoint back end. No
Oh, it's the SharePoint killer was
Hello friends and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris
My name is Wes and my name is Brent
Hello boys back together again in the studio in the beautiful smoky Pacific Northwest
It's good to be here with you coming up on the show today
we're chatting about a few things going on in the world of Linux that caught our attention during the road trip that we just didn't
get a chance to talk about with the crazy schedule and
There's some doozies in there. So we'll get to that then we'll round it out with a few stories
From our friends and from the meetups out there
Plus, of course, we have some boosts and pics and a lot more so before I go any further
Let's say hello to that virtual log who's here every single Sunday. Hello. Mumble room time appropriate greetings. Hello
Hello, and hello Brent and hello everybody up there in the quiet listening we see you in the what would that be like the lobby?
Like a virtual lobby or uh, you know when they like at big events and they've got these like TV screens for the people
That can't be in that main theater or what if it's more like you're behind it's actually more like you're backstage watching the show
I'm true like our theater techs running everything. Yeah, they're back
They're listening as we're up on stage because we're in there as we're setting up the studio
You know as we're hitting your cousin and fart and stuff. They're listening to all of that
So they're kind of like really behind the scenes
I was gonna make it a little more glamorous if I could but yeah, that's that's basically you're gonna mention the cousin in the fartin
I try not to yeah, we yeah, right theater as a surprise
There's totally no cousin of fartin going on in the studio. Totally not happening
Well, we're back barely perhaps but we're back barely back and I want to start by saying good morning to our friends over at
Tailscale tailscale is a mesh VPN protected by wire guard
We used the absolute crap out of it all of us every single person at the Airbnb
Had tailscale going we were all getting access to our systems behind firewalls not
Open ports for us. No, go try it out at tailscale.com. Go say good morning. Tell him Linux unplugged sent you
tailscale.com
Man, oh man. Okay, so we got back in last night about oh, I don't know 12 hours ago
I think about maybe maybe so maybe 12 hours ago. We got back into town and
The great great part about the return trip so much fun is Wes
You came down to join us in Portland and you caravan back with us. Yeah, I got the full experience this time
And we even got the third walkie-talkie working
So and then you guys like disappeared for a while
But you had what the thing was is like as long as you stay together
We like when you stop to get gas right you stay together
The radio still work like, you know, our radio doesn't work
But you guys can continue to talk and then when you catch back up we can all talk again
That was it's pretty neat how that works. Yeah, it was fun
Like we could tell we're getting close again like oh, that's a dia
Yeah, also dupes is probably I would imagine pretty easy to spot when you're coming up on her. She's sort of
So I was realizing and I felt kind of dumb especially now after that. I've spent the night in dupes
I didn't really know what she looked like from the back
I was like and I could see that there'd be like, you know, especially on a weekend
There could be a lot of rigs on the road sometimes sure. Yeah, and when I first pulled up on you
There was someone kind of tailgating you right behind so that threw me too
I was like who would drive that close to a rig that they're not associated. Oh, they do turns out they love to draft
They draft in me and they get right up in there
And the thing they don't realize is that I can't see them in my mirrors unless they are to the one of the sides
But if they're perfectly centered, I actually can't see them when they're that close
Well, if they're close enough you have that rear facing camera. Yeah, I learned that yeah, but that's dangerous
Yeah, I like to hang out just right
That's how bring kids 50 miles to the gallon and gas
Economy, what if we get you a pie powered home assistant integrated like little like text billboard thing
You know like the programmatic like little text. I like this just back off whatever you want
Yeah, maybe you integrate it with like a little speech to text you so you can sort of shout at something and then just like
Puts it on the back. Oh, I like that
I mean you brought up the whole home assistant raspberry pie thing a little too soon. I'm still grieving but
Yeah, yeah, but I'm for grief. You've got systems to build man. Why are you grieving again? I didn't oh, come on
That's salt in the wound my server and you know now like, you know
Like back home the kids are over and I'm like I got it
I got to explain to the kids it's gonna get a little cold here tonight because there's no system running the heat
Sorry, like, you know, sorry about that everybody
It's embarrassing family fail. We're gonna work on that
We're ripping the whole system out tonight after the show and we're gonna replace it with my home assistant yellow and rebuild
And rebuild eventually, we'll let you know how it goes
So this came up right as we were leaving right as we were hitting the road
Word came down that fedora was dropping a video acceleration
for h264 h265 and VC one codecs due to a legal concern and
It seems that this will primarily affect AMD GPU users using open-source drivers
so if you have done the hard work of switching off in video and
buying AMD pure systems so that way you can have a
3d accelerated environment that is completely open source vote with your wallet. They say you're getting particularly screwed by this
Ironically if you install an NVIDIA graphics card and install their binary proprietary driver
You don't have this problem. You got nothing to worry about so it kind of actually incentivizes using the proprietary driver, which is
Funny how that works out. It also affects any user who uses like any other open-source graphics
Like oh, I don't know Intel graphics users. You also will no longer get
video accelerated decoding
There's been talk about maybe other distributions doing this or not and ultimately it comes down to legal concerns
Red Hat legal is
concerned that they may be exposed to a lawsuit and
when a decision like this is made it actually exposes the real power structure behind fedora and
It's not that fedora isn't a community-run distribution. It absolutely is it's that when?
Red Hat legal gets heartburn about something fedora has to jump into action because if fedora were to become a legal liability for Red Hat
I would imagine the project status would become tenuous. And so the project's incentivized to
Over react to these concerns and as a result they fuck their end users over and over and over again
I was just looking it was like July or June of 2020 where Firefox
finally
Finally got hardware accelerated video playback in Wayland and it was celebrated at the time on fedora finally gets this and
Yet about a year later. Here we are. They now take us away and
Other distributions don't seem to be quite as worried about this
But they don't have this vulnerability that the fedora project has and it's a great project and it's primarily community-run
But this really shows us who's in charge, doesn't it? And I think it's a really kind of unfortunate thing because it's once again end
users that are getting
And it once again shows us why companies like Google have to come along and create a product like Chrome OS to actually make Linux
Usable for end users because we can't count on the distributions that are community-run to actually be able to do these things
It's an interesting time. We live in when Debian can vote to include
Proprietary firmware on their installer all of a sudden
But fedora can't decode that video. They were decoding for you yesterday
it just doesn't make a lot of sense, but in the end it's Linux users who always have to constantly navigate these changing rules and
Once again, it's fedora. That's making a change like this. I
Just find it really disappointing. I understand why they have to do it and you know realistically
We're all gonna be able to figure out how to work around it
It's not gonna be our problem. It's yeah
It's the sort of oh I wanted to give this a shot and I have no idea where to start with
Understanding why this thing that just works. I don't ever have to think about on other systems doesn't over here
Yeah, that's the tragedy of it, and I just took a little look skis before the show
I'm sure this will change with time
But it'll take time
But I just a little look sees before the show and was looking up video acceleration for Firefox
And guess what all the wiki pages all the tutorials all the blog posts all the YouTube videos talk about it
Like it's a working feature
It's something you can do on fedora
so now imagine when you install the next version of fedora and it doesn't work and there just hasn't been enough time for Google and
Everything to re-index and so you go searching for it and all the guides and all the things just talk about it
Like it actually works just fine out of the box
you're gonna get totally gas-lit like what a mind job and
if if all of a sudden could you imagine if all of a sudden
Apple announced that macOS wasn't gonna be able to play back h.264 videos
And I realized fedora is no Apple and they're definitely not but
it does strike me as a decision that was user hostile and
You know, it's kind of unfortunate because fedora has a history of doing this and it's kind of changed my perspective a little bit
And I think it's just sort of the vulnerability that they have as a project and it's just sort of the compromise
We have to accept is that if Red Hat legal has a little bit of heartburn about some concern that might happen to them that
They could just shake off financially like it's no big deal or you know, I don't know. Here's a idea license it
They're rich they could license it but no no instead all users who help us beta test this thing that make our product that actually
Pays the bills
They're the ones that get screwed. It is sort of an interesting. I think maybe it highlights the unique maybe not unique but
Particular situation that have fedora is structured just thinking, you know, we're used to community run distros
No money to tangle in some of these legal things just because like what they they're not gonna pay legal bills or have a lawyer
they have limited funding to begin with and it reminds me of
economicals legal sort of being willing to step out on a limb or what some people thought of a limb with the adding the
CFS module compiled, you know
So in some circumstances having like a corporate sponsor when who's willing to take those risks
It can be something that you know those type of Linux distributions benefit from but that's not really the case
Even though there is somewhat attached it it falls more on that community side
Well, and that is assuming that they could buy a license, you know
What do you want to buy a perpetual license forever for an indefinite amount?
it may be one of these situations where they can't buy it and
It just as a that makes it even more complicated and it doesn't speak to
Linux's ability to compete as a commercial desktop platform
If we can't even get past hurdles like this and I acknowledge it's a tough spot and maybe and I think you might be familiar
with with because this happened a few weeks ago, so I'm starting to get fady on it, but
What happened was a change upstream in Mesa to kind of kick this entire thing off?
That's why all of this came up all of a sudden. That's why there's a change to begin with
I don't know do West you recall what some of those changes were upstream
Straight over a matrix has a nice little summary that before this stuff was kind of just included in Mesa
I guess some thought maybe as an oversight before or at least in the the way that it was getting pulled into fedora
Now you need a build up an explicit build option if you want these codecs
So the non free things can be cut out in a technical sense in a way that before May I think roughly
It was not necessarily easy to do so
I
So now there's a little more scrutiny and if you're gonna have to like when this update comes out you update that and now you have
To explicitly add build flags to enable these non free things that raises a lot of questions
So now you're making a proactive choice, right? You're making this kind of like rolled in with
Yeah, Carl points out to you. There's some trickiness and we can't I think we should talk about just the very unfortunate
This would all be so much easy in a world where we weren't trying to deal with these
You know the horribly licensed codecs like any license that Red Hat
Paid for could result in restrictions on fedora itself
Whereas like because there are restrictions right on these proprietary OS is they want to know when you're installing that you got to get it
From them, whereas we don't think about that in the open source sense
And I guess mpeg la is not really interested in granting unlimited licenses. Anyway. Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah
See, that's just what I think
It's just like we're it's such a it's such a tough spot for like what we think of is this basic sort of human, right?
Of like you should have software that makes your machine fully operate
And that's not how a lot of the rest of the structures of society are set up to do
It's one of those things where I get now so a willful choice is being made and that is a legal thing
I get it, but it would be so much nicer if what we could do instead was
Wait for a letter that says hey, we think you're infringing before this change happens, you know before we just throw all these users under the bus or
Wait for a single person to get sued over this in this in this manner like
Not that I'm arguing for reactionary
but at the same time when you make a change like this is the equivalent of removing the ability to do mp3s and
kind of makes me sick that I've been doing this for 15 years and
This is what we were talking about 15 years ago. And here we are 15 effing years later
I mean, it's just yeah, I'm thinking about switching all next minute. I know right mp3s, man
I mean, that's why I meant was a thing right and so that's just sort of wild but I I understand what you're saying
But I'm not totally sure I'm convinced in the business incentives for
The h264 consortium to sue people for using h264 and playing back video because it only broadens their market share
It only increases their monopoly. It only strengthens their position in the market
So it doesn't seem like they're very incentivized to go after people that are using consuming
distributing h264
It seems like you know, probably they're going after set-top box manufacturers
cable providers
televisions
Blu-ray makers that's the kind of people that you know that they can get that they can extract millions out of
But going after somebody like the RIAA did back in the day for pirating mp3s
That's just not the world we live in anymore. It just doesn't make sense. They're never gonna make a dime at that
So I don't really know what the risk factor is. I guarantee that I can't just I know I understand
I can't come here and say guarantee. Well, they're not gonna sue I can't do that
So there so since the risk factor is you know, at least 1% or whatever
They're gonna respond this way and Carl sums it up nicely over in matrix. This whole thing is a mess. Yeah, it is it is
It just you know
and I think what's so upsetting about it at the core of it is it doesn't seem like there's a
right answer for the fedora project and
It seems like it's a tougher question for fedora than it is for every other Linux distribution
and I find that frustrating and then the other thing that I find frustrating is that there is a history of giving and taking a
little bit in features and I find that to be a
little bit aggravating and then it's like we just started to solve the Nvidia driver problem
We just started to get decent flat hub integration
We really started around the corner on codecs and being able to do all this stuff
Like it really was removing some friction and barriers of entry to fedora
And it was really truly making it possible to recommend one of the great distributions to everybody and now those barriers are
Starting to go back up. It is a form of free software gatekeeping and it's happening now at one of the I think most important
Distributions and I'm just sad about it
Yeah, there was kind of this era where like it felt like at least a lot of this sort of commentary layer would advise
You know like well if you're gonna go through you're probably gonna need something like rp infusion
Yeah, I'd have all these work around to that now
But and for a while it felt like we weren't like we'd really gotten to a point that you know for some esoteric use cases
Yeah, you got to figure out some stuff out
But for just normal using a computer stuff fedora had really gotten just installed and forget. Yeah, I agree
And I understand it too doesn't mean I'm not frustrated by it
I'm we're obviously still gonna use an install and love fedora, but yeah
Yeah, it's just now I'm gonna be getting that stuff from I don't know wherever I can get it
You know if I have to go down a shady alley on the internet
Oh, yeah, I've got a sketchily compiled copper that you might want to check out
Maybe fluendo is gonna get another 80 bucks out of me or something. I don't know. That's what I used to have to do
Back in the days to go buy my codecs and I'd put them in my folder so that way I could play my mp3s on
fedora
Alright, so there's another story going on on the internet right now that I thought we should talk about because we just haven't really gotten
a chance and
that is that the internet has discovered through some sleuthing that pop and the cosmic desktop is going to make use of a
rust based toolkit called iced
And they're doing this in place of GTK
So this is a replacement for a GTK and the news here is that cosmic was believed to be a GTK based desktop environment
but it seems that system 76 has evaluated their options and have picked the direction of
iced and
this was noticed by individuals on reddit and
Then a discussion kicked off from there and I thought before we got to the discussion
Maybe we talked a little bit about iced and kind of what it is and what the goals are
So simply as I understand it is a cross-platform
GUI library and it is as you may have noticed written in rust and it has a focus on simplicity and
type safety as many things in rust do and
And Wes you were mentioning that it's been inspired by something that maybe is a pretty good sign for this type of use case
Yeah, it's inspired by Elm
which is a front-end framework and and language but heavily inspired by functional reactive programming and functional programming in general and
it's a different model of how you think about modeling UIs and states and
Instead of sort of the older style that that GTK definitely is this promotes like you're separating
The things that implement how your stuff gets rendered from the data that describes the tree that you are rendering
And so you can kind of operate in a style where you describe what you want it
It's a it's a more declarative approach where you say like I need I want it to look like this and the underlying engine can
Figure out how do I take what we've got now and make it there instead of a much more
Imperative sort of procedural style that a lot of traditional UI programming has been right
But it would seem like the the mobile operating systems have been making a steady march towards declarative UI design and which
Accommodates a lot of different mobile use cases and size screen sizes and whatnot, right?
Well, I mean, yeah
You saw it in the front end and react has some of this at some of its underlying principles
Elm really defined the like that the data flow model in one way data flows and you sort of update your data and then that
Sort of can reactively cascade and then update the parts of the UI that need to get updated without you having to sort of
explicitly say that and
It turns out people like that approach or similar approaches
Especially if you can get the efficiency, right which seems like rust has a lot of opportunities to do that
But you've seen like Swift UI is an example of adopting some of that compared to the you know
the older objective C standards Swift UI is embracing some of the same thing, so I
Don't know how I've never used ice
I can't say how knife is experience it is but I think if you're trying to target developers who do
UI work in the modern world
They'll have heard about maybe they haven't used down
But this is a model that they're gonna be familiar with and I don't know. I still haven't really learned how to use GTK
And yeah, I mean GTK is certainly popular
But it doesn't seem like it's lit the world on fire and there's a lot of momentum around rust based of it
There's that element of it
And I don't know if I could really you know
Declare which one has more technical merits
But it seems the team at system 76 really likes what ice has to offer for what they want to build and obviously it seems
I mean, it's obviously new right system 76 as well. We'll get into here
There's gonna be need to be contributions to make iced fully functional GTK right is has a lot of functionality
I think no, we're not trying to say this could be directly comparable
Yeah, it's not feature to feature for sure
But there are some reasons why just used to GTK maybe isn't interesting to all developers
Do we know of any other projects using ice at this point or any projects we can look at to see maybe its capabilities?
We were taking a look earlier today at the iced toolkit
Which we will have a link to in the show notes
And so you might be able to from there figure out who else is using this they have a lot of examples
So I would like to try some software that's using this that might be something we tracked down
It is they do note on their github that it's currently experimental. So who knows things may change
I don't we'll get into this too, but it didn't seem like, you know system 76 weren't really coming out and
announcing a bunch of this
Maybe we should also view some of this as like exploring. Oh, hey, we're we know that they've heavily adopted rust internally
They've got people there who are comfortable using it like using it
And so if you did see like oh, there's a new approach to doing cross-platform GUI stuff
I wonder if this could work for some of our some of our software
Yeah
That was the sense I got is they were building widgets internally that kind of reached a point where like we got to decide and what?
We're gonna do here and ice just seemed like the way they wanted to go
they want to say this is our GUI toolkit for cosmic and
They said they deliberated about it a lot and decided to go with iced
and I I
Have seen the reaction to this and we'll get to that a moment
But my general take on this is that we'll see we'll see where they go
we'll see if they get the accessibility stuff added I think they've got the motivation and the determination to do it and
Pop is a reasonably sized distribution
But it isn't the largest player out there and it seems to me that it's in that in that almost perfect market position
To experiment with this kind of stuff where they'll get a good user base
They'll get a really good amount of varied feedback because they have a diverse user set they have feedback channels, right?
I mean they have they have short lines and sure it does seem like they have conversations with their user base to some extent
So yeah, they absolutely will get support tickets to when things don't work
There's that element because they're selling a product that runs this stuff too. So they get that channel
It's not getting thrown into the void. Really? That's what I'm trying to say
Yeah
I think that's probably a fair assessment and I think it's a good size to experiment and see how things go and
It's not like they're creating a bunch of proprietary code. That's only gonna work on cosmic
So if they build something that seems pretty reasonable, well, then maybe the folks over at mint can take a look at it
You know something something like that
So I feel like they're kind of in the perfect position to be an R&D lab for this type of endeavor
I think that's just fine because if it goes horribly wrong
It doesn't really hurt the rest of the Linux desktop in the upstream projects and if it goes tremendously well
Then that's free software that anybody can adapt and use if they want to
Will they that's the other question
the as they say bad blood here is
I think getting to an impasse and
This time around as Cassidy put it on Twitter
The annual flare-up was kicked off based on a comment
Made by a different system system 76 engineer in my opinion
It basically was just stating kind of matter of the fact why GTK wasn't working for them
and
I think you could argue the original iteration of the post wasn't
Probably as delicate as it could have been but it wasn't really necessarily hostile either. It was just matter of fact
And it essentially said that GTK just wasn't the best choice for the job and they preferred iced and kind of went to some reasons
But the way that GTK was described I think kicked off a whole new round of online battles
Just has been a mess since then. Mm-hmm, and it can be tough sometimes when you're looking, you know
And especially in various community forums. What's the scope?
Do you interpret this as a statement of fact from someone who's trying to assert a position or is it a more of a like?
An you know, IMO this is how I view this and think about it for my use cases. I don't know
you never say those things so they just sort of implicit in yeah, they're stated as an implicit statement and
We'll have links to all of some of this all of some of this in the show notes
It's kind of ridiculous for the most part a brief summary. I would describe it as I
think
the gnome team has been
sensitive about comments made by engineers at system 76 and
I think they've transitioned from being sensitive about those comments to being sensitive about the fact that
Something hasn't happened to those employees to penalize them for those statements or prevent them from making future statements
And so now it's kind of become
Gnome camp against system 76
which of course creates a hostile work environment and they throw shade back and forth at each other and
if you think that one side is has the moral high ground here, then you're probably not familiar with the argument because
there is I think a point on both sides and it's one of these things that I think also in my personal opinion is
Spurred on by the fact that there may be a bit of concern that iced once it's been properly
Contributed to and has enough features may be a genuine alternative to something like GTK and perhaps
It's created a little bit of defensiveness from the gnome side. Yeah, it may not be true
But that is how it's kind of coming across
Especially when you see the discussions that are going on in their matrix chat room, and I think we've all been in places
rightfully, or wrong only, you know when we see
ambitious or not new
Approaches in the Linux community. I think we're sensitive to like another one of those, you know
We have several cross-platform gooey toolkits like yeah, right or we have a package manager like that. I know you have your own ideas
I I don't think you know we get we're allowed to have those thoughts. We should be careful. Maybe how we articulate them because
That's always gonna happen. That's what happens in our free software world, right? Things things change new stuff. Get it opposite it wins
Contests either on merits or just on popularity. I the other part of this I found interesting though was
When cosmic was sort of first launched
We weren't sure what it was cuz it's kind of like a collection of plugins and is it like is it really just you know
Is it just you know? Yeah, so this to me signals like there might be a lot more interesting to watch in the cosmic space
Generally, right that's kind of how I see it. It's like, okay. Well now we all of a sudden have ourselves
A genuine new contribution here. That's actually based on some technologies that you know
If you're just looking at things from the surface level and you're like I I would like my
Desktop to be built with these tools or these tools
I would actually if I was just hitting the reset button, I would also probably pick iced
I mean look at it. It looks pretty great
And then Jeremy's got I mean the team does but I think Jeremy's been primarily updating it
He's got a checklist going which I have linked in the show notes about things that are going into iced for cosmic about accessibility
Features and font and issues and they have identified a lot of things that they want to contribute upstream and they have been I
Found at least three and there may be more but I found I think at least three
Contributions from the system 76 team to iced upstream
So there the work is going in and this is just beginning and I think you're right. Let them experiment. I feel like they need a summit
Like they need a Switzerland to come in and and a gnome system 76 summit
If I were Carl, I would be considering maybe flying out some of the gnome team to system 76 and just showing them what you're doing
Showing them your team meeting the team in person because that's always a different experience
Taking them out treating them
thanking them for their contributions for what you can build on top of and
And recognizing that stuff and celebrating that stuff and seeing if that doesn't create some kind of bridge because when I watch the discourse
this time around I
Feel like the fouls may be on the gnome side and I grant that
Initial language could have been a little more diplomatic, but the reaction the plotting all of that
that's really on the gnome side and
Unfortunately, I still think it's on system 76 to fix it. You know the gnome sides volunteers
They're people scratching an itch system 76 side their employees people building a product
Trying to make money. Maybe I don't want to make money
Trying to make money. Maybe I have a stronger notion of a sort of collective representation that you know
Folks don't you know can be tough to interpret to like a speaking as a person in the project or just as a person in your
Own who has your own opinions about these things and the people involved and yeah
I don't think this situation gets better until some side just puts their hands up does the mea culpa and just
Bears and grins it and I think I mean, right? Yeah, I mean I respect really all the people involved
There's a lot of important work happening. I use all of this software and I want to continue to do so
Mm-hmm. Yeah, I hope I hope it gets worked out
I really do and
I'm also very interested to see what gets built and if any of any new ideas can get explored from this so stay tuned
We'll let you know
Linode comm slash unplugged go there to get a hundred dollars and 60-day credit on a new account
And what a great way to support the show because you try out something fantastic like Linode
And you support the show Linode makes cloud computing simple affordable and accessible
They're 30 to 50 percent cheaper than the hyperscalers that want to lock you into their crazy platforms
They also have fantastic support and the thing you guys know, I always care about performance
In my opinion, it's the best and it's just not something I just randomly came to I tried them all
I've tried them all and nothing's as good as Linode. Let me tell you and I'm not the only one that says that
There are independent studies that verify that as well, you know, it's it's kind of a simple math
Really they started about 19 years ago
they had to be really good to survive especially when businesses that started as bookstores came along and realized they had a bunch of
Extra infrastructure they could sell and make even more money and then other cloud providers got in the game because they realized hey
There's this cloud thing and we can call stuff whatever we want and charge whatever we want. It's great
It's just so great. And so they invested from their other products
Maybe their operating system market or their book sales or maybe some VC guys just can't work out
Just came in and just started dumping money in there
Linode had to compete with all of that
While just building a good product to do it. So that means they've got fantastic dedicated support
That means they have the best performance. They've got 11 data centers today. That's fantastic and they are their own ISP, but coming soon
There's gonna be more than a dozen new Linode data centers
They're turning it up past 11
2023 is gonna be such a great year for Linode and that's kind of the point
I think I would just want to leave with you when I'm deploying infrastructure. I want something I can just leave running for three five
Maybe even longer, you know years. I'd love to have something that's up there eight years
You know if we could keep it up to date maintain it. I
Don't want to have to rebuild and move this stuff
So that's one of the big calculus is that goes into who I pick as my cloud infrastructure provider
And that's why when I just look at all of the things it's Linode every single time
And that's why they're willing to give you $100 so you can try it yourself
You can form a complete opinion because $100 at their pricing means you can really try things out
So go support the show and grab that $100 and try out Linode. It's Linode.com slash unplugged you go there
You support the show. It's a great way to thank them for supporting our road trip
Making the West Coast tour possible as well as checking out their service and kicking the tires Linode.com slash
unplugged
We do have some things to chat about here in the housekeeping
I want to give a big old plug skis for the matrix room any of them Jupiter broadcasting.com slash matrix join our decentralized chat
It's pretty simple to go create yourself a matrix.org account or set up a home server
Not as simple that way but you can do that as well
You come in here and you join us
we're gonna keep our West Coast crew room going because we're gonna have future West Coast trips and as we
Expand out and do our next future thing. We'll set up chat rooms
In fact, there's a petition going around around right now to create a Portland specific chat room. Yeah, I may may have made some promises and
Actually, I'm I guess I'm making promises for you Chris because you're the one who ultimately makes the room
So I guess I couldn't I forgot about that. I thought West had to do all things like that
But it turns out I do have the power
Yeah, and I also I want to just put on your radar for all things open coming up
I know Alex from self-hosted is gonna be there
There's gonna be some other community members that are making it to all things open
But we don't have any current meetups to plug. That's it for right now. We'll find out about future events pretty soon
But doesn't that feel kind of weird? I've got a few in the works that I yeah
May not have well, you know shower thoughts, but Wes and I may have one coming up
But we don't quite want to announce it just wow
So you guys are gonna just hold your own little private meetup without me. Is that what's happening?
Oh
My god audience Chris's are fine audience right right just not this one. Yeah, cuz I got you
Well, you'll be busy with some other things that we're cooking up. This is a interesting
We do have some baller boosts to get to we like to feature the high amount boosts that came into the show to really support
the production each episode and the first one this week came Zins from
What what came Zin it came Zins from sir lurks a lot
52,118 sets the truth is you bought him because you like them. They have value to you. That's what matters
He says I listened to the double live stream on my last day off and these stats reflect the duration five hours
21 minutes and 18 seconds. That's crazy. That was a long one. I'll be crazy including user lurks a lot
No wonder why we are exhausted when we hit the road
This is I hope you enjoy the sats as much as I enjoyed the show now boo CLI does not support the raw
Linux unplugged RSS feed. Oh, it's like if you just go to our website, really? Yeah, that's embarrassing
Well, it's because we don't generate that. Yeah, it keeps coming up, doesn't it? Yeah, that's the thing for the future
Talk about that in the future
But if you do grab the feed from podcast index, you can put you can point you can point you can point
Boo see like that. I can barely talk. You're trying to get some boost the first place to start podcast index
But so when boo CLI fails it gives you a broken heart emoji as the error message
If that's not a reason to get boo CLI installed. What is lurks a lot came in though with pod verse and Albie to the rescue
He says you sure did tout boo CLI as the leap man's boost a gram which got me to figure it out
It worked for office hours. Okay good it is I honestly if you get boost a gram working
It's sort of like a Littman's test of just like a certain level of technical excellence that you must hold
Yeah, boo CLI requires a domain of knowledge multiple domains of knowledge
So I feel like if you get boo CLI going well, then I we should be sending use it. Yeah, really?
Yeah
we should maybe that's something we should think about actually if people include like a lightning address or something or an invoice and their boost or
Like they're boost for boost lightning URL. We should boost them back some sats if they use boo CLI and thus declare them the master of their
own domain
John a comes in again, is this is this six is this might be six? This is insane
I wonder how long can this be kept up? We need a counter John a says well now I'm just trying to keep my streak alive
Maybe we can get like a JB website subdomain like, you know, yeah a John a streaks
Is it is it broken yet sort of thing, right? That's an interesting idea is John a still a baller.com
Then we just need a little way on github where we can just flip it yes
No, and then the action made that stuff, right? Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Yeah, I love it. I love it
Thank you, John a for your support also sir looks a lot
We have some more boosts that will be in the show in just a little bit
We really appreciate you guys for supporting us ask not what your podcast can boost for you
But what you can boost for your podcast?
So since we got together last week, we had one last meetup
We had a few things we wanted to chat about but we also have major breaking news on the show
The Pasadena geocache has been located brum brum brum
Tell us Brent. What are the details live on the scene in the studio? What are you learning Brent?
I'm here on locations a little rainy
But I did discover an email this morning that suggested that listener JD found the geocache
They write as luck would have it. I was at a nearby doctor's appointment while listening to Linux. I plugged on Monday morning
Amazing, which is literally the morning it aired the advantages to listening when it's just been published. That's right
I went to the park immediately after and honestly found it in the very first tree. I searched. Okay, that's great
There are a lot of trees in that park. Yeah, and it took you guys
Forever to find it. They give a little bit more information just for our sakes
I'm a recent listener having just started sometime after the JPL signups. Whoa, that's great
Otherwise, I would have loved to have put my name in the hat. I'm new to Linux in general last year
I installed Ubuntu then docker just to run a minecraft server for my son and his friends. Oh, yeah
I've also just started testing paperless NGX. Oh
Thanks for all that you do and feel free to leave more caches in Pasadena
Yeah, we'd had a good time doing that
I think that's something we could do more often because
We could come up with like a perpetual cache to one that's like designed to like have a note
You leave something take something. We could have a special
Matrix room for people who found the cache, you know with the URL
Oh, that's a fun idea see what when you can build your own rooms at willy-nilly styles
You can do all kinds of things. That's great. I am so glad that they found that if you found we have another geocache
we have one in Sacramento and
And there's another oh, yeah, the near grants pass near great in grants pass southern, Oregon area
We also failed to drop one near Portland. I think we meant to yesterday and we had a lot of things
So I may just grab it on my way home and drop it off somewhere in the mountains. Yeah, so we're up there in, Canada
Well, it could be in the US version. We'll see. Oh, no, I say do, Canada
All right, if you can that makes it a cross-border. Oh, I guess the problem is there's nobody up there
Well, the 16 of us can go searching for yeah, it might take a while. Let's get a sealant and syrup
It's a whole thing. Yeah. Yeah, you got it like bait them in. That's how it works
So since our last show we had the Portland meetup, which was our last meetup on our way north
We had we just have never stopped in Portland for a meetup because we're always blasting through to get home and we felt like we owed
this audience
You know a little bit of a get-together, you know for how much we talk about Seattle Portland's a special place
And you know, we gotta treat it right and it's not that far away. So Wes came down like a legend
He showed up during just just like, you know, like like like a like a total boss
He shows up about a half hour after it started. So of course, he has a grand entrance
Every everybody's sitting down. So when Wes comes in
And that was really great
I thought it was a highlight of the night that you made it down and it made it so much fun and then afterwards
um
You got to carpool with or I guess caravan with us for a bit and stay in lady jupes
You got your first night and lady. I know I mean, how long have I known you?
Yeah, and this is my first time I couldn't believe that was your first time. I mean, I've stayed there
What like 40 nights or something?
I'm sorry, you had to be there when the automation systems were down. I just felt very embarrassed about that
It's kind of nice actually because I think the next time you know next time I stay a night there
It's gonna be all the slides will be working. It'll be top-notch. That's true. I have a modern ZigBee setup. You're right
I'll be able yeah. Yeah, that's a good point. I'll be able to top the current one
Whereas if everything was working it would have peaked. Yeah. Yeah, okay. I'm gonna see a huge improvement
I'm excited for right at least now the pressures on a plus you got a little time with Levi
Oh, yeah, I got some morning snuggles with that cute dog. Yeah, he's a good boy about that
these were great meetups that we went to and the
amazing thing is
every single
location was sourced and ID'd by our audience by our listeners like
Micah, I'm wearing a NASA t-shirt in honor of the occasion the road trip
Very very thoughtful and did you come up with this place if I remember correctly? I did suggest it
I've eaten here before I live about ten blocks away. So
So you just wanted it to be convenient for you. Is that it? Well, it worked, didn't it?
And I noticed you grabbed a bunch of swag and stuff
Is it nice to hang out with a bunch of like-minded people here?
Yeah, it's great because you know, my wife is a very intelligent person
But her eyes glaze over when I start talking about Linux and she wishes I would change the subject
So it's fun to be around people who are interested in this stuff
And is this your first JB meetup?
It is not. I went to Chris's birthday bash in January.
I wanted to be there, but I couldn't be there. How was it? It was great
I thought I was gonna have the record for coming the farthest
But there was actually a listener there from Puerto Rico who happened to be in town on business. So I lost that contest
Of course, well you were second best that's good enough
Yes, it's funny how at these meetups like there's always the okay who came the furthest. Yeah, it's always shocking
It's shocking how far people come for these meetups. You know, that was listener Jose who showed up both in, Colorado
Do you remember that? Yeah, of course here at the studio and I was half expecting him to also show up at one of our meetups
I know I always do now. I always think about Jose. You're always welcome
Yeah, he's always welcome. They're really all great. The Portland one felt really easy
it just felt like just clicking and talking to old friends and there was such a a
broad range of topics at the entire table and
It was a long table. They they gave us basically one end of the building
Which was great because we needed that space and they were very accommodating
All of these breweries were so super chill and so accommodating. Yeah, that's what's nice
It's like you can have a kind of a really mixed group. It's not super crowded. There's a lot of nice space
There's you know, there's non-alcoholic drinks alcoholic drinks different types. There's stuff Brent can have
There's usually a pretty good food menu
Yeah, and just the general general vibe is you know come as you are and hang out for as long as you want
yeah, and just you know make for great conversation and
Listener Nick and listener Joel put some of the best things about these meetups into their own words. That's been great
we've had some wonderful cold beer here from migration brewing and
a lot of good people fun people and it's just good to sit and talk with people about
self-hosting and
Linux and and you know, yeah not get the glossed over stairs
And and so a lot of really good conversation tonight and was that your experience as well?
Yeah, the meetup has been a lot of fun
we've been able to talk about all kinds of topics from Linux related to
You know jogging or running or TV shows or
every everybody's
Familiar with ads and ad blockers and so that's been a common topic as well
For techies and non techies alike. So yeah, there's plenty to talk about. It's been wonderful
Yeah, I agree and at our end of the table we were talking about like no-till farming and all sorts of things
so it's like amazing to me the
breadth of topics that we can just connect on really easily and that's what I find about these meetups is it's just
Great fun and people that you could just become friends with really easily. So thank you both for being here
Yeah, thanks for having us and putting all this together
it's it's been great and it's great to put faces to your guys's voices and and
Get some great swag here from Linode and thank you as well. Thank you
Yeah, it's been great to chat with people all kinds of interesting conversation and like you said putting names to faces. It's been great
Thank you. You know, the real trick is once they see our faces do they keep listening? Yeah, that is we'll find out, right?
I think we have a good shot because
Several of these meetups that we went to
Afterwards there's talk about they want to organize their own event
They want to keep it going even if the JB crew can't be there. They want to be there big meetup energy
Yeah, there is a lot of big meetup energy and I always think man
I just wish we had a website we could tell them to go to and self organize
I want to build a self-hosted meetup site that the audience can use to self-organize. I think they'd use that
I will said there's some cool energy at the meetups as well
Like SUCD at the Portland meetup just gave us some gifts like some weird 3d printed. What would you call them Chris?
Fidget spinners kind of I mean they were really neat though. We sure fidgeted with them
Yeah, the kids are fidgeting with them right now. Yeah, that was really great
And other folks brought other gifts at the other meetups. So everyone who gave us all sorts of things. Thank you very much
Yeah, very nice audience. So generous. So nice. So too good too good
We should probably just fold in fold the cards close up shop and it right now
Ended on a high note because I mean just always so nice when you go see these people
How could it ever be any better? How could you ask for anything more when you're doing these shows?
I was chatting with someone at the Portland meetup and they put they put a nice contrast on it
This gentleman went to a fair number of regular sort of tech meetups
I think you know did sort of DevOps things professionally which many, you know
Many of our audience or developers or do full-time tech stuff
But that's really all you get at those sort of tech, you know, right focused meetups and a lot of these JB meetups
It's it's just such a nice mix of people who do it for work. Yeah, but
Not the people who only do it for work occasionally, but it's it's enthusiast, right?
And it can be like you're just doing home automation at home a lot of self strong self-hosted showing
I think in Portland or you know
You just like this stuff at work and you want to learn you you're so interested like I think you know
We have been that you just want more of it
So it's an interesting thing because you know Brent had a chance to chat with a few people and I was listening back to the audio
This morning and just based on the conversations I had had to
Yeah, not everybody is doing Linux as their day job that comes to these meetups and some of them
They're just people who like to geek out and go deep into topics and Linux is one of the topics
They're going deep into and I think they're just looking for content
That has you know high production standards that they want to listen to that digs into this kind of stuff
and so they begin to build a
whole set of knowledge around this topic by listening to the show and then by checking out the things we talked about because they're
Just intellectually curious and then they take it to the next level and actually go to these meetups
And I think these people are better than me because I just don't think I'd ever take it to that next level
But they do two things. I love about that is one. Yeah, right that they can take it to levels
I don't have because I think there's a there's an enthusiasm that sometimes you know the professionals you get a bit tired and jaded
Stuff when you gotta make it work and you have to get up at 9 a.m. And like do the thing
But like when it's when it's the when it's your release when it's a something you're genuinely excited about
It's good to have that energy. Yeah, and then the other part is once you've got the Linux bridge
Yeah, like for folks with so many different backgrounds. It's a chance for us to really learn a lot
Although I got to say some of my favorite conversations are the jaded professionals that have like, you know what I'm talking about
Those are great conversations. We always we always have a good chuckle with those ones too because yeah, we know we've been there
We feel we're part of that set. Yeah, I
Think it's probably also important to note that West the only reason you and I are here from from a bunch of JB meetups
It's right. Oh weird, right
Yeah, the meetups are us and we are in the meetups. Whoa, we are made on the meetups the drop. Yeah, it's crazy
Thank you to Linode too. If you're thinking about getting some hosting seriously, check out Linode, you know
They they invest in these kind of meetups so that way our community can connect
Professionals can talk to other professionals. They can network. I overheard people, you know exchanging details for jobs for you know
Contact us for getting a job like that kind of stuff was going down Linode, you know
They're investing long-term in the community and that I think is a particularly keen insight into how they think about this stuff
and how they try to support it at a real like
Grassroots level so Linode comm slash unplugged. Yeah, we had plenty of tech failures, but none of that was Linode's fault
I don't know the stuff we hosted on the node that just works
Bit warden comm slash Linux bit warden is my password manager
It's West's password manager and they have been just going at full speed. They recently announced fast mail email alias integration
They have great new features for your vault a browser extension that has been turned up to I'm gonna say 13 not even 11 and
They've even been giving love to their command-line interface. Yeah bit warden
I don't talk about it, but they have a command-line interface as well
They have a flat pack app too
Which is like the first thing I install now on my genome desktop and bit warden wants to remind everyone that October is cyber security
Awareness month. So this is something just as a moment as just say, you know, if you've been trying to bring up that conversation
This is something you can do to kind of put your foot in the door
It's cyber security awareness month and using a strong password is like number one with a bullet
Which you can do to protect yourself online and bit warden can generate and store strong passwords for you
it's easy to enable multi-factor authentication. It's also recommended you keep your software up to date and
Honestly, you should be aware if your passwords are being used online and watch out for phishing as well
These are all things along with a great password
Keeping your credentials unique across your websites and your services. You can do to really protect yourself online
As bit warden would like to tell you and I would like to remind you there's really nothing better you can do than just having
A great place to store your secrets and share them privately and securely because these are things you're gonna have to have
You're gonna have logins. You're gonna have two-factor codes
You're gonna have secret information like passphrases or maybe bank account information those types of things for families
Bit warden can be the place to store that you're gonna have that kind of information just happens. It's life
And multi-factor authentication is a great way to add a little extra security to your accounts there, too
And enabling two-step login on bit warden improves the security of your password vault
You've got options like verification through email or authenticator app or Fido to our Yubikey
You could also do that and premium subscribers can also have bit warden generate time-based one-time password authentication codes for your accounts
Which adds a little bit of strength there, doesn't it?
All of this added together makes bit warden a fantastic and incredible maybe even the best I'd say tool
To protect yourself online bit warden support security for all with fully featured free accounts available to everyone as well
So this cyber security awareness month protect yourself and help protect the loved ones around you your friends your family by educating them on password security
They probably already think of you as the tech person. They know this is a great opportunity to use that influence for good
And send them to bit warden.com
Slash Linux go get started with a free trial for teams or an individual plan right now at bit warden.com slash Linux
As always we got some great feedback
Thank you everyone for sending that in Paul wrote in and writes I want to thank you for introducing me to silver blue
For the first time I don't want to throw my ancient HP stream laptop into the trash every time I use it
This distro seems to run crazy fast compared to kabuntu running on the exact same system
And it's not nearly as glitchy with the suspend and resume
It's the first time I've used redhat and fedora anything and so far. I gotta say I'm impressed
hmm, you know, I didn't say which version of kabuntu he was
Switching from but some of this I don't know. What do you think West but couldn't some of this just be explained by a new
colonel
Well a new colonel is always a nice upgrade. Yeah, I mean especially you're talking like like a big jump
Yeah performance improvements sleep suspend improvements. There also could be something about Wayland
I notice a general smoothness with Wayland that I don't get on x11
So if you're coming from kabuntu using X you go over to your silver blues using the Wayland's
It's gonna be a smooth experience there, too
And I don't even know if we need a dissect it
I think we can just be happy like people live in that silver blue lifestyle
Like it's true right like silver blue works for people. It's not a you might expect sort of the reverse, right?
You're like, oh, well, I did silver blue it all of these weird exceptions. I had to figure out
That's not what Paul's writing it about. No, you know what the kids say. They say glow on
Glow on and they're really into a mutability
Ian has a pretty close to home request here for meetups
Ian writes when is JB coming to the East Coast like East Coast of Canada surely, you know
There's a big audience here in Toronto a big audience in Toronto. You say well, I believe that leads us right in teleboosts
And now it is time for the boost Sam's quanch boosts in with
16,180
You guys ever plan to come up to BC for stuff
I mean Vancouver and Victoria are pretty large tech communities these days
Thanks and keep up the great work. Also Sam's quanch here reveals that
16180 first five digits of the golden ratio nice
But I think here we have to defer to our local Canadian, right I think we should well
I think one thing that's fascinating about where we're sitting exactly right now geographically is
Sam's quanch here says when you're coming up to Victoria and it turns out it's kind of at the same latitude
I think so that's a fascinating thing about Canada. There's one tip for you
Mention maple syrup. Yeah, I would actually love to see a Canadian road trip
Although I feel like that's maybe a little bit more of a dedication than what we just did on the west coast here
But certainly there are a few locations that would be great to do a small little thing Chris
Vancouver's not even that far for you. Yeah. Yeah, I definitely want to make it up there gosh
I mean
It's hard to talk about it right now when I'm feeling like I never want to do another road trip for the rest of my life
And I live in an RV. So that really tells you how hard it was
Earlier you said you didn't want to do an American road trip. Oh
Right. No, actually I really would like to do it. I wonder I know
There is a season of life that I am in now
where it is really hard to travel and so I just kind of like cram it in there like a maniac and then just sort
of like
Chaos ensues hate yourself a little. Yeah, but I feel like there will be a season of life
Where dad is not as interesting and then maybe dad will travel more, you know, I'm saying I'm not saying I'm your dad
I'm saying I'm literally my kid's dad, you know get right you get where I'm going with this
And so maybe I'll travel more, but I don't want to wait that long at the same time. So
Well, I'll just you know what?
This is just the booster is listening now
So I'll get into it if you are in a city that has a venue that would be willing to host a couple of crazy
Podcasters and host, you know 30 40 60 of our closest friends
Get in contact with us if we could start finding venues in these areas where when we get there we can produce a show
because I'll tell you what happens friends is
We kill ourselves get into these places holding these meetups doing the driving and then we don't have any show afterwards
We don't actually record a show there and then you didn't because you're driving
It's hard to find the time to do the work to figure out the plan the show
Yeah, we're doing seven-hour drive days. Then we're prepping for a show
Then I'm waking up at six in the morning four in the morning
Whatever it is to drive or do a show and I'm either driving or I'm doing a show and I just realized that's crazy
So instead let's go to a location. We'll do a show there. We'll do it live and you know
Maybe moderate like ticket something cheap something that's affordable
But maybe we could pay for our tickets to fly in or something like that
So if you're in an area like Vancouver or I don't care, Ohio
I don't care if you got a venue they got food I can eat and they can host some of our friends and the three
Of us they're willing to watch some buffoons make a podcast in real time. Let us know Chris at Jupiter broadcasting calm
We're better yet. If you really want me to see it boost it in. Oh
Speaking of boosts a young dookie boosts in with four thousand and forty eight sets
I wanted to point out three projects that helped me mapping location searches on
Android I use an app called a castus photon
Which you can use to search for points of interest and then it lets you open the result in whatever your map or navigation tool
Of choice by default it uses the photon project public instance
But can be self-hosted. Ah, alternatively you can use the polis project polis.io
Which which can also be self-hosted via g code earth safe travels
So the mapping situation on Android is an interesting one. I've been running graphing since the road trip was like a
Weekend to the road trip. I started using graphing and I quickly realized that I still was I kind of ended up needing to use
Google Maps, but this is not a lot of great mapping options when you really are like
Really depending on this thing
like I need because I also I
Need satellite images to check out gas stations to see if they can fit tubes to make sure I can get in and out
And man Google makes that really crazy easy. And if you don't have Apple Maps
Which I didn't done graph, you know us I kind of ended up falling back to Google Maps, which kind of stunk
I'm sure I could figure out a better solution. I'd love to hear what people do for like the satellite images
I don't necessarily need it for navigation, but I needed to review an area
I need to be able to plug in an address or GPS coordinates, you know to me
Let me know Michael B. Boos in with 3000 cents
Chris I would love to hear which of the GNOME workflows you learned
GNOME workflows have been a very popular topic on
Like just I don't know every
Morning or every like constantly Brenner talking about this because he's been trying out pop OS
You're trying to get him to fundamentally change how he uses a computer. That's true. And
So workflows have been coming up a lot
I'll tell you here's a real quick rundown of how I've used GNOME and I found it really effective
It's very first thing I did around the GNOME 312 era
But I think you could do it anytime is I just decided to spend a month each day
Or each week or whatever I needed at the time learning the GNOME way of doing things
So I just decided well if GNOME doesn't want me to use minimize and maximize
I'll try without that for a bit
I didn't always stick with it like that one I I didn't stick with
but some of them I did and one of the things I adopted that I find to be pretty effective on GNOME especially now with
Horizontal or workspaces on laptops is I full screen a couple of apps
But I do that thing where I put two apps together
So maybe like one screen will be element
It'll be big and wide and then I'll have like a small version of telegram on that same desktop
And that is always desktop too. And then I I use an extension
I think it's called like auto window or something like that or there's an extension that will automatically
We'll find it for the show notes right Wes. Oh surely. Yeah, sure that automatically opens applications on specific workspaces
So desktop one is always my web browsers desktop two is always my primary chat applications
desktop three is gonna be steam and desktop four is usually just like a catch-all where I just put all kinds of stuff on there and
The console kind of just floats between the desktops where I need a console. I also have a drop-down console
I think it's called D term
But there's a few options that I like a lot and I combine all of that
Along with a couple of essential extensions like I like to see a workspace indicator
I like to have a few more system tray icons than you get by default. So I combine all that together
Auto move windows you already found it and it is in the show notes and that will automatically put
Certain windows and certain virtual desktop spaces and I find that to be an essential way to use
GNOME and Chris do you use a different workflow depending on whether you have three monitors or not?
More or less mostly with GNOME if I have a if I have multiple monitors I leave
The external monitors on a static workspace and I just switch the main monitor workspace most the time
not always
most of the time
We got a boost in from user
6475 just 64 humble sets
B-o-o-s-t coming in with my little fountain FM boost. I wanted to say thank you and keep up the great show
I'm curious though
Are there fewer emails to read on the show because people have moved to boosting or have those been getting put to the side?
Podcasting to know seems like a great way to support creators
But I don't want to see those who haven't come over being left behind kind of like the boosts
and we do the same thing with emails where we select for content and
There's definitely been less emails now that there's more boosts
But you also get more boosts because the lengths are shorter than probably 80% of the emails that we get
Yeah
It makes them very easy to select them because they're already
Essentially cut for the show and so you can get to more of them as well
But there has been a shift which has been interesting also seeing that on Kota radio not a huge shift not like a ginormous
shift but a noticeable difference as
And that's fine in a lot of ways. These are easy to process too. So that works for us
What I've noticed is actually the emails tend to be the long-form ideas that are sort of deep dives
if you will and the boost seems to be the place where all the the quick ideas or the just quick questions come in and
They're not lesser either way, but they've just evolved. I think yeah different things
And kind of what but each is best for I suppose
Cyprus boosted in with 1200 sats. Hey guys, have you thought of doing an osint? I guess that's like a
Open source intelligence episode. I've only just discovered a Loki net which looks like Tor but seems to use blockchain behind it
So I went and looked at Loki net have either one of you guys seen this? No. Oh, man
I don't know if this is anything actually worth totally trusting
But they sure make a cool-looking website totally like know their demo is
Oh, I better check that but when you scroll down look at that black hole animation they have on there
That's how you know, it must be high-quality software. It's got a black hole animation. You see that? Okay
It is it does seem to be GPL 3. Yeah, I actually I mean I joke but here's what they pitch
Decentralized network onion routed traffic and no IP address looking at hides your IP that you're connecting from and to
Your location and identity are unknown. All traffic is onion routed. Your browsing is private secure and anonymous
L-ok I net org if you want to check it out. Yeah, they do seem to have a fairly extensive FAQ there
I kind of I kind of minute. I actually kind of interested you started talking blockchain for this kind of thing
And I'm a little skeptical
Blockchain hasn't been great for much other than as a distributed ledger for Bitcoin
Maybe we'll see something else. I'm kind of impressed by hive. So maybe they're on to something
We shall see if you guys want to check it out. I'd be down if anybody actually let's start with this
If you've tried Loki net let us know give us your first impressions your thoughts and if you get us interested
Maybe we'll check it out. Yeah. Why is it worth spending time on? Yeah
Why that over tour because tour seems like it's got the network effect, but maybe I'm wrong on this kind of thing
But I don't have cool graphics. Oh, yeah tour doesn't have a black hole do they Wes?
I'm not that not last I checked I hadn't checked today. So yeah, we'll have to check back. Maybe they will
So true grits boosts in with the traditional Trek boost
So I had been asking
just to get an update on how far behind people tend to fall from time to time and then they're
They've been boosting in to let us know and true grit says I got about a month behind on all the podcast
But I'm glad to say I'm officially caught up now and thanks for the exclusive member feed bonus last week
Well, you're welcome. Yeah, we didn't have a traditional live show
but we had something we want to turn around for the audience because you know what we love our members and so we wanted to
Get them something even if we weren't live and we have a boost from bronzewing this week 9001 sats over 9000
Okay, so this is really awesome we mentioned that JPL used to use Solaris well bronzewing writes in
that the shadow UAV the drone that the US Army uses is currently in its second version and
The first version didn't use rail use Solaris, but the second version of the shadow UAV is running rail
They run rail on the stations to control it and they run Red Hat Enterprise Linux on the actual drone
Wow that the US Army uses that's pretty wild
Also bronze we wanted to say that fountain FM now has carplay support nice update
And so he can now earn sats while he drives glad you guys had a great time at JPL
Hoping maybe you guys can swing by Boise sometime. Thanks for the show boost you later
Yeah, we got to get to Eastern Washington. We got to get to Boise little Spokane Boise. Yeah, that'd be fun
Yeah, I'm not taking the RV though
Parking that thing
Never do another road trip again. Oh, yeah, just a car caravan this time. Yeah, why not? Why not? It's a race you say
I love a race. So let's go
But I mean that sounds a lot of fun. But no actually one day we'll road trip again
But in the meantime, I'm taking a break
Soltros boosted in with 11,000 sets
The coolest thing about stadia was its portability
I have a really nice gaming rig with Ryzen 5600 X a ton of RAM and an RTX 3060
But I also enjoyed gaming like destiny 2 on my phone. Oh destiny 2 is a great game
I know it had its issues, but it was just so ahead technologically compared to things like Amazon Luna Xbox xCloud
Etc. It's a shame to see it go. I agree. It was technically better
So for example, the NVIDIA GeForce streaming stuff is pretty great for a Linux user
Because you can import your Steam library
So if you bought a game on Steam, you can stream it on GeForce. Now stadia didn't get that stadia
You had to buy the game, but it was like a headless game
You would hit play and it would launch you like way into the game into like the menu of the game
But on things like GeForce now
You actually like remote desktoping into a Windows virtual desktop is renting yourself like a temporary Windows VM to game on and then it starts
Steam.exe and you sign into your Steam account including like you got to go do the two-factor stuff
And then like it's got to like super fast download the game which works pretty good because they got fast internet connections
But it downloads the game and installs it on the Windows VM then launches the game
And then you're playing the game and you go through the first time setup for all the game stuff
And while it detects your hardware right stadia didn't have any of that. I
Talk about like it's already gone
Marcel wrote in with 3000 sets
stadia is a self-fulfilling prophecy
Everyone knew Google would cancel it at some point just like they cancel everything. So nobody used it. So Google had to cancel it
It can't be Linux's fault alone the stadia failed
It's the old-school thinking of game publishers even a Windows VM would trip up anti-cheat
They were referring to Marcel's referring to the verge kind of pin some of this on the fact that you had to target Linux and Vulcan
Which is funny because I'm sure the same verge would be happy to run a piece about what a hit the deck is
Just so backwards for 12 Linux boosted in with
What do you call that two megs of sats?
Thanks for the shootout last week
I didn't purchase a stadia because I didn't trust Google to keep the service operational and leave me hung up to dry
When money is tight, it's hard to gamble on these types of devices
Perhaps if they stayed at launch they would keep it operational for a certain number of years
The reception would have been a bit better. Thanks for the quality content and great job everyone
So this makes me wonder I have a question for both of you
What does Google have to do in the future now to get you to think their next product? They're going to launch
Maybe it has a subscription. Maybe it doesn't what do they have to do to convince you to actually try it would something
Like a minimum years like 412 Linux is suggesting like we guarantee this will exist for five years
Would that get you to try it or is that ship sailed because of the privacy concerns like what?
What does Google have to do comprehensively to get you to trust their next product boy?
I mean on the face of it that sort of guarantee sounds nice, but can you really trust that guarantee?
You know like there's the question of that because like four years in they're just like wow
I know we said that we're gonna do the same thing where we refund you so we're not really like breaking our promise in that way
Yeah, I think I'd need to hear you know, I mean if they just had a product that legitimately went well and that I wasn't interested in
But there was like, you know, I would could get over that hump to the next phase that could do it barring that
I feel like I I would want to either understand how it was connected to their sort of core ad business
That could maybe justify like okay if I can understand how this is like directly in that bottom line then like a type of transparency almost
Yeah, maybe I could understand like do they have strong incentives to keep it working because it is part of their business
Otherwise, I think I'd want to hear more from ex Googlers or like some more of the culture
Because we just hear so much about like how segmented everything is sometimes internally how there's this sort of like
Launch a product to get promoted and then you know, you move off that team and go do some other things until that changes
Are there some kind of inkling that they have more of an overall holistic organizational focus?
I don't be hard to trust anything Brett. What if they guaranteed that?
Everything they do for this product if they ever shut it down will be GPL. Does that change the calculus for you?
This is such a hard question. I think I think that would at least get me really looking but then it becomes almost like
Very different than everything else they've done. So is it just a new business is interesting question. I feel like
Surely there are certainly some wonderfully intelligent people working there who are just like us and like the people who showed up at our meetups
And I want to get to know those people but Google as a huge massive business
Has always tripped me up and I've I don't I actually don't think they can really do anything
Get me signed up. I wonder if that's how I'm wondering if that's that's how most the audience is feeling to let us know what you think out there
What would Google have to do or could they do anything to convince you?
And I mean think about it
Like if there was some sort of transparency approach like Wes is talking about and some sort of commitment to a time and maybe a release of code
Maybe transparency on privacy. What would it take?
Let us know boostin or linuxunplug.com slash contact because I'm wondering if it's just they're too far gone as a brand
Could you imagine if they released stadia's source code just be like, oh we're shutting it down
But you guys can well the issue is and I'm wondering I'd like to hear somebody address this is
How do you solve the infrastructure aspect of something like that?
I like I mean the only way I can think of it is if they had some sort of portable self-hostable version of stadia that they let you download or something as a talker container
But the pie can't do it. Yeah, right
I mean, that's just I'm wondering I'd love to hear the audience feedback on that one. We got a thousand stats from happy listener
I thought y'all should get a boost for recognizing the fact that you maintained a really high audio quality standard even went on the road
I'm impressed. Oh, you should see what we had to do to make that possible
I don't know. We want to admit on air. We might get in trouble by Airbnb, but we had to make modifications temporary modifications
But I'll just say this turns out beds
Mattresses sheets blankets. They all make for good temporary sound 60 pillows too is yeah
What are you more useful for podcast any of what you usually use it for?
I wanted to say to happy listener
Thank you for recognizing that kind of value and then returning that value to the show
That's exactly the kind of value for value exchange
We're talking about or like how listeners that helped us source great locations
For breweries or listeners that show up to the mumble room or participate in the community
Those are types of a value for value exchange that we also really appreciate
So when you recognize something you appreciate we appreciate about the shows and you boost in to recognize it
It means a lot to us. Also. I think we should give a special shout out to our editor drew
Who did extra work to make sure that we sounded as best as possible?
No matter what we throw at him. Yeah, and also when we had technical difficulties
That meant that we recorded what like three hours later than we were expecting right still got through it, right?
That is very true. That really was pretty flexible and pretty awesome of drew
So thank you to drew for making it sound as good as it possibly could too and then last boost of the show goes to
Mr. Rustic cast of Versa
Comes in with a thousand sats
I've been a listener of JB for a decade. You spoiled my ears with amazing audio quality. Stop it you guys. Oh my gosh
JB is the best in the biz when it comes to high quality consistent audio
I hope to try out RoboSats soon the reason I actually included this boost right here. I hope to try out RoboSats soon
And I hope to have time to spend in the matrix channel and have someone hold my hand as well
lol RoboSats is a great way to get
Anonymous Bitcoin really simply through a system that I think is a great experience and
See, I was hoping I could buy robots with sats. You could probably one day probably
I mean, I don't know how you do us could try it
And I do have a few thank yous out there
We got 2600 sats from grounded grid suggesting that we try out software to find radio
We heard that at the meetups too. So something will be playing around with
10,000 sats from Deleted who is testing out his new breeze install because he don't want to switch podcast apps
We got a 500 sats from DM Marowski
Not sure about that. I don't think so the Marowski. All right with their first boost and a shout out to real maple syrup
Yeah, one of your brethren. Uh-huh one of 16 good and we got a thousand sats from couch Fox
Which is a great username who is a member and also boosted in and would like to have the member feed boostable
We do have member feed upgrade scheduled as one of our next projects and then bend
I boosted in with leet sat saying they're also looking forward to those member feed upgrades. Okay, okay got we got it
We got no bad coder or nomadic order five boosted in 557 sats. Just great to see you guys in Pasadena
Cheers, sir. That was so much fun
It was yeah
If you'd like to support the show get a new podcast app and get all the new podcasting features like chapters
Host info sat streaming search and boosts. Well, then you need a new podcast app new podcast apps comm go get a podcasting
2.0 compatible app or if you want to nerd out and go with boost CLI
You absolutely can and if you don't want to switch apps Albee alby something worth checking out and so is breeze
be our easy
Technology if you're interested in more of our back that behind the scenes adventures
Office hours this week is gonna have some pretty juicy content. I think we ran into let's just say a
Few little issues and so stay tuned for that one office hours 14 coming up and also
we'd love to hear from you if you have any ideas on how we might have done the trip a little differently or
Ideas on maybe a pic since we're missing one this week
Please hit us up Linux unplug comm slash contact. Yes, and it's a pics. Let's get some audience pics coming in
I like that. Remember if it's a certain language then it gets a standpoint clip
You're invited to hang out with us for the live stream as well. We do it every single Sunday
We and we don't have technical issues at Jupiter tube at noon Pacific 3 p.m
Eastern generally, but we'll convert it to your local time at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar
if you're in the industry
you owe it to yourself to check out Linux action news or if you just want to
Stay apprised of all the things going on in the world of Linux and open source that really impact the industry Linux action news
Comm it's really a companion to this show wouldn't you say? Oh, yeah, I would say I mean we're on it
So we might be biased. No, I think so, too. Yeah. Okay Brent's not on the show
We can't fit all the news in this show because we have like, you know stuff to talk about projects to update
Ridiculous servers to update live on the show
The news goes in the section is that's right links to everything we talked about today. Well, that's over at Linux unplugged comm slash
479 thanks for joining us. We'll see you right back here next Sunday
I
Have a little update that I think I should probably share well ain't honest
Well, as you know Chris intimately, I've been using the dev one the whole trip
Yeah
And we decided to leave my x250 here at the studio a big moment
The trusty ThinkPad was left behind for the newly deployed
dev one with
Cosmic not with plasma and I you know
Despite some listeners at some of the meetups trying to convince me
Otherwise I did stick with cosmic the whole time you did I did and I even resisted adding
13 extensions to make it look like Chris's setups
Yeah, I kept trying to tempt you
but I'm curious did you stick with it because you were committed to sticking with cosmic or did you stick with it because
The schedule was so unrelenting. We didn't even get five minutes to install packages. Let alone switch a desktop environment
Yeah, you know I
It's both. I certainly haven't updated since we left the studio
So I feel like yeah
The schedule was tricky in the sense that we were just moving constantly at every hour of the day
But now that we're stead now that we're staying put now that we're now that we're in the studio
What happens next this plasma go on there? Well, I don't know
I feel like maybe you know, we've got what an hour before our dinners ready
I feel like we can come up with something more adventurous
And I just want to take a nap