We've got to get real, we've got to talk about something more important, and that's beer.
And I want to know if you guys have seen Brewy.
It's a fully automated brewing machine with a compact design that runs Linux, and yes
this was one of my runs Linux, but I've got to talk to you, I've got to share it with
you guys.
Look at this, it's on IndieGoGo, $109,000 raised already of a goal of $100,000 with
46 days left.
So they're already at 109% with 46 days left, and I want to play this for you because this
is the most magical machine ever invented by mankind, and I'm really excited.
Until now.
That's why we created Brewy, the first fully automated home brewery.
Just place the ingredients into the machine, scan the RFID card that comes with the ingredients,
and that's it.
Brewy takes care of the rest, exactly like a master brewer would do.
Brewy is perfect for beginners and experts alike.
Experiment, modify recipes, or create new ones.
Set the temperature for mashing and loitering, choose your own ingredients, set different
times for adding hops, or choose one of the 23 other parameters for your brew.
With Brewy, you can literally brew any kind of beer.
Our system notifies you once your beer is ready, and you can drink it.
Right on the phone.
It's always online.
You can control and monitor your brew by a phone, PC, or tablet, so you have time for
other important things besides beer.
Brewy also has an online recipe database where you can browse recipes and even create your
own recipes.
Are you seeing this?
An online recipe database.
You can save your favorite recipe and reproduce it any time.
In some places, it is hard to connect with other brewers.
That's why we've created a platform where you can share your experiences, exchange ideas.
All right, so Blaster, what do you think?
Do you want to go halfsies on this with me, because this is the most amazing invention
of our lifetime, and I feel like we need to take advantage of this, and we could easily
make it a show segment.
Yes.
Let's do this.
All right.
Okay, we're doing it.
I think this is so cool.
I'm really excited about it.
It's called Brewy.
Now, here's the problem.
This is why we got to go halfsies, because maybe we want to go thirdsies, actually.
The beginner pack, 15 out of 50 claimed, $1,500.
Damn it.
Yeah, I mean, this is a real... This is a big boy rig.
This is the real deal, right?
I mean, you're making a lot of beer out of this thing, okay?
You're controlling it with your smartphone, and the damn thing runs on Linux.
I mean, let's get real.
Of course, it's $1,500.
It should be more than that.
Think about it.
It runs on Linux.
Let me tell you about some of the specs before you get a little scared away.
It's got a 4.3 inch color LCD screen on the front.
It has 802.11 BG and N, plus an RFID transceiver built in.
It's got a USB port.
This is a brewer, an automatic brewer, okay?
It can hold 20 liters, 5.2 gallons for us yanks.
Takes about five to six hours to brew, and then 14 days for fermentation.
That's amazing, okay?
That's worth $1,500 right there.
Okay.
It runs something called, and I'm not familiar with this, Pokey-based Linux.
What the hell is Pokey-based Linux?
I don't know, but you manage it from Android, iOS, Windows Phone, mobile apps, or just a
generic web interface.
It has magnetic valves with brushless pumps, stainless steel containers, 20,000 hour pumps,
automatic water inlet, two, my friends, automatic hop inserters, okay?
Solid state relay controls.
I'm sorry.
How could we not back this?
I almost feel like it's so damn expensive, but this is the most... We got to get these
people on the show.
Rotten Corpse, you got to make a note about this.
We got to get these people-
Party now.
Oh, you are.
Yeah, we got to talk to these-
He's on it.
Maybe we can get a review unit.
This is amazing.
Okay.
Would this bring back beer as tasty?
We would have to.
I mean, I think it would.
Uh-huh.
I think that would happen.
See, they had early... See, I wish I would have jumped on this early, because they had
$100,000 early bird packages.
This would create a competition between the brewers at Linux Fest Northwest.
Yeah.
Oh, here's the-
Yeah, totally.
Here's what we'd want, too.
The unique skin package includes all the items of the professional package... Oh, a professional
package, huh?
That sounds like us, too.
We're professionals, right?
But you get to add your own logo to it.
Come on, let's do this.
We could put the Jupiter Broadcasting logo on there.
But the professional package, check this out, includes a beginner package... Oh, hello.
These accessories include a pH meter.
Nice.
Amazing.
One measuring cylinder, one water quality testing instrument, and one ball and hydrometer.
I don't think I'll say that right.
This is really exciting.
When beer and Linux come together, magic happens.
So anyways, it's Brewery, and it's on IndieGoGo.
Hey, those guys at Linux Fest proved that.
Yeah, it's still got 46 days left, too.
So if you want to fund that ass, there is a link in the show notes.
Gosh, that's cool.
I really, really want one.
Man.
I smell a revival of podcasts.
You know, I tell you what, guys.
The truth of the matter is... I'm not bitter, but if I had Leo Laporte money...
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
I would be just buying all kinds of crap.
I would just be buying crap like that all the time.
It does.
Yeah.
Well, it looks like they're based in Hungary, so regionally, they're closer to Popeye and
Popeye, so I think you should have it sent to the UK and save on shipping expenses.
I agree.
All right.
Okay.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's filled with the holiday
GNU spirit, well, and a little bit of Santa's rum.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey there, Matt.
So we got so much going on in today's episode.
It's a little ridiculous, so I'm really excited.
Coming up earlier on in the show, we're going to talk with Antibody from the Xenotic Project
about something really cool coming up in my favorite open source game, but there's also
some other news in gaming that we're going to get to for the holidays because there's
probably going to be a big sale coming up, but later on in the show, Dustin Kirkland
from Canonical comes back with some additional comments about Ubuntu Snappy potentially being
the future of the Ubuntu project, so I'll ask him about that and we'll get his insights
on that.
So what the heck is Juju and how does it fit into the whole Ubuntu core thing?
He'll answer that and what all the different packages are, and then later on in the show,
it's our community review of Fedora 21.
We're going to get everybody's opinion on how it's been since they've installed it.
I'll give you some additional thoughts that I've had trying out Fedora 21, so it's a really,
really big show, and on top of that, we got a whole bunch of feedback, Matt.
It's a little cray, so why don't we get started?
Let's clear the deck.
Let's bring in the awesome mumble room, Goldfish, who I believe is here for his first time even
for Linux Unplugged.
All of you, welcome.
Time appropriate greetings, mumble room.
Hey.
Hello.
Hi.
Hello, hello.
It sounds like there's like three of you.
You guys got to get better at that.
You got to really represent.
All right, so let's get started here.
Yesterday, before we go too much further here, yesterday we had something kind of exciting
happen.
We launched on the Quota Radio Show an open source project right here on the Jupiter Broadcasting
Network, GPL2, and I believe it may prove to fundamentally be the most important project
for 2015 of all open source projects, Matt.
Whoa.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, it's called Open Your Mouth, and it's at OpenYourMouth.recipes.
These are open source GPL2-licensed recipes from the Jupiter Broadcasting Community.
This is an opportunity to go out there and meet your fellow Jupiter Broadcasting developer,
learn a little GitHub and Markdown in the process, and commit your recipes to one central
place, OpenYourMouth.
We've set it up, OpenYourMouth.recipes.com.
It's open source recipes from the Jupiter Broadcasting Community, and it's actually,
you know, it's kind of amazing.
It's taking off in a big way.
We've got breakfast, desserts, pizzas, sandwiches, sauces, different types of these things.
And Matt, this is already a huge hit.
That's awesome.
I love it.
So go to OpenYourMouth.recipes.
OpenYourMouth.recipes.
Okay.
And Rekai's been in there.
He's been engaging with the community, and right now they're working on a pretty killer
barbecue pizza, and they've merged in some of the changes.
Everything's written down in Markdown, so if you just want to go look at the recipe,
you can read them.
And here's what we were thinking.
We talk a lot about open source code and community and all of that, but I realize there are hundreds
of developers that listen to these shows that are not talking to each other, that run into
jams.
You know, they get into a spot where they're stuck and they need a resource.
They're not communicating, even though they're all listening to the same content.
Wouldn't it be cool if we could create a fun, sort of no pressure way for people to connect,
maybe even for folks that are not familiar with GitHub, maybe folks that want to learn
Markdown or just connect with a community that's pretty cool, but not have to know code.
And that's what we've done here.
It's tongue-in-cheek, but it's also a serious attempt to give people a way to connect.
Also we're encouraging people to hang out in our Jupyter Dev chat room.
We have a dedicated JB Dev chat room on Geek Shed.
In fact, if you want to know more about any of this, we've got a whole bunch of projects
going on for the community to work on right now.
If you're interested in developing code for the Jupyter Broadcasting Network, go to jbdev.community.
Blaster set that up for us, jbdev.community, and it will give you a link of resources,
all of them right there, like different account information, the IRC info.
Well hello there, hello there.
And that's a great place to start also, Jupyter Dev on the IRC is another place to start.
And it's really kind of fun to see people work on this.
We're launching a lot of projects in 2015, and so we're trying to get people engaged
and that's kind of just a fun way to start.
And it turns out, some pretty good recipes.
We started it yesterday and now there's more than a dozen, I think it's actually a lot
more than that.
I like how bacon's at the top.
Oh Matt, yeah.
Let's not kid ourselves.
And Angel and I want to submit some of our own recipes from the Fisher family.
And then before we get into our feedback, which I got a great one, I'm really glad,
so this is the last Linux Unplugged before Christmas.
Next week we will have a new episode, but it is a best of episode.
However, right now, Linux Unplugged has the least submissions for best ofs, and I know
we've had some great moments.
We've had some great arguments, we've had some great interviews, we've had some, we've
had like, there's some stuff we've already got on the list.
Like when Wimpy released the Ubuntu Mate 14.04 live on the show, how do you top that?
Like that's already on our list.
But we still need your help.
At the top of the show notes, your best of submissions.
Linux Unplugged, for some reason, has the least amount of submissions right now.
Now come on, we all love the Unplugged show, right?
So hook us up with your submissions, go over there, you'll find a link at the top of the
show notes if you go look at episode 71 of Linux Unplugged.
We just need the episode title, a link to the episode, the time code, and what it was.
And then Rekai, see the thing is, what we're trying to do here is we're trying to give
everybody time off, but the problem is we don't get these submissions in.
I'm afraid Rekai might start pulling the hair out of his beard, and he has a beautiful beard,
and I do not want to see that happen.
Right?
I mean, could you imagine, Matt, if he starts tearing it, that thing's a masterpiece.
Oh my goodness.
I picture him chasing us around the studio with like beard particles in hand, just screaming.
Yeah, absolutely.
When you have a content catalog as deep as ours, and the shows that are as long as they
are, it is the most, just assembling a best of, just all of the formatting that goes into
that is an incredible task, but he really could use your help, and we have links at
the top of the show notes.
You literally have like just a few hours.
So if you're listening to this show now, please go do it, because it takes days and days and
days and days of work just for one single episode, and he's working on them already.
He's already started.
All right, let's get into our first bit of feedback.
KZ650 sent a frequent chatter, emails into the show about IPFire, and this was an email
that I was really glad to get in towards the end of 2014, because earlier in the year,
I had decided Chris is going to replace the firewalls both at JBHQ, which is where the
operations happen, and JB1 Studios, which is where the production happens.
At both ends, I wanted to replace the firewalls.
My leading candidate for replacing those firewalls was PFSense, but the thing is PFSense runs
on FreeBSD, and I didn't really want to deploy FreeBSD when I do this other show called the
Linux Action Show.
Just didn't feel right.
So I was looking around for suggestions on what I could use instead, and I still haven't
really come to a conclusion.
Colonel Linux thinks I should use these MicroTik routers that look pretty compelling, and he's
even so far into it, he's even sent me two of them now to make sure I deploy them.
And then on the other end, I've looked at a few other distributions to see if something
met my needs, and I wasn't really happy with any of them until KZ650 sent emails in about
IPFire.
He says, Chris and Matt, you've mentioned in the past about the epicness of PFSense.
You talk about it all the time on TechSnap even, but you've never mentioned IPFire.
After using several firewall distros, I landed on IPFire, and it's awesome.
It's a very good project, and it deserves a spotlight.
So I went and checked it out, Matt, and it totally, well, it basically kind of looks
like PFSense.
You download the ISO, and it is a dedicated firewall distribution, and you can get a nice
gooey on top of that to manage your firewall rules.
And it looks really nice.
So I'm going to take a look at IPFire.
Right now, I'm leaning towards the Microtech routers, or whatever they're called.
Colonel X, do you have any thoughts on this?
Are you listening?
No.
We know he's got thoughts on it.
I'm sure he does.
Hey, I do have thoughts.
Here's the thing.
For me, and I've done a lot of soul searching over the past couple years, and I think what
I've come down to is it comes down to this.
My first priority is that something runs on Linux, whether or not it's open source, whether
or not it's, I don't mind paying for something, like Steam is a perfect example.
I'll pay for it, and it's not open source, but it runs perfectly on Linux.
So that's my, like, that's my bare line.
And then after that, if it's open source, even better.
And after that, if it's true free software, foundation, specialty stuff, even better.
That's like double, double better, yeah.
Right.
But with the Microtech, it meets that very bottom line.
Everything works perfectly on Linux, which I can't say is the same for Cisco.
And I can do all the stuff that I could do on the Microtechs that I used to be able to
do on Cisco, except it all works on Linux, oh, and by the way, it's like a tenth of
the price.
Yeah.
All right.
I mean, and I like their size, too.
So it's something I'm going to figure out soon.
I got to get this solved.
I got to get this problem worked out.
I've got a mess right now where my home network and the studio network are using the same
IP address space, so it screws the hell out of my devices when I move between them.
I cannot manage them remotely when I'm at one location or the other.
I feel like I'm in the 1990s where TCP IP is this new thing that's really neat that I'm
trying out, but I still prefer IPX.
So yeah, this is a problem I've got to solve seriously in early January or else I think
my blood pressure will suffer.
All right.
I'll tell you what doesn't make my blood pressure suffer.
I'll tell you what makes me feel a little bit better, and that's personal accomplishments,
seriously.
And that's why Linux Academy is a great sponsor for Linux Unplugged.
I can go there.
I can challenge myself.
I can see what interests me.
And I know that Linux Academy is built by people who truly understand and know Linux.
They are Linux users themselves.
They're not generic educators.
They don't have everything from fixing the sink to setting up an Apache server.
They're people that genuinely love and use Linux themselves.
Educators, Linux users, system administrators, developers that came together and they created
something they're passionate about, and that's Linux Academy.
And if you go to linuxacademy.com.plugged, you'll get a 33% discount, and that's for
the lifetime right there.
Boom.
Actually, I think it's for the quarter.
Go over there and check it out.
Go to linuxacademy.com.plugged.
Try them out for a little while and see what the discount is.
It's 33% off.
That's if you think about it, sort of an amazing discount.
They have everything you'd want to learn, seriously.
Everything from doing your own backups to managing your own Linux servers.
You can choose from 7 plus Linux distributions that automatically adjust the course.
If you're in DevOps, if you're learning about OpenStack, if you're learning about Docker,
they've got courses on that.
They're always adding new content constantly.
In fact, they just wrapped up the puppet professional courses from beginner to puppet professional
to be certified ready at Linux Academy.
Vagrant, they've got courses on that.
Docker, courses on that.
They're on top of all of this stuff because they're Linux enthusiasts themselves, so they
are following the technology trends.
They're following the open source developments.
They're watching all of this, and then they're curating the courseware based on that.
Nobody else can offer that.
Linuxacademy.com.plugged.
Go there.
Check it out.
Sign up.
I've been using them now for months.
It's seriously one of the best online learning tools I've ever seen in many years.
I go back to years when it required some clunky ActiveX installer.
It was the worst of the worst.
It was like, here Chris, we have bought you this as part of your educational package for
working here.
This is the course you can take, and it was the worst.
Linux Academy is nothing like that.
They have learning plans where you can go in and tell them how much time you have available.
They'll automatically create courseware based on that time availability with reminders and
quizzes and self-checks, and they also have a community that's available to you.
And I think one of the best things about Linux Academy is the way that they automatically
spin up virtual machines on demand that match the courseware.
They give you remote access to them.
You log in over SSH.
You actually work with the technology you're learning about.
You can download the comprehensive study guides, bring them with you on the phone, treat
them as podcasts, be like Skookiesprite, listen to them in the shower.
This is a really great opportunity, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
They also have added a lot of DevOps content in the past few months because that's an area
that's really growing, and they've really doubled down on it, linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged.
And a huge thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
You guys, like almost every week, you guys have something new for me to talk about, and
that is truly a treat, and it is really neat, and it's really awesome to watch them work.
I feel a bit of a kinship with them.
I feel like if Jupyter Broadcasting were to start today, maybe I might go this direction.
And they are truly advocating and spreading the use of Linux by making it accessible to
learn to everybody, from experts to beginners.
I think they're one of the best sponsors we've ever had, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go check them out, and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged
program.
All right.
So I wanted to start with some, let's start with a bang, literally.
Why don't we talk with Antibody.
Antibody is joining us in the mumble room.
We have an open mumble room, and you're welcome to join us.
We just do a mic check.
He's joining us from the Xenotic Project, my favorite first person shooter.
It's open source.
We often talk about Steam games, and I'm delighted when we get a chance to talk about a genuine
open source game.
So Antibody, welcome to Linux Unplugged.
How are you doing today, sir?
I'm doing great, Chris.
Thanks for having me.
Absolutely.
So, you know me, we've had a Xenotic server for quite a while.
I've been a player of Xenotic for quite a bit, but a little birdie told me there's something
new in the works coming up in the near future.
Yes, indeed.
That little birdie is correct, and thanks for running a server, by the way.
I didn't get the chance to check your server ID to sport you some nice stats, but yeah,
the little birdie says that there's going to be a release quote unquote soon.
Very soon.
Maybe even before the new year?
Like maybe.
You know, this is an open source project, and we have like a gazillion developers from
around the world, so we got to herd the cats.
You know what I mean?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So what kind of things, and when this new release does land, what kind of things are
we looking forward to?
Okay, so drum roll please.
Wait for it.
Okay, no.
So Xenotic's getting a new weapon, actually.
The long-awaited ARC is going to be arriving, well actually has arrived in Master if you
run a git.
But to the ARC, if you are from the Quake slash genre of shooters, ARC is like the lightning
gun.
Right?
Yes.
Oh my gosh, I love that gun.
We're working on some really, really cool audio effects at the moment, get it to echo
and sound like really powerful, really meaty, you know?
Yeah.
And other dudes, so we've got three new official maps, we're focusing on the capture the flag
game mode, so we have three official new maps for that.
We have a very active developer in Mario who's developed this really neat little system that
he calls buffs.
And so it's not like your little strength or shield type power-ups, they're more wacky.
So you get this so-called buff, it's like a hovering little coin thing, right?
And then suddenly you can fly, or suddenly you can move really fast.
Oh, really?
So we've got a bunch of little variety, a little potpourri, if you will, into the game.
So tell me, so give me a little background for folks that are not familiar.
Xenotic is a first-person shooter, you can set up your own server, am I correct when
I say it's based on the Quake 3 engine, or is that wrong?
It is actually based on Quake 1, but it's like uber-modified.
I would say it looks amazing for that.
It's basically like taking the core engine out of a game and stripping it all the way
down, building it back up with some kind of more realistic expectations.
We're not going to pretend that we're a state-of-the-art engine, but it's pretty darn spiffy.
It seems like it, I would say, here's how I would rate the graphics.
It's still rewarding on a higher Nvidia class card, but it's still playable on, say, the
Iris graphics, which is a pretty great range, and it also means it's pretty playable on
a lot of the open-source drivers, right?
Absolutely, it's playable on your open-source drivers, and more than just playable, it's
really configurable.
So we have people running it off of, like, I personally have an Acer Revo that runs Xenotic
just fine off of a little teeny Atom processor.
Very cool.
Well, so we should be checking out Xenotic.org, X-O-N-O-T-I-C.org, maybe around the New Year's
timeframe around in that area?
Yeah, in that general vicinity, yeah, and look for the new maps, look for the new weapon.
We got a nice tiered server browser.
Before we would just kind of slap you with all the servers, a ginormous list that you
had to parse through.
Well, and I'm looking at the servers, I'm looking at the most active servers, and it's
very disappointing, Jupiter Broadcasting, which was once at number one, is now falling to
number 25.
So if you guys go out there and install Xenotic, join the Jupiter Broadcasting last Xenotic
server and get that number back up there.
We used to rank it, so I think we can do it again.
Yeah, come on, guys.
Yeah, right?
Get fragging.
So Antibody, you do me a solid and come back on the show when the new release comes out,
and maybe we'll do a little live gameplay and the mumble room can shoot each other and
all that?
Absolutely.
I would love to personally frag you, Chris.
I'll hover, you know, my right index finger.
It's really itchy.
All right.
You know what I'm saying?
It's really itchy.
Fair enough.
You know what?
I will take it.
I will.
I am horrible at games.
But all right.
I'm an old man.
So before we get out of the feedback segment, and thanks to Antibody for coming on and talking
about that, I wanted to send out a request to the audience to get their feedback on Wallbag.
What?
Yeah.
Wallbag.
And maybe if anybody in the mumble room has any experience with Wallbag, I'd love to hear
about this.
But I've recently talked about on Linux Action Show this Sunday how I use Instapaper to read
long form articles.
And in Instapaper, I have the open dyslexic font configured.
Now there is an alternative to Instapaper that is open source that you could host yourself
even called Wallbag.
And it does the same thing.
It goes, it's like an offline stash where you can read stuff later.
The thing is, is I don't know what the end reading experience is like with Wallbag.
But because this is something I do a lot for our shows.
When I'm in the middle of something and I see an article that's relevant to our shows,
but it's going to take me more than a few minutes to read, I send it to Instapaper and
then I go offline later and I read it all.
And so Wallbag would be, it's something I could put on a DigitalOcean droplet.
It's something that could be under my control.
And you know how I'm all for that.
But I have no idea what the experience is like.
And I'm putting a request out there to the audience to go over to the contact form and
send in their feedback or in the subreddit.
And I wonder if anybody in the mumble room has any experience with Wallbag.
No.
Negative.
Negative?
Okay.
No.
Yeah, I really hadn't heard a lot about it either.
But I've seen it for a long time and so I'll put my feelers out there.
We'll see what happens.
And maybe somebody out there has tried it and they can send us in their feedback.
Oh!
You hear that?
Oh, I think it's time for a little Steam update too.
So speaking of, before we get away from gaming completely, super quick here, Boiling Steam
has a great post on a proper end of year of gaming on Linux.
And there's been some recent releases that are really big deals for Linux.
And we won't spend a lot of time on this, I know not all of you are big gamers.
But for those of you that are gamers, there's some holiday sales coming up and there's some
great games that have come out.
A Metro 23 Redux has relaunched and this is the rebuilt version that has a lot better
textures.
Linux Gamecast just did a review on that if you want to check that out.
For you football fans, Football Manager 2015 is out.
Some games that we weren't expecting, Empire Total War, and this has gotten some serious
traction in our subreddit.
Geometry Wars 3 is an Aspire port, which Aspire has done all good work so far and it's a great
game.
I had my friend John just totally consumed by it.
War Thunder, it's an MMO shooter, which looks really fun.
And Counter Strike Global Offensive, of course, we've given mention to.
Also expected before the end of the year, Civilization Beyond Earth.
So there's a lot of really good games.
Zonotic obviously an open source option that's really great.
And if you are thinking about picking up some Steam games, I just want to, just a quick
PSA to remind you, try to buy them under the Linux Steam client so that way the Linux sale
is counted.
I'm not sure what happens if you buy it on the web.
And even if you buy it on a Windows machine and then play it under Linux, at least for
two weeks, that sale is going to be counted towards Windows.
So if you can, make these purchases as the Steam holiday sale comes up on your Linux
rig as sort of a vote for supporting Linux.
Just something to remind people about as we get close to the crazy ass rape your wallet
Steam sale that comes up where I feel like Gabe personally comes into my house, knocks
everything over, breaks all my piggy banks, and takes all of my money.
It's a holly jolly time of year.
And then yells at the top of his lungs, you're welcome.
You wanted this!
Alright so we had Dustin Kirkland come on the show and I asked him some questions pertaining
to the future of the Ubuntu project.
So we're going to play that here in just a second.
It's some extra stuff that didn't make it into our last review.
And I don't know, I think it could make for a great desktop.
I think it's a pretty compelling option.
I'll play his answer and we'll talk about it.
But first I want to mention DigitalOcean.
Head over to DigitalOcean.com right now and let's give the Linux Unplugged show a great
end of 2014 showing.
Use the promo code UnpluggedDecember when you actually just apply it to your account.
It's a habit to say when you check out, but it's actually you can apply the balance to
your account even after you've signed up if you forgot to use it.
UnpluggedDecember will give you a $10 credit for DigitalOcean.
Now we've talked about DigitalOcean for a long, long time.
And it really is one of the coolest resources and one of the coolest manifestations of different
Linux technologies that has been put into a product that is also extremely awesome for
Linux users to use.
So what is it?
If you're not familiar, DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to
offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up a cloud server.
Now why does that matter?
Well that matters because if it's super simple and straightforward for you to set up, not
a hobbled system, but a system that you have full access, full control over, that you can
deploy applications to with one click.
And if that process of setting that up just takes mere moments or can even be scripted,
that fundamentally changes it.
Removing all of that friction is a huge deal and DigitalOcean saw that and they realized
that's why the UI was super important and then they built it on top of SSD drives way
before anybody else was doing SSD and of course they had to pair it with tier one bandwidth.
And you can get started in less than a minute and pricing plans start at only five dollars
a month.
So if you use our promo code unplugdecember with that ten dollar credit, you can go for
two months.
Here's what you're going to get for five dollars, 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one
CPU and a terabyte of transfer, a terabyte.
And they have data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam
and London.
But that interface right, I mean it's inspired.
It's so simple and very intuitive and power users can replicate that interface on a larger
scale with DigitalOcean's straightforward API.
And I've said that a lot, but I want to show you how that actually manifests in stuff you
can use.
Now you could take advantage of that API.
Maybe you have more skills than I have and you would actually be able to write your own
scripts or manage to snap it into your own puppet management infrastructure on your own.
That honestly is just beyond my capability, but what is easily within my capability is
taking advantage of all of the cool stuff that the DigitalOcean community has already
created around this API for me for absolutely free.
Like it's just a benny of being a DigitalOcean customer.
Like number one, right here, dropper control panel.
Have you seen this?
This is a management control panel for your DigitalOcean droplets for the Android device.
There's even a nicer one for iOS.
But you know I know most of you are probably Android users, no judging, that's cool.
Dropper control panel.
It lets you start them up, back them up, copy them, move them around, take a snapshot, resize
them, rename them from your freaking Android, right?
That's just one use of the API.
Here's another cool one, Lita.
It's a chatroom bot that allows you to manage your DigitalOcean droplet within an IRC room.
Now why would you want to use that?
Psst, Honey Badger, I don't know.
But I think that's amazing.
The fact that you can do that is amazing.
Here's another one.
We're going to talk with Dustin very soon.
Juju DigitalOcean provider.
This is a way to snap in your DigitalOcean droplets with your Juju management infrastructure.
And you can start doing all of this for $5 per month.
And if you're just an average user, you don't have anything super sophisticated like this
that you want to do, that doesn't matter.
You can still take advantage of $5 a month to build your own own cloud installation,
your own BitTorrent sync server, your own GitLab instance.
You can do all of this with DigitalOcean and if you use our promo code, unplug December,
you'll get that $10 credit.
You can try it out for two months for absolutely free.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go check them out.
Use the promo code, unplug December when you check out.
And a huge thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux unplug program.
You guys are so awesome and the community around them.
And I didn't even get a chance to mention their tutorials that you can go right up and
they'll pay you for them.
It's so slick.
DigitalOcean.com, unplug December when you check out.
Alright, so let's shift gears.
Let's start, let's talk about Ubuntu Snappy.
So this was a topic of interest on this Sunday's Linux action show.
During the news, we brought on Dustin Kirkland from Canonical.
He's the Ubuntu cloud product manager and a strategist at Canonical.
And his new baby is Ubuntu Snappy Core.
Now just a super quick recap, Ubuntu Snappy Core is a new release from Ubuntu based, uses
system deep.
But what's actually more important is the base file system is tiny.
The base system is very small and it's read only.
When you get an update, you get a new instance of the file system.
And when you reboot, you boot into that new instance.
And if something doesn't work, you just choose the other one.
The applications are fairly unaffected because essentially they're isolated probably in containers.
And then when you can do these updates to the base system, you don't really affect the
application data, the version of the application, the libraries they depend on.
And if the update doesn't work, well it was a transactional update.
So it's easy to roll back to the past version.
So when Dustin was talking about this, I realized this would probably be a great way to have
a very secure and stable rolling desktop release.
So I asked him, is this the future of the Ubuntu project?
Potentially.
I don't know that it'll ever, we certainly haven't indicated that it will replace apps.
Maybe being offered on all Ubuntu platforms in addition.
Yeah, I think that's reasonable to say that anywhere you're doing Ubuntu, you can do either
the traditional Debian package app get update, app get upgrade, or the snappy.
I think that's a reasonable goal to shoot for.
Myself as a long time Debian packager and Ubuntu developer, there's certainly places
where I need to do Debian packages for the foreseeable future.
So I guess my last question for you, just as some jargon I want to help clear up for
the audience.
So we have your standard Debian packages, we have click packages, snappy packages, and
then there's also the management piece, which is called Juju.
How does Juju fit in with Ubuntu snappy core?
Can it be used to manage some of the services that might be riding on top of some of those
containers?
Yeah, so that's certainly on the longer term roadmap.
Maybe a little bit farther out, a few months to a year out.
Fundamentally, Juju is, as an orchestration tool, the goal of Juju is to create resources
in the public cloud, private cloud, or bare metal solution of your choice.
And Juju can create instances in Amazon, Google, Azure, as well as OpenStack on the private
side of things.
That instance would be like a full web stack with database ready to go, sort of like I
click this and I deploy this charm and it's my whole setup, right?
Yep, exactly.
And that one charm might be a bundle of charms.
It might not just be a single web app.
It might be a web app that depends on a database, which has to be configured in a cluster with
an HA proxy in front of it, a memcache on the side accelerating things.
By the way, you want to log everything to a single aggregator, an RSS log.
By the way, those logs you want to then pump into a big data solution, a Hadoop, and then
MapReduce that and be able to elastic search your logs.
That's a very typical Juju deploy one thing and it deploys all those services onto a dozen
different instances running in the public cloud, private cloud, or bare metal of your
choice.
Now, when Juju starts that instance, I would see Juju as being able to start that instance
as a traditional Ubuntu image or perhaps a snappy Ubuntu image where you've made the
opinionated decision that this suite of services you're going to deploy in that snappy, transactionally
upgraded model.
That is going to be a pretty compelling product offering altogether and it's a really interesting
space.
Containerization is bringing a lot of changes.
Dustin, is there anything else you want to cover, anything else you want to let us know
about Ubuntu snappy?
Come talk to us.
Snappy devel is a mailing list.
We've got an active community.
We released just two days ago, just on Tuesday, and we put out images in the first public
cloud, Azure.
The other public clouds will be coming along the next couple of weeks.
We published an initial image that you could play with in KVM and within six hours, we
had posts on the list of people contributing vagrant images and VMware images.
Personally, it caught me a little bit by surprise, not being a VMware, a vagrant user, that,
oh yeah, how we missed that, but fortunately we've got an active community developing very
quickly.
So, yeah, come help us fill the gaps, scratch your own itches in the snappy world.
A big thank you to Dustin for coming on the show and, Poppy, I couldn't help but notice,
oh, he left, didn't he?
Dang it, I couldn't help but notice on that video there, if you look closely, if you're
watching the video version, you'll notice right there on the page, big pull quote from
Microsoft, Microsoft loves Linux.
Boom, right there on the page.
Premier Azure, the launch partner for Ubuntu Snappy Core.
So he didn't seem to be too big on the whole Ubuntu Snappy Core for the desktop, but of
course he's the cloud guy, right?
He's focused on the server stuff.
So that makes sense.
I can't judge, I can't judge, but I'm looking forward to trying out Snappy Core.
We've got Snappy Core, Fedora Cloud, and CoreOS that are all kind of, Fedora Cloud though
doesn't, so what's different here is Ubuntu Snappy and CoreOS inherently, as part of their
product offering, sort of solve that, I gotta update the base OS, but keep the applications
isolated.
Fedora Cloud is more of a traditional OS, distro, but if you employ things like Atomic,
then you get more of that functionality.
That's kind of my rough understanding.
So it's really, it's an area that you've got really like three or four very clear different
attempts to solve this problem.
Some people would say it's fragmentation, but I think it's, we're gonna see which one
actually wins the race.
So anybody in the Mumba room have any thoughts on the interview before we move on to our
Fedora review?
I think it's great and I'm really, I'm looking forward, I'm paying attention, that's pretty
much it.
Yeah, I agree.
I think it's, I think what, where we're at right now is solving the I gotta patch a lot
and I don't want to break my apps problem.
That's where we're at today.
But what we're, where we're going to end up, I suspect at the end of all of it is this
is how you install a new application on Linux, period.
Now we're not, we're not anywhere near there yet, but I feel like what we are working towards
is the world's most amazing solution to solving that problem.
How do you install X on Linux?
I don't care what distro it is, how do you do it?
And it's going to be one answer and when it's going to take us, what we're going to document
on this show and it's going to take a long ass tedious time is the process of us going
from how do I update my rig all the time because man, I keep getting exploited.
That's where we're at today.
But what we're going to watch that transform into is that how do I install it on Linux?
And that's going to be an interesting journey for us to document.
I think it's going to take more than 70 episodes though.
Oh yeah.
I think so.
Yeah.
Well, I think everybody wants to get to the Fedora review and I agree.
I think Fedora 21 has been an amazing release.
We've talked a lot about it.
I hope the audience is okay with this deep diving like this because we've, we obviously
have been talking and this will be about the third week or in a row or so that we're talking
about it.
But I feel like when, when a Linux distribution that's at least as important as Fedora, but
any Linux distribution that has, that has as much of a wide reach that Fedora has, that
has many, that has as many contributors working for it that Fedora has and has the role that
Fedora has to go through what we've seen it go through, to split off into these three
distinctive flavors, to be, to be willing when you're, when you're at the size of Fedora
to just say eff it and just go for it and just do something totally different.
And then to pull that off, like I, I'm going to be honest.
I kind of thought when Fedora was talking about going with three flavors and doing it
in like essentially one release cycle, I was like, yeah, okay, well if you think you can
pull that off, good luck to you.
You know, really.
I mean, I was skeptical about it.
And now here we are.
Fedora 21 is released.
Yeah.
A little delayed.
No bigs.
And it, and they seriously did it.
So that's incredible to me.
And I think it might be one of the most interesting distribution related things has happened this
year.
Not just one, but one of them.
So we're going to get the community's input on that.
But first let's talk about our friends at Ting.
They're ending 2015 with a freaking bang.
Ting is mobile.
That makes sense.
My mobile service provider and Matt's linux.ting.com is where you go.
Let's represent for the Linux Unplugged show at the end of 2014 linux.ting.com.
So why Ting?
Why does it make sense?
What do I mean by that?
Well, first of all, no contract, right?
Because the contract, it just really doesn't make any sense.
But what also doesn't make any sense is paying into these plans that you may use plans like,
like it feels like insurance and I always kind of feel like that doesn't make sense
either.
Ting instead, it's just pay for what you use.
So it starts with $6 for the line.
That's all you pay.
And that's pretty straightforward.
I can afford that.
That's why I've got three of them, right?
Because what matters is what you actually freaking use.
So it's just your minutes, your megabytes, your messages.
They add them all up and that's what you pay.
If you want to turn on hotspot, that's fine.
Do it.
Make it, make it a wifi access point.
That's just data usage.
Just not a big deal.
And if you're savvy about using wifi, like when you're on wifi and you make your calls
over that, I mean you can have incredible savings with Ting because again, you're just
paying for what you use.
So linux.ting.com, start there, okay?
That'll get you $25 off your first Ting device.
If you have advice that's compatible, they have a bring your own device page where you
can check that out.
If you have a device that's compatible, well, they'll give you $25 of credits.
Well, the first month, like usually is like 26 bucks.
So you're going to get your first month pretty much for free.
If you have a contract, well, Ting's going to help you get out of that.
So you're going to get $150 for the line that you have to cancel.
Yeah, it's $150 in credits, but it's $150 in freaking credits.
That's money you won't have to pay for your cell service.
That's really great.
Plus, they have an awesome control panel.
You can call them at 1855-TING-FTW anytime between 8 a.m. or 8 p.m. east coast time.
Yeah, it's east coast time.
I'm sorry about that.
I know, I know.
It's not Pacific.
I'm sorry.
But it's east coast time.
The human being answers the phone.
That's okay.
So that's like boom.
That's the foundation of Ting.
You can already see they're thinking about this differently.
You can see they're trying to disrupt the crazy ass restrictive mobile industry.
Okay, that's pretty straightforward.
Well, what struck me about Ting is when they don't have to, when they don't gotta, they're
going out of their way to make their stance on issues clear.
They recently had a blog post about net neutrality that I thought was really well reasoned and
really well put together.
I thought, okay, I feel like my money's going to a good place.
They're coming here.
They're thinking about this rationally.
They're taking a stand.
They're articulating that stand really well, and I thought that's really cool.
They're screwing with the mobile industry by offering something totally different.
They're about to roll GSM and CDMA out at the same time starting in 2015, which is gonna
be a game changer.
I'm loving all of that, but let's be honest.
There's more that could be done, right?
Wireless is fundamentally critical to the future of a lot of mobile apps, a lot of mobile
web stuff, but at the end of the day, I still got that wired connection.
I cannot believe it.
This is what I love about Ting.
This is why I always preach vote with your wallet.
Ting is going to launch, and now they're starting small.
I mean, they have to start within reason, but they're going after residential internet
access now.
See, now this is just the beginning of something.
It's not a big thing.
It's only in one area right now because it's just like Google Fiber.
They gotta start small, but they're starting to roll out crazy fast fiber access to the
home, and they're gonna take the whole Ting model to all of it.
I think it's... This could be huge for everyone, like not just users of Ting, but everyone
on the internet.
They seriously care about this stuff, and again, that's why we talk about voting with
your wallet, linux.ting.com.
Go there.
They got it on their blog.
You can read about it, but go to linux.ting.com first.
That way, we get credit for your visit, but then go over to their blog and check this
out.
They're rolling out fiber.
Unfortunately, it's like in Virginia right now, yeah, Charlottesville, Charlottesville.
I want it so bad.
This is so cool.
I think this is another example of a great sponsor that I'm really, really happy to have
because I really believe in what they're trying to do, and I think that's just so amazing.
I mean, they've already... For the last two years, it's totally changed the way I think
about mobile.
It's changed how I look at the whole industry, and now, I'm going to look at what they're
doing at residential ISP service.
This Ting is crazy, and I love it, linux.ting.com.
Go over there and check them out.
See how much you could save.
They have a savings calculator.
Check them out, linux.ting.com, and a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged
Show.
Okay, guys, so let's talk about Fedora 21.
Let's get started.
First up, get fedora.org.
It's their new site.
They're very proud of it, and you know what I find to be interesting on this site?
First sentence, Fedora is now more focused, and isn't that true?
Isn't that exactly what they've addressed in Fedora 21?
You've got your workstation release, your server release, and your cloud release.
Now, I think probably not a large leap of assumption here to consider.
We've probably all just been looking at the workstation release.
Not a lot of us looked at the server or cloud, right?
Anybody done any of the server or cloud stuff?
I didn't think so.
That's fine.
Maybe we'll do that in the future.
So let's start with Fedora workstation.
Go ahead and tag me in the mumble room, anybody that wants to start.
I'll begin with my experience, tell you what I did, and then we'll jump into the mumble
room.
So I installed Fedora 21 64-bit on my Bonobo and also on a Dell Sputnik laptop that was
sent to me by Colonel Linux in the mumble room, and I also tried it for about a half
hour on an Apple MacBook Pro 2013-ish.
I don't really know the model number.
So that was the range of hardware that I experimented with Fedora 21 on, all GNOME across the board,
because I decided to go with the environment that I was most comfortable with.
So let's start with Colonel Linux.
How was your experience on your laptop?
So I installed it on my Dell E6320, and that worked really great.
In fact, that's my new daily operating system now, is 21, and that worked really well.
But I had a nook that I used for doing different things, and that was when it first came out,
I wanted to throw it on something, and that was what happened to be laying around, and
it sucks.
The lock screen freezes up.
So like if I were to switch over to that computer right now, I have to hit escape like 15 times
and wait like 30 seconds, and it's running on an 840 Pro SSD.
So I shouldn't be waiting for it, but I do wait for it.
That doesn't happen in Ubuntu 14.4, so I don't know.
You know, I had my first like, oh my God, it's going to happen moment with Fedora 21.
I don't have these very often anymore with computers.
I guess it just doesn't happen a lot.
And Matt, it's kind of funny because it made me think of the monkey suit right away.
Of course.
Oh no.
I was on the Sputnik that Colonel Linux sent me that I've selfishly held onto.
Thank you, Colonel Linux.
And it's an Intel chip in the Sputnik, and I thought, well, so I'm all open source through
and through right now.
And at the GDM login screen, and you hit the little gear button, you have your GNOME desktop,
GNOME Classic, and then on there is GNOME and Wayland.
And so I chose GNOME Wayland, and I logged in, and then at first I thought, did it not
work?
I think it's still using X.
Like, and I launched like Terminal, I launched Chrome, I launched the activities overview.
I'm like, oh, I guess it didn't work.
And then I started to realize like a couple of things weren't working quite right.
Like my trackpad, like I couldn't click on stuff.
I could move the mouse with the trackpad, but I couldn't click on anything, and I couldn't
scroll.
But if I had a USB mouse, I could use that.
And I started to realize, oh, I actually, I actually, I'm using Wayland right now.
I'm using Wayland with GNOME 3 and the Chrome browser right now.
And I had this total like, oh my God, I'm using Wayland and it's working flawlessly
moment.
And like, it was amazing.
Like here we are, I keep saying this, the end of 2014, but I actually, I actually just
had like a essentially trouble-free Wayland desktop, no futzing, except for my trackpad
didn't work.
But it was, it was kind of like Fedora 21 was my first and it was like, oh wow, thank
you.
That was incredible.
And now I know like it's ex-Wayland doing all the windowing stuff, but it was, it was
kind of amazing.
RA, I know you were here specifically to touch on Wayland.
Do you have any comments on that?
RA?
RA.
Oh, I'm sorry, RA, yeah, I'm sorry, RA.
Yeah, actually I would like to announce that I'm running on Wayland right now.
And I think I'm the first person in the chat room to talk while on Wayland.
Is that true?
Yeah, you might be.
I think you are our first Wayland-based mumbler.
And actually I had the same story like you, Chris.
My trackpad doesn't work.
And I had the same Wayland surprise.
Like I tried Rebecca Black Linux, which was supposed to work out well.
And also Fedora 20 and all those shenanigans, as Matt would say.
And it didn't work and Fedora, suddenly I realized I was on Wayland and it didn't crash
and it runs fine.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's pretty neat.
I mean, it's not done, but it's pretty neat to see that happen.
And I don't know, I mean, it's been a big discussion piece for a long time.
So RA, I'm sorry, you'll be our Wayland correspondent, okay?
You keep us updated on your Wayland developments, all right?
Okay.
All right, very good.
Thank you.
So any other comments from the Mumble Room on their Fedora 21 experience?
I'll end it with this.
And I was, I'm hoping maybe somebody can walk me back from the ledge.
But I'm ready to declare Fedora 21 my next distro if I jump.
I'm ready.
Wow.
I've never heard of it before.
I mean, I'll give people, walk me back, walk me back from it.
But I'm just right now, here's the thing, here's what's limiting, is the software availability
still sucks.
And I will, I also, before I go in this, have to acknowledge-
How do you mean?
Well, like, for example, Heropad, a Markdown editor, does not exist for Fedora.
It's a total impossibility.
It's a nightmare.
I even tried building it from source and it ran like ass.
It was a total nightmare.
But if I'm on Ubuntu, I've got a PPA ready to go.
If I'm on the Arch, well, of course, the AUR has got that ass a decade ago, it had that
in there.
200 years ago, it had that in there.
But when I go to Fedora, I'm like in no man's land, right?
Okay, Viber.
Viber is another example.
I don't like it.
I admit it is a crap application that we should move away from, but I need it to correspond
with people that are in the field and people that are out and about and, okay, Viber is
a thing.
You know what?
If you're on Fedora, go screw yourself.
You're on Arch, no problem.
You're on Ubuntu, no problem.
You're on Fedora, I hate you.
That kind of stuff drives me crazy with Fedora.
Whereas with Arch, again, I'm not saying this applies to everybody, but because I install
four to five to six to seven to eight to 10 applications a week, that way I can pick one
of those mother effers on the Linux Action Show, because I reinstall that many applications,
like when I have to go out of my way to find a repo or download an RPM or build it from
source, that adds 10 to 15 minutes, and if I'm doing five to 10 to those a week, that's
stupid because in the AUR, nowadays, I just go packer-s and I just put the name of the
damn package in there and I've got it.
I don't even look to see if they've got it because they've got it.
Now that's where Fedora falls short, which only probably applies literally maybe to me.
There might not be anybody else in the world that that applies to, and I accept that.
If that does not apply to you, I feel like Fedora's got most of it because Copper's got
a lot of stuff.
There's a lot of stuff in the RPM Fusion and additional repos around Fedora, and if we
use scripts like Fedly, F-E-D-L-Y or whatever it is, it'll set up a ton of stuff for you
under Fedora that makes it a pretty good setup.
For me right now, Fedora 21, it's the longest setup.
It's the most post-installation work, but the process of doing that is fairly automated,
fairly easy.
You can pretty much just do it, sit, click, click, click, and you're done.
It takes a lot of work, but after that work's done, it's ready to go.
If you start with something like Karora, which I don't think has their 21 release out yet,
but Karora Linux, which is Fedora with all the goodies that are evil pre-built in, then
it's even a quicker go.
That's what I mean with Fedora 21.
It's great with the exception that it does require a lot of work to get going.
If you want Steam, you want proprietary drivers, you want Codex, you want Flash, you want Java,
you know Chrome, you know that kind of stuff, it takes a while.
That's fine.
Yeah, I've definitely found that the one area Fedora doesn't quite do it for me is package
availability because I do find myself needing either PPAs or AUR, something that has a little
bit more.
It's not even about being recent.
It's just about me not having to compile it or dig through an RPM on an old ice or whatever.
Yeah, I agree with you, Matt.
I do.
Rotten Corpse, go ahead.
Yeah, I've actually set up my laptop to be the Fedora, so it's like my second distro
choice now, but mainly because copper is one of the things I'm super excited about.
Yeah, so can you kind of explain a little bit about copper because we've name dropped
it.
We talked about it on Sunday's Linux Action Show.
Is it fair to say it's sort of an AUR arch user repository equivalent?
Well, it's more of a PPA equivalent, so you can build different branches kind of thing,
so the different packages.
The only thing that I see so far that I don't like about copper is that it's restricted
to open source free software type of stuff.
So the reason you say that is because the building doesn't happen on the Fedora workstation
when you install the package?
Right.
They set up the builds on their servers.
Gotcha.
Now, Dave, you wanted to comment on other desktops besides GNOME?
Yeah, I'm just saying while GNOME is the default offering, it's not the only offering, and
other desktops do work flawlessly on Fedora.
If you're running Cinnamon, KDE, LXDE, whatever, don't expect to have problems.
If not, something like Unity, you can only install that.
Yeah, very true.
In fact, Matthew Miller said that KDE is a very important desktop, as well as many of
the others.
Ra, you've been using the OpenSUSE build service with your Fedora installation?
Yeah, and I found that it works really nice.
Sometimes they provide Fedora packages.
Sometimes the OpenSUSE packages work.
It's been really smooth, but I agree that it's kind of hard.
For example, I didn't get Eclipse to work until I found out that the dev tool that they
bundle with the workstation actually works perfect for that.
Well, I'll tell you, it is a pretty great service.
Eric, I know that's something you're familiar with, right?
Correct.
I have used the OpenSUSE build service quite a bit, especially in OpenSUSE, to get stuff
installed, find packages and whatnot.
The only thing is they don't have Fedora 21 just yet.
They probably will in the soon future, I would imagine, but they don't have the ability to
build packages for Fedora 21 just yet.
I'm looking forward to that because, for instance, the KDE Connect indicator, which has been
our subreddit a couple of times, it can be installed on OpenSUSE.
It's just not very successful, but it's built for Fedora 20.
It works properly in Fedora 20.
It just needs to be compiled for Fedora 21, and that'd be fine.
You kind of went through the process of trying to submit that to the Copper...
Is it repository?
I'm not sure what to call it.
Yeah, just Copper, I guess.
I did, but the build failed.
The build failed because it...Well, actually, no, the build succeeded.
I apologize.
The build succeeded.
When I went to install, it failed to function, so I'm not exactly sure why that is.
It does the same thing in OpenSUSE, so I imagine because they're in the Git sources, I think
it is built more for Debian and Ubuntu than it is for anything else, so it's a matter
of just making it compatible.
I know there's people working on it in the Git repository.
This is the hurdle that Fedora now has to overcome, is the Linux desktop market has
moved on, and I don't mean to disparage Fedora, but in that sense, it is just simply so much
easier to get some of that software for Ubuntu and for Arch.
Two examples that are very popular, KDE Connect and Herupad.
Herupad is an amazing markdown editor that is really gaining in popularity.
We talked about it three or four months ago in the Linux action show, and they've just
been blowing up since then.
It's available for Ubuntu.
It's available for Arch.
It's not available for Fedora.
Those are just isolated examples, but I believe that is Fedora's problem now.
What they have done here, I think, has laid the groundwork to address that.
Fedora workstation.
I had a conversation with Michael Dominic on Monday's Coda Radio, where he's back on
Linux now for his development workstation, and he was asking, if I reload, what should
I switch to?
And I made a pitch for Fedora, because honestly, they've got dev assist.
They're really close to upstream.
That's one of the things I've always said about Arch that I liked a lot, is I felt like
I'm closer to upstream.
Well, Fedora's got that, but it also has that background leadership by Red Hat, which I
believe, at the end of the day, to have a commercial entity that says, you know what?
We've got to produce something here.
We've got stuff we've got to do.
I think that actually is just what it takes to prevent issues like we've just seen with
Debian, but it's not where they're directly pulling all of the strings.
I think it's just the right mix.
I like that about Fedora, right?
From that perspective, I enjoy it.
The fact that they're all in with Gnome, I think that really makes it a great Gnome experience.
The dev assist stuff, all of that, I think, actually makes it a pretty compelling developer's
workstation, just like they've been pitching it.
So when he asked me, what should I use for my Linux workstation, honestly, I gave a harder
pitch for Ubuntu Mate 14.04, but I said, with that considered, Fedora 21 is a serious, serious
contender.
And if you've watched me over the years, you know how I've felt about Fedora, right?
If you look at some of our shows from five years ago, compared to what I'm saying about
Fedora today, they have turned it around, I think.
Oh, I agree.
I definitely agree with that.
I definitely like the direction they're going with everything, except software availability.
Everything else is honestly blowing everyone else out of the water.
Yeah, nailed it.
You nailed it.
That's exactly it, in a nutshell.
That's exactly the...
And the software availability is slowly improving, and it actually is going in the right direction.
So it's pretty cool.
And I think that'll probably button up our coverage of...
Oh, go ahead.
Yeah, I just have a word of clarity that KDE Connect works flawlessly in Fedora under KDE,
however using the KDE Connect indicator, which is for other desktop environments, it doesn't
work quite so well.
Also the chat room has been asking, and Colonel Linux, you'll be happy to hear.
So I tried out Fedora 21 on a MacBook.
It does not go to graphical environment at all if you have a second monitor hooked up
over the Thunderbolt adapter, but if you are just doing a single monitor, everything except
for...I didn't try the webcam or wireless, but Bluetooth, Thunderbolt, Ethernet works.
But what was really impressive is it not only supports the retina display on the MacBook,
but GNOME looks pretty good.
Chrome and Firefox, the text is really small, but the GNOME UI itself, I don't have a lot
of experience with retina display, but it was amazing.
Look at GNOME on that resolution, it looked great.
I think you could fix the remainder of your problems just by...I think what the problem
is is it conflicts with the existing Mac OS operating system.
I think if you were to take that off, I think then everything would work fine.
So anyways, I was kind of flabbergasted.
It's the first time I've ever just put a thumb drive into a MacBook Pro, booted it up, and
actually had Linux working on it, and able to use the networking and all of that.
So there you go.
I am very impressed with Fedora 21.
Ww, why don't you give us your closing thoughts on your experience with Fedora 21?
Well, I'm going to have to preface it with saying I tried it on seven-year-old hardware
and I thought, oh, it's Linux, it should work.
And I ran into issues where I could just not install for the life of me, no matter what.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
I mean, I'm running it on an AMD.
It's my other laptop, not my main laptop.
It's an AMD 2 gigahertz dual-core with an NVIDIA 6150.
And it just, after like, when it went to format the drive and install, I left it there for
like two hours.
And you were doing text snap at the time, and by the time that was over, I'm still waiting
for the system to run.
Now that's a long time.
Yeah.
I did want to, for the most part, from what I experienced of the install, it kind of reminded
me of that Windows feel where it had a good level of polish, but I still felt it had some
work to be done, like the warnings could be up higher for when you're trying to install
something.
Well, actually, pause right there just for a sec.
I was actually kind of impressed with the way that they brought forward the SE Linux
alerts, and would tell you, here's what SE Linux has detected.
Here's like three or four fairly solid options you can do to resolve this problem.
I thought A, that was impressive, and B, YUM or DNF, like I added the Dropbox repository
for Fedora before it was ready, and what YUM does, when you do a YUM update, and then the
Dropbox repo 404s, because they don't have anything set up for 21 yet, instead of YUM
essing the bed, what it does is it says, hey, bro, I'm having troubles contacting this repo,
you can run this command to disable the repo, or you can run this command and just say,
you know what, ignore it when it 404s, it's no bigs.
It's just enough power, but yet enough hand holding, that when you're new to YUM or DNF,
you know what to do next.
Having some basic Linux knowledge and system administration knowledge, okay, admittedly
more than basic, but that was enough, the information they provided me, I was able to
take actions based on that and resolve my SC Linux issues, and resolve my YUM repo issues,
and I thought it was really slick the way they handled it.
So are you talking about that, WW, or are you talking about something else?
No, no, I feel like my issue was more like a hardware incompatibility issue, or maybe
I needed to throw a switch on some setup script, or when it booted off of the USB stick to
do something, but I got no such prompt at all during the process.
I know Poppy felt the same way about a certain issue with how the setup was for partitioning,
and I thought it was confusing, and he did as well.
I don't know if he had some further thoughts on that.
Thank you for bringing that up too.
I did feel like, while the overall installer, it's growing on me, they've had this essential
one for a little while now, I felt like, so every time I was installing Fedora 21 on every
rig I installed it on, because it's 2014, I already had an operating system installed,
right?
It wasn't a blank drive.
I don't know in what scenario somebody's installing Fedora on a system that's never had another
operating system, but it probably happens in the server space and stuff, I'll grant
them that.
But on the desktop, what Fedora tries to do is it's going to hook you up.
It doesn't want to mess with you, so it's going to shrink stuff, and it's going to try
to fit Fedora in some free space for you.
But I don't want it to do that.
I want it to wipe out all the partitions and set up, have at it Haas, go for it Fedora.
In order to get to that, you've got to select the drive, and then you've got to go into
the special reclaim space menu, and then you've got to select the partitions that you're willing
to reclaim space from, and then when you click that, it doesn't actually represent in the
visual that you're now reclaiming that space.
It's not until you click apply that it then represents it, so you don't really get a chance
to visualize what it is you're about to do before you make the action.
And the entire time, you're not even sure that's where you're supposed to be making
that change at.
And so I felt like the partitioning definitely was one of the rougher areas, but once I wrapped
my brain around what they were trying to do, every subsequent Fedora install, I didn't
have a problem.
Yeah.
I did try it on another laptop, and I think it worked better, so I think I might just
try a different USB stick and put some space and give it a better try on another system
and see how it turns out for me.
Ra, you had some ButterFS experience feedback?
Yeah.
Actually I had a preview set up with OpenSUSE, and there were a couple of ButterFS partitions
on there, and then I decided to go all in on Fedora 21 even before it came out.
And that's not happened since I ditched Windows, let me tell you.
And Fedora, just the partitioning scheme, the editor, messed it up.
Then I had 20 ButterFS partitions, which all were empty sub-volumes, in the partitioning
editor, and it actually created all those, and I thought, well, let's do it.
Maybe it's just a bug.
And then it actually created all those.
But that was before the release, and they fixed that, so it should work right now.
I hope it does.
Yeah.
All right.
And Dave, you have a better way for the partitioning?
Yeah, there are simpler ways to actually do it.
You just simply delete the partitions.
The thing about Fedora 21, and most Fedora installs since, I think, the new installer,
it doesn't actually write changes to your disk until you begin the installation.
Right, okay.
So you can make changes whichever way you want by just simply adding and deleting disks
and deleting partitions.
When you actually get to the partition menu, which I admit is a little confusing at first,
but you just press the little minus sign on the bottom and your partitions will be gone,
and you can write whatever new configuration that you want, any way you want it.
So there is that.
Secondly, to WWE NSX's point, I would like to ask him which spin he was using, because
if he was installing Gnome Tree or something heavy, it might take a very long time, because
a default Gnome Tree install has, I think, somewhere around 1400 packages to install,
from the core utilities to all of the Gnome stuff, so obviously it would take a while.
The advantage, obviously, is that it doesn't download stuff from the internet, so you can
do it offline.
Right.
I also, before we go any further, I just want to make a caveat that Dave, his audio is a
little crackly.
He's been experiencing some problems under Linux, when he boots into Windows, the crackle
goes away.
So we're troubleshooting that, so we apologize, but you know, it's what happens sometimes
as Linux users.
All right, so WWE, did you have a response to that?
Yeah, I just grabbed a workstation ISO 64-bit off of Fedora's site and just downloaded it,
put it on the USB drive and just ran it.
What I think happened is the whole system locked up, because my mouse was movable, I
was just letting it sit and just format the partition, and at one point it just became
immovable and I left it until I thought, I'm going to have to hard reboot, and it just
froze on the formatting of the drive, so that's what happened for me.
Then obviously, yeah, that was probably an installer bug, that happens from time to time
to the best of us.
Yeah, is that true?
It happens with every disher out there, you have to be careful about that.
Bugs happen from time to time to the best of us, Raw, you have our closing thought you
wanted to say?
Yes.
Go ahead.
Go ahead, you have it sir.
No?
All right.
Oh yeah, I'm there, sorry, I didn't push.
So the Budgie desktop, I'm not sure whether you tried it out, but it's on, it's big on
Google+, they have a great community, and it's actually quite a good desktop, I wouldn't
prefer it over GNOME 3, but that's just because I'm used to it.
Is it Fedora based, or what's it based on?
It's GTK based, it's GNOME based.
Right, yeah, I know that, but what's the underlying distro that it's based on?
Yes, Fedora, I think.
I don't know what it's based on, but it's at least easily installable on Fedora, just
to add a repo file.
Yeah, very good.
All right, that's another check it out.
Every now and then, as the holidays come up from time to time, some of you have a little
extra time on your hands, some of you don't, if you're like me, especially with the three
kids.
Tell you what, Matt, I want to move to Texas, I'm going to set up the JB Ranch, I'll have
all of the hosts come down, they can live on the ranch, I'll be like George Lucas, and
all of it is just so that way when the family calls up and they're like, hey, are you coming
to Christmas?
I'll be like, oh yeah, you know what, sorry, gosh, I'd love to come to Christmas, but you
know what, I'm in Texas, yeah, I'm in Texas.
That's what I want to do, Matt.
What do you think?
Well, you know what would be cool, is when bacon's ready, you could just ring a bell,
right?
Yeah.
And all the hosts come, like, heads pop up out of the kennel, you know, it's like, come
running in.
And all the hosts, all the producers, that would get some stuff done.
I think that's a great idea.
Well, maybe we'll work that out in 2016.
In the meantime, go over to Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash contact and send us your feedback, it's
a huge part of the Linux Unplugged show.
Also linuxactionshow.reddit.com is where you go to give us your feedback.
If there was something like, God, why didn't these guys talk about this, these idiots?
Well, it's probably because you didn't submit it to our subreddit, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Also go over there to Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
We won't have a live show next week, but we will have a new show, but we need your best
of submissions, we're still taking those.
Check it out, we need your help.
Next week we'll have a new episode of sorts, it'll be some of our best of stuff with some
moments from me mixed in there.
So Matt, have a great Christmas, and I'll see you in two weeks, okay?
Sounds good, see you then.
All right everybody, thank you so much for tuning in to this week's episode of Linux
Unplugged.
We'll be right back here in two weeks.
I totally, I totally want to mess with Texas.
Great show.
That was a good show, great end of year, well of course it's not the end of year, we have
one more show in us.
But I feel like this is the last show of the year in a sense.
The next show, it's like a, I don't know what it is, it's like a freebie.
But thanks everybody, it was a great input.
So JBTitles.com, we gotta go boat, boat, everybody go over there right now.
One thing I'd just like to say, everything you talked about, think about YUM, and YUM
has its flaws, let me tell you that, but think about YUM, think about SELinux, the installer,
everything has worked perfectly fine since Fidelity 18.
Yeah, right, thank you.
I didn't mean to imply that the SELinux alerts and stuff, and the YUM stuff was new to 21.
I didn't, so you know, I sometimes assume people know that, and so I don't disclose
that, and really what I was trying to say is, it's part of the overall experience now
on 21 is you have all of that stuff combined with everything else.
Yes, so.
No, the thing is YUM sucks, YUM is a god damn, and coming from me that's saying something.
Oh!
I don't know, I mean it didn't seem that bad, of course I was mostly using DNF, it didn't
seem that bad.
Yeah, no, you have to, god damn.
So I can see it on the internet, that I do not like YUM as much as I like the app.
That being said, there are certain advantages, and these advantages have been there for a
very long time.
I haven't tried using DNF.
I have, I have a couple of times, it's YUM, it's what YUM should have been.
I like Lord Wimpy as one of our title suggestions, that's pretty good considering that Wimpy
is so badass.
Fedora 21 frags, Misconceptions is a little long.
That's not bad though.
It's a little long.
Like my opinion.
I'm sorry, it has a little nod to, is it not?
Yeah, I do like that aspect of it, I do agree.
Steam's winter is coming, ww, you know where my head's at.
Wifi enabled micro-brew, that's right Token Ring, paying attention.
Chris' bacon farm down in Texas.
Bacon farm?
I had a question for Wimpy as well, does his remote cloud top work with the brewery?
The brewery?
What is it called?
Sure it does.
The brewery?
The brewery, I think it is?
The brewery, yeah.
I have no idea.
If you buy me one, I'll test it.
Yeah, there you go.
All right, so.
I can see that becoming popular.
Christmas is coming.
Houses.
I don't mean to over-hype this, but I think we are currently experiencing a title crisis.
This is the title crisis of 2014 Winter Vortex Edition.
I don't like any of the titles in the top five ranking right now.
I need everybody to go to JBtitles.com.
This is a crisis.
You are entitled to your wrong opinion.
I'm entitled.
Hey yo.
Hey Wimpy, I like your, what did you call it, cloud top computing, what did you call
that?
Yeah, link bait, that's what that was.
I know, but that was good.
That was good.
Yeah, cloud top computing, yeah.
You know, it reminded me, I was on Tech Talk today, I was telling on the pre-show, I was
telling a story about five or six years ago, I worked at a school district.
And not only did they have abysmally slow internet, but they also had really restrictive
filters, content filters, as you might expect.
But to the point of where it made it hard to even do some IT troubleshooting and things
like that.
Because certain open source projects were flagged, and it was really, even like I think
for a time, Jupiter Broadcasting was flagged.
But this was five or six years ago, right?
This wasn't really in the era of digital ocean droplets anymore.
And so I had a friend who had a data center down in Texas, and he gave me a co-located
server.
It was like an Optron box.
I think it had two Optron processors in it, and about 16 gigabytes of RAM.
And it was a Red Hat Linux, I think it was Red Hat Enterprise something old.
And it was a full-fledged like real PC server, like it wasn't a VM, it was a full racked
box that I was getting for about $120 to $135 a month, including an NFS-attached storage
array that I had for like big stuff, which was really cool.
And what I did back then, and I know I think we've talked about this before, Wimpy, is
I didn't use X2GO, which is what you're using.
I use something called No Machine NX or MX.
Do you remember this?
Yeah.
Yeah, well that's what I'm using at work at the moment, and I'm about to replace with
X2GO.
Yeah.
So from what my experience is with No Machine, again it goes over SSH, it uses pretty good
compression, it can even do like remote sound.
You know, I mean it was amazing for me because I essentially had like a Gnome 2 or XFCE style
desktop, and I could even watch YouTube videos, 20, 30 frames per second maybe if I was lucky,
and the audio would be synced up, and it was extremely, extremely usable.
I would close the window, my session would just remain, I would reconnect, I would resume
right where I left off.
So what is the main advantage of X2GO over, say, No Machine?
Because No Machine is still a thing too.
Yeah, X2GO is just blitzing quick and lighter weight.
So the core implementation takes about 35 meg of RAM, and when you actually connect
to a full Ubuntu Mate session, you can run it in 125 meg of RAM.
And doing that over, I use FreeNX currently with Ubuntu 10.04, we're about to ditch that
and update, but that uses about twice the RAM, and that's where FreeNX, which is the
open source implementation of No Machine.
So yeah, but like you say, you've got all of that good stuff like transparent audio
relay, so your audio transparently shifts from the remote instance to your local instance.
Yes, it's very exciting.
And yes, you can watch SD video from YouTube and what have you.
But where X2GO starts to differentiate itself is you've got this transparent shunting of
your directories from your local machine to the remote machine, which all happens over
SSHFS, and you just right click, share a folder, pick a folder, and then boom, it appears on
the desktop as a mounted drive on the remote instance.
Would you be up for doing a segment with us on last, like in January sometime on that?
Because that is really cool.
The file system set up like that is definitely very neat.
I'd love to show people.
I can.
I tell you what, maybe we'll want to wait a little bit longer, because since I posted
about that, I've been talking to DigitalOcean, and I'm now working with their editorial team
to turn this into a proper tutorial.
So there's going to be several articles, and I was talking about this in the lobby with
some of the other guys prior to the stream starting.
So we're going to do the initial recreating what I've done.
So as an individual, you can create a droplet and deploy a desktop into it, and I'll explain
what the potential use cases for that are.
But then taking it full circle, what we're going to be looking at is if you're a small
business and you want to control your distributed workforces computing environment, and you've
got to bring your own device policy, how you can set up centralized authentication for
these multiple instances, and you know what your fixed costs are per employee per month.
It's going to cost you 10 bucks a month for a workstation instance, which they can connect
to from a Mac machine or a Windows machine or a tablet or whatever.
So just to hold on, just to put you on pause, are you telling me that what you're working
on is a way to take somebody, say, that has multiple droplets that are desktop instances
that they connect to where they have a secure place to work, but they would all also have,
maybe like on the private networking side, a centralized login system, like an open
ELD app or something?
Precisely that on the centralized authentication side, but also building on DigitalOcean's
private networking, the end game is once you've got central authentication and multiple instances
on a larger droplet, deploying Open Media Vault and using the private networking to
create a virtual distributed office.
Oh my gosh.
That is brilliant.
Yeah, of course.
Oh wow.
Of course you could do that.
That is so slick.
That is, that is, I want to do that.
I want to do that.
Nice.
Right, Matt?
You know what I'm saying?
That's like, when you hear that, you're like, wait a minute, okay, hold on, who needs computers
anymore?
I'm just going to build droplets.
I'll have an Open Media Vault rig up there.
Seriously?
I'll have a Plex rig up there.
I'm going to do this.
That is wimpy.
You've got to tell us how that goes.
That's really cool.
It changes the economics of everything, really.
Quite.
And what I've got here, what I've been experimenting with is there are a number of thin client solutions,
and we were talking about some of those earlier, but the one I'm using is I've got a Raspberry
Pi with, in fact, you know about this, Chris, because Q5Sys gave you one, a Raspberry Pi
with an Atrix lap dock, and then a wireless dongle.
The whole thing runs wirelessly off the internal battery for 10 hours, and I've got a minimal
arch instance on that Raspberry Pi, which boots to open box, automatically starts the
X2Go client, and then I log in to my remote Ubuntu MATE droplet, and as far as my workstation
is concerned, I've got a full Ubuntu MATE workstation, far more powerful than the Raspberry
Pi I'm using to connect to.
No kidding.
Talk about taking a Raspberry Pi and just making it, essentially, a transparent shim
between you and the remote system that has potentially a huge connection, super fast
SSD.
That is wimpy.
Geez, that's cool.
And a Raspberry Pi is like a super cheap version of this, but when you look at these deployments
that are happening where Windows is being replaced with a Linux desktop, it's not being
replaced with a Linux desktop on that Windows machine.
By and large, they are remote terminal services, and that Windows machine is being repurposed
as a thin client.
So this is how you can bridge that gap and minimize your hardware expenditure.
This pushes so many buttons for me, because remote desktops used to be something that
not only did I... So I took what was once the largest independent bank here in Washington,
which is no longer the case after 2008, but we moved them from DOS to terminal services.
But then I went to school districts and did Linux terminal services project.
And then when I was working for the school district, I did the no machine thing for myself.
And what you're talking about right now is so up my alley.
It is like my bag, so I really want you to keep me updated on this, because I would love
... Not only would I love to just talk to you about this, but I would love to even show
people how to do this, because this could be seriously a way to show people that watch
the Linux action show, a very straightforward, very cost-effective way to build out a remote
Linux-based desktop.
Doesn't matter if all of their employees want to have Macbooks and iPads and iPhones.
That's fine.
But when you log in to do the work, you log into our secure environment under control,
under our control, up in the cloud, connected over private networking to our internal resources.
Exactly.
And that solves your bring your own device IT governance problem right there, and your
file format compatibility problem with Mac users with one version of Microsoft Office
and Windows users with another Microsoft Office version, and it just solves all of that.
Wow, that's slick.
Wow.
And the other piece, a little bit further out, because this is in the unstable branch
at the moment, and I mentioned it a few weeks ago, but there's a bolt-on protocol for ExtaGo
called Telekinesis, and that's a general purpose protocol, but it was really developed to facilitate
a mTeleplayer.
So now what you can do is you can have full HD content on the remote instance, and instead
of using the ExtaGo protocol to send the rendered video, it actually streams the video back
to your remote machine, but in a window, and it looks like it's being rendered on the remote
machine, but it's not, it's actually the video's being streamed.
So I'll just go off and find a little video, there's a video of two full HD screens running
a 4K video over ExtaGo and mTeleplayer.
No, no.
Yeah, I'll just go and find it, it's on YouTube, hang on a sec, I'll be back, I'll be back
in a bit.
Wow, that is amazing.
This feels like we're getting like ice cream with our pie, and getting like double scoops.
So you guys know I've been trying out this touch screen for a little bit.
And it's pretty solid, surprising, it's surprisingly good.
I'm happy overall with the picture quality, one thing that I have noticed is, you know,
it's like the things you don't expect, I guess thinking about it, when I got this monitor,
my plan was to fix up one of the old hackintoshes that I used to use as the switcher, it's a
pretty nice hackintosh, and I thought, alright, I'm going to fix this up, I'm going to make
it an arch box, and then I'll put that under the table, and I'll take the Bonobo home.
Because, you know, I bought it to be able to do quite a heavy video load, so it's still,
even though it was a couple of years ago, it still makes a pretty good, like, just dedicated
GNOME workstation.
And I would just have that hooked up to the Dell monitor and the other mirrored port going
out to the HDMI capture.
But you know, it needs some work, it needs like some data has to be backed up off of
it, and it needs fans replaced, and it just has, like, stuff that has to be done to it.
It just, I'm not getting to that.
So I realized, well, you know, this Bonobo here, this frickin' Bonobo's got HDMI out,
display port out, and a built-in screen.
I've always wondered, as long as I've owned the Bonobo, would the Bonobo be down for a
three-way monitor hookup?
I've never, you know, I've always been a little cautious about, I didn't want to approach
the Bonobo and be like, hey, Bonobos, I got this idea, and then the Bonobo would be like,
are you serious?
When my HDMI port is full, that display port is off, buddy, that is off limits.
But it turns out, it actually works great.
I plugged in both the display port and the HDMI port, they're filled up now, and the
internal screen's also on, and it works magically, I mean, it really works well.
The downside though, and I'm running the latest Nvidia driver here, but from time to time,
you know, about seven, eight days in, the driver just starts crapping itself.
I don't know what exactly is going on, because usually it seems to happen right after I get
done playing a full-screen video.
And then the X session drops, GNOME restarts, well, the X session comes back, GNOME restarts,
fairly gracefully, everything actually kind of resumes, you know?
All my apps are still running, it's not like a full jump out, it's more like something
just changes.
And I go back to the default X layout, I no longer am in a three-way, I'm now back to
one monitor, and then two remote displays, well that immediately breaks capture.
And the thing is, if I'm playing a full-screen video, there's like a 98.9% chance that I'm
actually in the middle of a show, because that's why I'm playing the video.
So that means my whole session takes a crap in the middle of a show, and the only way
to fix it is if I get up and walk away from the microphone, and I walk around the table,
and I go over to the Bonobo, and I go there and I bring up the NVIDIA control panel on
the Bonobo's display, and I mirror everything again, and then I walk back.
So it's been a bit of a bumpy ride because of that.
So the touchscreen, on its own, has been pretty solid.
The unexpected consequence, though, of forcing my video card into a three-way has been not
so stable drivers that seem to impact me about seven or eight days, just about the time you
forget the problem even exists, and think it's maybe not going to happen again, BOOM!
It gets you right in the middle of a, I don't know, unfilter, and then Rekai has to fix
it in editing.
That happened.
Um.
Have you considered using a different desktop environment?
Pfft!
No!
Cri...