Okay. Well, we love to talk up Chris's hair and rightfully so I'm here. It's quaffed. It's lovely
I want to get a little closer to it, but I'm sad to say I think I've discovered one hair based competition
I don't think you'd win. I don't know Wes don't count the hair out. What do you got?
All right. Well, maybe you want to throw down in the USA mullet championship. I'll do it for the show. Hello
friends and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is was my name is
Brent. My name is Alex. Hello gentlemen. Well, we have a really fun show today. We took on a challenge
could a demanding Linux user someone who demands excellence live with a reasonably low cost Linux
box. We take a look at a couple of surprising budget Linux PCs. I bet you've never even heard of and
we'll see how they hold out. Plus, we've been challenged to put Linux Mint to the test is the
freshest mint the best Linux for a low end PC. We'll give that a shot and tell you our opinions as
well. Then we'll round out the show with some great boosts, some pics and a lot more. So before we go
any further, you know, it's our duty. We got to say time appropriate greetings to our virtual lug.
Hello, Mumble Room. Hello, Chris. So many names today. A very strong Mumble Room. Wow. So great.
Hello, everybody. And hello, all of you up there in the quiet listening as well. Very nice to have
you along for the show today. I also want to say good morning over to our friends over at tail
scale. tail scale is a mesh VPN protected by wire guard. We love it. And it's going to change your
networking game. It's going to blow your mind. Go see what wire guard is capable of. Oh, it's a good
morning to go over there. I don't care what time of day it is. Say good morning from Linux unplugged
at tailscale.com. Go try it up to 20 devices free. You can wish them good night too. I suppose I just
like the idea of it's always morning at tailscale. You know, it's always a good morning over at
tailscale. Okay, so we got to start the show off with the meetups. You know, we've been talking
about meetups, we've been talking about meetups. And I know I've listened to podcasts where I'm
like, well, that meetup doesn't apply to me. I wish they didn't talk about it all the time. But
here, here's the thing, buddy, here's the thing. These meetups are a bigger deal than I think you
appreciate until you can attend them. And that's kind of why we continue to talk about them is
because once you go to a meetup, you experience the kind of connection that I think is, I don't
know, it's almost like built into us that we need that kind of social connection with our with our
tribe. And so it can be re energizing, it can be profound in a lot of ways. And so we just had a
couple of them wrap up. And that's one of the reasons Alex is here today. How you feeling, Alex?
Good morning. I know you just woke up a little a little bit before the show, you just got back
home. How was the meetup and everything? How was your flight and all that stuff?
Well, I'm not gonna lie, Chris, you're probably hearing my voice. I'm a little tired right now.
Yeah, I can hear it. Well, yeah, you got a little bit of that frog flight was fine. You know, 18
month old toddler on a nine hour fart tube flight, what could go wrong? We only had one meltdown
that was I don't know, like if anybody that's listening is a parent and has been in that
situation where your kid is just hyperventilating from the crying on the plane. You just feel
helpless in that moment. Like you want the child to be okay. You want all the people to not be
there. It's just Yeah, that was that was a fun moment. But the meetup made it all worthwhile.
And we got a clip from the meetup from our buddy Joe Resington to just give us a quick flavor of
the event.
Hello, and welcome everyone to late night self hosted after dark in the park. So great. You can
hear the whole thing in late night Linux 190, which is going to come out on August 15. But I
think it's pretty great that Joe joined. And so you've got the late night Linux crew there. You've
got the JB crew there. It's a big conspiracy to make us as jealous as possible. Yeah, I was
watching some I was looking from afar watching some of the pictures come in thinking, man, I
wish I could have been there. It was a beautiful evening. So to set the scene, we're in this
Jubilee Park and gardens just underneath the London Eye down by the River Thames on the South
Bank. And it's just you know, groups of people peppered around on the grass, you know, having a
little picnic and stuff. You know, mid 20s in the temperature, a little bit of sunshine. It was
just the perfect evening to be outside with a group of friends. And a pretty good crowd too. It
looks like you got what nearly 100 folks there. So almost as many people that signed up or more.
Well, I took with me 75 stickers, 150 stickers, sorry. And I had two packs and I came back with
one unsealed pack. So by my count, there were 74 people plus a random lady that decided to come and
sit behind Joe and I whilst we were recording. And we there was this moment where we were in the
middle of this show about 20 minutes in and this just random lady comes and sits like, you know, a
foot behind me and I'm like, Oh, this is going to go south. She what is was because I could see the
cider in her hand. I was like, Hmm, is she drunk? Is she going to cause problems? And no, she
didn't. She sat there the whole time. And then after we finished, I was you know, a shout out to
anybody as anybody not got a sticker because I was very insistent that everybody got a sticker
because it was basically my counter for attendance. Good idea, Alex. And she she went,
Yeah, I'll take a sticker. I'm like, Sorry, who are you? And she went, Do you need to know? I was
like, Hmm, no, I don't actually.
Man, this location is just so beautiful. It's got the Ferris wheel. Of course, you can see the
rivers right there. A huge crowd. It looks like actually, look at that crowd.
Yeah. So the thing about the South Bank down by the Thames there is you get a lot of street
performers and they they gather crowds of 2300 people at a time and this shows last 10 minutes
and then at the end, you give them a couple of quid to say thank you. And so it's just this
really nice family relaxed vibe down by the river, which is exactly what I was going for with the
location. So well, it's out great. And, you know, the fact that we had 75 or so people show up as
well, you know, it was I was very, very pleased. And we had people from all over we had some, I
think the furthest that, you know, by myself, the people came was the Czech Republic. We had two or
three Norwegians there. There was a couple of Dutch people there. I know bites in the mumble
room today. I met bite at the meetup as well. That was nice.
I spent some money to be there for one day.
Did you? Was it kind of expensive to get there?
Yeah. Even taking the train is enormously expensive. I found one of the cheaper flights. But
then I made a little mistake by taking a train back to the airport and paying 40 pounds for a one
way trip and some other little mistakes that made the trip a bit more expensive than I would like.
But yeah, it's not it can't be beaten by something else.
Lessons learned for next year. Right. So that way, if Wes and I make it out there next year,
you can be our tour guide. Yeah. But you get what I'm saying, too, right, Alex, you get that kind
of that charge by being around people that want to talk about the same stuff or excited about the
same stuff. Follow the shows. It's really fun.
It's very surreal meeting a group of complete strangers that know a lot about you and you know
nothing about them because this medium is a very one way, for the most part, a very one way
medium, you know, very weird people like, Oh, how's your mother in law's internet work? And I'm
like, Oh, yeah, we talked about that in self hosted, didn't we? That's that's how you know
that. Yeah. Yeah, you do get a few things like that, for sure. They might know more than we know
about ourselves at times. And then you want to know how you know that Alex is truly a party animal
is that Brent managed to talk him into going to another meetup when he got back to Raleigh. Yeah.
Yeah, they got back at about 2pm here local time in Raleigh. And since I'm you know, to give a
little context, I was house sitting while Alex was away. So but I organized a little sneaky little
micro meetup here in Raleigh. Thanks to our matrix room. It was amazing.
Hi, this is Brent from Raleigh. I found an Alex. Apparently he's doing two days, two continents
and two JB meetups. Hi, Alex. And I even have some stickers left for this one that is planning. It's
true. They've been re imported for this purpose. And I found a few people. Hi. Hello. We've got
what how many are we six, six of us and we're having a great time. A Raleigh rabble. Raleigh
Raleigh. Sounds like you're really enjoying yourselves. Yeah, we had a great time. I think it
was probably a very different energy than the London meetup, right? Well, I think I was awake
for like, our 16 when we sat down. 18. By the time we left, I was a little bit drunk with tiredness,
wasn't I? Not even from the beer I've had. Yeah, easily. But you made it. It was a great time. We
probably laughed more than anything. We had some good food. And it was a nice low key thing. And I
hope the whole idea with these sort of regional based matrix rooms is that some of these meetups
can happen on a regular basis. And maybe even without JB folks. So we hope that I think we can
facilitate that for listeners. Right. That does seem to be happening that we have a listener that
emailed into office hours that wants to start organizing meetups on their own with just other
JB listeners. I love it. I think we'll cover it a bit more in self hosted as well, no doubt talking
about the meter. But for anybody that's listening to this show that was in London or in Raleigh last
night, huge thanks for showing up. I got a huge amount of energy from you all to continue doing
this for a lot longer. You know, it's it's, it's weird sitting in your own room, just talking to a
microphone. It feels a little bit disconnected from reality sometimes. And to actually connect
in meat space with real human meat bags that have been listening. It's it's hard to describe
really, but thank you all for coming. It means a lot. Yeah, yeah, I'm really looking forward to
them to more meetups, too, because it's just you want to keep it rolling. I kind of loved it, too.
You know, I was a little distracted, but I could see the various channels and matrix just just
exploding with little pics. And it made me feel like I was I was almost there. Yeah, it was nice
to watch the London meetup and then the Raleigh group later. And like, you know, happens often
at these events, some gifts were given as well. My name is Philip, and I brought some retired
raspberry pies that have been collecting dust and I thought maybe you could put them to good use.
That is super generous. Now when you say retired, what exactly do you mean? And how old are they?
And what have they been used for? They are several years old. Actually, I can't remember how old they
are. One is a Raspberry Pi three, which is quite a bit older. And one is a Raspberry Pi four.
They started out as a home assistant, of course. And then I kind of moved on from home assistant
to home kit and had grand designs to do other projects with them and never got around to.
That sounds familiar. Well, thank you for bringing gifts. We didn't ask for gifts,
but this is super amazing. Thank you. You're very welcome. That is so great,
you know, and everybody's got a Raspberry Pi these days. They're not using see instead of
feeling guilty about it, you could gift to Brantley, who has been Raspberry Pi short,
you know, not anymore. Thanks. Wonderful listeners. Now you're Raspberry Pi rich.
You know, Philip did also reveal a little later, which I unfortunately didn't get an audio,
but he did reveal that his upgrade that sort of replace these Raspberry Pis is now running Umbral
and he's really loving it. That is great. Boy, he's right in sync, isn't he? Although he went
from home assistant to home kit. And my humble opinion, usually you want to go from home kit
to home assistant, but no judgment. Oh, no home automation shame on the show. Come on.
No, no judgment. Now, Alex, we got a little gift from London as well, didn't we?
We did. Listener Thor, who came in from Norway, has gifted the network one of these remarkable
e-ink tablets. Remarkable is the brand name of the thing. It's this iPad sized e-ink tablet
display annotation device, note taking device. And so we're going to let Brent put it through
its paces over the next week or two before he comes to see you, Chris.
That's fun. Now, is it a touch screen as well? Yes. You know, I've explored it for about 38
seconds so far. So the journey begins now. And I think I'll put it through its paces. It'll see a
few airplanes and cars and hopefully trains as well. So we'll see how it does. Thank you,
by the way. I can't help but think that the best job for that would be a low power home assistant
dashboard that's displaying you info. But yeah, buddy, you turn everything into a dashboard.
That's true. I would say please send in your ideas. I would love to find about, you know,
20 different ways to use this thing. So send them in. What OS do we know? Currently, it says
out of battery. Is that an OS? I'm wondering if it's a Linux. If anybody knows, send it in.
Are you suggesting the poor battery life is a Linux thing? No, it must be Android then.
Hey, yo. All right. So the next round of meetups is Nye. We have a whole swath of West Coast
meetups. So go to meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting. Wes, you caught this in the news
recently, but it looks like NASA is going all in on the Linux copters. The future plans, I guess,
for Mars exploration are going to include a set of two helicopters for like the next rover.
It's going to come with two of them. They're also thinking of having them pick up samples
for additional missions to return those samples to Earth. So how about that? Yeah. So that's
amazing. Ingenuity has not only, I think, exceeded expectations, but it's clearly set the path
forward for future space exploration with Linux copters. That's just so awesome. When we get down
to JPL, I hope to get a chance to talk to Tim about this specifically and just kind of get his
take on this. And if this wasn't kind of the long goal, maybe they didn't want to outwardly say it,
but I got to imagine they were kind of hoping if this all worked out, this is where things were
going. I wonder if we can get any tips to make our own Linux copter. They're not going anywhere.
They're not going anywhere. I kind of want one now. You could ask Tim yourself, dear listener,
just get your name in the hat. Go to linuxunplug.com slash JPL. We have 15 slots available to our
audience to take a personalized tour of JPL. And we'll be pulling names from that hat as the event
gets closer. So that's linuxunplug.com slash JPL. And that's just a simple next cloud form that we
have that you can fill out. And then we also have our West Coast crew matrix room where we are
organizing with locals along the West Coast and figuring out where people are at. We'd love to
have you join us there as well. That's in our matrix colony. And details for all the meetups,
the individual meetups we're stopping at from Oregon down to Southern California at meetup.com
slash Jupiter broadcasting. All right. I think that's everything with that. The meetups take a
big part of the show during the summer, but they're super important to us. So we want to
dedicate some time to that. You know what? There's not always a lot else going on. That's true. It
is the summer. A lot of developers, especially the ones outside the US, they do this crazy thing
called vacation. And I think some of them are even taking like six weeks off at a time. I don't know.
They must not get paid for it, I'm sure. And they probably have all their medical coverage suspended
because it's tied to their job, I'm sure. Of course. Yeah. Because otherwise that wouldn't
make any sense. It'd be completely unfair. And that's not how we would do it in the States,
right guys? But it's cool. So development slows down a little bit sometimes.
Are you all right over there?
Yeah, I'm good. I'm good.
Extra, extra patriotic today.
Yeah. I just, that's just one thing that, you know, whatever. Let's talk about saving money
because some of us, you know, we don't need to be blowing money right now on expensive computers
that can do the job perfectly fine. This is great too for friends and family, people that just want
a go to Linux machine. And you know, here's one tip that remember to remember tweeted at me that
I think is really the key one. It's just got to remember to shop with Linux in mind when you're
looking for this stuff. Just like you would, if you're going to buy something for the Mac,
you got to shop with the Mac in mind. It's a little less of a problem on windows, but let's be
honest, you got to do it on windows too, because you could end up with something that's really
crap drivers. And that just makes your whole system suck. So you really got to kind of shop
careful on windows. Pick which third-party weird driver applications you want running on your box.
Right. Which auto-updater that starts every time your windows box boots, which one do you want?
So, you know, it's to say it's a compromise to have to kind of shop with Linux in mind
and compatibility in mind. I just disagree. I think that's just the state of computing,
but I just wanted to put that up front. Everything we're going to talk about today,
you just kind of want to shop with Linux compatibility in mind. And today I want to
talk about four cheap Linux PCs. And I use that term generously. I don't mean cheap as in quality.
I just mean cheap as in price. And I want to tell you about four I found. And then I,
and if you guys have any suggestions to, I definitely want to hear those first,
first starting with not one that I have tried personally, but I heard about this from Adam
Curry and it just seems like a crazy good deal right now. Brand new from Amazon,
160 US greenbacks for a Beelink mini SPC with an 11th gen Intel N5095 processor,
eight gigs of Ram and 128 gigabyte SSD. I think it ships with windows 11, but you could put Linux
on there. It's 160 bucks new. And they even have like a $10 off coupon right now. It's crazy.
So 150 bucks for a brand new 11th gen Intel PC or run Linux. That's kind of like just from start
right there, but maybe you want to go even cheaper. Maybe you're really on a budget. Maybe it's for,
you know, maybe it's for your kids, maybe it's for yourself and you just don't want to spend a
lot of money on this kind of stuff right now. I want to tell you about a machine that I got
since the last episode. It is the Acer switch one Intel, Adam's Z 8,300, 1.4 gigahertz laptop.
And it's one of these that you can flip the screen around and run Linux as a tablet if you have the
right distro. So some people are into that, you know, convertible style. I have it here with me
in the studio right now. It's about the size of an 11 inch, you know, or so iPad with the keyboard.
It reminds me back of the days of like the netbook era, you know, kind of that size.
Yeah. And then of course you can flip the screen around and do those kinds of shenanigans. Although
I don't know if I actually would ever try that. Here's the problem. I haven't tried this machine
personally because I got it off eBay and the bastard didn't include the power down there.
Oh no. Didn't even, I forget. And of course it's some random barrel one, right?
So I'm just mentioning this because $45. Oh my goodness. $45. Yes, it's an Adam, but $45.
That's like, you're in pie prices now. And you could have basically a tablet,
PC with a keyboard and Linux is going to run just fine on there, right?
Chris, what's the age of this thing?
Well, the Intel Atom X5 is pretty old. I mean, it's not, it's not a brand new machine. I think
it's like a 2015 model. Again, you're not going to get the latest and greatest for under a hundred
bucks, but you know, to have something under a hundred bucks that you could put Linux on,
it's nice to have that option.
I think this is the episode where you're putting on like the used car salesman vibe. You know,
let me put you in an Intel Atom.
This is a previously loved laptop with a special undercoating.
You're right. It is very tablet-like in that like a bunch of the ports and stuff seem to be
in on the screen side. And then the keyboard is, you know, really just kind of like the keyboard
that's attached.
Right. And it's got a front and back camera on the screen.
Oh, perfect for selfies.
So that's an interesting one. But now I want to tell you about a really practical one.
This is just another hot Chris pick here. This is one that I personally own. I actually bought
this machine to run as, to test it as potentially a replacement for JOOPS's home server to replace
my Raspberry Pi 4. But in the end, I decided the IO was too limiting.
And so this is the Ideapad 3, 14 IML 5, 128 gigabyte SSD, Intel Pentium Gold, 2.4 gigahertz.
This one came with four gigs of RAM, but the bottom pops right off and you can upgrade
basically all the components, but it's very, it's very serviceable in that regard.
The RAM and the hard drive are accessible in the Ideapad 3. And it's actually a pretty
good little laptop. It's got a decent size to it. It's got a decent trackpad. It's got
a good keyboard for this price range.
Doesn't look bad. I mean, it doesn't stand out, but that's kind of what you want in a
laptop like this.
It's just a simple ThinkPad. It's of the kind of older ThinkPad styling because it's a little
bit older. And it has the Intel Gold CPU, which means it has quick sync, which is one of the
reasons I bought it, but that might be useful to you. Check that out there, Wes. So that
one's a little heavier. This one goes for $260.
It's not bad, though. And it's well weighted. It does not feel off-kilter.
It does not feel off-kilter or off-access when I'm holding it in here, which I like.
Yeah, it is. It's got a lot of the pros of a well-designed Lenovo. It's a little old,
but I still think that Intel Pentium Gold CPU is actually a pretty good little chip.
So I think overall, that's like, out of all of the list, that's going to be my most practical
recommendation right here.
Now, Chris, I see you have a dongle dangling off that thing. Is there a specific purpose
for that, that you're using it for?
Yeah, you could have taken these off before you handed it to me.
Well, it doesn't have Ethernet built in. So that is an Ethernet dongle, just because
I likes to have it wired sometimes. And that's not too uncommon at this price point, is to
not get Ethernet in there.
Or at the higher price points, too.
Yeah, unfortunately, you're right about that. This next one I'm about to talk about doesn't
have Ethernet, but it's not because they're being cheap. It's because it literally wouldn't
fit on the hardware. This one's a lot of fun, guys. This is something really special. I
don't even know how I didn't know about this. It's called the Acer Mini PC. And it was sold
in a Cloud Professor Kit. It's a whole kit that comes...
You could just say Cloud Professor Kit like that and assume we know what that means.
Try it. Open it up here, Wes. I brought it into the studio. This is the Cloud Professor
Kit. And maybe you could describe what's in there. Take a look while I talk about this
device. So this device is smaller than a Chromecast in overall size, or about the size of a Chromecast.
It has a 1.4 gigahertz CPU, two gigabytes of RAM, 16 gigabytes of hard drive space.
It has an HDMI out. They managed to put USB-A on the thing. And they have what seems to
be like a micro SD type slot and a mini USB slot probably for power. The thing fits literally
in the palm of my hand. It is absolutely tiny. And it comes pre-installed with Linux on it.
Okay. So it looks like this thing is targeted. Like, is this a PC to use while you're making
an Arduino?
Yeah, it's for training.
Embedded. Oh, okay.
Yeah. So this kit actually comes with an Arduino in the box, too. So you can connect it.
Yeah. It's got a nice little seed shield here, too.
So you get a whole kit with a book. You get the kit.
Sensor sensor, light sensor. You can make some fun projects with this.
Yes. And it is $38 US dollars. $38 US dollars.
Now I think we also, you get to call yourself a cloud professor after you bought this, right?
So that's also a big part of that.
Well, it's on the thing. So it says-
It also comes with a badge.
Right.
Yeah. And so it's an Atom. It's a fifth gen Atom CPU. So it's an x86 CPU. It's smaller
than a Raspberry Pi in terms of overall width, but it's about the length of a Raspberry Pi
board.
And you could just slap it on the back of one of these studio monitors. It's obviously
fanless.
Yeah. And with the HDMI out, you could hook it up to anything that takes HDMI. It's totally
silent. This has me rethinking the Raspberry Pi for a lot of things. And that's what I
want to use this for, is what I might use a Pi for, but I want x86 compatibility.
Whoa. Okay. So you kind of undersold this whole segment. You know, interesting, yeah,
but really it's a titanic shift in how you're deploying things.
Well, we'll see. I mean, they're cheaper and more available than a Raspberry Pi. That's
just the reality of it right now.
Hopefully more successful than the Titanic, though, Wes.
Oh, we'll see about that. I mean, that's probably why they're going for 30 bucks or 40 bucks
on eBay, right?
I mean, I do think it's interesting though, anytime you mentioned the Pi and the fact
that you have, you know, you have what, five or six and we had Josh on Self Hosted a few
weeks ago who has 47 or something crazy. Like the first place that my mind goes to has always
been just get a single x86 box and replace all of them and you'll save power, you'll
save money. These days, definitely save money. So it's interesting to see you finally go
down this path.
Yeah, that's how I actually got the idea, Pat, is I was thinking, well, one x86 box,
a little more powerful. It has quick sync on there, so it'd be great for Jellyfin or
AirPlex. And then I just wasn't really happy with the overall availability and I thought,
well, if I'm really going to go to the extreme, something like a Raspberry Pi that's x86 would
be the way to go. And this thing, as far as I can tell, runs off of a micro USB for power.
So the power consumption is going to be nothing, right? How cool is that? What do you think,
Wes? You're holding it right now.
Yeah, I mean, it's nice. It's a good little form factor. I like that there's a full size
USB 3 on here, right? So it seems kind of, sure, could I have a few more plugins? You're
going to need dongles maybe, but what it is for the price, yeah, seems worth a shot.
Yeah. So it's the Acer Mini PC with an Atom CPU, or you could just search for the Cloud
Professor. It is what it is, guys. That's just what they call it. I mean, I think you
can find them on eBay without the whole kit as well, but I kind of wanted the kit. I mean,
why not get the Arduino?
You may be able to sell the Arduino for $38 and get your money back.
Well, I think I want to give it away. I think I want to give the whole kit away after I
play with it for a little bit.
That's a nice idea.
Yeah. So I'll keep it all together so that way we can just package the box back up and
ship it out to a listener in the future. So I'll put links to all of the eBay listings
to these in the show notes if you want to try it out. Do any of you guys have a really
just quick go-to budget Linux PC? We've got some recommendations that came in from the
audience that we're going to get to as well, but we'll get to those in a bit.
I do. It's the HP290 Slim. It's one of these old thin client boxes. I think it's 8th Gen
Intel CPUs. They used to be available for under $100. I think it's closer to $150 now,
but typically these things come with the Celeron G4900, which has very capable quick sync performance.
It's been running my Blue Iris box now for a couple of years. Just does the job. It comes
with a 500 gigabyte spinner, I think, from most eBay sellers. I upgraded that to a SATA
or an M.2 SATA or an NVMe SSD. I can't remember which. So for under $200, I've got a very
capable box. I know it's running Windows. I know you asked for a Linux box, but it would
run Linux just fine.
That's a great recommendation. We got a suggestion too for a Dell Wyze thin client from an anonymous
supplier, the 5070 thin client. They said that it actually works pretty well for them.
$120 shipped. They added a 512 gigabyte M.2 and two 8 gig sticks of RAM. The whole thing
off of Amazon is like $105 after they added the upgrades. Then you buy the thin client
itself for $120. You put it all together. You're under $300 and he says you've got a
great or they say you've got a great Linux learning machine. So it's the Wyze 5070 thin
client. So two thin client recommendations.
I have been kind of decently surprised at some of those lower end, you know, the atoms
and the Celeron line even these days. Like if you don't need to do much, you're not doing
serious crunching, it works.
Right. The thing is about the Celeron that's in the HP box are recommended. With QuickSync,
all of the hard processing is going through a hardware chip. So all the threads are doing
is just keeping the OS going really.
Yeah.
It's great.
I mean, it works for the iPad. Why not here? Right? You just got to have the right software
hardware combo. And that's where looking for something with QuickSync can make that. We
got a recommendation from Colin, I believe. Was it Brent?
We actually got this recommendation twice. So I think it's probably a good one. Colin
and Antal also suggested this one. It's a Minis Forum Desk Mini UM350 Ryzen Mini PC.
And this one ships with Manjaro pre-installed on it, it looks like.
Yeah, it's a maybe a little higher budget. It's at the $299. It's currently on sale for
$299. But directly, it's brand new. And so I think you can buy it directly from Minis
Forum and a whole bunch of other places, eBay, you can get it on Amazon as well. And I saw
it, I didn't click into it, but I also saw a link at Walmart. So I don't know what that's
about. But it seems like Minis Forum, which is new to me, has an interesting catalog of
small and not too expensive machines that are worth checking out.
I love this tip. This looks like it'd be a great podcasting machine for doing recordings
and whatnot there. What I love about Linux is that you can actually build a really awesome
budget machine and not feel bad about it. There's something about the Linux community
where it can actually be kind of an awesome cool guy thing to do to go down low end and
make it work with the lowest end PC where it always seems like in Windows, especially
get to the gaming culture, it's always skews towards the biggest graphics card, the fastest
CPU, the fastest machine, all of the lights, all the RGB lighting you possibly can stuff
in there, liquid cooling just to the absolute maximum extreme. And that's just like only
accessible to such a small amount of people. But in the Linux community, we also will celebrate
the really low end and try to make that work and try to find these cool little budget machines
that can get a crap ton of work done for you at a great price.
I love that it's the same Linux, too. You know, because couldn't you just imagine on
some of these lower end machines like other vendors are going to ship a more limited operating
system. But right. We get the we get the same for doesn't come with like Windows starter
edition. Right. That's a great point.
I think what I find really amazing and something that I guess I have lived this lifestyle for
the last many years, you know, with my low end hardware that I somehow make productive.
We've got our low end expert brand in our low end correspondence checking in here. What
I have really loved and and that was true since the beginning of my Linux journey was
that you can you can throw Linux on some of this lower end hardware and it performs in
a way that other operating systems, at least other popular operating systems, just can't
even match, can't even come close. You know, if you are choosing something like I don't
know Joe's XFC favorite or lesser process intensive desktop environments, CPU challenged
machines. Right. I think it's kind of amazing that you can run that on really what fits
in the palm of your hand. You know, that's right. I think one of Linux is major strengths
is it can do that and it can be, you know, the top 100 supercomputers as well.
I agree. So the question becomes which distribution is the right? You got a lot of choice, but
only one can be king.
Linode dot com slash unplugged. Go there to get one hundred dollars and 60 day credit
on a new account. And it's a great way to show your support for the show. Linode is
definitely the Linux geeks cloud. They've got 11 data centers around the world and they've
been hard at work at building something awesome for nearly 19 years because they saw the trajectory
of Linux almost 20 years ago. I can relate to that. And it's that passion that they've
built this business on top of. And if you like to build these systems up from the ground
yourself, or have the option to deploy one of their many one click stacks, Linode has
excellent options for you. And the thing I can say confidently is the performance is
incredible. I just wouldn't put all of our J.B. audience facing stuff on Linode if it
wasn't the case. But it's not just me saying that. Stable Point listed Linode as the fastest
growing cloud provider and the best fit for low latency based use cases thanks to Linode's
high performing MVME storage. But you know this. It's not just the storage that makes
it low latency. It's the fact that they are their own ISP, that they've hyper optimized
their data centers and they know how to build these things efficiently. And they're always
cramming in the latest and greatest hardware, just smoothly and elegantly upgrading your
systems as you go. And they have a bunch of great back end features. S3 compatible object
storage is one of my absolute favorite cloud firewalls, DDoS protection, VLAN support,
Kubernetes support, including now the, you know, Ansible and Terraform too. I mean Kubernetes
is like the go to, but let's be real. Let's be real. I know a ton of people out there
using Ansible to manage their Linode systems. I mean maybe they're doing the whole stack.
I don't know. But I hear from the audience all the time. They're deploying stuff on Linode
using Ansible. And it makes sense. Pricing's 30 to 50% cheaper than other major cloud providers
out there that want to lock you into their esoteric hyperscaler platform. They've got
the best support in the business. Nobody can touch it because nobody's built their business
model like Linode has. So if you run into any trouble getting set up, Linode comes with
amazing 24 seven customer support phone ticket. They'll answer the phone and a human's going
to help you. Linode is dedicated to offering the best in virtualized cloud computing. If
it runs on Linux, it'll run on Linode. So go try it today. Learn for yourself. Take
advantage of that hundred dollar offer and support the show. You can do it all by going
to linode.com slash unplugged. That's linode.com slash unplugged.
It's that time of year again. We've got ourselves a new Linux Mint LTS 21 Vanessa. And you know
with impeccable timing, we also got a relevant bit of feedback. A boost from Tim Apple. 2,222
sets. New Mint is out. It rarely gets love from any of the Linux podcasts. It'd be great
to get you guys to live with it for a week or maybe just make Wes do it. That's my favorite
part of the email or the boost. Dang it. I mean, I love you Tim Apple, but throw me right
under that bus. Yeah, I think, you know, he wants to, he wants to hear your thoughts.
So could Mint be on a minimum viable machine? Is it the right distribution for that? There's
a lot of choices. And I think for the purposes of these types of machines that we're going
to be talking about today, we should just stick with the cinnamon flavor. I don't, you
know, cause there's a lot of ways you can go, but let's just talk about Mint cinnamon.
Are you, you boys okay with that? Agreed? Let's do it. So Linux Mint 21 is notable because
it's been rebased onto Ubuntu 2204 and it will be supported until 2027. So if you invest
now you get some, you get some use out of it. Yeah. And so this, I think if you're a
Mint user today might be worth listening to as well, but it also means if you're going
to buy a machine, you want it to last a few years, which was one of the requirements we
set this install will be good until 2027, which is about the lifetime we expect from
some of these budget machines. And so there is a lot of small improvements, but it's not
nothing super major to end users, but to the development team, I think some big stuff went
into this. It is really the release where Muffin, which is the compositor and window
manager for cinnamon saw a lot of, a lot of work. Muffin was originally based on Gnome's
Mutter 3.2 release. Gnome 3.2, which is like forever ago. Yeah. Well it's been forked for
like 11 years now. That's a long time to maintain something like that. Yes. And they completely
rebased it around the Gnome 3.36 code base now. So Muffin has been totally rejuvenized
and completely rebased. And as a result, I think you feel the performance throughout
Mint and there's a lot of nice little visual tweaks and improvements that are also taking
advantage of that newer code base. Linux Mint 21 also features improved Bluetooth handling.
They replaced the Blueberry subsystem with Blue Man. Their own Xapps have seen a lot
of improvements throughout this printing and scanning have gotten improvements. And then
there's just some general artwork and theming improvements because of the advantages they
got by updating Muffin. So there's a lot in this one. And I decided to try to get an idea,
try to get my head around how much horsepower does a fully up to date lived in it, you know,
for a little bit Mint install actually take. And I went through a process of loading up
on a couple of different systems and trying to get baseline ideas of how much resources
I should expect. I feel like this is kind of perfect timing too because you've been
tweaking yourself a real nice Gnome setup, right? And kind of just, you know, on the
other side of the fence now, checking out how Cinnamon's been doing. Yeah, I've been
really deep down the NixOS as my desktop using Gnome. And so this was a bit of a shift going
from NixOS to Mint. I mean, talk about two totally different approaches to Linux, right?
Dramatically, right? Because NixOS is essentially a rolling OS, totally super fresh. And you
just mentioned how Mint went 12 years without really updating the backend compositor to
their desktop, right? So it's a real different approach, but different strokes. There's some
people who just really like the Ubuntu base and they want a really solid workstation that
lasts for years. And you see stuff like with their improvements to the thumbnail support
where because they've kind of been, you know, just incrementally improving, there's some
areas like that where it can be really nice. Yeah, it's polished. And it's interesting
to me how you get this true sense of a classic Linux desktop. For those of us who remember,
there are elements of the Cinnamon desktop that strike this balance between Gnome and
Plasma and it brings in stuff that was in Gnome 2, which we used to call Gnome. It has
applets that you can just like right click and you can add a system monitor to the tray.
You know, these things that are just sort of used to come built into Gnome 2, but then
like Plasma, it'll also let you download new ones and install them. The UI is a little
rough. It could be better, you know, it'd be nice to have click and drag and stuff like
that, but it's fine. It really has like the, that feel of classic Linux, like even the
options, the ones that it makes like a drawer where you can have, you can stack more icons
in in your tray and old notes apps that are forked from maps I used to love back in the
day. I don't know if maybe this is only going to make sense to certain people, but if you're
a kid of the nineties, it's like when you get an old car of the nineties, it was a car
in transition, right? Maybe you've updated the stereo, so it's got like a newer stereo,
but it's got the old components of a nineties dash, but it's got some new modules in it
that like can play MP3s that didn't even exist when the car was built. You know what I'm
saying? Yeah, that's what the mint experiences to me and it's not necessarily bad. It's kind
of a nostalgic feeling. There's a sort of comfort to it and that like I know how to
operate that desktop already, you know, I'm familiar with the pair time and to be honest
with you, there's just things about it that are simpler in a lot, in a lot of ways. And
with this, you know, last couple of versions of mint, they've been doing a decent enough
job of integrating flat hub and flat packs, well not flat hub, but flat packs into mint
and they out now with software flat hub and they feel pretty much right at home on the
mint desktop. It's very much a fully loaded Linux. So I thought, Oh, it's going to be
too bloated for these low end PCs because they, you know, it comes with like streaming
TV app, the entire LibreOffice by default, you know, at least those things that I just
don't do anymore. But when I, when I put it to the test and I'm talking to like loading
it up, got it all up to date, got logged into my Firefox, you know, got my stuff the way
I like it, like trying to do some work, get some stuff done after about four hours of
average use. Now this is without electron apps, 1.6 gigabytes of RAM being used, just
1.6 gigs of RAM. That's impressive. Right. Not bad at all. My lowest end machine had
two gigs of RAM and the average is four gigs or above at everything I looked at. A lot
of them have eight gigs and 16 gigs. So using 1.6 gigs of RAM, you're going to get by with
that. You're going to be fine. 13 gigabytes of disk space used. Every machine I looked
at had at least 16 gigs. A lot of them had 128 or more. Right. So six, I'm sorry. So
13 gigabytes of disk space, and that includes the kitchen sink. It's pretty impressive.
And Cinnamon's performance, it holds up. It really holds up. I actually think Mint may
be one of the top contenders for a low end PC after doing my testing. I didn't really
know how it would turn out, but I was actually very impressed. I think I'd like to compare
it to other desktops. Like POP comes to mind. I'd like to see how POP compares. I did play
around with a really minimal configured Plasma desktop, but maybe it's just my usage. I
didn't get it that low on RAM and disk. It ended up being more RAM and more disk with
a Plasma desktop version. So I just, I was curious. I've kind of found Cinnamon decent
when I'm just casually playing some Steam games and stuff. I feel like I ended up fighting
with it less than I do with some other sort of setups where it doesn't understand my full
screen window or wants to steal focus back or just won't hide itself at the right time.
They've done a good job now too for years, but even more so now of integrating Timeshift,
the snapshot management tool. And they've taken it over now as the primary developers
of Timeshift. And because I like to be a jerk, I decided to install Mint with ButterFS. I
did the manual partitioning option and then did the ButterFS option just cause they thought
like, well, let's see what happens when I do this. Actually it didn't boot properly
on my dev one that I tested. I don't know if that was why, but then if I, if I use the
dev one, you know, built in BIOS boot menu and manually selected the UEFI file, it would
boot fine. Might've just been a dev one thing. Don't know. So I decided let's try it. And
when I loaded up Timeshift, like you'd expect, but it was really good to see. Timeshift goes,
Hey, you've got ButterFS. Would you like me to go with ButterFS mode instead of rsync
mode? And so it just starts working with ButterFS snapshots right then and there. Isn't that
amazing? It is. And then they've built in this backend process monitor to let you know,
kind of like when things are happening in the backend, like a Timeshift backup. So you
get kind of like this really subtle notification thing. Just, Hey, there's some backend stuff
happening here. Your machine might be running a little slow. Makes me feel kind of comfortable.
I know I've had Mint machines in the past deployed at like friends and families or that
kind of thing. And you know, I don't need it to be super rock solid necessarily, but
like just this extra layer of protection, peace of mind. Doesn't it feel like, and you
guys tell me if you disagree, but doesn't it feel like if your backs up against the
wall and you've got to recommend a Linux distro to somebody who's on a little bit lower end
hardware and you just want it to be one of those set it and forget it things because
you can't help them later. Mint feels like a pretty safe one to recommend. Like it feels
like you'd give that to a person that maybe isn't super technical. It seems like with
some of the Xapps with like having like a thought of like, Hey, you should probably
do some backups or have some tools for that. Like they're thinking of a more day to day
user than what I'm typically designing for or designing for myself.
But they've also managed to include some of the retro stuff that I as a long time hardcore
Linux user love, you know, like they've got like some of the stuff that made old Linux
desktops the best like screensavers.
You talking about X-Size?
Yeah, X-Size is in there. They've got X screensavers in there. They're not even for better for
worse, right? They're not even dicking around with Wayland, right? It's just, they're honest
about what they are. They are tried and true Linux and they've taken ideas that have worked
in the past and they've kept them integrated into their desktop instead of getting rid
of them.
And as a team, they've just opted to take on more and more work, more and more responsibility.
And a couple of years ago, I thought, well, this is only going to last for so long. They're
going to burn out. But here we two, three years later, they're still doing it.
It's like you almost said something there. What's like, you know, you kind of get out
of like the Linux hipster scene a bit with Mint. You know, they're not necessarily deploying
the coolest thing or, you know, kind of going to shame you about not yet having switched
to pipeline, but, but you get, you get a nice Linux experience still.
Yeah. You get a machine, you turn on and it works. And tomorrow when you turn it on, it's
going to work. And if it doesn't, you got time shift. That's appealing, right? It's
kind of, in a way they're going about a different way of solving what Nix is solving for me.
Okay. Well, you know, as you vary it, you put on various hats and you nebulous think
about what happens to a future studio. What about Cinnamon in the studio?
Yeah, I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I what's your hesitation. I like cinnamon.
I just like modern plasma and modern genome more, especially my current implementations.
My current implementation that I've set up both my plasma and my genome setups are so
freaking great. I've never been happier with desktop Linux ever. It's so for me, I it's
not that it's not great. It's just that it's not really my style. And, um, and you seem
to be having a little, um, you know, renaissance with the desktop on it. It seems like you're
kind of back in a mode of it. Oh, I will. I'm gonna spend a little time and like tweak
this and really make it something I want to see again. I am. Yeah, I'm going through a
tweaking phase and I love it because there's a real unquantifiable thing that I have struggled
for years to describe on this show. And I'm right in the middle of it right now. And it
drives me crazy that as a professional communicator, I cannot communicate what this is. But I've
just this weekend because I was going through the mint stuff and I was testing testing different
hardware and I wanted to compare plasma, cinnamon and genome. So this weekend I deployed NixOS
with plasma on the dev one. Oh, and it was good. But modern Linux. There's something
that genome shell is doing where it feels like it's all one OS and plasma feels like
a desktop window system on top of my Linux box. Like I can feel like there's the plasma
layer and then there's the Linux layer, which is good. In fact, I could even see why people
prefer that in some cases, right? Yeah. But when I when I'm using GNOME on modern Linux
with the latest like system, the latest kernel, latest Wayland, latest GNOME stack, latest
GTK, everything's totally like current. It feels like one cohesive OS like Mac OS does
or even FreeBSD does to a degree. But of course, FreeBSD doesn't once you get into the window
manager. But it's all just one smooth, slick experience that it just feels like everything's
communicating in a good way. And I just can't better. I can't describe it better than that.
But do you kind of get what I'm saying? And so I just don't get that with anything but
GNOME Shell right now.
Oh, that's fair. I mean, I think you have a particular sensitivity to some of the you
know, just how your desktop, the interactivity that you're presented with when you're sitting
at your computer trying to get work done. I wonder if that's would you say the same
in like in the studio environment or something else like that? I think it doesn't matter
as much there. Yeah. I think maybe you're talking about like your primary workstation.
Yeah. Yeah. So Cinnamon just didn't give me that feeling. And I don't know. I don't have
a great way to describe it, but I just don't get that kind of connection like I do where
it feels like and faster like with GNOME Shell. It feels like I'm closer to the metal. I don't
know why. Maybe because everything is running in Wayland and it's just super smooth right
now. But that's just my thing. And it wouldn't stop me from using it on a on a budget machine.
I think I think Cinnamon would do great on there. I'm curious, Brentley, I know you had
a chance to kind of take a look at I think you had a you know, a few thoughts. What was
your takeaway from the latest Mint and where you think it kind of fits in? Well, I have
quite a bit of history with Mint actually that I thought would be related to this these
topics and I think that's important to mention just before I get to my experience, my current
experience. So you mentioned low end hardware. I put Linux Mint on a piece of machinery,
I'll call it, for a friend who had an old laptop that was a four by three screen and
was a 32 bit, a machine that I couldn't buy a hard drive for to upgrade. So this thing
took an IDE, our drive was that old, but my friend was still using it and loved the thing
and said, hey, is there any way you can like it? It was running Windows. I don't know which
version, but it was extremely slow. So she said, hey, is there any way you can kind of
throw that fancy Linux thing you use on here and make it maybe last another year or two?
And the hard drive is starting to present some issues. So I ended up somehow she was
OK with this, but we strapped like duct taped literally an external hard drive to this thing.
But it was an SSD, right? OK, it was USB, like probably one, but it still ran better
than Windows was from the failing IDE hard drive that was in there. This was probably
Linux Mint. I think last time I updated on that machine is Linux Mint 19 at the time.
And it just ran forever and it ran great. And she's not technical, but she just loved
the thing so much that when she bought a new machine that she said, no, no, get rid of
this Windows thing. I want Linux Mint on there again. And I suggested other things. She's
like, nope, I love that thing. So there's there's something to that like stability and
it doesn't change very often. But when it does is just to like tweak a few little things
to make them more stable even. You know, and so I think there's something really nice to
that. And for years at about the same time I ran Linux Mint on my ThinkPad X220. And
last episode I recommended that as the low end piece hardware that I thought was was
worth looking at. And back then it ran beautifully. I don't see why it wouldn't run just as beautifully
now. You have or have not ran Mint on that box on the X220. I have ran Mint. It was the
second choice that I put on there. The first choice was XFC, which I ran I think for a
year. Oh, I let's call it an upgrade upgraded to Mint. And I loved it for I think about
two years. I just love that thing. It was a bit more problematic back then. Wes, you
and I were talking about how there used to be a I think it was a right click menu or
something for Mint back then that would re reinitialize Cinnamon. Oh, sure. Right. You
could just restart that. Restart that real quick. Cinnamon was let's call it fresh back
then. Good news. Good news, gentlemen. You can actually still find that applet. If you
go add applets, you can still find it and add it back. It just isn't default. Yeah, it's
still there. I like that. I like that as like a nervous tick. You know, you type L.S. in
the terminal and you just hit and refresh. Well, you know, now in the Wayland world looking
back and thinking, wow, I could just restart the desktop and all my applications aren't
affected and my whole desktop remains. That's actually a pretty nice feature. This X thing
is neat. It's got some cool stuff in it. So I would say that's like my background with
Linux Mint, sort of a love relationship that slowly faded. And then I moved on to other
other things. So it wasn't meant it was you and you just had outgrown it. It's not you.
It's me. Yeah. And I don't mean to make it sound like, you know, if you're using Mint,
you're not a pro user, because I think the point the point we're trying to hit here is
it's it's it's absolutely a totally usable workstation. And it probably scales very well
on high end hardware as well, I would imagine. And what's really impressive about Mint for
me is two things that come to mind right away is one, the users that use it really love
it. And you see that in forums, you see that on Reddit, you see that all over the place.
Some people really love it. And I can see why and I used to be one. The other thing
I noticed is that the Linux Mint project gets a lot of donations, like a surprising amount
of donations. If you if you browse to their website, they they kindly list them all I
think on a monthly, monthly sort of routine. And it's very impressive how many donations
they get on a monthly basis. And I think that's a testament to how much they matter for some
people. I like this woodcarver over in our matrix room. Linux Mint is super boring. That's
why it's been my daily driver for the last five years. Absolutely rock solid. See what
I mean? Yeah. I don't know, Alex, have you looked at it before? Have you tried Linux
Mint before? Yeah, I did. It's been it's been a long time. And I think I agree generally
with your assessments here that Linux Mint really is the appliance of desktop Linux.
You can just set it up and forget it and just expect it to continue working for a long time.
And that's really an accolade in this day and age. I think one of the reasons I like
recommending it to for a budget Linux machine is not just because it's only for low end
hardware, but because you can recommend it to somebody and it's a full fledged Ubuntu
based Linux. It is not a watered down like tiny distro that has some esoteric crazy little
tiny desktop. It is like a proven track record team behind this desktop environment who has
been producing and like Brent touched on, clearly as a community that is supporting
it that sees a lot of value and it's their contributing value back to the Mint project
and it seems to be working for them. Okay, maybe this is an awkward question, but where
does Ubuntu MATE or something like that fit into this picture?
Right, MATE I think is the other question. I also could see the argument for an XFCE
desktop if it's maybe set up kind of more like in a Windows style. I don't know. That's
a good question.
I think they both fill a very similar space, don't they? And much like the old Steve Jobs
adage, one doesn't have to lose for the other one to win. They can both coexist. They feel
different niches maybe, but...
I agree.
Chris, you asked about my experience with modern Mint and I think it's much like yours.
Comparing to the Mint of yesteryear that I was used to, I just thought it looked super
familiar. I jumped in there and I felt right at home in a nostalgic kind of way and it
was really easy to understand where everything still was because it hadn't really changed.
I mean, there were some neat options that you mentioned with styling that was presented
in the welcome screen that I really appreciated, like highlight color that you could choose,
like little things that I think are nice touches but not too involved. You don't have to get
in there and really know what you're doing. So that felt like a really nice experience
and I thought it just felt super polished. I was really impressed.
See, that's saying something. I'm curious because I mean, you're our head of QA. I mean,
have you managed to break it in any odd ways yet?
I did try to install encryption through the installer because I feel like I've caught
a few distributions, not maybe test that enough, shall we say, that presents some weird like
edge cases, but I haven't found any bugs yet. And I will try a little harder, but I thought
that was, you know, that's something.
You didn't find any bugs. I don't believe it.
I can't either.
I was out late drinking last night, so there's that. But yeah, I thought it was really polished
and I was really impressed and I was surprised that that was my take. So there you go.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux. Go there to get started with a free trial for yourself, your
team or an enterprise. That's Bitwarden.com slash Linux. Bitwarden, quite simply, is the
easiest and the best way for you or a business to store, share and sync your sensitive data.
And Bitwarden is fully customizable. You can use it with your enterprise policies. You
can start on your machine. They've got a Flatpak available. It's, of course, available for
mobile operating systems. And the beauty is Bitwarden is open source, so you can trust
it and it is already trusted by millions of individuals and teams and organizations in
their community. It's what Wes and I use to manage our passwords. It's how we also manage
our two factor codes and other sensitive data like recovery keys for certain applications
and whatnot. It's awesome if you're a matrix user and you want to get a recovery key in
there, just save it right in there with your login information. And Bitwarden has slick
account switching support, so you can jump between a work account, you can jump between
your personal account or maybe the free software project you're working on. And things over
Bitwarden are always improving. In fact, rolling out this week is SCIM support. Yeah, that's
I call it SCIM. Maybe it's pronounced S-C-I-M, but you enterprise folks, you know what a
big deal this is. And it's becoming available this week for Bitwarden to make it easier
than ever to provision and manage users. Bitwarden just made your life so much simpler in the
enterprise. And for all of us out there, that new username generator continues to be a real
winner. Why not have a unique username and a unique password for every site and service
that you sign up for? Maybe you already know about how important it is to have a great
password manager, but does everyone in your family, to your friends, is your business,
your place of work, are they covered here? Are they using the right tool for the job?
Maybe this is an opportunity to try it out for yourself or your business and support
the show. You can do all of that by going to bitwarden.com slash Linux. Go check out
the brand new features rolling out to Bitwarden this week. Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
As always, we got some amazing boosts and feedback into our email. Thank you everyone
for that. Chris and I did touch on, I think what was a little bit of a delicate topic.
So if you feel maybe a little rubbed the wrong way by the boosts, well, we hate crypto too,
it turns out. And we discussed that a little bit more in Office Hours 9. And we just want
you to know that you're still with us. We hear you. Yeah. And we have a rationale. And
we explain it. OfficeHours.hair slash 9. Well, hey, speaking of boosts, Noob Steve
boosted in with 2,222 sets. I'm a duck. D-U-K duck. Loaded with talent. Couldn't boost Coder
without boosting love. Aw, thanks Noob Steve. Wish I could get to one of those meetups,
but hashtag gas for Brent. Gas for Brent. That is great Steve. And I'm happy to report
we were starting to actually get some like details down in terms of dates on when Brent's
going to make it here before the road trip and all that kind of stuff. So it is happening
and your boosts are going to put gas in that tank. So we really, really appreciate that.
And you can't have him. He's mine. And you're going to keep him forever. I understand. Ah,
that's why you got that brand. We're going to, we're going to have to mount a Brent rescue
operation West. We'll break into the middle of the night. Come on Brent, you're coming
with us. And coordinate it all on Matrix. Right, right, right. There you go. Oh, oh
gosh. It's, it's a double duck day from Parrish potato. Honestly, if you find a used laptop
with at least eight gigs of RAM, you'd be able to do a decent amount of quote, regular
computer stuff. I've been playing Skyrim on a laptop I bought for 200 at work between
calls and it works just fine. Hey, that's great. I mean, Skyrim is not the most modern
game, but if that's the one you want to play, that's all that matters. Exactly. The golden
dragon boosts in with 1024 sets. B O O S T. Coming hot with the boost. Coming in hot with
the boost. Back in the day when wifi didn't work, I use Kumbantu and had to go right back
to windows. Ouch. Yeah. Then I tried again here in the last three years and it's been
a dream. Sometimes Linux is hard to love, but that tough love forces you to learn new
skills and you appreciate computing that much more. You do learn more. There is something
to that. And sometimes it's an angry learning. You're all, you're like, this is not what
I wanted to be learning right now, but you still learn. You know, here's my thought.
You want anything? Here's what I think. Wes, you want anything? I think I'm going to find
out either way. All right, Wes, I'll tell you what I think. I think it's not necessarily
a bad thing that it's the hard way to learn. I think you need that. You know, it's good
to have that option. There's easy ways to, you can't always take the easy path. That's
right. That's good. Mic Mac boosts in with, oh, oh, hey, double 1024. It's 2048 sets.
Would love to get your guys take on manage IQ. That's manage IQ.org as I'm looking for
an open source single management pain for my local compute management as well as my
cloud formation templates for both my home lab, which is a micro. Okay. It's on a three
node Raspberry Pi four cluster. And then he, he blames you for that, Chris. Okay. I am
aware of terraform. However, I've been hesitant to jump into that world. Thoughts, suggestions.
Thanks for all the content. So it's manage IQ.org for this site. And this, okay, so this
does have one kind of thing that appeals to me right off the bat. And that is you kind
of use one tool and you're spinning images for your box at home. You're spinning, you're
spinning Docker containers. You're spinning public cloud images. I see a lot of different
platforms on here, VMware, Ansible tower Foreman, of course, Kubernetes. Yeah. I've never tried
this though. I wonder, I wonder if our dear Mr. Alex has thought, yeah, I thought that
was my first thought too. So I wonder what Alex thinks of this. So manage IQ is the upstream
version of a red hat project called cloud forms. And I was sent on a training course
to learn cloud forms as a consultant four or five years ago now. And I spent the entire
week with my head in my hands. I know who pays my wages and I should probably choose
my words carefully, but I think it's terrible. I hate it because it's for me, I like infrastructure
as code and cloud forms was everything the other direction. Everything in the interface
was click, click, click. You know, if you like gooey's manage IQ is for you, but for
me, it's just not the right tool for the job. And you mentioned Terraform in your question.
And I just think you've got the answer there already. Like the infrastructure as code tooling
is there, it's mature. If you combine it with some of the continuous integration tools that
are now available as well, you can do a lot of the clever stuff that manage IQ purports
to be able to do yourself and not be tied into a specific development cycle of a product.
That is great insight, Alex. You know, I have to channel the Nix nerds matrix room right
now just for a moment. And I didn't see that coming at all. They would say check out Nix
OS generators, one config, multiple output formats. Boys, I installed this last night.
It is so fricking cool. So you installed super easy on Nix and then you have this Nix OS
generator command and then you tell it what image based on your config on that local box
that you want. You want an Amazon EC2 image. All right. Tell it that you want a Docker
image. Okay. Hyper V. Sure. No problem. You want just a regular ISO image. You can have
that to K exec. Yep. It's got K exec. It'll output all of that different stuff and more
Proxmox, OpenStack, just a raw file, VMware file, virtual box file, vagrant file. I mean,
it does everything. And what's so cool about it, you just go about setting up your config
like you would anyways. And once you get the box just the way you likes it, you run this,
it outputs your image and you can tell it for which public cloud you want or what, you
know, what format you want and it's done. It's easy. You sneaky over there and generating
a whole bunch of images. Well, I was trying to come up with a way to test and I thought
I really like this base and then I can add gnome or I can add plasma. And so that's just
what I did is I created a small little base that I could then just add the different desktop
environment on to do my testing. So it was kind of as close to the same machine as possible.
Plus you could generate your own nice little sort of like live Nix environment, but with
your setup there, you know, just keep it on, keep it on your little vent toy. I hadn't
even thought of that or a VM image even where I could. Oh, that's so cool, Wes. Great idea.
You know, if you stay tuned till next week, Chris is going to reveal that he's got his
own Nix based distribution that you can download in any format you'd like for no, no, no, no,
it's going to be Jupiter OS. We're going to come full circle from the start of the network.
We actually started the podcast network originally was actually a Linux based OS initiative called
Jupiter. I did not know this and it was, you know, don't call it a distro. It was a Linux
operating system. We were very Brian and I were really very insistent about that. And
you just like cat slash dev slash Linux action show. Yeah. Well, no, not yet, but we would
have built that in. I mean, come on. We would have definitely had our show automatically
subscribed on the desktop. Let's be honest when that's what happened is we started podcasting
and we realized, man, we're way better at podcasting than we are building a desktop.
And so we stopped and thankfully the elementary OS guys continued on. And so you got Jupiter
OS and all of that kind of stuff, which was inspired from some of that work that we did
early on. I'm just inspired. I'm not saying just inspired. And yeah, we did the podcast
thing. So it all worked out. So it would be full circle now for me to start publishing
my own OS. That would be, that would be kind of perfect. You just need to do JP coin next
and then you're all set. Oh, how else are you going to donate to get your eyes? Well,
you know, I'm a big crypto guy. I love crypto. So again, office hours nine, we, we address
this quite in depth. I like gene being boosted in again. Uh, 1000 sats package formats matter
because it's a pain in the butt to deal with all the variety because you can't just pick
one or two. Even when using gooey's like pop as an example, you can't install snaps or
things from homebrew via the package pop shop. Yet I want stuff from both so that everything
is installed from somewhere that checks for updates. Sadly, homebrew requires manual updating
unless you drop to cron. So this is in response to a topic I kind of just lamented last week,
which was why our package management and tooling and application still such a big deal. I mean,
I realized stuff never dies in the Linux community. We still debate system D as well. But today
as we record the number one post on our Linux with 725 up boats, 282 comments is canonical
should ditch snap, embrace flat pack and improve apt. And then of course you can probably imagine
how that discussion devolves nuanced. It is informed. Yes. You nailed it. West. It's so
annoying. Like why won't it die? It's funny too, because like, you know, at, at meetups,
just hanging out with like people. I know they use Linux. It does not organically come
up hardly at all. You don't fight over packaging. It's totally an internet fight thing, but
gene being is right in the sense that I think it does come up because it clearly is something
that matters to people. Gene being also wrote in for a double boost 7,000 sets. Oh, I combined
it cause he had a double send in there. So that is a, but that's a great, that's near
baller boost. That's close. Not quite though. Right? Close. They write again, the XPS change
you talked about sounds like how Lenovo does things where you can order many laptops with
Ubuntu pre-installed Dell also offers multiple latitude laptops with Ubuntu pre-installed,
at least if you go through a rep, I've just taken advantage of this at work for some special
use laptops with built in Intel broadband modems that work out of the box. Buying with
compatibility is different in Linux. You can't read a box or Amazon description to know if
it works with distro X. You can know that for a Mac or windows system. That's a fair
point. You do have a little bit easier time there. I can't argue that. I do have good
news though. Just looking at the Dell.com slash Linux page, it does look like they've
added the new XPS. At least I think it's hard to tell what the XPS these days, cause I think
they make both models available at the same time, the previous one and the current one,
but they have one labeled the new XPS 13 plus and it comes with a 12th gen Intel processor.
And I think this is it. And they just have three options, windows 11 home pro or Ubuntu
LTS. So I think maybe they were just updating the site and we had people sound the alarm
bells. I think it's okay. Next up we have gene being with a triple boost.
2674 sets. I think that might just be a double leet sets, right Chris?
Double leet.
They right. I love our clone for getting stuff out of other cloud services and into next
cloud with local disks, AKA not object storage behind next cloud. All the timestamps from
Dropbox and other places are preserved.
I kind of love the idea. Like maybe you're not a huge fan of the next cloud sinking client,
but you something great like our clone and just, you can still get, you know, benefits
of the next cloud experience, but just kind of take that part into yourself.
Yeah. I'm also going to give a plug for my pick last week that lets you do local encryption
before you upload it to the cloud. Might check that out too.
Yeah. Alex, I was for a bit of context here since you were probably flying or doing some
meetups or something in a different continent at the time. I was mentioning how you turned
me onto our clone and it's changed my life in a little tiny way. So thank you for that.
Very welcome.
Next, we have a great booster, Gene Bean for quad booze.
Not only did Gene Bean become the number one supporter for this episode with the amount
of boosting that he did, but I think, you know what boys, that's technically a baller
boost too.
Cause I'm a back home baller. If I want something, I just holler.
Gene Bean writes, I got a little excited sending boosts this episode, which is I think clearly
true to make myself feel better about sending so many questions and comments. Here's an
extra bit of leetness for Brent's gas tank.
Thank you, Gene Bean. Thank you for your support on this episode. That is, you are definitely
our top supporter this week. And also thank you everybody who participated in boosting
for Brent to get him down to the studio for some projects that we have. If we can ever
save them from Alex's house continued to boost in. We appreciate your support there. Also,
we recently were sending some splits to the open stats project, which has been contributed
to free software projects. That money has now been contributed several hundred dollars
there. So thank you everybody. Congratulations. And then also one of the things that's fantastic
about these stats that you boost in is we don't sell them.
We kind of consider them maybe as a long-term investment. So it's a way for you to give
us something at a small amount of value today that will continue to work for the network.
But instead of just sitting there, not doing anything, we actually put them to work. They
help us open up bigger channels and they helped me get Brent's node up and going with multiple
channels. And just recently, which is a big milestone for me, I was able to open a direct
channel to the fountain FM node, which is just a lot more efficient in terms of routing
and whatnot. So the boosts also are being put to work today to help us participate in
that peer-to-peer network even more. And it's just kind of a great way that we can actually
do something with those stats instead of just letting them sit there, which is also fine.
But you know, we don't got stuff. All right. We have a boost in from Prozac, a 1999 boost
for Brent's gas fund. And he says, I keep independent media alive. Go podcasting.
I think that should be my bumper sticker. And it feels like maybe I might need a bigger
gas tank pretty soon. Well, you got to drive back to Brent. Don't remind him. So listen,
we're doing something just as this is a new segment. And again, we talked about this more
in office hours, but we're going to start tightening the segment up just a little bit
to kind of keep the show moving. So we will be implementing a 1000 minimum sat to get
your boost read on the show. But we do read 100 percent of every boost that come in every
single one of them, which I actually can't make that claim for email just because the
volume difference. But we do want to keep things moving. So we will have a one K and
above limit for boost to be read on the show. But every now and then, since we read all
of them, we'll pull some forward. Crypto Kyle this week had one of those. He boosted with
five hundred stats. So just, you know, about half under the minimum. But I wanted to read
it anyways. He said, I picked up a Lenovo P50 for just under 400 dollars USD. Super
powerful with a built in M2000M GPU, a Xeon processor, actually pretty great power and
performance. And it runs NixOS great with ZFS on route with KD Plasma. That seems like
a nice choice for something like a workstation alternative. You don't need to be super portable
necessarily. But do you want to move it around? Those are nice machines. You got to figure
West with that Xeon CPU in there to probably do probably some virtualization loads. I mean,
I bet that thing works. I mean, I wouldn't bet it's the best battery life. But if that's
not your goal, I think that's fine. And then we got a bunch of thank you boost. Two hundred
and ten sats, six hundred sats, fifty sats, ten sats, six hundred sats from Ibuki, Resta
Casta Versta, Burji, User 64 1 and Authorities. You didn't get any of those right. But I know
I did not. I did not. I absolutely did not. Thank you, everyone. Also, who streams in
the sats in the background. We appreciate you. I just had you know, I'm trying to keep
it tight. I love trying to try to keep on moving. I'm doing my best, living my best
podcast life. But we really appreciate everybody that came in. And those of you who also just
stream them in the background. Thank you very much. Go get a new podcast app, new podcast
apps dot com. We love Fountain, Castamatic and Podverse are our favorites. And then the
nerds like to boost in with boost CLI. I don't know if we got to boost CLI. Did we get it?
I don't know if we did this week. But then you've got to change your podcast client.
Also Breeze, B-R-E-E-Z dot technology. And one day everyone's going to have this stuff
figured out and I won't have to sit here and I won't be the only one talking about this.
I do want to mention this is going to be on the longer side. But just to wrap this up,
when we started talking about boosts on this show, there were 4000 podcasts on the Lightning
Network. Now we are quickly approaching 8000. We've nearly doubled, not saying we did it,
but the amount of podcasts have nearly doubled on the Lightning Network since we started
talking about it here on the show. It's growing like crazy. So why not grab a new app and
try it out? Okay, I'm pretty proud of this pic this week, guys. You ever just need yourself
a little FTP? It's pretty hard to come by these days. I try not to admit it, but yeah.
The old file transfer protocol, it got the job done, Wes. It got the job done. But you
know, running FTP, that's for your dad and well, me actually back in the day. But now
you can do it quickly on your desktop with user mode FTP. And it's just a simple, clean
graphical app that you load up, you set things like the username, the password, the directory
you want to share, and which particular protocol FTP, FTPS, or SFTP that you want to use. Then
you click start, and you got yourself a little temporary FTP server on your box that you
can connect to to transfer apps, files, data, whatever. Super easy and quick.
This feels like a weird full circle thing where this is almost like an Android app that
would do this, you know, on your phone, just a quick little FTP server, but now it's a
desktop Linux. I mean, yeah, I think there are definitely apps like this for Android.
So I but this is for your desktop. And you know, this is kind of for me strikes the perfect
balance because I don't really need an FTP server anymore ever. And when I do, I don't
really want to set one up. But this is so easy. Why not? And nice to see for the folks
who may be your concern. They do have FTP S and SFTP. We'll have a link in the show
notes. I think I might just have a bonus pic that I found late last night. You want to
hear this one?
Bring on us. So I think good ever happens after midnight, dude. Well, it depends. It's
always after midnight somewhere. Right, Alex? Yes. What time is it? What day is it? Right
now? Actually, right.
As some or most of you may know, our new website is coming along really well. We would love
to get some testing there. So if you can go to Jupiter broadcasting dot net and try to
break it or think of some new features, that would be awesome. And there's a little GitHub
link there. And that brings me to this new app that I found. I was noticing because we
have so many great people who are contributing to the new website. It wasn't enough for me
to sit down multiple times a day at the computer and get all the notifications of commits and
issues and discussions and things like that. So I needed a mobile app. But as some of you
may know, I lean very heavily on after it. And I wanted to see if there were any open
source ways to interact with GitHub. And I found an amazing one that I think is worth
trying. It's called and Wes, I'll see if you've maybe used this before. It's called Octodroid.
The way I chose it was that it's extremely active on its own GitHub page. And it seems
like it's got some amazing features. So I'm brand new to it. But it has been working fabulously
for me at least in the last 12 hours. So I think people should check it out.
Hey, looks handy. I don't know that I need more notifications in my life. But if I did,
this seems nice. I love I love when it's on after it as well. You know, it's easy to get
and it's open source. Why not put a link to that in the notes as well. All them notes
over at Linux unplugged.com slash 470. Hello. Hello. Remember how we were just planning
episode 400? And that seemed like a lot of work. And now should we start fermenting something?
Yeah, we better. Yeah, we better start brewing now is what I'm saying. You know, who let's
worry about it after the road trip road trip first. Then we'll worry about episode 500.
I think we got a little time deal Linux unplugged.com slash JPL to get your name in that hat so
you can come hang out with us. Of course, we'll also meet down there near the JPL area
if you can make it a JPL. And we've got road stops, several of them, like four or five
of them along the way. And I'm always kind of putting my feelers out there and hearing
where you're all at. Today was kind of a sweet day, I have to say, because within 24 hours,
I heard from two long timers that have been listening since the very start of Linux action
show. And one of them I'm going to get to meet on the West Coast tour. But one of them
lives in the Midwest. But it was neat to get to connect on Matrix last night. That's lovely.
And talk to them. So, oh, man, you guys have really got me, Johnson, for the meetup. So
I'm looking forward to that. Meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting for all that. You can
also just connect with us every single Sunday. We do the show live on Sundays at noon, Pacific
three p.m. Eastern over at Jupiter Dot Tube. And we have an open mumble room. You can join
our virtual log, hang out with us. We like to chat during the show during the pre and
post show. It's a great way to kind of get kind of a taste of the meetup experience,
but from the comfort of your own home. So join us. We have it in your time at Jupiter
broadcasting dot com slash calendar. But of course, I know you all can't make it. See
you next week. Same bad time, same bad station. So, of course, we do have Linux unplugged
dot com slash subscribe. That way you can get the episode every single week when it
comes out like a do. We never miss a week. And of course, go grab Linux action news loaded
with deets. You didn't hear tons of things going on in the world of Linux and open source.
We cover it every single week. Linux action news dot com. As for us, well, that just about
wraps it up. You can find all of our resources over at Linux unplugged dot com and go check
out that new test website. Let us know what you think. Jupiter broadcasting dot net. Thank
you to our members who helped make the show possible in some plug core dot com. And we'll
see you right back here next week.
I enjoyed that I'd still like to get more submissions on budget PCs, so do feel free
to still send them into the show at the contact page or or however you likes. I think it's
still more we can get to. You know, we did get some some extras that I you know, we couldn't
squeeze into the show, but I thought it would be worth mentioning them quickly. Dave suggested
an HP MT 20 or MT 21 says my four below and suggestions those they are pro books that
were marketed as thin clients. So there's another thin clients recommendation. Hey,
I'm a pro. I want a pro book. Yeah, well under $100 on eBay, apparently. And one of the best
reasons to choose it was all of the different. My brain is fried all of the different plugs
and things like connectivity and ports. Thank you, Chris. Yes, thank, thank, thanks. Cool.
And so that's one. We also got a recommendation for a $400 refurbished horizon mini PC, which
sounds great. That's that'd be a great machine, right? ThinkPad T for 80s came in hot, which
I'm I'm leaning towards one on the desk behind you. Alex is going to sell his if you want
it. Well, it's red. It's red hot property. I might get in trouble if I did that. We know
the T for 80 is a solid machine, though. That's one that we've had direct experience with.
Yeah, Matt also has a Linux build from a bunch of parts for sub $300, which sounds pretty
sweet. If you want to do it yourself a little, I like it. Turns out if you try hard enough,
you can. And the last suggestion was a ThinkCenter M 91 P Tower PC. I'm not familiar with the
ThinkCenters as much, but I know that they have been certifying the more recent ThinkCenters
with Linux. That's a good sign. I mean, this one sounds pretty great. Actually, I 7 2600
with 16 gigs of RAM and an IPS display and apparently open Sousa. Oh, hey, IPS display
would be nice. You know, I have to say, we didn't talk about it this week, but we covered
it in Linux action news. I think the Lenovo situation was clocked wrong. It sounds like
they had a series of bad events that caused things to go slower than they want with their
Linux initiative last year. You can probably imagine some of its supply chain related.
Some of it was driver issues and other things. But we played the clips in land, but something
like 36 different Lenovo machines are being certified to run Linux this year. Can you
believe that? That's crazy. That seems like a good sign. It's episode 252. If you're curious,
I will put an extra plug. It was a great episode. I really enjoyed it over breakfast the other
day. So thank you to gentlemen. Oh, stop. Thank you. No, I can do that. It was a blush.
Well, you were already blushing because it's hot. But now you're blushing more. It's so