In celebration of Unix turning 50 today, we open with a special clip.
Back in 1969, a couple of computer scientists here at Bell Labs started to develop some
programs they needed for their own use.
What Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie started developing then has evolved into the Unix
operating system, which by now is widely used around the world.
We were trying to make computing as simple as possible.
In the late 1960s, Dennis Ritchie and I realized that the then current operating systems were
much too complex.
We attempted to reverse this trend by building a small, simple operating system on a minicomputer.
What we wanted to preserve was not just a good programming environment in which to do
programming, but a system around which a community could form, fellowship.
Hello friends and welcome into the Unplugged program.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Hello.
You know, we have something special planned for old 324.
Oh, we've been hard at work.
We have.
We've been having a lot of fun this week.
We wanted to put ZFS and Extended 4 to the test.
The promise of ZFS is pretty high.
Oh, yeah.
But is there a performance bottleneck for that data security?
What's this going to be like using it for real day to day?
Yeah, maybe you're on a laptop, you've got an SSD, but it's nothing super fancy.
In our case, this week, we used a Samsung Evo 850.
And we wanted to see how Extended 4 and ZFS performed against each other in both normal
conditions and lower memory conditions.
Maybe you've got a few electron apps running, you've got some tabs going, how then do things
perform?
And what kind of penalty do you take for that data security?
Or do you?
So we wanted to find out.
Plus, we've got some more thoughts on 1910.
And we've also been running Pop OS as just our daily driver, which has been pretty great.
We have some thoughts on that.
And I had a quick chat with Carl from System76 and have some good little insight nuggets
from him on things we can talk about, including that upgrade process.
Yeah, that sounds pretty smooth.
I want to talk about that too.
But before we get to that and the community news and all the other goodies, I got to say
hello to Cheese and Alex.
Hello, gentlemen.
Hey there.
Hello, internet.
Hello there.
And of course, a big time appropriate greetings to that mumble room.
Hello.
Howdy.
Happy Linux Tuesday.
We've got a chipper bunch today.
That's great.
Everybody's been properly caffeinated, at least I have been.
Now I have to also admit that I've got a CPAP machine now.
So not only am I sleeping, but I'm also still caffeinating.
So you better watch out, Wes.
Superpower of regular sleep.
Well, we have some community news that I wanted to start with.
Besides the fact that Unix turned 50, they actually, it's a funny thing, I have some
links in the show notes, they celebrated over like a two day period.
So I think it was either yesterday and today or today and tomorrow.
But it's technically the 50th anniversary of Unix.
And I have a really great clip that when I was playing as part of a longer series.
And I linked that in the show notes.
So if you guys want to watch that, it's so great.
So great.
In fact, if I remember, I'll play part of a training video that they did.
Some of these old clips are hilarious.
But also, I mean, it's shocking both how far we've come in 50 years and also how much is
pretty much the same.
Yeah.
It's kind of shocking how far we've come in 15 years.
This is a really great interview with Matthew Miller over at Tech Republic about Fedora
at 15 years old.
Wow.
It doesn't feel like it.
Considering I was using Red Hat before Fedora as my desktop.
Kind of it really does.
It kind of it shocks me.
It's really it's something.
It's been a long time, but it doesn't feel that long anyways.
Good interview.
We'll leave it to you to read most of it.
But there's a couple of tidbits in here that I wanted to chat about with you guys.
Throughout the process, he asked a series of questions.
He being James Sanders, sorry, over at Tech Republic.
And one of the topics that comes up is flat packs and snaps.
And he asked why Fedora prefers flat packs as the portable application standard.
And Matthew responds, there are definitely some technical differences.
If you talk to our engineers who are working on this, they're very, very passionate about
the technical differences.
One of the things with snap is it's the answer to all things.
We see OCI docker containers as having won the server enterprise and IoT use cases.
Docker doesn't necessarily fit well for the desktop.
So flat pack is a technology specifically meant for the desktop.
I mean, it shows right?
We talk about that property of flat pack all the time.
It does put a different spin on it.
I kind of thought of it always as like a limitation.
You know, I kind of mix command line and gooey apps.
So this was weird.
That does make some sense, though.
I don't think I have heard that as clearly just enunciated like it's, it's just simply
not trying to address that I like you saw it more as an oversight as a lack of like
something.
Wait a minute, you know, Wes, now that I think about it, I think I've even seen developer
statements to the extent saying they were planning to add server support, like that
was something they were going to build in later on.
I'm pretty sure I've read those statements.
Perhaps things have changed because I also tend to agree with this, as I've been getting
pretty excited about self hosting, and been spinning up more and more of my own infrastructure.
I've had the option for a couple of them to use snaps.
But the reality is it's containers all the way down, baby.
Yeah, and mostly advice and workflows and styles of doing so well, it's built around
the container ecosystem.
And that ecosystem has come a long way in having cross compatibility on its own.
I'm glad to hear that, Chris, by the way.
I bet you are.
I mean, you know, the thing is, is, you know, this very well.
It's just that containers just kind of came in and became a default way for people to
ship software on servers.
Absolutely right.
For better or for worse, in some cases, perhaps, but we're not here really to debate that today.
There's a part in this interview that he touches on about improvements that have come along
or innovations, as the article puts it.
And I was just waxing about this on the live stream about how this has really changed the
game for me.
Yeah, right.
It is something if you think about it, it makes sense.
And Matthew Miller's answer is interesting.
I think it's when the graphics driver people decided to go with open source, Intel buying
in first on the network drivers, and then on the graphics drivers was huge.
Now AMD coming along, I have an AMD desktop that I use for gaming.
It's awesome how it just works without having to fiddle with anything.
I love that.
There's also obviously a subtext of, come on, NVIDIA, get with the program.
I am blown away on my desktop workstation upstairs.
I've got full 3D acceleration, and I'm playing nice games, and I'm using zero proprietary
drivers, no binary driver for my video card.
It's so great.
And then, of course, the Intel side has been like that for quite a while.
Right.
Not for granted, but over the 15 years, that's definitely changed, and I wouldn't want to
go back.
Tech Republic also touches on a spot that seems to have really left a mark on the project.
This was a while ago in 2011, I think before Matthew Miller was even involved with the
project.
There was a shock to the ecosystem when Fedora 15 landed.
Fedora 15 was the version that shipped Gnome Shell for the first time, Gnome Shell 3.0.
At the same time, System D.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
What?
Miller says the release had an incredibly dramatic amount of change.
Both Gnome Shell 3.0 and System D. landed in that release, and basically, we lost half
our users doing that.
Or at least, put another way, half of them did not upgrade to Fedora 14, and they stopped
growing.
They say it was a pretty bad situation, and that there were plenty of ways that blame
was getting thrown around, but just absorbing all of that change all at once is really hard
on people.
But what they learned, if you look at the Gnome user interface, is if you go back and
install Gnome 3.0 and compare it to 3.3.2, it's a very different experience.
Yeah.
I mean, he's totally right.
I don't think about it that way, but it is.
Oh, it is radically different.
It was a totally, it was almost a different vision now.
He says in here, I think that if Gnome Shell goes to 4.0, it's not going to be a radical
redesign like that.
It's going to be architectural shifts under the hood.
That makes sense, right?
I mean, we need to move, and yes, Fedora moves quickly, but at the end of the day, I still
want it to work.
15 years old.
Are you kidding me?
Here's to the next 15, huh?
No kidding.
I'd love to know a little more, Chris, what you mean when you say that version three is
such a huge departure from 3.3.2.
Oh, boy.
Well, first of all, it's a huge, there's a lot of UI differences.
It's very, very big, like big.
It's big.
Everything's big.
Everything's touch focused.
Huge.
It looks like a maniac.
Crashes like Richard Hammond, just frequently and big, and also is very, very, very early.
It's very rough.
Let's just say a clunky doesn't feel well put together yet.
Go look at a screenshot of it.
It's really, it's remarkable, and if you remember back then too, touchscreens were really becoming
a big thing.
The iPad was a new product, the PC was a truck, and iPads were a car, and everybody was going
to be on a car.
What date was name three released?
I don't know.
I mean, it was a long time ago.
I'll look it up.
Kind of, you know, I think I recall where I was when I heard about it.
There's a few major moments.
I remember where I was when Unity was announced.
I remember where I was when it was announced that Unity was ending.
I was at Linux Fest Northwest when it was announced in a room with Brian, and we were
about to do Alas.
And I was at Dell when they announced that it was ending with Noah in a room with the
Sputnik team who also learned about it at the same time, and it was really something.
So name three was April 2011, so it's a different world in terms of mobile and everything else,
you know?
Absolutely.
Well, speaking of interviews, just a quick plug for me.
I was interviewed by opensource.com, Mr. Don Watkins, a gentleman over there who I've met
in Denver.
Really nice guy.
Yeah, we met him over at System76.
Look at you with the memory.
Just dang, West is on fire today.
And it's a Jupiter Broadcasting origin story and sort of like the future where we're going
under the wing of Linux Academy.
And it published a couple of weeks ago.
I just have not been good about mentioning it because I was traveling.
It's worth a read, though.
I mean, it's not too long.
Oh, stop.
I even learned some things.
You did?
Oh, yeah.
Really?
Yeah.
I mean, there's a lot of stuff in kind of the longer term history that I just didn't
know.
Early days stuff.
Sure, yeah.
We'll put a link in the show notes if people are interested.
I think, you know, that kind of stuff to me, it's like I'm so focused on what we're working
on now that I actually kind of forget every now and then to look back at how far things
have come.
And it really is pretty remarkable.
It's pretty, like I was just saying to West, it's like, you know, it's really, there's
a lot that has changed.
And in such a way that I'm really proud of, it's really been for the benefit of us taking
our craft more seriously and trying to do a better job and trying to do better reporting
and doing research and contacting sources, all these things, staffing editors, it's been
pretty awesome.
It's just enabling us to do a better job of doing this.
It's been iterative.
If you've been a listener for a while, you can really hear an iterative trend.
And that's another nice way of saying our old stuff is really crappy.
I mean, you tell me if the whole clip, oh boy.
It's bad.
We just cringe.
All right.
Well, we got a little interesting valve news in the show.
It's been a while.
Did you hear about Steam Remote Play?
It is a new Steam feature that lets you play on your couch or on your computer with your
friends over the internet.
With Remote Play together, they say, you can now invite Steam friends to join your local
co-op or your local multiplayer with a shared or split screen game.
Yeah.
Only the host needs to own and install the game.
The additional players just connect through Steam Remote Play.
It's kind of neat because it just kind of shows up as a menu entry item.
If everybody supports it, it's just a little button and the menu says Remote Play together.
It's really easy.
Yeah.
And then like all your friends, their controllers just act like they are right there on your
computer.
And then you've got a little menu.
You can control voice and volume and hear everybody.
This is some magic.
It sounds so easy.
And they right here say just some words on the screen.
Supports Linux.
It's going to be good.
I mean, you know, they've done a lot of work on the streaming stuff in the back end.
I remember playing with it, I don't know, four or five years ago now.
And I haven't heard about it since.
Obviously it still works.
So it's nice to see a new development.
I have to tell you, man.
I had a Valve developer in my ear like two years ago telling me we're doing big things
with streaming.
Just wait.
And I was like, great.
Oh, I'm super excited.
And then never heard anything and never saw anything.
I was like, oh, that project must have been killed.
I think this is this is what it was.
Skunkworks.
It was in the Skunkworks for quite a while.
And sometimes this stuff takes a little while to suss out, especially when you're supporting
Windows, Mac and Linux.
I mean, and over the network, that's always a little bit tricky.
Well, I'm curious how it's doing the device stuff.
Like how is it taking my like, say I got a controller over USB or Bluetooth hooked up
to my Linux box.
Is Steam just taking those inputs and then forwarding it to the remote?
Is it just like raw throwing it over the network?
Is there something more sophisticated in the middle?
The other thing that's fascinating about this, as you think about it, is they're now first
to streaming.
They beat Stadia and they beat the Xbox.
I mean, does this count?
It is only in beta.
They're at least right.
They're up there.
I'll tell you what I like about it is without a shadow of a doubt, it's going to have the
best game catalog.
The thing I'm thinking about Stadia is I'm going to get my Stadia package in like late
November and it's going to show up and I'm going to be able to play two games that are
even worth it.
I hope you like them.
Yeah.
Whereas this could be any game I've ever owned in Steam and the fact that you can do local
player stuff.
So that opens up to a whole range of games and you're not having to futz with firewall
stuff or anything.
So got to give this a go.
I'm going to try it.
You know, I haven't really needed or needed to do this, had an opportunity, but it's something
I'd be worth it.
You know, the whole Steam Machine thing.
It's funny.
Now it's almost a perfect time.
I kind of want just a little Steam Machine set up next to my TV now.
Oh yeah.
Steam Machines.
That was a thing for a little bit.
Oh, you know, you know what you always say, Wes, and you always say this.
It turns out if you try hard enough, you can.
But sometimes not.
Yeah.
Hey, why don't we just take a moment and mention that the Gnome Foundation is full on fighting
this patent troll that is coming after them for this Shotwell photo transfer feature.
Yeah, they're bringing it.
It's nice to see.
It is really nice to see.
And in that effort, they are attempting to raise some funds.
So so far they've done pretty good.
They've got 108 donors and they have raised $28,000.
They have a goal of 125, but my instinct says they could probably use triple that amount
because it'd be really nice for them to be able to bring this fight.
So we're going to have a link in the show notes Linux Unplugged dot com slash three
to four.
If you can throw, you know, any amount at them.
They have some one times that are just click one buttons.
They have some monthlies you can do.
It looks like it's a really nice, clean, simple, not going to have to like sign up with a whole
bunch of accounts crap to do it.
And it would definitely be a good cause because even if you're not a Gnome Shell user, this
patent fight is really important because if they can come well, I guess another way to
put this is Shotwell is damn lucky they're part of the Gnome Foundation.
If they were an open source independent project that wasn't part of a foundation like this,
they would be royally screwed right now.
So it's important that even if you're not a Gnome Shell user, that we help them fight
this crap.
Right.
I mean, we want to send this tone that you don't you don't get to be abusive and trolling
these open free and open source projects.
You know, it gets me worked up and I'm already over caffeinated with and you know what happens
when I get worked up as I start renting.
Let me get the soapbox.
Yeah.
Yeah, we left it outside.
It's been a little while since we got up on the soapbox.
You never know.
It could be just around the corner, though.
You can never tell with that soapbox.
It's sometimes it's sometimes lurking.
Well, you're right.
It was very easy.
I've just made a donation now.
Really?
Once I got past identifying the cars in the capture, of course.
Oh, yeah.
You got to make sure you find the cars.
Or buses.
Somebody's got to train that machine.
Let's do a little housekeeping.
Oh, so we went down to Texas, went to a cyber summit, and you may be wondering how that
went.
Well, my friends, I've got just the thing for you.
Elle, Wes, Cheese, and myself did an extra on our trip to Texas Cyber Summit extras dot
show slash 24.
Nice little wrap up of not just what it's like for some Linux people to go to a cyber
summit, but also good details on the great food that Carl took us to.
Oh, boy.
So don't listen if you're hungry.
I can't help it.
You know, I just got Carl, you might want to listen to that.
I think you get name dropped a couple of times in that one.
And also, to go along with that, Elle wrote up a fantastic write up wrote up write up
blogged blog post.
Don't call it a blog.
It's an article.
Article post that will link in the show notes.
It has some descriptions, some pictures, some some of the characters I was talking about
in that extra.
And then if you want even more than that, cheese is popping off like crazy in that Jupiter
gallery.
Jupiter.
So good.
Dot gallery.
How about that?
Jupiter dot gallery.
Chris, what's this?
You say you say, well, here we go out to these things like these Linux fests.
Or maybe you heard about Alex and I taking a road trip to go see Wendell recently or
Texas Linux Fest or Red Hat Summit or Linux Fest Northwest and you wonder, are there any
pictures from this event?
Well, friends, cheese bacon has the answer for you.
That's right.
And if you have any pictures from these events that you'd like to submit, you can do so by
emailing me at cheese at Jupiter broadcasting dot com and that's CHZ at Jupiter broadcasting
dot com and I'll be happy to put them on the gallery.
That's the best part is as that happens, when I go back and check, there's like more pictures.
There's new stuff.
I haven't seen.
Yeah.
Jupiter dot gallery.
What else do I got to say?
We'll just keep updating that throughout the next year and stuff as we go to events and
whatnot.
Well, we'll have that up there and check out extras.
Extras dot show slash 24.
But not just that one.
For goodness sake, go over there and and look at the what is a container listen to the what
is a container episode.
It's just 20 19.
I mean, you don't want to be behind.
You don't.
And it's 24 minutes.
And Alex, you did a great job explaining this stuff.
You and I talk about how we use these in practical setups that are approachable by people that
are either beginners or using this in an enterprise because we you know, we've really we've talked
about these things a lot.
We've taken all of the experience we have talking about these and Alex talks about them
all day for his day job.
And we've put it into this episode.
So I think it's helpful for people.
And it's a great companion for the new self hosted show.
Check that out.
Extras dot show.
And also recently, some brunches just got posted.
So got to go get so many good brunches, especially that one there with Alan Jude mentioned that
last week.
You got to go get that Alan Jude brunch, you know, he's gonna be talking about BSD and
making your question your Linux faith.
You don't want to miss that.
And then come back to Linux on plug and we'll set you straight.
It's true, though.
All right.
That's the housekeeping for this week.
I mean, speaking of Linux, right?
Mm hmm.
Let's get into this 1910 in more detail.
There is a lot to talk about with this release, but we're gonna actually put some of it aside
and just wait for 2004.
And just focus on a few details for you this week that drew our attention.
And one that I know cheese and I have been talking about, and I think West you and I
talked about a little bit is I'm noticing more than I thought I would that there's a
lot of apps in the software center that are actually snaps.
It seems to be with the way it works is if there is a snap version of an application,
the software center prefers that and installs that first.
Now, maybe we should be clear.
How are you noticing this right because Oh, they clearly label it right.
But would you have noticed right?
Isn't that the test?
You know, is it detrimental if you're a regular user?
Do you care?
Because you're investigating, you know, we're doing a review here.
The only two ways in which I notice it is startup time.
And when I sometimes go to edit something on my local file system, it's like a couple
clicks.
Right.
There's the confinement comes into play.
Yeah.
And so there's a couple of instances where I'm like, well, the job of this application
is to be like all over my file system.
So I don't actually want the snap version.
And the way I've just worked around that is I just didn't go to the terminal, I apt install
and I got the debt.
Right.
But to your point, for the most part, no, not really actually an issue.
And in the case of VS code seems to have been a net benefit because it just like self updated
and got the latest VS code and it was good to go.
Right.
Yeah.
And it does seem like they've gotten better, you know, I mean, the, the, the theming, the
system integration, that stuff is a lot better than the last time I used these.
Yes.
That has been, that has gotten a lot better.
So cheese, you had a chance to not just only use stock 1910, but also Mate 1910 over the
week, trying out different systems.
And what was your extra week with 1910 like?
Overall it was great.
So I started with the beta, then the dailies, and then the final.
I tried it on three different machines.
I tried it on my desktop, which is a rise in 2600, 16 gigs of Ram, 256 gigabyte NVME
and an Nvidia 1060, an older Dell and Spearion and this new ThinkPad 440 S T 440 S that I've
recently picked up.
I will say that out of the box whenever I try to Ubuntu, I installed steam immediately
went to CSGO, dropped in and was playing some games, some deathmatch there in CSGO and I
was averaging around, you know, 200 frames per second, something like that.
What?
Yeah.
200 frames per second.
What do you normally get on that box?
Under windows, it was right around the same.
So I mean, there was really no difference.
It would peak up to like 230 frames a second, which was about average for what windows was
doing as well.
Oh, so this was your, uh, the last windows box, the gaming rig.
Yes.
So this was the gaming rig that I ditched.
Um, I had an extra NVME tossed in there and I ditched the SSD.
Are you telling me 1910 killed windows for you?
Uh, yeah.
I mean, I really, the desk, this desktop was only ever really used for gaming anyway.
So, um, I decided just to make that, make that jump.
I do have the fallback SSD if I want to toss it back in the box.
I physically removed it though, so it would take some effort.
You go take this victory lap, geez.
This is a big moment and Wes and I are proud of you.
Thank you guys.
God.
So good.
So it sounds like performance is comparable.
You haven't taken like a Linux tax for switching.
No, not at all.
And I was using the Nvidia, uh, which one thing that's awesome about 1910 is it comes
bundled with the Nvidia driver.
So I was using, um, the 435, uh, Nvidia driver, uh, worked great.
Um, whenever I flipped over to Monte though, I did notice a performance hit.
Uh, I was averaging about a hundred frames per second.
I'm not sure exactly what's going on there.
Again, this was just kind of out of the box testing.
I didn't do any additional stuff.
So you're saying you had a hundred frames per second switch that there must be something
there.
There that's gotta be a bug or comp is issue or something probably worth troubleshooting
or the fact that Linux and Nvidia aren't best friends could be a thing too.
I don't know.
So, um, I had some PI problems in my week with 1910.
I mean, we primarily, the rest of the episode, we're going to talk about the ZFS and extended
four and comparing that in low memory and regular memory.
But I just want to take a moment and say that they sneaky included support for the PI four
in 1910.
It was sneaky.
They did list it in their official, like a canonical.com.
Not much before.
Yeah.
So PI four supports not easy and it's something that distributions are slowly getting to.
There are architectural changes that are pretty significant.
I heard it described as the PI four is in appearance in similarity only to the previous
PI's like there's all, there's total differences for the USB stack for the, for the way that
the PCI bus is addressed for the video card.
Like there's just major changes.
Isn't it great that we don't have to care about that at all?
I mean, once it's fixed.
And if you're using Raspbian and you don't even think about it, they just did it.
Which yeah, that's the point of Raspbian, but they got, they got like the bulk of everything
in 1910 to their credit, which is great because people like to use that Raspberry PI's for
like Kubernetes training and things like that.
And I threw it on there and they spun two images, a 32 bit and a 64 bit.
As we record, although this is very rapidly in progress, the 64 bit image has an issue
where USB devices don't work.
And there's a couple other limitations of it.
It's an issue once you go over like three gigs of RAM ish, like 348 I think is the magical
number.
And the USB quits working.
And so if you use the 32 bit image, it's totally fine and no issues.
So you get to play around with 1910 on a Raspberry PI if you're okay with 32.
But you've been hoping to escape 32.
Come on, 32 bit, everybody knows it's going away.
I mean, you're using all the bits.
I will mention to the 64 bit and 32 bit images have SSH turned on by default.
So even if you can't use the USB to like plug in a keyboard, if you got the ethernet plugged
in, you can still SSH it.
Perfect.
They already have it in progress though.
I did a little, you know, I did my part in the bug report because I was a good boy this
time and went in there and said, here's my system information.
Here's my, you know, I can reproduce the bug.
And they seem to have identified the, all the issues and fixes are in progress right
now as we record.
So they'll probably, I don't know, maybe they'll spin a new image, I would hope.
Yeah, hopefully so.
Hopefully it just works in the future.
Yeah.
Now what about you?
How's your week been on 1910?
Any updates to your initial impressions last week?
Honestly, I mean, it's just been pretty smooth.
I had to, you know, make a few changes here, there.
There's an app armor was still enabled on this system, which I mean, I left it enabled,
but you know, I did some tweaks, got all my regular tooling working.
Really it's kind of just nice.
I mean, I've been enjoying neon and I do miss plasma sometimes there's little, little pieces
of my workflow that I just haven't really adapted over, but I have surprisingly few
complaints.
Like there's no weird oddities.
I haven't had any glitches.
There's been no surprising reboots or programs not working.
And I was doing a bunch of testing, sort of messing around with some of the bootloader
stuff and modifying the system.
It's just resilient.
My past experiences with gnome shell tell me that this may be subject to change, but
right now I haven't had any shell stability issues.
It's all been very solid, very reliable, and I'm very happy to report that I had a chance
to try out pop as well.
I think we all did.
Most of us.
Boy, did I see a lot of excitement online about this.
I wasn't even positive I was going to try it out, but then I was getting so much like,
Hey, Chris, you got to try this.
Hey, Chris, have you tried pop?
It's really good.
Yeah.
Talking about the release.
Yes.
So we did some digging into what, why are people so happy about this?
Like what's going on?
And there's a few things that I think a system 76 has done here, but the one that like a
lot of people were talking about on day one and two for obvious reasons was how buttery
smooth the upgrade process was from the previous version of pop.
And they appear to have done some custom engineering around this.
And so I emailed Carl, the CEO of system 76 and asked him, what have you guys done to
change the upgrade process?
And why is it, why is everybody saying it's so much better?
Carl wrote back and he said, the Ubuntu updates weren't well integrated into gnome and we
found that live upgrades while in the user session can be unreliable.
We also had no way to communicate the upgrade and changes to the user through the product.
Instead users learned about the available upgrades through news or social media or like
an email campaign or whatever.
Now customers receive a notification when there's a new OS upgrade and they click a
button to start the process.
The pop upgrade first prepares the system for upgrade, ensuring that all the required
dependencies and upgrades are in place and then downloads the new packages.
If there are conflicts, the upgrade is automatically rolled back.
The customer can go off and do other work while the upgrade is being prepared and downloaded.
They'll receive a second notification when the upgrade is ready to be installed.
The tracking upgrade prompts to reboot where the offline upgrade will then take place.
And with the pop upgrade, customers will be able to upgrade from an LTS to any release.
So for example, if you decide you don't want to be stuck on pop 1804 until 2004, you could
go to 1910.
You'll be able to jump directly from 1804 to 1910.
That's coming in early November.
So they've done some really interesting engineering there.
So I love some of the other things.
He says to him, the most striking change in 1910 is the new aesthetic.
The team, Kate himself, Ian, they started working together on a new color palette and
contrast.
He says they measured the contrast ratios between elements and text to achieve a high
contrast by default rather than requiring a separate theme.
He says the difference is noticeable throughout, but especially in the shell menus.
He's right about that.
He says, I love the new dark color palette.
It's incredible.
It's like candy, like a luxurious kind of candy.
I think they're very proud of it.
It does look very nice.
I mean, I enjoyed using it.
Yeah.
Also worth mentioning their work around Tensor Man.
I didn't really appreciate what a pain in the butt apparently TensorFlow is to set up.
I love this.
Packaging TensorFlow for Linux distributions is notoriously difficult, if not impossible.
That's the first line of the GitHub.
Yeah.
And I guess even like using the Docker container is still a huge pain in the butt.
You've got all kinds of different versions depending on quite what you're doing or how
you need TensorFlow configured.
And I mean, if you're running these just off the command line in Docker, it's not a lot
of fun.
So Tensor Man, which is a little Rust daemon, of course, it just sits there and makes this
easy for you and kind of orchestrates on top of Docker to get you all the stuff you need
and smooth out the process.
That's pretty great.
And it seems to me like they've keyed in on a good customer demo there because what do
they do?
They use powerful systems and like laptops and desktops that people buy to use TensorFlow.
Like that must be a decent customer base.
Right.
I mean, that could be pretty useful.
And if it just gets you out of the gate with the standard technology you want to use on
Linux faster, that's superb.
The thing that I have to acknowledge before we go any further is I was skeptical of PopOS.
In fact, I was pretty vocal about thinking it was a bad idea that they had limited resources
and it could be better spent in other places.
We're several releases in now, and thankfully I left myself a little bit of wiggle room
on this.
And I said, you know, if they add value and they make it something that's a true differentiator,
then I'll reconsider.
They've done that.
They've done that with the installer.
They've done that with the upgrade process.
They've done that with the theme.
It's truly one of the best themes on Linux.
And now they've done it.
There's a couple other things that are in there, like the pop shop that are really nice.
Like they've opted to keep Chromium as a deb.
They can make that choice as they do with their platform.
They've integrated their system firmware updater into no shell settings now, just built right
in.
You don't have to go find it.
And even on a non-System 76 machine, I appreciate that.
That's I think what has stood out to me is it hasn't felt like Pop was some walled off
garden, hidden away, totally different.
It is its own thing.
But a lot of the stuff you can still take, right?
If I want to use Tensor Man, I can just go get that from GitHub and use it.
Or if I want to use the theme, but not all of Pop OS, that's possible too.
I think Pop OS, because it's not tied to System 76's hardware, you get benefits by using
it as I experienced in my recent laptop review.
But you don't really have any downsides.
There's like not any negatives to it.
And it's not so derivative of Ubuntu that it's totally different.
Mint is kind of its own thing.
You can still skirt by by following some Ubuntu tutorials or getting a PPA and it's probably
going to be fine.
But with Pop, there's no like probably about it.
It's going to be fine.
It just works.
And it's 1910.
They want it to work.
Exactly.
So there's not a penalty really for using it.
There's an upside if you like their aesthetic and the value add that they've contributed.
And you're not running something that's so foreign that you can't just treat it like
an Ubuntu system.
Exactly.
So I really nailed a sweet spot.
And because of that, when I do one more reload for some testing upstairs, when I'm on my
final build for my daily driver workstation, I'm going with Pop 1910.
And the reason for me is I'm going to take Carl at his word about that upgrade system.
Because this is my got to get shit done workstation.
And I was after all of this going to just reload it back to an LTS.
I don't got time to play around on that thing.
When we reinstall all the other machines in the studio, you got to have one you know is
working.
Right.
And I honestly was not looking forward to it because the new gnome shell has kind of
broken me.
It's very fast.
It's very nice.
And I hate to go back to slower.
Cannot stand to downgrade.
And I was really hemming and hawing putting it off.
And this gives me an opportunity here.
I can I can get the latest and greatest and have a pretty solid chance it's going to upgrade
as smoothly as say a fedora system will.
I mean, I'm already looking forward to finding out how that goes.
So I'm going to put it on my main workstation upstairs.
Hooey Wes.
Here I go.
You know, my dad used to have a saying, I used to be indecisive, but now I'm not so
sure.
I think that applies to you in desktop environments.
You know, hey, if they keep making it better, I'm not going to ignore it.
I'm no fool.
I'm going to acknowledge it.
Plus, I mean, you'll already be set up for making all those deep fakes.
You know, that's my new hobby.
I'm going to set up a side hustle where I just do deep fakes for hire.
I probably should have said that on air.
Damn it.
Well, I can I can attest to pop us being pretty solid, man.
I mean, I've been using it since March.
The upgrade process was super.
I mean, it was just painless.
It did, in fact, pop up, say that there's a new version available.
So what I did there, it popped up, hey, oh, it did say there was a new version available.
It pulled everything down, asked me to reboot, you know, installed the update perfectly right
back into it.
The new contrast.
I mean, immediately, you know, I could notice a difference.
And it was overall a really great experience for me.
I'm installing this on an older 2015 MacBook Pro.
And I really I really have no reason to to go with another distro on that machine, because
very much like you, it's just the get shit done type machine, you know, and it works
great.
I really have no reason to move anywhere else on it.
It was almost good enough to give me to give up fedora on the ThinkPad.
I got close.
And what I ended up doing to compromise is I went through and just beautied up my fedora
install.
Oh, it does.
It does look pretty nice.
I got my dash to doc more dialed in.
I got my theme dialed in.
I went and got the pop theme.
You know, something to note here, too.
There is no ZFS on route in the installer for pop OS.
So let's talk about ZFS on route.
The promise is huge.
Eventually one day you have a file system that protects you from bit rot.
It can do incremental snapshots that are elegant.
You could potentially have boot environments, you could move data around, you could over
commit storage.
It integrates with container platforms.
I mean, it's it's truly worth all of the hype.
Right.
I mean, the advantages are clear.
Now, is it worth it on route, especially if maybe you don't have an MVD drive or maybe
you don't have 32 gigs of RAM?
Right.
Oftentimes we're thinking about, you know, big systems, maybe custom server builds that
you've designed to be running this file system with a lot of data.
The old myth was you can't use ZFS without ECC RAM.
Right.
And what about a laptop?
What about kind of not the newest laptop with run of the mill hardware?
Maybe you got a Samsung Evo in there, maybe you got 16 gigs of RAM and you got a few apps
you're using every single day and you don't have a bunch of available memory.
Is this still a good idea?
Genuinely did not know the answer to this question.
And now I'm feeling like we have figured it out.
So Wes and I, I'll give you I'll give you a little bit of basics.
So Wes and I took the Librem 15 with a Evo 850 drive, 512 gigabyte capacity and 16 gigabytes
of RAM.
And I think it's a Skylake processor and we installed Ubuntu 1910 fresh latest spun ISOs
and did one install with extended four and one install with ZFS on route.
Ran the same exact software setup, same exact steps, same exact benchmarks.
Then we did it all over again, but this time we robbed the system of RAM to create and
simulate a very exact amount on both of them.
We took out a chunk of RAM so both of them had to operate in a low memory environment.
And then we started a user session with a terminal and a web browser with some complicated,
but not overly complicated work in there that was reproducible in both environments.
Right.
You know, model something like maybe you're running a bunch of virtual machines or doing
other work or possibly just have a, you know, more low end computer available.
Right.
And so we did things like we threw some compile jobs at the hard disk.
We threw some SQL work, creating lots of little files, creating large files, creating small
files.
We did it with as much RAM as the system could eat and we did it in a more memory pressure
environment.
So we essentially operated the system as if we were using about 60 percent of that 16
gigs when we did the low memory test.
Because then the way we got to this number is we took several of our systems here in
the studio and we loaded them up with our daily driver applications.
Couple of electron apps, some cute apps, some GTK apps, a web browser, a couple of terminals,
you know, that kind of stuff.
And then we came to an average memory usage after they'd been running for a while and
determined, all right, this is what it costs us in memory to run our workstations.
And then we allocated that for this test and ate that up virtually by just slicing it off
from the kernel saying you can't have it and let it go.
And what we found in some ways really surprised the heck out of me.
It's the answer on the broad perspective is it depends on your workload.
Of course.
Of course it does.
But there's some areas where even in low memory situations, ZFS pulled ahead.
Not in all areas.
No, certainly not.
Because there's many categories where EXE4 is just going to be faster, it's doing less.
If you were to attribute performance failures in a high memory pressure environment, it
was actually extended for the demonstrated most of the variance.
Yeah, that's what kind of surprised us the most is even test where maybe it was already
slower or already faster, the change between having more memory available and it was like
nothing in ZFS.
I mean, you know, it got a little bit worse, but not much.
There was some degradation, but not much.
And then much more for EXE4.
Yeah, you got like an entirely different box in some benchmarks with extended for now in
some situations, extended for may have still performed better than ZFS.
I'll give you an example.
Say you're unzipping a project and you're assembling it and getting it ready to compile.
In that situation, in a low memory or a regular memory situation, extended for is simply faster.
ZFS, though, remains consistent.
And then once you begin to actually build the project, and this could be attributed
to how ZFS caches files, ZFS is actually significantly faster than extended for.
Yeah, you know, it was a pretty healthy competition here between what EXE4 was better at and what
ZFS.
Certainly not one sided in favor of EXE4.
No.
Michael Lerbal did some of his own benchmarks over at Phyronix, which we'll have linked.
On some higher end hardware.
Yeah, and our results are pretty consistent.
Now he also had a bunch of other more like server applications, stuff like various databases.
And of course, those were faster with EXE4.
And I mean, that's kind of expected.
I was just surprised how similar things were just in the everyday use case and how resilient
ZFS was to memory pressure.
It doesn't really make sense to me if I didn't have the data here.
And we will publish all of this.
And you can compare it to your own systems.
If you are familiar with how to use the Phyronix test suite, actually comparing your system
to our benchmark is one of the easiest things to do with the test suite.
If you're just curious to see how your system would perform.
So we'll publish all of our data with the charts in the show notes.
But by going with this, I have to say, I would advise you're perfectly fine using ZFS.
When you add the benefits.
Right.
Yes, you're probably going to need to be taking care of the benefits and things may still
change here and how Ubuntu is using it.
And one time we did run into a little snag where grub wasn't quite updating properly
after, you know, and that only happened on the ZFS side.
So totally worth doing.
It does seems like it's very usable day to day.
Be aware, you may need to learn a few things about ZFS administration.
That is a good red flag to bring up because I'm only talking about it from a performance
penalty standpoint, not yet from an implementation standpoint.
That's still in flux.
And it's, as they label, experimental.
And you need to consider it as such because ZFS won't protect you from like a total different
scheme of layout change that's incompatible with what you got set up.
Like there's just nothing that's going to or like we ran into grub not updating properly
when we were trying to do a couple of small little things to reduce memory and increase
pressure.
Thankfully, we were just going to reinstall anyway.
Yeah.
Yeah, true.
So I do want to make sure it's clear at this point in time as we record, we are talking
about performance and not necessarily about implementation, but in a performance sense,
when you look at all of the crap ZFS does from snapshots to write verification to ZFS
send, which once you wrap your head around what you can do with ZFS send, Extended4 is
going to look like a child's file system.
And when you think about all of this, it just comes with ZFS and it's so big and it's got
all this stuff, the fact that it is competitive on a three-year-old laptop where we intentionally
drain the thing of RAM to give it a real world heavily used system condition.
I mean, we were monitoring too.
I mean, it was busy.
It was working hard.
It was working really hard.
It was great.
And I'm just damn impressed with what the ZFS project has managed.
I mean, ZFS on Linux, open ZFS in general, it's just fantastic.
And having it available, ready to go without messing around with DKMS, which by and large
is pretty reliable, but I still find myself running into issues and not having that, it
just feels so much more reliable and professional.
I thought what we'd do is I thought we'd come on the show and say, if you just need all-out
performance and you don't care about data integrity, snapshots or any of the other features,
compression, encryption, which by the way, we did not have compression turned on.
Compression may have significantly changed the game here.
We were just using defaults on both.
If we had used compression, ZFS may have kicked ass on this.
It would be really interesting to run it again actually now that I think about it.
Oh boy, there's always more benchmarks.
But anyways, I honestly thought at the end of all this, we'd come here and say, if you
just want full, nothing but performance, go with Extended 4.
But the reality is, depending on your use case, you may actually get higher performance
even in low memory conditions with ZFS, depending on your use case.
We have a few links in the show notes.
The one that I think would be really interesting for you to check out are the low memory versus
regular memory tests and the low memory Extended 4 versus low memory ZFS.
And then it's really easy to compare all of them actually, but we'll have the links in
the show notes.
There's some interesting data.
I walk away from this thinking, it's safe from a performance standpoint to use ZFS,
and even if it's on a system that you want to have high performance from.
And then there's additional benefits as you go up the hardware scale, like when you start
going to MV and E drives, there's additional benefits to going with ZFS.
It just gets better.
And when you start wanting to use multiple disks and pool them together, there's a lot
more benefits to going with ZFS that Extended 4 can't offer without having to strap on LVM
or other management tools, whereas ZFS brings it all in one suite of tools.
So this is really fascinating for me because what the data says is even in a worst case
ZFS scenario, old SSD, three-year-old system, limited memory, it's still very competitive.
And then when you put it in a situation where you have a lot more hardware to throw at it
and you have a lot more disks to throw at it, the benefits just really get bigger.
All right.
Well, then I think it's prediction time.
What do you think?
Does this pave the way to ZFS on root by default in a future Ubuntu release?
Can you see it?
I mean, it would make a lot of sense, especially on the server side when you want to protect
from bogus updates or configuration mistakes.
Right.
And it would be a big advertising point if you had that integrated into that Ubuntu tooling,
right?
Ubuntu is a great choice because look, you can just roll back.
If we could properly get boot environment support at grub, it'd be worth it just to annoy
the BSD crowd that already has it.
You know what I mean?
Look, we caught up.
Yeah.
But we talk about it like it's the first time we've got to pretend we've never heard that
they've done it.
Yeah.
They hate that.
Because they hate that.
And so that would really make it perfect.
And that's what I hope for.
Do you think that they would ever shift and do ZFS on the Ubuntu server while ext4 on
the desktop?
Could do.
You know, on my machine upstairs when I reload it, I'm not going with CFS on my root.
I'm still waiting.
Again, because that's an implementation thing.
Also likely go pop and they don't have it in the installer.
However, I have three disks that I pooled together and I am absolutely going to move
them over from XFS to ZFS.
Right.
That's the other nice thing here.
Even if you don't do it on root, well, if you're running Ubuntu, it's at hand.
I may be near the end of ever really using LVM again.
Although LVM has been great and solid and I've got nothing against it, I like the ZFS
tools better.
And as I learn them more, I think they seem to be more complete.
And the whole idea of bringing it all together where the file system is aware of the hardware
and aware of the RAID and aware of what the user space is doing brings so many advantages.
So it's a bright future either way, because you can still pick whichever file system floats
your boat.
But you could also go with something new and furniture.
Chris, if you say it out loud, you know, the BSD folks might hear you.
Are they listening?
Have you done any ZFS experimentation over there?
I have.
Yeah.
So I moved from Debian to Ubuntu for my primary server simply to get the ZFS support.
Oh, really?
Why?
What was so like, gotta have?
Because you've had what, various solutions in the past?
I went to a talk by Jim Salter at Lennox Fest Northwest, and then Alan Jude gave me one
of his books for free and that was that.
That's having two devils on your shoulder in that case, Tanya.
It's really compelling, you know, all the checksumming stuff.
So the use case I use it for is I just have a pair of drives mirrored that store all of
the irreplaceable data.
So my drone footage, my photos and stuff like that.
You know, the stuff that is irreplaceable, genuinely irreplaceable.
And then I use ZFS Send to send that to England and then Duplicati does a bunch of other stuff
with it as well.
But I've really been enjoying it.
And yes, there's a lot to learn and there's some monitoring stuff with how like DF handles
monitoring free space and there are some things to learn, but I don't mind learning stuff.
That's part of the fun for me.
Yeah, it does have a learning overhead.
Yeah, but that's true for, you know, anytime you kind of step out of the box, right?
Even with ThunderFest.
True.
Okay.
Yeah, very fair.
Brent, you had a question about CFS capabilities.
Yeah, well, I often tend to like default to using encryption in many places as a way of
forcing myself to learn it.
But I wondered about ZFS and encryption.
Does anybody have any experience with that or has done any research?
I haven't played with it too much yet, but they do now have it natively inside CFS.
I think before I usually would, you know, kind of to layer it on, but that would sidestep
some of the direct, give CFS direct access to the disk benefits.
I haven't played too much with it though.
Yeah, so it, I think just recently landed in the last couple of point releases for CFS
on Linux.
Rebsd has had some solutions for a little while, but it's pretty nice.
One of the things that I'll probably look at doing in the future is you can, in CFS,
you can have these concepts of pools of disks.
So you can have like a media pool and like a documents pool and stuff like that.
And you can do partitions across them or whatnot, but you can also just say encrypt everything
in this pool.
So if you have, if you want to have like a documents folder in your home folder, that
could actually be mapped to an entire storage pool.
That one folder could be mapped to the documents pool and you could just say anything I put,
which just looks like a folder to you, but it's actually an entire pool of disks.
Anything I put in this folder encrypted.
And then once you set it, it's done.
You don't worry about it.
You're exciting me.
I think, you know, it's not quite there.
It's not daily driver yet, but we've got such great potential where the desktop environments
and the toolkits around them, because like we haven't given a lot of attention to plasma
on this release, but also just still doing great, still doing great, very solid and working
away at their Wayland support, making it, making it a top priority for Kwin.
It's really gotten to a good spot.
So, and this is just another part of it.
This is just, this is a part of the stack that we get to enjoy as free software users.
We just get this stuff for free and a whole team of people worked on packaging this all
up for us and then one day an arbitrary date, they decide you now get this thing and it,
it can change your life.
It can like, it can save your precious memories.
It can change how you back up and move data around the world.
It can provide features that you've never thought possible with your computer before.
It makes your computer more capable, even if you choose not to use it.
That's awesome.
That's it, right?
Like, I mean, there's no going back if you're like, Oh, I didn't think I'd want those pictures,
but I left them on this old drive here.
I mean, if you have ZFS underneath, you know, better safe than sorry.
Well, and if you just look at it from like an old school, like imagine your, your favorite
Linux distro as a boxed product on the shelf and you know, every year they got to have
new bullet points on that box.
Well, your favorite distro box, if it's Ubuntu based, just got some unbelievable features
that just would, if you're looking at it from like features on a box standpoint, it's just
incredible.
And you combine that with everything else we can do on Linux these days and just, just
blows my mind.
Just blows my mind.
So check out the links in the show notes for our benchmarks, including the comparison of
low memory versus high memory, them with just, you know, having at the system as much as
they can and then compare it to your system.
Yeah, we'd love to see that.
Maybe let us know if you get some interesting results.
I have a pick for you this week that I think is going to be perfect for you, Mr. Bacon.
It's called ThinkPad Tools.
This is going to be applicable to everybody, but it's pretty nice for those of you that
have a ThinkPad out there and it sounds like you just got one.
Yeah.
So I just recently picked one up.
I picked up the older T440S.
After doing some research, I probably should have got the T440P, but you know, it is what
it is.
170 bucks, 12 gigs of RAM, 256 gig SSD.
I think he just wanted to brag.
That's why he brought this up.
Shut up.
This is the biggest humble brag.
Well, I mean, you could find the same deal for a little bit cheaper if you did some digging
out there.
But after watching Popey go on his spiel about it, he makes me want to buy used ThinkPads
too.
Well, and then I just given my older ThinkPad to L, so I was jonesing for that track point
again, you know?
Well, welcome back to the club.
You know, like having a ThinkPad, I hadn't experienced this before having one.
It kind of is like a little club.
There's something special about Linux users and ThinkPads, and that's why we get all the
nice toys like the pick this week, ThinkPad tools.
So sorry if you don't have a ThinkPad, although maybe take Jesus advice and go find one near
you.
I can't believe that.
That's a great value.
And that'll be a great test machine.
You know, we've got a nice range now.
We've got a good range of super high end machines that are ridiculous in scale.
And then we've got machines that are real practical daily drivers that people might
be picking up either second hand or just own for a couple of years and don't need to replace
it.
So I think we're going to get a good, with the whole team now, we're getting good representative
sample of people's machines.
The other thing I'd like to add about ThinkPads is that they're super easy to repair.
I swapped out the keyboard on my wife's ThinkPad in about an hour.
You know, so even if you pour water over the thing, it's cheap and easy to repair.
We don't recommend you do that.
We do not recommend you do that.
Anyways, if you're thinking, well, what does it do?
It'll adjust the track point speed and sensitivity.
It'll help you get better battery information and it can help you troubleshoot that under
vaulting CPU issue.
We've talked about before.
I mean, I didn't know that my sensitivity was 128, but now I do.
Now you do, Wes.
Actually, it is like, I mean, the little battery status is nicely displayed in the terminal
and it's just in Python.
So it's easy to install.
Yeah.
So check that out.
Link in the notes for that and all of it's at linuxunplug.com slash three, two, four.
While you're there, you can subscribe to get the show directly every single week at linuxunplug.com
slash subscribe.
But more importantly, if you want to give us your thoughts, your feedback, your take
on the new release of 1910 or anything else we've talked about, linuxunplug.com slash
contact.
That's so easy.
There's just like a form there and it sends an email for you.
Easy, easy.
You could also tweet us at Linux Unplugged on the Twitter.
Yeah.
And the whole network's at Jupiter Signal.
That guy right there.
At Wes Payne.
I'm at Chris LAS.
Cheesy.
I'm at cheesebacon.
C-H-C-B-A-C-O-N.
Go get some Alex.
At Alex is a K-T-Z on the Twitter.
Ironic Badger.
Oh, that's right.
Yes.
Ironic Badger.
Go get some Alex, too.
It's so ironic that I forgot that, except for that's not ironic.
That's not ironic at all.
I know.
I'm sorry.
Anyways, and did I mention mine?
Probably.
You did, yeah.
But you didn't mention that you should go get more of you and Alex over at that self-hosted
show.
Oh, we should mention that.
Uh-huh.
Yeah.
And while we're just doing plug skis, I should mention TechSnap.Systems slash 414.
Wes and Jim have such a great discussion on ZFS in general, especially like around the
snapshot stuff.
There's so many good points.
But Jim's explanation of snapshots truly made me understand it and appreciate why it can
happen pretty quick, why the snapshots don't take a ton of disk space, and why it's kind
of a big deal that this is landing on such a large Linux distro.
Yeah.
Put it all into perspective.
TechSnap.Systems slash 414, and join us next Tuesday over at jblive.tv.
We do this show at 2 p.m. Pacific at jblive.tv.
Got a chat room, the mumble.
See you back here next Tuesday!
Now, we gotta title this thing.
Potato Computing.
I like that.
It's as slow as a potato.
You know what?
Potatoes are great, so let's not throw potatoes under the bus.
Especially them free-range taters.
It's the only ethical kind of tater.
Of course.
It's a free-range tater.
Be kind to the potatoes.
So, uh, let's go get this thing named.
I'm gonna vote for RamBurglars.
I'm going to, like, try to slam this install on my system, and then be done.
Because in the last three weeks, I got a different phone, I've been loading and reloading systems,
and so, like, nothing's set up.
Like, I gotta log into everything, you know what I'm saying?
Like, it's just been weeks of setting up software, so, like, I'm gonna, after this show's over.
Should we take away your root privileges on there?
Just to be fair.
I'll set a BIOS password.
Right, yes.
No more.
So, after this episode, I'm going upstairs, I'm reloading that box, I'm ordering food,
and I'm not leaving the studio until my basics are logged into.
And I'm calling it good for a while.
It's nice to have that ready to go, though, right?
So, like, tomorrow, you can actually just get work done.