So I've been trying out Google Stadia this week.
Oh, boy.
Just a little bit.
You hipster, you.
Well, I decided to get the, what do they call it,
like the Founders Pack or whatever.
My thinking was, is twofold.
This is going to be somewhat good for Linux gaming,
even if it's a little, because it actually
requires developers target Vulkan,
and they have to target Linux.
Right.
That's what's running on the back end.
And Google requires that.
So I like that idea.
But for me, it's sort of like outsourcing the bad,
outsourcing the proprietary.
With Stadia, I can have all free Intel drivers on my laptop,
great power, low heat, all the stuff I want.
But then I can open up a browser,
and I can play actual, real, quality video games.
That's the dream.
And when you're done with it, you can forget about it,
and you don't have this hardware laying around.
Or maybe I get home, and all of a sudden,
something changes in our plans, and I find myself
with a free evening.
All I've got is systems that are incapable of really gaming.
And that happens three times a year.
So you're not really wanting to invest.
Well, then you've got to imagine, too,
as far as disk space goes, games these days
are anywhere from 20 to 100 plus gigs worth of storage.
And if you don't play them all that often,
you're just sitting there with a disk that's
starting to fill up with games you don't play that often.
I had that problem.
I had Steam installed, and I was like,
I haven't played for a while.
I'm just going to delete all of this.
And then you wanted to play with me,
and I didn't have any of it ready.
Steam Cash, bro, that's what you need to do.
Yeah, I know.
That's going to happen at the RV,
but that's a topic for self-hosted.
What were your first impressions?
You got to try it a little bit.
You had the controller wired into my PC,
because that's the only way to do it.
I'm impressed.
I mean, I'm definitely in the casual gamer style,
more than enough for my needs.
And if I had not known about Stadia,
and I just walked up and you gave me the controller,
I was thinking I was playing any console.
Have you ever played Destiny 2 before?
Not two.
I've played Destiny once.
Because you walked in and cleaned that entire room
out with a shotgun.
I mean, I may have played some video games in a past life.
I mean, you had some tactics, too.
You went around the corner.
So response-wise, it's pretty dead on.
Yeah.
What I see it as is you trade.
So you could do some of these games on a cheaper GPU
if you didn't want to invest every year, every couple
of years, on a big GPU.
But you'd have to turn down the textures,
turn down the distance, turn down the reflections,
the shadows, the lights.
With Stadia, you can have mostly that stuff turned up
pretty decently well.
But you trade a little bit of fuzz
when you've got a lot of motion.
Right.
It was a little bit of blur.
But honestly, I mean, in the middle of the firefight,
you don't notice any of that.
You're not paying attention because you're just
really focused on the thing you're shooting at.
So I probably am going to stick with it.
My next big commitment, though, would be to move up from the free games
to the pay games, and they're full price, Wes.
And they just live on Stadia.
And of course, you're worried, how long is Stadia
going to be around?
I mean, yeah.
It is Google.
Hello, friends, and welcome in episode 329 of your Unplugged program.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Mr. Payne.
Hello.
Big show.
Huge show.
Hello, Cheesy.
We have about as many people in the quiet listening lobby
as we do in the actual room.
This new time has been interesting and well-attended.
I really appreciate it.
We're glad to see all of you.
So this week, we're talking about a problem
I've been trying to solve.
In the spirit of free and open source, I am scratching my own itch this week.
And I am NAT busting with my VPNs.
I have a situation where I'm behind carrier-grade NAT at home.
And I want to create an overlay network across all my machines
that are on a Linno data center, on a Digital Ocean data center,
in my RV, at the studio, when I'm traveling, on my laptop.
I want an overlay network that spans the entire internet that
puts them all on one LAN.
Right.
So you can just forget about it.
It doesn't matter if you're here at the studio
or you're down at Linux Academy headquarters.
You can pop onto your home network no problem.
There's a plethora of options to do this.
We talk a lot about WireGuard.
WireGuard's not necessarily the best solution for that.
We'll tell you why, and we'll tell you what some of our favorite solutions are.
And then we went and got interviews with the creators of them.
So that's all coming up in today's episode.
But first, we have some community news to get into.
This one's nuts, Mr. Payne.
Did you see this Android, which has its very own weird, strange kernel
legacy, its own strange sets of patches, may, may, may end up going mainline.
I actually think this is one of those initiatives
that's going to die on the vine about a year in.
Right, it seems like there's a lot of pressure and momentum against this.
Yes, well, people don't like proprietary crap in the kernel.
But the current Android ecosystem is really
kind of polluted with hundreds of different versions of Android,
each running a different variant of their own Linux kernel.
Each version is designed for a different phone,
and it's different configurations.
That's always the way it's been.
And Google has been working to fix that problem by mainlining the Linux kernel,
just going with a straight upstream kernel one day.
It's kind of the dream, right?
I mean, we talk about all the great things about Linux
and why upstream development is good.
And of course, we don't get any of that on Android.
And that's because before it reaches you,
the Linux kernel on your Android phone goes through three major steps.
First, Google has to take the long-term support version of the kernel,
whichever one it's going to use for that version of Android,
and then add all those Android-specific changes.
This is called the Android Common Kernel.
And then this code goes to the company that creates the system on a chip
that actually runs your phone, which is probably Qualcomm.
And once the system on a chip maker finishes adding all that code
to support the CPU and whatever other chips are on there,
the kernel is then passed on to the actual device maker,
such as Samsung or Motorola.
And then they add code to support the rest of the phone,
like the display and the camera.
Yeah, or maybe some new fancy feature that is their differentiator.
Each of these steps takes a while to complete.
That's how software and hardware development works.
And it means that the end product,
that kernel doesn't work with any other device.
It also means that the kernel's very old,
usually about two years old on an Android device when it ships.
The Pixel 4, which shipped last month, has a kernel from November 2017.
Ouch.
I don't even want to know what kernel my Pixel 3 is running.
I know.
Now, Google did announce plans last year to fix this mess.
Yeah, that's right.
They said, we know what it takes to run Android,
but not necessarily on any given hardware.
So our goal is to basically find all of that out, then upstream it,
and try to be as close to mainline as possible.
Kind of sounds like maybe we won't get fully mainline,
even in Google's vision.
That might be difficult with Android's long history.
It's a good goal, though.
Yeah, they did show it off on a prototype up on stage.
I don't think it was perfect, though.
No, no, I don't think so.
Does seem like some things were not working,
like the battery percentage, which was stuck at zero.
That sounds like the Librem.
So what's Google's plan to make all this work?
Well, they plan to take a page from their Project Treble playbook.
Before Project Treble, the low-level code
that interacted with the device in Android itself
was just a big old stack of mess.
What Project Treble did was it separated the two
and made them modular, so Android updates could be shipped quicker,
and the low-level code could remain unchanged between these updates.
What Google wants to do is bring that same modularity to the kernel.
Their plan, quote, involves stabilizing Linuxes in kernel ABI
and having stable interfaces for the Linux kernel
and hardware vendors to write to.
Google wants to decouple the Linux kernel from its hardware support,
end quote.
So this means that Google would ship a kernel,
and then hardware drivers would just be loaded
as regular old kernel modules.
Now, of course, this is just a proposal, and there are still
quite a few technical problems that have yet to be solved.
I mean, that does sound like a big change, right?
That's a different way to approach things,
although I can see why some decoupling would be nice
given these slower cycles outside the kernel development.
Yes, I don't actually think it's necessarily a bad idea.
It's just such a radical change to serve one group's needs.
It is a large group, but it is a radical change.
I think the Android problem is not a unique one.
There's probably thousands of hardware vendors,
at smaller scales, in Google's shoes.
They make a product that's an IoT device or something like that.
It doesn't have to be Android.
It could just be based on Linux.
But it takes a long time for a group of people
to build hardware and software.
And so it's easy for a couple of years to go by,
even if you're not a phone maker.
Like, phone makers probably have it down at this point.
They probably have it about as efficient as they can
because profitability is driving that.
But Fred's IoT shop that's making router boards and stuff
that get shipped in 100 different Chinese types
of knockoffs, they don't have that kind
of efficiency of scale.
It's probably a much wider spread problem.
So there could be some real logic in doing this.
I'll be curious to see what the upstream kernel community
thinks of these proposals.
Yeah, it doesn't seem like it's got initially
a very good reaction.
And I mean, I wonder how much of it
do you lose some of those advantages, the things
that the kernel community is always talking about,
about getting proper upstream, traditional upstream support.
How much of that will actually apply here?
Yeah, they really want to see people just make it open source,
make it GPL, and then it's just included.
We'll all maintain it together.
And that's a pretty deep philosophical outlook,
which is why it's been really fascinating to watch
WireGuard's slow march into mainstreaming.
WireGuard is the VPN technology we traditionally
talk about all the time on this show
because we've been following it very closely.
It's been held up by the adoption of its main crypto,
which we thought may slide.
We thought perhaps they were going to swap out
the clever crypto that WireGuard uses for something
already in the kernel.
Well, this week, Linux 5.5 seems to support key elements
of the zinc crypto effort, which WireGuard depends on,
which I thought wasn't going to happen.
I think what's happening here is when WireGuard
was sort of released, the crypto stuff kind of came fully formed.
And the kernel community doesn't always love, oh, here's
this giant chunk of code.
Will you apply this patch, please?
So I think what needed to happen was the kernel community
and working with the WireGuard community
and sort of working out which pieces made the most sense
and in what order are we going to start
making some of these changes.
Thankfully, what's landing in Linux 5.5
is enough to unblock the dependencies in WireGuard.
Now, with that said, WireGuard is not landing in 5.5,
but should, emphasis on should, land in 5.6.
Yeah, I'll believe it when I see it at this point.
It's just been crazy because it's
been every couple of releases, we're like,
well, the next one from this is going to have WireGuard.
I mean, the other good part here, too, is that we're just
getting better crypto in the kernel, too, right?
I mean, good point.
Zinc looks like it's super good.
But I think the thing that you'd mentioned
is really the key underlying here.
It's just enough to unblock WireGuard.
So we're not getting a complete implementation.
And there'll probably be continued discussions
on more code changes in the future.
I do love it, though.
I think I could easily do an episode
if we wanted on the open source projects
that I'm loving this year, because the list is different
than it was last year.
And there's just so much good stuff.
WireGuard is definitely on that list.
Game changer.
There's just some tools that they're
great fundamental building blocks,
and that means the things you can do with them
are almost endless.
It's funny we're talking about 5.5.
It's probably worth mentioning that 5.4 just came out.
Right.
So it's actually just shipped as being kernel 5.4.
And one notable thing that we've mentioned in the past
is it's coming with that lockdown feature, as well
as early extended FAT support.
There's more details in Linux Headlines.
If you're not listening to Linux Headlines,
that's where we put that kind of stuff, linuxheadlines.show.
I think that was the Monday episode,
because I think I did that one.
That's right.
And I think I covered it in Monday.
So the details are in the Monday episode of Linux Headlines.
But it's everything you need to know
in Linux and the world of open source in less than three
minutes.
Three minutes or less?
It's so great.
Well, guess what, Mr. Payne?
It's time for a little housekeeping.
And it's about time.
Last week, we talked about the System76 Superfan event.
Well, cheesy.
You got updates on that and some Pinebook updates, too.
Yeah, absolutely.
So we didn't get a lot of time to cover the Superfan event,
because we were pretty packed that show.
But I've done a write-up there.
And if you go to linuxunplug.com and hit the Blog tab,
you can check out that write-up.
A lot of cool pictures and just really a great synopsis
of the event itself.
It was wonderful.
It's really interesting to be around Linux nerds that
are actually producing hardware.
So it was just an experience that you'll
have to go read for yourself.
And I've also updated the jupyter.gallery page
with some photos from that event as well,
and also included a Pinebook Pro review.
So if you caught last week's show
and you want a little bit more information,
I suggest you hit the linuxunplug.com blog
and check out those posts as well.
I love it, man.
What's neat about that gallery, first of all,
I got to say, these posts, you did a great job.
So thank you for writing these up.
But what I love about that gallery
is you get to see some insides of the System76 warehouse.
You got some in this post, too.
I love this picture of Carl.
He should make that his Twitter profile.
That's amazing.
That's really good.
So you can find those linuxunplug.com slash articles.
This is something we try to do.
You know, we talk about this stuff in the show.
But we've recently, within like the last nine months or so,
started doing these write-ups and posting these pictures.
So that way, you actually have a little more, too,
than what we're just saying here.
You can go see what we're talking about,
get a better sense of the vibe.
And Cheezy has been doing a great job of updating
the jupyter.gallery, jupyter.gallery.
So go check that stuff out.
Al, also, did you mention your ThinkPads with Popeye episode?
Oh, dude, that was such a fun episode with Popeye.
Anybody that's looking at like a used ThinkPad
and wants to kind of know what might be the right one for them,
but also what you can replace and fix after you've
bought the ThinkPad, that stuff blew my mind.
I had no idea.
No idea.
So that was a great episode.
That's over at Extras.
And while I'm talking about Extras,
well, I'll mention it because we're on a roll right now.
Extras is on YouTube.
All of them are now posted on YouTube.
If you're a YouTube connoisseur, I'll
have a link to the channel.
We don't have any subscribers yet
because we just turned this thing on.
So we don't have a name.
Go subscribe, and you'll get little notifications
when we get new stuff in there.
How many subs do we got to get to name it?
100, maybe?
Maybe it's 1,000.
Might be 1,000.
Either way, we need your help.
Yeah.
So you'll find the link at linuxunplug.com slash 329.
Go subscribe so that way we can give it a name.
And we'll be posting all of the Extras on YouTube
as well as extras.show.
It's all over there, including that Popeye on ThinkPads
episode.
That extra stuff is so good.
I should also mention, Brent isn't here today,
but he did message me earlier and said,
a new Brunch with Brent is out with Jacob, and it's fantastic.
He talks about how TechSnap specifically
got him into the industry.
Oh, yeah.
It sounds like a, I've not had a chance to listen.
Yeah.
Because it just came out this morning.
Jacob's a good guy, though.
I've had breakfast with Jacob.
It's good.
Brunch with Brent and breakfast with Jacob.
All right, that's the housekeeping.
Now, let's get into these net-busting VPNs.
So we're not talking about WireGuard this week.
This week, we want to create a mesh network of sense,
or an overlay network.
And the granddaddy from the 90s in this space is Tink.
So how does Tink differentiate from WireGuard, Wes?
Tink is quite different from WireGuard.
WireGuard is very simple, which is great.
That's one of the things we love about WireGuard.
But when you're making a WireGuard connection,
you're really just making one point-to-point link here.
You've got the machine you're connecting to,
and the machine you're connecting from.
Tink can do a whole lot more.
Not only does it also have support for things like Layer
2, but it's a mesh network.
So it has a concept of understanding
all the different nodes you've got on the network.
It manages that.
The best routes to those nodes.
And it can figure out the best routes
to traverse that network.
So as long as two nodes that you've got on your Tink network
can talk through somehow, they will find a way.
So you could set up a public relay on a VPS,
and you could have my systems, which
are behind a massive carrier-grade NAT.
It is punishingly awful.
But Tink can accommodate that.
Yes, very much so.
It'll try to figure out whatever.
Yeah, you just need enough information,
and usually having some sort of public node not behind NAT.
That will make things a lot easier.
But it's got a lot of sophisticated NAT
busting integrated right inside of it.
So we sat down with one of the original creators of Tink,
and we asked how did he get the idea for Tink to begin with?
It started out when I found this new feature in one
of the very early Linux kernels.
So it was called EtherTap.
It was the predecessor to what's now called TUN.
And yeah, I wrote a little program to experiment with it.
And then naturally, I created some kind of tool
to create a network connection between two computers
and tunnel the packets back and forth.
And yeah, so that was already a working kind of VPN,
except it didn't do encryption, or it was very hard
to actually set it up.
I had to do a lot of things manually.
And then a friend, Ivo Timmermans, he joined in.
And he actually took this a step further,
and he made a proper demon out of it, introduced encryption.
And then yeah, also with some other people who joined in.
But I think Ivo and me were the people who
coded most in the beginning.
So how long ago was this, roughly?
So we started in 1997.
Wow, that was a whole other internet.
That is literally another internet ago.
Yes.
What's that like?
What's it like a project like this?
I mean, there must have been moments of security panic.
There must have been moments of trying
to decide if it's worth modernizing
as the kernel changes.
I mean, there must have been all kinds of things
to keep up with over that time period.
Yes.
Well, you mentioned a few things that indeed happened.
It started out as kind of a hobby project.
So we were all students back then.
And we actually wanted to have our own private network
so we could exchange files easily without having to,
well, without being that visible to the rest of the network.
Of course.
And well, one thing was that, of course,
we were not the first one to invent a tool like this.
There were already commercial solutions.
Or I think we had VTUN and SIPE in the Linux world
that did something similar.
Was the beauty, though, that it really sort of created
a truly flat mesh network?
I mean, you could have friends all over the world,
essentially, that are in one flat network.
Exactly.
So for example, Evo was not in the same city as we were.
So this was a good way to make sure
that we could access his computer
and run things like IRC and FTP.
I like the idea you can use it for development resources
of the project you're developing.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
So I noticed that the project for a while
has been nearing 1.1.
So it doesn't seem like the project's moving at 100 miles
per hour.
But just as of a couple of months ago,
there was an update on the news list.
So things are still continuing.
So development continues.
How would you describe the pace and future velocity of that?
Yeah, it's very slow, sadly.
So 1.0 is quite stable.
And I'm not planning to add any features to that.
There are still users who sometimes find bugs or say,
well, OK, with this little change,
it will be more useful for us.
So then we try to implement that.
And then, of course, yeah, there's 1.1,
which is a big improvement over 1.0.
I just need to find time to finally finish this.
Of course, that's always hard.
I thought several years ago that I would have the time
to do this.
But unfortunately, I'm not a student anymore.
So I have a proper job and a life.
Real work comes first, yeah.
What sort of features might we be looking forward
to when you do find that time?
I think already a lot of the features
that I want to have in 1.1 are there.
But there are some rough edges that I
want to have smoothed out.
One of them is, for example, key management.
So already it's a big improvement over 1.0.
It's much easier to create keys, exchange keys with others,
also in a secure way.
Oh, that's great.
But one of the issues is still, I would say,
handling key renewal.
If, for example, your public key is compromised somehow,
you want to update it.
You want to make sure that all the other nodes in the network
get that new key in a safe way.
Yeah, absolutely.
Also, if you don't trust someone anymore at the moment,
it's kind of a manual process to block this person or this node
on all the other nodes.
And it would also be great if that would be done
in a much more automated way.
But that requires some changes.
So there is no infrastructure at the moment
to spread that information throughout the network.
Right, that sounds like a lot of coordinating to coordinate.
Yes.
I'm curious what you might see on the larger
side of a Tink network.
How many nodes have you seen out there?
So myself, I've seen networks of over 500 nodes.
One of the biggest ones that is kind of public
is the Kales VPN network.
So it's kind of the European hackerspaces.
They are united using this network.
There's actually a counterpart in the US, DN42,
where they use various technologies,
including also Tink.
That's quite a large network.
But I've heard from other people that they
have similar-sized networks.
And there are also businesses, companies
that use Tink internally to connect offices together.
And it's very hard to get information of exactly how
many nodes they have and so on.
Yeah, I would imagine people are in part
doing this for security.
So they're not keen to share all their details.
No.
But I'm just always fascinated, because I
can see it working well for myself with a dozen nodes.
But I was just curious, since I probably
won't ever take it that far.
I was just kind of interested to see how far it could go.
So it sounds like 1.1 is still out in the works,
but not necessarily a timetable.
But as far as features go, really,
everything that's in the release now is pretty solid.
It's there.
It's fairly feature-complete.
As we noted, Tink's been around for a while.
I'm curious if there's any features about Tink,
things you love that stand out as reasons to use Tink.
I mean, there are more competitors these days,
but Tink is still great software.
Yeah.
Well, one thing that I think makes Tink stand out
is it doesn't impose any kind of restrictions
on the network topology use.
If you try to configure Tink, you
will notice that there is nothing in a configuration
file that basically says use this IP address or this subnet.
Basically, it says, well, yeah, you
can create a script yourself, which Tink will call for you.
But in the script, you have to configure actually
the virtual network interface that's created by Tink.
Right.
So you have all the control.
You can modify that, make it configure whatever you need.
Yeah.
That is great.
Right.
And it also strikes me as similar,
Tink supports Layer 2, which a lot of the newer VPN solutions
just sort of skip.
But that can make for very flexible implementations.
Yes.
Yeah.
It seems particularly attractive for someone like myself
who's behind a NAT.
And it's a particularly challenging NAT.
I've got a VPS.
I can throw Tink on that as well.
And Tink can sort of navigate that for me
and solve that problem.
And that's what makes it really special for me.
Well, Hus, thank you so much for joining us
and just kind of giving us some background details on it.
I find this stuff fascinating.
And your project is one of those that's
been around for such a long time.
It's sort of an unsung hero to a lot of people
where they find it solves that perfect problem.
But it's not a project that gets a ton of attention either.
Really appreciate you taking a moment
so we could shine a little light on it.
Well, thank you for having me.
So let's kind of define more specifically
how we're using the term overlay network
and what we're using it for.
I'll give you an example, a day-to-day example.
Myself, Drew, and Wes, we all have home studios.
And we'll sometimes need to connect into resources here
for production purposes.
Or sometimes Chris forgets to export an episode of Linux
Action News and somebody needs to remote in and.
Never happens.
And we all need to connect back to JP1.
I would like to connect to my home network
as well, regardless of where I'm at from my laptop,
and be able to connect to the JP1 infrastructure.
And so I needed a solution that could kind of create
an overlay network for all of this, one LAN.
Right, there's sort of a magical feeling
when you have a flat network, because everything's
accessible.
It just feels right next to you, right,
and right at your fingertips.
Yeah, yeah, things that do auto discovery,
like old video games, like StarCraft.
You can all see each other.
It's a really unique experience, because you
can be on a Raspberry Pi on a MiFi connection in an RV
and be pinging a box in the studio
like it's just a local machine.
Right, and you can simplify some things
and work across regions.
Maybe you've got different providers or different data
centers.
You can make things flat that way, too.
Unfortunately, I've used Tink, and we started evaluating Tink
for our use case here.
And we ran into some problems, because really, we've
got a few different security domains.
I don't need access to your home network.
And really, there's some parts of the studio that not every,
you know, we only need access to a few machines
here at the studio.
Tink doesn't really have any filtering capabilities.
There's nothing built in to help you manage
multiple different sets of users.
And when you want to add a new host, well,
if I want to talk to a new machine
that you've added to the studio, you've
got to go give me a new file that's
got all the information about that.
And that works OK for a few machines.
But if Drew's adding a new machine
that he wants to share with us, it gets tedious fast.
Wes and I were pretty excited when
we saw Slack announce Nebula, an open source global overlay
network.
And we invited Ryan on to tell us about it.
Ryan, this seems like something that's, A, I mean,
it's pretty notable that it's a pretty big open source
project from Slack, but B, it seems
like it's pretty well-developed.
Like, it's a complete ready-to-go solution.
Yeah, that's right.
You know, it's funny to have Nebula out in the wild
and people seeing it for the first time
because it's actually old news inside of Slack at this point.
It's three years old.
Oh, wow.
OK, yeah.
So you've been using it in production for a while then?
It's been in production for about two of those years.
All right, so an overlay network,
it seems like you could have accomplished this possibly
using IPSec or maybe even WireGuard with some really
sophisticated routing.
I'm guessing that was tried and done and didn't work.
Where did that kind of fall down for you guys?
So our original network, and are you
going to provide a link to the blog post in the show notes
possibly?
Absolutely.
Your Medium post and also the official announcement too
on the, you bet.
Yeah, we've been reading it voraciously.
Great.
Yeah, so we actually did IPSec originally.
And we ran into, so at first it was fine, right?
As you expand out, you have one region in a cloud provider
and everything's fine.
And then you expand to another region
and IPSec was kind of the obvious choice
for connecting multiple regions.
It was the most supported way.
There weren't, there are now in the past year or so,
they've added support for connecting remote regions that
don't require VPN, but we can get into that in a minute.
So we used IPSec out of the gate and it actually
worked fine in the beginning.
But as we scaled up, the complexity grew.
And I jokingly called our IPSec set up our RAID 0 network
configuration because the problem was
you had to do these kind of strange routing tricks
because no one box could handle the traffic.
And because of that, if you lost any of the boxes on one side,
even one of them, you lost routing
to an unknown number of nodes.
And so it wasn't really viable to keep
running that remote region that way.
So we would have to offline an entire region,
hence RAID 0 network configuration.
No kidding.
That was one of the major challenges.
And so we were already many thousands of servers
at that point.
And there were also folks that dissuaded us
from using IPSec at scales that we were planning to hit.
And I can't speak to whether they were correct or not,
but that was a caution that even some folks that
work with IPSec regularly, they said in transport mode, which
is sort of the node to node version of IPSec,
they said you might start to see performance issues when
you're above 1,000 nodes.
And again, this is secondhand, so I'm not
saying that we saw that.
I'm just saying that was kind of a warning that I was given.
And so when we thought about the problem also,
we looked at kind of traditional VPNs.
And one of the things that we didn't care for
was having to tell every node about every other node
ahead of time.
Right, that's a lot of overhead.
You have to manage it somewhere, configuration management,
or it's got to be somewhere.
Yeah, and it's not just that.
But think about when you get to many thousands of nodes,
say you're running a dynamic environment where
hosts come up and autoscale and that kind of thing.
A host comes up, and you have to ensure
with some measure of certainty that every other host it
might talk to has the proper key before it starts
talking to that host, right?
And that becomes a complex to manage problem when you're
talking thousands of hosts.
And so we went a different way with Nebula,
and we did certificate-based authentication between nodes.
And another part that I note, I mean,
certificate authentication is notable,
but the other thing that I noted about this that
seems to stand out is groups play
a large role in sort of the access control of this.
That was one of the events that was really
the moment we decided to write Nebula.
And so the primary authors are myself and Nate Brown,
who also works at Slack and has worked there
for four and a half years.
By the way, a bit of history, I've worked there five years
and was the first security employee.
Nate has worked there four and a half years
and was the second security employee.
So we've-
That is fantastic.
Yeah, so we've been there quite a while,
and we've actually done some really fun work
outside of this.
But so we were actually just chatting,
and we were actually, I know you mentioned Tink.
Before the show, we were talking about that briefly.
I really liked Tink.
Tink's this great project from the 90s,
and I think the guy's name is Gus
that's been working on it.
And it's got some really, really cool routing tricks
and sort of gets around NAT and that kind of thing.
And so we actually very seriously looked at
what it would take to use Tink
or maybe contribute back to Tink and go that route.
But what really led us to writing Nebula
was this idea that we wanted to encapsulate security groups,
as you mentioned.
Hmm, this, at first I struggled to quite understand this,
but when I started looking at the example configuration
files, and I saw an example in there
where it was broken down by servers, laptops,
it started to click a little bit more
that you could start to manage a much larger set of machines
by grouping them up.
Yeah, maybe you could clue us in
on how you guys are using groups.
Yeah, so the kind of contrived example,
I mean, we actually tie groups to Chef roles.
So if you're familiar with, yeah, so with config management,
because the Chef role really describes what a host
or what a container's job is,
then that kind of makes a natural grouping.
And we also add in some special stuff
like which region it's in,
which availability zone it's in, that kind of thing,
just so that we can do even more fine-grained.
And we opportunistically add groups we might use,
and even if we don't actually use them for filtering rules,
but we add as much kind of metadata as we can about hosts.
And so, you know, the contrived example I give is,
if you're a database server and say, you know,
in a very simple setup,
you just allow web servers to talk to that database,
then the only rule on your database servers is,
you know, assume MySQL.
The only rule on the database servers would be,
I allow TCP 3306 from anything
that's in the group web servers.
And that's powerful because you no longer have to
care about IP addresses or host names or anything.
And this isn't new, right?
This is something that, you know,
cloud security groups have existed for a long time.
The difference is Nebula security groups are,
well, they're cross-platform, which is pretty cool,
but they're also cross-provider and cross-region.
Right, right, that is a big deal.
I mean, we're talking about as an overlay network
and you can really use this to stitch everything together.
I mean, is this a lot of traffic then going through Nebula?
Yeah, I don't have the numbers in front of me,
but it's many billions of packets per second.
It's really neat to see.
Yeah, it's in heavy use.
I can only imagine what it must have been like
to evangelize that inside a company and then roll it out
and then have to work out the kinks.
That must have been quite an experience.
Yeah, there were some fun times,
especially in the early days.
One of the really great things about this project in general
and kind of following on some of the other projects
I've worked on and Nate's worked on is
this is something we also just wanted for ourselves, right?
So there's that selfish aspect,
which is we want this to be great for Slack.
We also want to use this for our home networks
and everything else.
Like we really wrote it for ourselves
and for Slack at the same time.
So tell me the thoughts behind going open source.
Yeah, there are a lot of good reasons to do it.
I think the main one is,
you know, everyone says they give back to the community
and I very much agree.
Like every company is built on so much open source software
that if you've done something that can save someone else time
and it doesn't, you know, degrade your security posture
or there's not a business reason,
I think it's really nice to open source software in general.
An open source by default sort of thing.
Yeah, and I think we've been pretty good about that.
Anytime we've had something that's sort of generally useful,
we've kind of put it up there.
But the other reason is getting more eyes on it
and just having more people use it, you know?
So one of the things that I lobbied for internally
was to add Nebula to our official Slack Bug Bounty program.
And so that means that when we put this out there,
if people find security-related flaws in Nebula,
we'll actually pay them for those
through the Slack Bug Bounty process.
That is great.
Yeah, that was a big one for me
because again, this is a pretty key part
of our infrastructure.
And on top of it, you know,
some amount of trust from a community
when people are using it.
And so, you know, we wanted to make sure
that we weren't just throwing this over the wall
and then saying, good luck.
I love that.
I think we're seriously considering using it
for remote studio productions
to connect back to the main studio.
And looking through the configuration,
there's a couple of things that I really love.
Like the BeaconSys service,
or whatever you want to call it, is named Lighthouse.
So we can put that on an external system.
That's great, that's a great name.
The server, I don't know what you call it,
but the function to make sure
that the NAT mapping remains is called Punchy.
It keeps punching a hole.
My friend and colleague, Nate, hates the name Punchy.
So I'm going to make sure and play this section,
but I call it that.
It made me smile.
Yeah, and there's some other stuff
that over time we really learned.
I'm not speaking ill of GoGo,
but one of the best debugging steps we had
was whenever I would be on a flight using this,
the latency over that really taught us a lot
about some of the handshake issues we might run into
in extreme cases, so that was pretty neat.
The core of Nebula has existed
and been in production for two years,
but we've added features sort of as we worked on it.
And there's, you mentioned Punchy.
One of the features that we added not long ago,
probably six or seven months ago,
I don't have it in front of me,
was something called Punch Back.
And I don't know if you saw that in the config as well.
I think I did, yeah.
Yeah, so sometimes you're behind a really difficult NAT,
and like a symmetric NAT,
I won't go into the details of why,
but a symmetric NAT can be extremely difficult.
I live that life right now, actually.
I have one of my systems.
Are you on mobile?
Yes.
Yeah, so you would really enjoy Punch Back.
And I actually did that because I use a hotspot
quite a bit of the time as well.
I really enjoy road trips,
and so I have like an AT&T hotspot.
Kindred spirits.
Oh, you're speaking my language.
And so what Punch Back does is,
when a host wants to connect to another host,
it asks the Lighthouse how to reach it.
The Lighthouse gives back an IP address
and a UDP port to try.
And when I query the Lighthouse from a node,
it also signals the node I'm about to connect to
to punch outbound to me, right?
So as I query the Lighthouse and ask about a node,
the Lighthouse is signaling that node
that I'm about to try and send a packet to it,
and it should punch out.
And by the way, a really important thing here is,
the Lighthouses actually don't transit any of these packets.
They're there purely for querying and finding nodes.
The handshake never goes through a Lighthouse.
So the Lighthouse signals that node to punch out,
and then we start sending packets,
and we try all the different IPs that we know about
or that we've learned about.
And the thing that Punchback does is it says,
okay, the Lighthouse signaled me
that somebody's trying to reach me.
I'm gonna give it five seconds,
and if they don't reach me, I'm gonna try and reach them
as though I had initiated the connection.
And that, as long as there aren't two boxes
behind really terrible symmetric NATs,
that works almost every time.
Oh my gosh, well, I think that just sealed the deal
right there.
I mean, it's clear that you've had to fight
through some of these things
and worked out a lot of those kinks.
Yeah.
Oh man, that's so fantastic.
Ryan, this is one of those moments,
you know, you always hear, it's almost cliche,
like the thing about open source and free software
is everybody's scratching their own itch.
It sounds like in this particular case,
you had exactly the same itch.
And I just am so thrilled.
I think it's great.
I will link to the announcement,
and we're gonna play with it.
We're absolutely gonna try it out.
Yeah, is there anything we need to know?
I mean, we've talked about a lot of good things here,
but is there anything as potential adopters
we should be aware of?
Depending on the platform you run,
there's some stuff that hasn't been merged yet
that's going to make that easier,
especially if you use any Macs or Windows devices.
And so one of the difficulties in Windows
that when I was sort of developing
some of this with a friend,
by the way, there's a gentleman that we work with
named Wade who did every port.
So we wrote this for Linux,
and he ported it, and Go makes porting just so nice,
but he ported it to Windows and Mac.
And even in one single hack day,
Wade is the person that got it running on iOS.
So, yeah, it was really impressive stuff.
And so, but one of the difficulties with Windows,
I haven't run Windows as a primary OS in many years,
so I'm kind of out of date on it.
But one of the issues was installing services
and how services need to behave is kind of,
it's very foreign if you're used to Unix style services.
And so there's a really nice Go library out there
that can make a binary service aware.
And so I integrated that into Nebula
and made a version of Nebula
that's a self-installing service.
And so in that case, you can actually copy nebula.exe
and one config file to a Windows host,
and then you can run nebula-service install,
and it actually does the whole bit
and installs it as a Windows service.
And that library is actually cross-platform.
It's really neat.
So it even does that on Linux or OS 10,
whatever you're using.
We have a bit of a pettance argument
about doing that on Linux,
so I don't think that'll be the default build on Linux
because just use systemd or upstart
is kind of the right way to go.
But for the other OSs, you know, OS 10 or Windows,
I think that's gonna be the default behavior very soon.
And there's a branch that already works.
That's one thing I mean, you can't miss about Nebula
is that simplicity.
It just seems ready to integrate
into all kinds of other systems, however you might do it.
Yeah, we were brainstorming a couple of ideas already.
Ryan, I hope you'll keep us in mind in the future
if there's any developments you wanna share
with the community, we'd love to pass it along.
I think you can count us officially as fans of the project.
Well, that's great to hear.
I know people probably say this and it sounds cliche,
but I was really surprised
how many people were interested in this
because before we put it out there,
you know, we knew we were super into this,
but you always think your thing is really neat
and you hope other people do,
but the response has been really great
and we're really happy about that
and we wanna keep that going.
So we're gonna do some things
to make it even easier to stand up Nebula,
especially for folks that maybe don't wanna stand up
a lighthouse and do all of that just to test it out.
So we're gonna make that a bit easier going forward
and I can't wait to see what use cases people come up with.
Very good, well, thank you for joining us.
Thank you.
Something we didn't touch on,
but Nebula has also undergone
a paid security vulnerability assessment
along with numerous internal Slack reviews as well.
So it's looking like it's in pretty good shape.
Yeah, they're certainly using it.
And we did give it a go.
In fact, we have been really having quite a bit of fun
playing around with Nebula.
It's been one of those projects that just is,
like you feel like it's cutting edge,
but it's doing something that solves such a cool problem.
It's great.
And it's simple.
It's just, it's easy to get started with.
I mean, it's go, so you just go download
the two binaries that you need
and the configuration files are easy.
It's just YAML and because of the way it works,
you don't need a whole bunch of configuration files.
You basically just need the key pair for your machine.
You need the CA certificate
and then the config file for the daemon and you're done.
Yeah, it's a lot of kind of like conceptual stuff.
You have to shift your head a little bit
because it's all key-based.
So you gotta get used to that, but that's not a big deal.
It's not necessarily like a service.
It's not gonna be a package you install.
It's a tarball you download and extract and you run it.
But if you're okay with,
and you're comfortable with those kinds of things,
with very minimal effort,
you can create an overlay network that is secured.
And it's like being, like browsing a local LAN.
For fun, like we went on two different Mifis.
Wes did it from his place.
I did it from the RV.
We have systems at the studio.
And they can just all immediately talk to each other.
And it'll be smart about things, so it'll figure it out.
You know, if I'm from my house,
I can talk to one of the studio machines,
but if I come into the studio,
they figure out that that traffic
just stays on the local LAN.
So we even got it going on my Raspberry Pis
to an extent.
My Raspberry Pi 4s, I think,
did we figure out they were in 64-bit mode?
I can't remember now.
But there's a 32-bit and a 64-bit version
that'll run on the Raspberry Pi.
And we got it working really solid for a bit
on one of my Raspberry Pis.
But when we set it up on a second Raspberry Pi,
we ran into some strange issues
where it really kind of came into our limits
of the ability to troubleshoot.
And because this is new,
there isn't a huge community around it to solve it.
Yeah, and there are some downsides, it is very simple.
It just means that it only operates in the one mode.
And right now, the NAT punching
doesn't seem quite to be working.
There are some extenuating circumstances
because, as you said, you have two layers of NAT,
which makes just about everything difficult.
I have this fantastic, best ISP I've ever had in my life,
local ISP.
They're like one of the last in Washington,
little small outfit.
Like if you call them and they don't answer,
they see it on their caller ID and they call you back.
Hello, Mr. Fisher, I saw I missed your call.
Oh yes, I see, I could lower your bill by $10.
I'll get that taken care of for you, sir.
Thank you for calling, seriously.
Like yeah, no problem.
Okay.
Thanks.
So they're a great ISP except for, you don't get.
I get like a 192.168.5.whatever.
So I get some weird public IP address
that is obviously NAT.
And I don't know,
I don't even know how far down the NAT chain I really am.
But then of course, I have a NAT of my own network.
So I have a gateway device that's connected to that NAT,
which then does NAT behind it.
And so, as you heard in the chat there,
it is designed, Nebula, to punch through this.
And it does to an extent.
We can get one Raspberry Pi working for a bit.
It can't talk to all the nodes though.
Yeah, we're having a few.
We haven't got it quite working.
That said, we did just pick this up yesterday
and on 80% of the machines, it just worked.
The ones that aren't behind super crazy NAT,
even mild NAT, like MiFi NATs.
Right, yeah.
Tether into my phone, no problem.
Yeah, that'll work fine.
Jump into the studio.
And it's really neat to just see it work.
And Wes was able to bang it out
into a system to unit file in like 30 seconds.
So now it's a service that just runs on our boxes.
Yeah, no problem.
Super simple.
So I have a question for Wes.
I use a tool called SSH Shuttle
to tunnel my DNS around from the US to Europe and stuff.
Can you send with either Nebula or Tink,
can you route DNS through those tunnels easily?
Or like, where does the DNS actually happen?
I mean, I don't see why not.
You just need an endpoint at the other side.
Yeah, so they both have provisions for it.
Specifically to Nebula, there is a configuration option
to declare where the DNS is
or even to act as a DNS forwarder.
And so we have experimented a little bit with that,
but you do kind of need a name server on either end
to do it, you have to do that part.
Okay.
It's not, it kind of sounds hard if you don't try,
but once you try it, it's really,
turns out if you try hard enough, you can.
It's really not so bad.
No, no, it's not.
And it's just nice, you know, it's neat to have,
we live in a world where you share things in the cloud,
and everything is an HTTP service
or HTTPS really these days.
Having a flat network sort of harkens back
to the good old Unix days.
So now we could have a Samba server running
here at the studio, but if it's listening
on that overlay network, you can get those files
from anywhere.
But especially because of the security group stuff
built right into Nebula, which I love,
you can do that securely and not have to worry
about exposing Samba to the public internet,
which you just shouldn't do.
Yeah, listeners of our self-hosted program
know that I have a mandate to never expose the RV
to the public internet.
So something like this, that's why this double net
situation, I take it as a challenge,
because I really have a mandate
to not publicly expose anything.
That's a good rule for life, Chris.
I agree, and what I love about both Nebula and Tink,
but specifically Nebula and WireGuard,
they're really good about reconnecting
once your connection comes back online,
which is really useful for me for both laptop and the RV.
Nebula also is, it's not that old,
they've been using internally for a little bit
and it's certainly new to us.
But you can tell it's a modern tool.
I mean, not only is that written in Go,
but it's got great logging support built right in
and metrics, so if you've got a graphite server
or a Prometheus server, that's built right in.
Yeah, there's some, I could see Slack building
some services around this thing in the future.
I could absolutely see them productizing this
if they wanted to.
I don't know if they will.
What Ryan told us is essentially it's enough
for them already, because they have a situation
where they have systems on AWS,
they have systems on Azure.
I'm assuming, he didn't tell me this,
but they have multi-provider systems
and they want a LAN where they can have secure
MySQL things happen or secure Samba things happen.
Or you can sort of abstract that away
and not your individual hosts don't have to deal
with that anymore, they can just receive traffic.
I think that cross-provider thing is gonna be
what makes this really take off.
If they keep talking about it like that,
that's gonna click with people.
All this talk about hybrid cloud,
I mean, one of the providers could be your own LAN.
Absolutely.
I have a system on Linode,
I have a system on DigitalOcean,
and we have the Reaper box here.
I would like to connect all three of them together.
Both of these allow for that.
I think it'd just be on one private network.
Flat network.
I haven't done extensive testing,
but I did a little bit last night,
just being in my house in the studio
and performance is looking good.
That was one of my concerns with Tink.
It's older and not necessarily optimized for performance,
but this is using new quick crypto and it did great.
Yeah, I guess it's worth mentioning.
Neither one of them run in the kernel.
Yeah, just using the ton driver.
Yeah, which is perfectly fine.
I think there might be probably
a slightly higher performance story with Nebula than Tink.
Yeah, I believe so.
I guess that's something to consider
when you have a lot of nodes, right?
Because who's talked about 500 nodes
and Ryan talked about thousands of nodes.
So that's something to consider too.
Yeah, and because of the key base
and the certificate based authentication,
you don't have to do anything to add a new node.
I mean, the certificate authority
needs to sign the new keys for that node,
but that's it because the lighthouse
actually takes care of communicating those details.
So if I want to go talk to Chris's laptop,
I don't know where that is.
And he might not trust that I should talk to them.
All I have to do is go share my information.
And because it's signed with the certificate authority,
it's all good, that's it.
Yep, so if you have any questions,
go to linuxunplug.com slash contact
because we're still tooling away with this.
So we're having a lot of fun building networks
and I think we're gonna get my net situation resolved.
I don't know exactly how,
but I think we're gonna get there.
We'll figure it out, right Wes?
Well, maybe we'll have to ask Ryan, we'll see.
I think we might.
Okay, let's do some feedback.
Before we go, I said I want to do some more feedback
and follow up in this here show
and people took me up on it, linuxunplug.com slash contact.
Our first one, Matthias,
who says he's a happy Manjaro user in Germany.
He had to mention that, didn't he?
Of course.
No, I love it.
I actually love to know.
He has a question about command line autocompletes.
Short question, a while ago,
you guys mentioned a cool little tool for the command line
that helps me remember my complicated commands
and make suggestions while I start typing,
but I forgot the name of it.
I think he might be talking about fish shell.
We do talk about fish shell basically all the time
and it's fantastic.
Fish shell is now the thing that I install
almost immediately on a new Linux box
and I go into the Etsy password file
and at that right there, I replace my shell with fish.
Now, another one we've I think mentioned before
is fzf, the little command line tool, the fuzzy finder,
and that also will search your command line history.
So I was thinking it could be that one too.
So that's a good one.
Do you want to toss a link?
Absolutely.
In the news.
All right, Liam writes, hello, Chris.
I've also been experiencing random lag
or skipping on my workstation
with an NVIDIA GTX 1060 after I upgraded to Fedora 31.
I was wondering if you ever got anywhere
with the mouse lag or if it's an active bug
somewhere I could contribute to.
Oh, I like what you ended up doing.
This is a good sort of come clean moment.
I hadn't actually thought about.
I was like, I'll do an update.
Well, okay.
So, you know, I really can't stand lag.
This is a particularly weak spot for me.
So what I did was I burned the entire house down.
I decided I wanted to switch to plasma for a bit
to see if there was an issue over there.
So then I went down the rabbit hole
of trying to find a great plasma implementation.
Really, I actually downloaded the neon ISO.
I was going to go just with neon again
because I had such a great experience last time.
I'm imagining you standing in front of your computer,
USB drive in hand, sort of waffling,
considering just about to plug it in.
That is literally the situation.
I'm not kidding.
And I came across and I said,
Self, you know, you don't want to always...
You need to challenge your assumptions about distro self
because I had a real kind of realization
when we put Fedora on that there server.
It went so good, Wes.
I was like, this is way better than I expected.
I came with all these assumptions about Fedora
on the server and I was schooled.
So I thought, I need to give Manjaro like a real go again
because my early conceptions of Manjaro are not really...
Manjaro has come so far.
It really has.
And it's really one of the great distros.
And I thought, I got to try out one of the greats.
So I pulled down their plasma edition of Manjaro
and I formatted my workstation yet again
and I put Manjaro plasma edition on there.
I didn't think I'd ever see you remove Fedora.
I really am not trying to be a distro hopper guy.
I just want to get my work done,
but somehow I have fallen into this trap
of working on my tools again.
Yeah, maybe that's the thing I should be doing
at the end of the year, get myself positioned for 2020.
Yeah, maybe that's what I'll tell myself.
Nice new workstation, everything working ideally,
no mouse leg.
Here's the thing, Wes, still had mouse leg.
No.
Yep, on plasma, using X instead of Wayland,
Kwin, AMD graphics, still had mouse leg.
Have you considered just getting a faster mouse?
Well, I just thought about locking myself
in the bathroom, honestly, I was so upset.
Can you switch to just the console directly?
Because that's, you know.
Yeah, yeah.
So I went down, again, different threads
and a common thread I kept coming across
was people were noticing this issue
when they were experiencing high disk IO
and GPU usage at the same time.
Not gaming types of usage, but just like things
that use the GPU on the Linux desktop,
which Chrome uses the hell out of the disk cache
and the GPU when it's rendering a page.
And that is primarily when I would notice it,
when I'd have a video or something playing perhaps,
or something going on.
Maybe you've opened a bunch of new tabs.
And of course, I've got multiple monitors,
even though I've got like an AMD 560 in there, whatever,
570 actually, I'd have the issue, I'd have leg.
I'd still, even on plasma, I'd have the damn mouse leg.
So I thought, okay, well, maybe I could reduce some of this.
I can't really reduce the GPU usage.
That's modern browsers, but can I reduce disk IO?
And so I decided to load up profile sync daemon,
which sim links and syncs your browser profile directories
to RAM using tempFS and RAM.
Thus, it reduces the hard drive calls.
It speeds up your browser.
I wanna make it clear here.
I'm doing this on a really nice MVNE, okay?
I've got-
It's not some 5400 RPM.
No, it's no slouch.
I legitimately noticed an improvement when I did this.
I mean, have you tried RAM?
It's the best.
It is the best.
Everything's faster.
What's great about profile sync daemon,
besides the fact that it could cause you
to lose your entire profile,
is that it supports like all of the browsers,
even Vivaldi, and I'm not sure about Brave,
but like all the different browsers.
And it automatically detects them if you like.
And it handles and manages the syncing to RAM and back.
So you wanna properly close and open your browser
at the beginning and the end of your day
to give it a chance to sync.
You'll notice if you watch the cache usage
from the kernel file system cache,
you'll notice if you watch that indicator closely,
you can see it blast the cache
as profile sync daemon does it sync.
It just, it saturates.
It complete on my system with, I think this box,
it's either 32 or 64 gigs of RAM.
I mean, it just uses a ton of cache for like 15 seconds.
It's really fast because it's going from RAM to an MVNE.
But if you like were to lock up and hit reboot,
it would never have had a chance
to write that profile back to disk.
And so any changes would be lost.
Now, the nice thing is that's pretty much mitigated
these days by browser sync for the most part.
So it's constantly syncing to the Vivaldi cloud service.
And yeah, I'm on Vivaldi too.
A part of this I switched over to Vivaldi.
That's a whole nother story.
But so thank you for asking about the mouse leg.
Hey, you know, it works out well too
because of course profile sync daemon is in the AUR.
Of course it is.
Yeah, but it's pretty much available for anything.
I think my suspicion is,
is that something is no longer great on my box
or perhaps my original suspicion is that
around kernel 5.2 time period,
somewhere when I transitioned from the four series kernel
from an older distribution
to the five series kernels on this box,
that's when these problems manifested.
I do suspect if I were willing
to not have the latest goodies.
So you're saying you're going to switch to Neon.
Yeah, cause you're like what on 4.16 or something?
Well, let's find out.
Because I never had leg on Neon, same hardware.
4.15 baby.
Yeah, and when I use the gnome implementation of Ubuntu,
that's on 1804, I didn't have mouse leg.
It wasn't until I went to five series kernels
that I started getting mouse leg.
And I wonder if this is never going to be fixed.
It's kind of getting, you know, three year old box now,
something like that, getting there two and a half,
something people are not going to be releasing new drivers
for it's just, I think I'm doomed.
So my solution is to just reduce the disk IO
while using GPU for a web rendering stuff.
It doesn't seem to affect games.
It doesn't seem to affect that stuff.
How well does this actually work?
I mean, do you still get occasional mouse leg
or is it pretty much done?
Very, very, very well.
Nearly gone.
Excellent.
Maybe a glitch or two a day now,
instead of every few minutes.
It's a huge difference.
So you can use your nice computer now.
Yeah, so give that a go and see if that works for you.
I don't know if it will.
Okay, now we've got to get out of here,
but we'll do one more.
Cause I promise, towards the end of the video,
we'll start doing this.
And we'll do another batch,
if you'd like linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
But I think this is a good one to end on.
Cameron writes in, regarding some requests for feedback,
I'd love to have a forum for the podcast
or better yet for Jupiter broadcasting as a whole.
So the listeners and maybe you guys can all communicate
and share info, news, et cetera.
So that's something we've actually been talking about
internally. Indeed.
We have been around for so long now
that we have had about three different iterations of,
oh, if you count before Jupiter broadcasting was formed,
probably five different iterations of community forums.
Some of them were so large
that that's actually how we ended up
starting to work with Alan on Scale Engine,
is we had to move on to infrastructure
that could handle the amount of traffic we were getting.
So we definitely have had some in the past,
but they generally over time kind of declined.
And they become a pretty large source of work.
And I want our interactions with the community
to be excited, like we're excited to do it,
not unsure. Yeah, absolutely.
So our current outlets are not quite,
they're not like something on the web.
And that's what's so great about forum software,
because we do have the IRC,
irc.geekshed.net pound Jupiter broadcasting,
hashtag. Octothorp.
Octothorp.
So of course we have that,
that's a persistent chat going all the time.
But we also have the Telegram group,
jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Telegram.
There's over a thousand people in there chatting,
usually about a hundred online at any given time.
And then last but not least,
we actually have a discord too.
We don't do much with it,
but there is a Jupiter broadcasting discord
and I'll put a link in the show notes.
I mentioned all of those because we do have some outlets
of persistent chat where you can come
and talk about the shows.
But the nice thing about forums is you've got topics,
you can, you know, episode 329 of Linux Unplugged,
where they talked about flat networks.
It is a different thing, it's its own beast.
So I could be convinced of it again.
Probably need some feedback about it though.
And what would be the advantage of that,
say over the Jupiter Broadcasting subreddit,
which we've never really mentioned,
but we have a Jupiter Broadcasting subreddit,
which also kind of acts in that forum capacity,
but not everybody wants a Reddit account,
but not everybody wants to go make a forum account.
So feedback, linuxunplugged.com slash contact,
probably won't read them all on air,
but we will read them off air
and help it inform our decision.
So there you have it.
We did some feedback.
Really quick before we run,
also just a few picks to mention because I love these.
Check out Wee Slack.
It's a WeChat plugin for Slack
and its developer was Ryan, our guest today.
It has its own community now, it's its own thing,
but he started it all.
Yeah, he no longer is even involved,
but it's still a thing.
So if you want to use Slack still in an IRC client,
it's possible using Wee Slack.
And then I came across,
I don't even know how I'm gonna say this one, Grinds.
What do you say, Wes, give it a shot.
Yeah, oh, why do you do this to me?
Geerins. Geerins. Geerins.
This is a fairly slick GTK desktop front end to Plex.
We finally have one.
Why would you want this, you say?
I'll tell you why, because browsers are monsters.
They take everything, your disk, your CPU, your RAM.
They make your damn mouse leg.
They are the worst.
They're huge.
One tab takes up way more CPU and memory
than it should.
And during some of our benchmarks,
we have seen when a system gets loaded,
we have seen how a browser tab can bring a system
down to its knees when it's under load.
It's crazy.
This does none of that.
It's a native, clean client.
When it's sitting there and you're not playing anything,
it's not using any resources.
It just sits there quietly,
doesn't peg your CPU constantly.
And when you do want to play,
it takes only the amount of resources
it takes to just decode the video,
which is probably pretty damn fast on your system.
It's glorious.
And it's a GTK application,
so it looks great on your GNOME shell.
What am I going to do with all this extra CPU time?
I don't know.
Run Slack probably.
But I was so elated when I found that
because I like to have like,
I have series on Plex that are like my barely kind of
just background stuff that I play while working.
So now throwing it up on a screen
and not eating a bunch of resources while I'm working
is fantastic.
Trying to reduce resource usage,
even though I have 12 cores.
It's ridiculous.
Mr. Payne, you're over there on the Tech Snaps,
techsnaps.systems.
Techsnaps.systems.
There's no S on the Tech Snap,
but I like saying it.
Don't confuse everyone.
I like saying it.
I like it.
So yeah, I've been really enjoying it.
Give my rounds of compliments to Mr. Salter
because I think he's really,
both of you really hit your groove
for a while now on that show.
So it's been the sequence like good for a while, you know?
I love that.
Totally agree.
Awesome show.
And of course, Alex and I on Self Hosted next week.
Brand new episode of Self Hosted.
Oh, I'm excited.
Tomorrow, live stream, live Self Hosted hack tomorrow,
Wednesday, jblive.tv,
10.30 a.m. Jupiter Broadcasting time.
Alex is going to do a little live hacking on the stream.
Oh.
Just a little Self Hosted bobo.
Bomo bobo for Self Hosto.
ESP8266 hacking and LSDs and all that kind of stuff.
Yeah.
Sounds like just what we need to start up the holidays.
I know.
I love it.
Of course, all of that can be found
at jupitbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
We're at ledxunplugged.com.
And we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Ah!
The party of the century.
Before we get out of here, JBtitles.com, I have a question for the virtual lug.
Does anybody own a USB stick that they could still find that is less than 16 gigabytes?
Megabytes.
Megabytes?
We have one for...
No, megabytes.
Hey, I mean...
Joe does not play.
Yeah, Joe has a 16 megabyte SD card.
No, not megabytes.
Oh, wow.
I can't believe that.
Yeah, I have a 256 megabyte SD card.
256 is also here.
Oh, I thought I'd be Mr. Bregsy here with my four gigabytes.
Yeah, he just keeps his favorite GIF, just one on there.
Oh, sorry, GIF.
Is that what you prefer?
Hey, do you remember those early digital cameras that actually took an entire floppy disk?
They took a 1.4 megabyte floppy disk and then they saved the horrible JPEGs to the floppy?
Yeah, I think it was a Canon camera and I think you could shoot...
You could get 12 photos on one floppy, I believe.
You would have killed for 16 megabytes back then.