You know, I mean right now where do they tell you not where do they tell you not to use it?
Because this is kde.org's announcement and maybe they do say somewhere in here. I haven't read the entire thing
It says kde ships plasma 5.0 and so it might it might say don't use it yet
I don't know but I mean in here
It's not really looking like it looks like it's trying to market itself to new users
It does talk about having Wayland technology previews, but that's okay. That's a given
They said that they until they say it's ready to use it for to put be prepared production
They have inherently not saying that it is they don't have to every time they make a release
This is not ready. Like for example, I mean gnome was garbage until 3.6. I
Would argue 312 but okay, maybe 310
Well, I mean garbage like fundamentally not workable not usable like three six where it became where you could actually use it
Yeah, I mean, but okay
Do you see but do you see what I'm saying how what you're what you're saying essentially calls for a tribal knowledge of?
How this works like yeah, they're not clear about their their kde is not being clear about what is what is usable and what?
Is not that's true
But that's pretty much all de's and you could like you could say well
Kde also has a lot of other problems in the fact that their their website looks like it was made ten years ago
By the same time they have other websites that are like sub projects that look nice like plasma mobile looks nice
But they have their main one looks like crap
So like they have a lot of things that they need to work on
But they're not they until they say that it actually is ready to go for like just production
You know releases then that's why for is still the stable and that's why they still suggest it
It's just not
Like if for example, I would love to have I just whatever I I mean that is
So, okay, so let's let's take everything you've just said and I will grant you all of it is 100% true
And so now if you grant me that like most new people or let's not even say new people
I would say casual linux users and new linux users people who don't closely follow linux news and things like that
I don't think it's unreasonable for them to think that something called kde plasma
5.4 with a very nice release announcement and press coverage around it
I don't think it's unreasonable for them to think that's production ready 5.4 version 5.4 of something. I
agree
Well, yeah, it's not properly
Announced sure, but there's like for example Katie kabuntu released
1504 with 5.2 which was completely unstable and a garbage decision and I know why they did it because they were trying to get like
Some testing in and there yeah, so they can gradually go to five three and then gradually go to five four
It's like yeah, I get why they did it
But it was still a garbage decision because people who moved it was like, oh kabuntu's got this new KDE and like and it's crap
So and so people when I when someone suggests I want to use
KDE on Ubuntu the current solution is either 1404 or don't touch kabuntu
So is anyone in here using plasma 5 desktop?
I'm using it right now. I have two drives in my 17-inch laptop. I
Have the Wiley wolf alpha 2 and that's you and that's using plasma
5.3.95 pretty current which yeah
It's like I just I just saw that 5.4 got announced today
I'm like, well, I might swap the hard drives and just see if there's a back port for kabuntu
15 no
1504 which I'm running on the other drive
even
Plasma 5.3 point you I still you're so I'm like I've had less crash issues on
5.3.95 then on
3.2
3.2 still crashes on plasma 5 on whatever
I haven't had any issue with the audio app and I'm wondering if their new audio app is causing the problem for you Chris
You know what? I would I would not be surprised if my audio applet didn't install
Simply because it you know
I am in the middle I installed last night and maybe that's one of the few packages that has
Transitioned to the K to plasma 5 for and because I'm not installing the rest of the packages. I didn't get it
But so ww as a fairly consistent plasma 5 desktop user
It is my characterization of its stability consistent with your use cases with the versions previous to version 5 for and it's RC's
Yeah, like even rotten's correct. I'm like 5.2 because like I I've been like I was on like
1404 then I went to 1410 and I was pretty happy with the plasma for it was working great
You know, I didn't really have an issue and then like plasma 5 came out. I'm like that looks really good
I want to try that and it was just like shut down script issues and
It was just I could totally tell a difference between system D and the system in it
that they had previously even between like 1510 and or no 1504 to 1410 and
That was a pretty big difference for me. And then I'm
Just like plasma. It's been crashing consistently since five. It's slowly been getting better. So maybe
Maybe by the next release it will get better. But um, I really don't know. We still have like two months to go, right?
But this is this is what that happened last time like with three to four the same thing happened for the first few versions
It was a beta of release and people were not told it was beta
But in the version 5 they were told it was beta. I mean, I said yes, I specifically remember that transition
I was a KD user at that time and I remember it not being quite this bad for this long
I remember essentially what had happened was it was pretty unstable and then it became more
Functionality and refinement features after release after release after release. It wasn't we're seeing some of that
But I mean, I'm talking fundamental instabilities and I maybe you can blame the Nvidia driver the proprietary Nvidia driver
Darn it, maybe you can blame something else. That's not you know, the plasma desktop, but I
Remember that transition because I lived that transition and I do not remember being this bumpy
First of all, they're also doing a lot more than this time because they they were just adding features from three to four
Yeah, they weren't fundamentally rewriting pretty much everything and changing the way it's structured. And yeah
So there is a lot more for them to do
Yeah, essentially like 80% of the entire project is replayed as being like rebuilt. Well, right, you know, it's funny is in some sense
When no made the transition from gnome 2 to gnome 3 it was obvious. That was such a huge change
It was like they just threw out everything it looked different
It was everything was different
But when when when they went from from the plasma 4 desktop to the plasma 5 desktop
They actually took a lot of work to make sure it looked and functioned very similar
And so the amount of revolutionary change behind the scenes I think is lost a little bit on the average user because so much
functions and looks the same on
Purpose, do you agree?
Um, I think it's confusing for people because there are certain things that are very similar and they look the same especially like the worst
part is that when people use for like
Qt4 kt4 apps inside of qt5 and kte5 or plasma 5 and they look the same
They're like they like but they but they they're wrapped inside the new win interface
I think that's a negative thing because it makes people think that those are like five version apps when they're just actually
Yes, potentially really old apps. I agree. Yes, I agree. That is also kind of confusing
So there's there's kte5, you know plasma 5 and framework 5
They're doing a lot of cool things and I can't wait for them to actually get it where the point where it is stable
But right now it's still not like it's I mean, I haven't tried 5.4 yet, but
They haven't announced that it's ready to go. So I would assume that it's not
Yeah, I'm pretty much using I'm pretty much using
Both versions like 1504 and 1510 alpha 2 on my system
Just like as testing. I'm not full. I'm like using it for like web browsing
Trying out steam games and you know, just seeing how it reacts and how it works
And if I encounter something hopefully I can do a report, you know, that's what I kind of
Trying to keep in the mind. That's really cool data. That's really cool
You know that good for you and you know
One of the things that jumped out at me is their language they used in the release announcement for plasma 5.4
The new volume control applet directly manages pulse audio
It says and I thought that was particularly interesting that set off some ding-ding-dings in my brain and I'm thinking
Hmm, maybe it's time to try it again on a studio machine because I believe if you recall my main issues was it felt
Like that phonon layer there was particularly interfering between when I would hook up. I like a like a
Audio out to the line out on say the bonobo
KDE would still only send the audio to my hdmi out regardless of what I'd set in the in the audio out settings
and I always kind of felt like maybe there was like a miscommunication between
Phone on and pulse audio because if I opened a poof control or poof a controller, whatever you call it
I I could go manually set it still and then it would work fine
But I just couldn't use any of the built-in KDE tools and so when they say in that release announcement that
In fact, I still have it open right here
I'll read it to you because I when I read that I was like, oh what are you I almost felt like they were like
Talking to me here. Here's what they say a new audio volume applet our new audio volume applet works directly with pulse audio
the popular sound server for linux
To give you full control over volume and output settings in beautifully designed simple interface
And I don't know if it's called super simple
But one of the things that jumped out at me is right there in the audio settings. Look at that a volume slider
a volume slider
Took him uh took him a few releases, but we finally got it. I'm happy. I'm a happy boy
This is linux unplugged episode 107 for august 25th
Welcome to linux unplugged your weekly linux talk show that you know now that I think about it
I wish all of our gadgets just ran off of dc power. My name is chris. We got a good show for you today episode
107 not only do I have something that i'm extremely excited to share with you guys that
Only the really linux unplugged crew gets to know about right now
But we'll be we'll be telling everybody down the road, but exclusive right here linux unplugged first and after that
We're going to throw a birthday party for linux. We're going to go in the way back machine and visit. Mr
Linus torvalds in the late 90s a much more humble quieter
Down to earth linus torvalds to celebrate linux's birthday and then there's a big old rumor floating around about ubuntu
We'll get to that and there's a new file system in the world
That kind of accidentally came to be and it turns out it's crazy fast. Even in its early days
It's smoking zfs. It's smoking extended four butter fs. You might need a solid state though
So stay tuned for that and then later you might have heard from linux con that ibm is hooking up with linux
And they're making the mainframe one a mainframe designed to run linux and you got ubuntu on there open
Sousa's are susa's on there. We're going to talk about that and what they're actually doing and it turns out
They're doing kind of what you could do on your pc, but just a lot of it like I mean a lot of it
I'm going to tell you about that and it's kind of quaint after all of that and then
Supporting an open source legend someone who's created a lot of code and someone who's about to create some code that we're going to depend
On even more so ntp was recently um, kind of attacked for asking for support from the community
And uh some folks threw in behind him and we're going to discuss that quote unquote controversy
But I think it's kind of interesting when a community that relies on open source code and uh, these kinds of contributions
Gets a little riled up when somebody comes and asks for money and I wonder what that's about
So we're going to discuss that but before we get into all of that
I got to bring in our virtual lug timer time appropriate greetings l mumble room. Hey guys
Hello
Hey, hey, hey, hey, hello there. Hi there now. I don't know what the chances are that any of you
Are going to be impacted by my first announcement. I'm going to take a moment
Nothing really linux related at the top of the show. I am
Too excited to bury this later in the show
I'm too excited to tease it with an ad break because I want to tell you guys
Those of you who listen on linux unplugged get the 411 first, uh today
Something uh kind of a big moment for me. You know, i've been doing jupyter broadcasting
full time
For I think three years or so. Who knows? Um,
Nobody can tell and uh, one of the things that when you go off and probably a lot of you have ever done your own
Small business might be able to relate to this
Scariest thing you could do when you own your own small business is go get yourself a payment on something because then you know
You got to make the business work, uh, because you got to make payments
Uh, and I kind of got over that like when we hired employees and stuff like I you know
But it never for me it never that was a mental block that never cleared
Uh, like i've never
Since I became full-time, I kibosh on like new house. No good didn't get a new house. Didn't matter couldn't get a new car
We're not getting anything. I don't want any payments because that freaks me out because I now i'm paying for myself
Uh, and so it's been a few years and one of the things through all of that
That has been consistent is man. I've wanted to do a road show. I've wanted to get on the road
I wanted to do a jb road show do meetups broadcast from the road because a it's going to be full of technical issues and
Challenges which sounds like a total nightmare, but it's not
But it's a whole new set of challenges that i've never had to face before so that sounds kind of exciting and b
There's a ton of content in that like if I can't do a show for for a day
But I put up a camera and I document the fact why I can't do a show
I'm going to release that as a show so anyways and get ahead of myself what i'm really excited to say is this morning
I became the proud owner of jupiter broadcasting's first mobile studio. I got an amazing deal on a trailer rv
25 foot rv that uh is uh
Some unfortunate circumstances for the previous owners. We became my good fortune and uh, it needs a little work
Which is happening right now. It's in the shop right now
And i'm going to have a mobile studio and we are this is going to be the rig that I will take and broadcast from
When we do the linux action show cribs edition where I go over to noah's house
So i'm going to start on the here on the west coast
And i'm going to drive across us state uh us2
So if you are anywhere on us highway 2 between uh, japan and korea
If you are anywhere on us highway 2 between the pacific ocean and grand force north dakota
I would love to come say hi to you and I will be driving from the from the west coast to noah's house
When I get there, we will do a last cribs edition on noah's automated house
We'll find the spots that are powered by linux and the spots
I believe there are a few spots that are not powered by linux and I will reveal those spots on the show
Wouldn't it be interesting if noah had a dark?
dark
Redmond based secret. I will discover it and I will air it that dirty laundry when I get over there
So the idea is i'm going to uh, this is in this is in progress right now. It just all happened this morning
I'm going to eventually convert it into a mobile studio over the next month
Um on a budget it's going to be pretty pretty lean but around uh mid september ideally, um
Like around, you know, the september 19th time frame will hit the road and be doing shows from the road in the mobile
jb2
Studio so i'm very very excited because I did tech talk early this morning
So I could go out there did an inspection made sure everything checked out
And uh boy, am I pumped and I have no idea what i'm doing
Like i'm gonna have to run off batteries. I'm gonna have to run off water tanks. I'm gonna have to flush my poop
Yes, and imacon it has the first meetup
Imacon tell the good folks where we're meeting up actually because uh, it's pretty exciting
So we're gonna do a meetups. I want to do as many meetups along the way as possible
So go to jupiter broadcasting.com slash meet up i'm i'm right now
I'm kind of planning for like a 17 day road trip to give lots of time to come say hi to folks
Uh, I know I know it's in spokane imacon. I mean the brewery that we're going to be going to it's a super cool place
And uh, we're going to do meetups along the way and so go to meetup.com slash jupiter broadcasting to sign up for that
And uh, and there you go the steam plant steam plant in spokane will be our probably our first meetup
Along the way i'm really pumped. I'm super excited and I bet it's going to be awful
The good news is I happen to be tight with a mobile carrier
So I think i'm going to get a hookup on data connectivity that said though
Uh, if you have any ideas how to boost signal like on a budget because like I don't have
A lot of money to do this
But I need to be able to get like any kind of scrap of signal I can get and get it into
The mobile studio
So if you have any ideas on how to do that, please email me chris at jupiter broadcasting.com
Or any kind of thing like that anything that you think would be very useful for me to do
No to do a mobile road trip and i'm probably going to be doing some of the test broadcasts from it before we get going
But uh, yeah
Oh, yeah. I'm a con. You're first on the list. Don't worry. So i'm really excited and uh,
We'll tell you more about it as it gets going. Um
and I just
I was going to do this road trip in my in my truck or I was actually thinking about renting an rv
Because uh, who the hell wants an rv? But uh, if I but the deal I got this actually works out to be almost
If we take this one road trip, uh, it actually works out to be um, just about half the cost of renting the rv to begin
With so it's it's almost a no-brainer and then we can invest in actually setting up as a mobile studio
And so uh trip one is kind of hey, maybe we'll go to grand forks
We're going to do the last cribs and this is going to be like me kind of learning what i'm doing because it's a very
challenging drive in some aspects
trip two though
You know, I think then it's going to be like going to conventions like wouldn't it be great for scale?
To uh, just take the rig down to scale and be able to broadcast live from outside of scale
And then we have control over our broadcasting environment because right now one of the trickiest things
Is getting control over the broadcast environment at conventions because you're really uh,
It's funny. It's a mixed bag between uh, no provisioned ethernet to uh unions that actually object to you broadcasting
In their area, like it's a wide range of issues that I never ever thought i'd have to deal with
So I kind of I kind of find it
uh kind of appealing actually
So anyways, that's my news and uh, you'll see that rolled into uh content
And also there's going to be a lot of stuff for our patrons that is going to be wrapped into this too
So if you go to patreon.com slash today
Uh, you'll find out more about that down the road and i'm really excited
We're going to go crash a kernel linux's pad like uh d1 says in the chat room and we'll do a linux action show
From over there and I would really love to meet up with some of you. I'm i'm crazy excited
Something else i'm kind of excited about i'm wondering I think maybe poppy
Maybe it was you I got this from on google plus, but maybe not
I mean you're pretty sharesy on google plus, uh, and i'm i'm hoping this replaces google docs for the jupiter broadcasting crew
It's called hackpad and it's a web-based real-time wiki
Dropbox bought them a while back and now is open sourced and and placed it up on github a real-time web-based wiki now
Talk about an awesome way to make some serious podcast show notes and hackpad is web-based real-time wiki based on the open source etherpad
Collaborative document editor the etherpad package you guys might or may not be familiar with i've drooled about it quite a bit in the past
and uh
Now, uh, the the dropbox folks have posted up online. It's a whole bunch of javascript and jquery and uh, node.js stuff, but uh
If anybody out there like has a droplet and an implementation of this
I would love to check it out because I am biting at the chomp chomping at the bite. What is that called chomping at the bit?
to replace google docs now in the uh
In the mumble room is somebody who's very familiar with podcast show notes
Uh, and those of you who may have listened to a few other linux podcasts you there's a guy
You probably are not familiar with him actually because I mean he doesn't he doesn't really get on many shows
but from time to time he shows up on a couple of podcasts and uh
His name is joe now joe help me. Is it joe resinger joe? Is that how you pronounce? Is it risinger joe?
How do you pronounce that last name?
Ressington now joe i've never heard of your name before where maybe if uh, if i've maybe heard that
What kind of shows would I have possibly have heard your name on before?
Well, you're gonna let me plug all my shows. Yeah, absolutely. How long have you got?
Hey joe, if you're if you're willing to take the time to come on you can plug away. Go ahead
Okay, linux luddites is the kind of main one and that's a show where we try all the latest free and open source software
And then decide that we like the old stuff better
um recently just launched the pie podcast, which is a show about the raspberry pie with wimpy
He was the first guest on there
um, and I also sometimes guest host on mintcast which is the show by the linux mint community for all users of linux
And um, oh, yeah, I occasionally guest on the ubuntu podcast, but uh only when they have me only when ax not available
Uh, very good, so what do you use do you have a standardized solution for all I mean you do a lot of shows
You must constantly be having the show note challenge. What do you do?
Google docs simple as that drive. Does it drive you crazy for show notes or do you find it workable?
And I find it really good. I can use it on my phone. I can use it on the laptop. That is on a tablet
And uh, it's it's brilliant. I think now what about and maybe see this is something we do
That's kind of unique and maybe this is why you don't have a challenge with it is what what we compose in the doc
Literally gets copy pasted onto the web page. We write we write all of our show notes and markdown
so that way we only do the work once and we structure it so that way it can be pasted right into the show notes, but
google docs was never created with the intention of you writing anything in any kind of
Markdown language at all and so it's constantly trying to help by like indenting and and all kinds of things
I just find it to be a nightmare. Not only that
but I find it to be strikingly ironic that
that you know, uh
Many of the largest open source podcasts are being created
in a very proprietary
System that is controlled by google. Like it's just kind of ironic. We're all doing it
Because it's the best solution, but it seems like
Not all of us are doing it chris. Oh
Yeah, we use uh etherpad oh and how does that work for you bobby
Well, you can put your markdown in there and not worry about something automatically automagically screwing with it
um, it's not as friendly as google docs and uh
It's not as straightforward to share with like guest presenter joe came on as a guest presenter recently
And we had to monkey about a little bit. So yeah, it's you know, there's
Ease of use versus you know being freedom lovers and uh and wanting to host the stuff yourself, really and so
Uh how what is the process when joe wants to come on?
Do you have to create him an account and then what like is that?
What did you make him a user id and that kind of stuff?
So that's what we should do
Like a guest account or something, right?
Yeah, we should do that secret source poppy. Don't know
Yeah, what yeah
What I actually do is I uh
I copy the notes onto my local pc and then I print them out and I fax them over to him
And then he reads them
Listen you could consider it an advertising fee for coming on the show week after week now
I just curious because i'm really considering switching to etherpad
But it sounds very clunky and the primary issue that I have is like for example on today's episode
I just wanted to just quickly loop ham radio into the show notes. It's a boom share it
I added his collab email address bob's your uncle and now he's looped in and it takes me
10 seconds so I can do it while i'm on air and while i'm talking to you at the same time and that
seems invaluable you don't you don't find that to be a
like a barrier
The guy you looped in to get in to talk about how he's using colab instead of using google
You forced him to use google in order to contribute to your show. Yes. Yes. That's correct. Okay, just checking
You avoided the question, but all right, very good. Hey, why let's see. I got another question. Maybe you could avoid for me
Uh, apparently canonical is killing the ubuntu software center with a lot of vengeance according to the var guy
Desktop app stores are dead and their mobile oriented equivalents are the future
That's the message from canonical
He says which is uh
Quietly made clear that it intends to jettison the software center in ubuntu linux to focus on mobile apps for snappy ubuntu core
He says that the software center is dead and that canonical plant has no plans
Uh in respect the the depreciation of the ubuntu software center means that canonical's open source operating system will be unique in another
important way from the rest of linux world
I don't know what to make of this poppy
But there's a lot of people talking there's a lot of people writing a lot of things about the software center
Do you have any opinions on all of this media buzz?
Is it all just like are people just getting ahead of themselves or is there actually some real fire to the smoke that i'm not seeing?
I I like the fact that the var guy talks about how canonical is killing the software center and on the same day softpedia
Have an article titled. No canonical is not killing. Yes
Who do you believe I don't know who do you believe i'm gonna believe you
The the the var guy's article points to um
I had a really well written article on I think it's on pcworld.com
um, which
Kind of summarizes the state of play of the ubuntu software center the fact that it's not had a lot of maintenance
You know, we've talked about this in the past with wimpy
And you know when he was talking about the rationale for removing it from the default ubuntu marty install, you know
It's not had a lot of love and it's not super performant and there are problems with it
And there have been problems with the developers have experienced putting their apps in the store
um, and
Yeah, that's that's all well known. There's nothing new here
Well, that's what I mean it I don't know where they I mean they they kind of pull a bunch of threads together and maybe
Um put two and two together and it's not an unreasonable thing to think
That an application that where the upstream isn't actually doing any active development or maintenance
Is dead, you know, that's that's a reasonable conclusion to draw
But we've got an lts around the corner
So, you know, what are we going to do there? Are we going to drop the ubuntu software center from 1604?
and then have
no
Default graphical way to install applications that that seems that seems like not a good idea for people who are upgrading from 1404
So I I don't quite understand why this makes sense
Um from a you know looking at the distro point of view
But I can understand why on the outside looking in it totally does make sense. You know, it's what pushes my buttons is I I feel like
Like uh, so much controversy and crap gets stirred up just on speculation alone. So it's this seems like particularly
In the in the fact that there's no like announcement
You know to say but there's no announcement saying we are not killing a bunch of software center, right?
So is it reasonable to expect that we are killing it? But equally there's no there's no announcement saying
We are not killing unity 8. Is it reasonable to expect? We are killing that then, you know
Just because it says it doesn't say in the instruction manual don't fill your vhs player full of you know
Washing up liquid doesn't mean you know, you should do it. Thank you
It's you know ridiculous a bit. Yeah. All right, so uh point well taken and that's exactly what was my my take on it as as well
All right, so enough with that today is actually an awesome day to be recording uh linux unplugged
It is linux's big big big birthday
Well big in the sense that uh in the us after this one
That's when you get your big insurance discount and you can rent cars for a much lower price pretty soon
Linux is going to be driving around in some nice cars when it when it travels, but before we get to that and
Something that I have to play for you guys
It is a great moment in time when it was a different linus and linux was a very humble upstart operating system
We're going to cover that we're going to go back in time to the 90s
Uh and talk about that. But first I want to mention digital ocean sponsors of linux unplugged digital oceans
My go-to linux infrastructure and I think it could be yours too. And it's funny. I even say that now
As someone who's been in it for so many years and then became a podcaster and I thought well
I'm never going to do anything on demand
I'll build all my own infrastructure when we when we created and we moved into the jb1 studio
I set up a pretty nice kvm system using um proxmox
And several arch machines doing specific dedicated tasks and a couple of a couple of ubuntu lts machines on there
And I thought this is how i'm going to do infrastructure for jupiter broadcasting
Nope no not once I discovered digital ocean
It just makes so much sense digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you
To get your own linux rig going you could also do free bsd if you want, uh, but I wouldn't hmm
No, i'm kidding
Users can get started in less than 55 seconds and that's really nice. I can't even get a new system setup
In less than 55 seconds in proxmox, maybe if I really blast through it, but i'll probably screw it up
But here's the nuts part
I'm, not even sure that the electricity on the proxmox rig is this cheap because the first the base digital ocean droplet
Five dollars a month and then give you 512 megabytes of ram a 20 gigabyte ssd
one cpu
And a terabyte of transfer that is slick that terabyte of transfer is a lot more than you probably think of I mean
Think about it in terms of your cell phone plan how many how many gigabytes to use on your cell phone plan now apply that
To the fact that you're going to get a terabyte on your digital ocean droplet
And so i've thought about this a little bit and i think you know i'm not really using all of my transfer
They have a really good dashboard that tells you all this stuff and you can get on your phone, too
Uh, so one of the things that's kind of nice is I decided to download the most recent antergos release or antagonos or whatever
And I just you know what like why not continue to seed it for a few hours from my droplet. I have
literally tens and tens and tens and tens of gigabytes to spare so why not just help them out for a little bit like
It's not a big thing
But as as an advocate of that project it feels kind of good and for five dollars a month
I've got own cloud on there. I've got all kinds of other functionality on there
So the fact that i'm just you know, i'm burning a few extra gigabytes doing that. That's awesome
And you can get started right now
For free for two months if you get their five dollar if you use the promo code do unplugged do unplugged one word lowercase
You can apply to your account after the fact too if you forgot to use it
They'll give you a ten dollar credit and of course their pricing plans are pretty straightforward if you want something with more horsepower
It's right. Just do it just you go to this website. They have it right there. They're proud of it
So they don't try to hide it from you. It's just right right up front and center
They also have a lot of really good documentation so you can get a even if you're not a digital ocean user
They have stuff that's just like super applicable
Uh to to managing linux installations because they have editors and they really actually care about that kind of thing
And the best part about digital ocean is I can kind of have a global footprint
They have data center locations in new york san francisco singapore amsterdam germany and london and uh, listen
When I first started deploying servers it was it was literally 1200 a month
So you have the base cost of the server that goes in the rack then you have to rent the rack
You have to rent the power and then you have to commit to a certain percent of bandwidth usage and that's about 12
1300 a month to get it in one freaking data center
And now now I can have a five dollar rig in san francisco a five dollar rig in new york and a five dollar rig in
germany
This just blows my mind. I just I can't even fathom it because then you combine that with the interface
That is so much better than anything I ever ever used and I for a long time
I had to administer vmware esx servers
That were running on top of an old redhat kernel
But forced you
To use windows to administer them and it's just the slowest most pathetic interface now. It's better now
But this is years ago. It was awful and it burned me
It burned me so bad that i'm managing this entire linux infrastructure all linux virtual machines all powered by linux
And I have to use a windows workstation to manage it now today
Digital ocean has this amazing interface written in html5 that works on your mobile device or your desktop
Even even the console access from from post all the way up to login all html5 like slick super nice
Really intuitive and then they have an api on top of that so you can extend it even further
And there's a bunch of community apps that already take advantage of that api because if you're like me
And you're never going to code anything
There's a bunch of good stuff. You can take advantage of so go use the promo code do unplugged
Try it out two months for free go put something up in the cloud. There's a new release of own cloud go play with it
digitalocean.com do unplug and a big big thank you to
And a big big thank you digitalocean for sponsoring linux unplugged
So let's celebrate I I can't play happy birthday as much as I have a soundboard sitting right here
And I would love to be able to play it for you and the value of this is negative. I cannot play it
It is linux's birthday. Well things I can play are things that i've personally recorded and captured negative in the freedom
Dimension so instead i'll play those and i'll tell you about today today august
25th
2015 linux has turned 24 years old and uh, that's pretty super badass
I have a really great write-up from ours technica about it
It took them till about midday to get this posted just before we went on air
They got it up and it's a really great write-up
They go back and they find like uh linus's original post and everybody has seen that like a hundred times or more
But uh, they expand way way beyond that i'm gonna read it just because I mean, let's be honest
This is pretty cool. But uh, this was linus 24 years ago today august 25th in 1991
Hello everybody out there using minix. I'm doing a free operating system
Just a hobby won't be big and professional like gnu for 386 and 486 at clones
There has been brewing this has been brewing since april
And it's starting to get ready
In fact, I remember back then linus never thought it would run on anything but uh certain types of like ide hard drives
Uh, and it took the mainstream press a really long time to figure it out
Like an embarrassingly long time and it's so much so that as an early linux user
I thought maybe i'd I had made a mistake like maybe I I
For a very long time. I thought maybe I was betting on the wrong horse because
Nobody else was seeing what I was seeing. I think
What made linux fast and linux cons?
So electric back then is so many of us felt that way
Oh, i'm the only one that gets it and then you'd go to a fest or you'd go to a lug meetup and you'd meet
Other people that also got it and you would connect with them and you'd realize people get what a big deal linux is
But it took it took the average user and the mainstream much much much much longer
In fact, I have a piece from the computer chronicles. I've played it before on the network, but I absolutely love it
It's only a couple of minutes long and it's a visit to linus torvalds in 1998
And it was sort of like well look the new microsoft product windows 98 is coming out soon
let's go look at the quaint alternative linux created by some guy in his house and and
And you can see the bias in the press
You there's so much you can extract from this if you just take it all in from 1998
Here it is. And I love love looking back at the state of linux so long ago on its birthday
Oh, hold on, let me turn it on
By a finnish programmer named linus torvalds
Linus torvalds
Linus torvalds is a 28 year old software engineer from sweden
In 1991 when he was a student at helsinki university in finland
He wanted to buy a personal computer, but he was not happy with the choice of operating systems
the problem was
The machine is just
Half of what you need. The other part is the software and quite frankly it just sucked
For that one so linus developed his own operating system one he could afford based on unix
I had been programming for half my life at that point. I was 21 20. Yeah 20 21
and
I I just knew that I was the best programmer in the world. I mean
I was young I was brash
uh
and
I thought hey
I can do better than this
Lennox grew from one user to 10 in its first year then a few hundred
As more programmers discovered it they added their own features
Today there are well over five million users and the software is still open source and completely free
Thanks to a lot of programmers all around the world. I mean it's
it's
It's been a lot of people working on it
But even the people who haven't actually made contributions in the form of code
There are lots of people who have contributed in
Testing out things even when they didn't intend to they they did by using it. They tested it
Lennox took another leap in popularity this year when major computer companies including netscape and oracle
Announced their support of the operating system
There is plenty of free software available through the internet, but few commercial applications so far
So how can linux compete with microsoft windows?
Linus says the difference is in the way it competes
linux
Doesn't compete on the terms of the marketplace
uh linux competes on its own terms
which is that
Yes, you can buy it on a cd
But a if you buy one cd, you can install it legally on a hundred machines
uh, and
If you don't want to buy the p and the cd you can actually install it directly over the internet
If linux is given away free of charge. How can anyone build a business selling it?
Va research is one company that is not concerned by the lack of licensing fees
Licensing fees va has built complete ready to use linux systems since 1993
The company now ships an average of 20 systems a day
They are no threat to dell or compact yet. They're dependent on what works best for microsoft
On the other hand we have a lot of leeway there and we have a lot of things that that we can do to make
those things better
We can add to linux we can develop code in linux where it makes things more stable more reliable
And supporting our hardware and our customers better for linus torvalds
His creation may not provide him with a paycheck, but there are other rewards
It's great for your
Kind of self-esteem to have people
Use your system and really enjoy using it
Yeah, it's a it's a great feeling you I mean, I I feel that i've done something relevant for the computer chronicles
I'm, sarah o'brien
So, uh, that's a wow wow, that's a trip down memory lane
That's back in a time when va was still a thing uh linus didn't work for the linux foundation
He did all for free still and uh in you can see in 1998. They were still very skeptical about what it would be
It was just on the precipice. So here we are. I mean next year's 25, uh, and I I don't know
It's just um, it's kind of incredible to look bad to look back like that
And uh, it's just so much has changed so much has changed in the way the press covers it too, uh, which really stands out to me
um watching that clip and uh, you know, uh
Also, the other thing that really stands out to me as a father is at the end there in the video
uh
Linus is putting his daughter into a swing and she's uh, she's just a little girl
And it was just two weeks ago that she was pretty much, you know an adult now
And she was talking about uh diversity
In technology just a couple. I don't know if anybody saw that but uh linus's daughter was uh,
She gave a speech about diversity and women in technology
And we just watched a clip of him putting her in a swing as a baby
It's that's uh, that's amazing that he has been in the public eye now for this long and uh,
How much linux has changed since that clip originally aired on the computer chronicles in uh, 1998
And for those of you who want to look that up
You can look that up that whole episode windows 98 and linux I think is the title and uh, there's a little easter egg in there
If you watch the twit network, uh, mike elgin is in there and uh, his delivery style is exactly like his delivery style
Is today
I'll leave that for you. Anyways, uh moving on. I want to tell you a little bit about uh,
Our next sponsor and then we're going to jump into this new file system
So ting, uh ting, uh
I don't know for sure exactly how my road trip is going to work out
But I think a big uh big part component of it is going to probably involve ting
It's just mobile that makes sense. I'm just going to pay for my usage. That's what I love about ting go to uh,
Linux.ting.com. I mean just go there now anyways just to support this show
Just to learn more about ting and I I just encourage you even if you're not going to switch to ting
Just go take a look because it's it's kind of funny to see like um, there is uh,
If you follow different corporations some people like they put on a pink shirt and a leather jacket and they say some of the same
Stuff that ting says and and that kind of works
Uh other companies like they try to restructure their their pricing plans to make it more similar to ting
And uh as somebody who's been on ting now for two years
I look at this and I go. Oh, it's wow. You guys are finally trying to catch up
Ting is actually making you a little nervous go to linux.ting.com and find out how awesome ting is
It's it's mobile to make sense because there's no contract and you only pay for what you use
It's a flat six dollars for the line and then it's just your usage on top of that
So I got a couple of devices because it's not a big deal. It's just six dollars for the devices. They're all unlocked
They have no whole customer service. So i'm totally comfortable putting like my family on that because
I really at the end of the day. I do not at all want to deal with tech issues. So the fact that they have a
No, whole customer support at 1855 ting ftw between 8 a.m. And 8 p.m
That right there is so nice for me when I recommend it plus they have a gsm and cdma network
So there's a lot of coverage options depending on like what best works for them when noah's out here was interesting
Noah has really good coverage in grand forks using a lot of the same technology
He has really good coverage in grand forks using cdma
And when he was out here in the pacific northwest, he switched over to gsm and we were getting 20 megabits
Right here 20 megabits right here in the jb1 studio on the gsm
So it's that's what's cool about ting is if you're even just a little bit savvy
You can make those kind of command decisions for yourself. Oh cdma is better here gsm is better there
I want data
I want to call you know all those kinds of things and you just pay for your usage ting doesn't care if you turn on
The hot spot and they have a they have a dashboard that helps you manage all of it
Go to linux.ting.com right now and try it out linux.ting.com and just go try it out
And just see what you think you can get 25 off your first month of service or 25 off your first device
They have a lot of really inexpensive devices and a lot of really great devices and a lot of data only devices
They have a savings calculator. Click that just kind of get an idea of what you would save and i'm asking you even if you've just uh,
Recently got a contract to try it out. The reason I suggest that is they have an early termination relief program
So if you kind of have second thoughts about signing up for a contract and you know
It's funny because you kind of got burned if you recently got in a contract even I don't know in the last six months
I mean these contracts how long are they two years now? So even in the last year if you got in a contract
Didn't you just get burned?
Because verizon just said oh contracts. Well, we're going to do something different. Of course, you're going to pay more, aren't you?
Yeah, you're going to pay more but we're not doing contracts anymore. Oh that really nice new smartphone
Yeah, just pay us 22 a month for that
It's a good system, I don't blame them for trying to do it
I mean, yeah, it's making them a whole lot of money and wall street loves it, but i'll be honest with you. It's
just
Awful linux.ting.com go there. No contract. No early termination fee. They have an early termination relief program
And you can get a great device that's unlocked linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring
linux unplugged, okay, so uh, you know
For quite a while. I was running my rigs on butter fs
And of course i'm always doing that tech snap with alan. He's going on and on about zfs all the time
And I I eventually gave up on butter fs
I switched over to as xfs and for my machines and i've been pretty happy but I kind of wish it had a little more
Modern feature set and that's why this story has gotten my attention
Maybe a lot of you saw it too a new linux file system that aims for speed while having some zfs
Or as you americans say it zfs butter fs like features
and uh
I don't know really much about it because it's super super super super new and it's totally not ready for production
But it's called bcash fs and it's based on bcash
The linux kernel block layer cache for pairing a large capacity hard drive with a low capacity
High performance solid state drive to act as a cache in developing this block layer system kent overstreet now
Remember that name overstreet, which is a great name, by the way
And by the way before I talk my ass off and I sound like a jerk if anybody knows more about bcash
Please feel free to speak up
i'm, just based on my research and
Things like that. I'm going to regurgitate what I have learned today and yesterday
But if you are in the mumble room or in the chat room, you know more
Absolutely, please let me know but anyways
The idea here is you kind of get like uh, apple's uh, uh
Effect and and the other effects where you can have some stuff on on your on your big spinning disk and some stuff on
Your solid state disk that you get to more more often and in the process kent overstreet realized that they're basically writing their own file system
When in his own words, he says the bcash code base has been evolving and metastasizing into a full-blown general purpose posix file system
A modern copy-on-write file system with checksum in compression multiple device support caching
And eventually even snapshots are in the works and all other kinds of nifty features
We can already envision I and other people are working on bcash
We realized that we were working on was almost by accident a good chunk of the functionality of full-blown file system needs
And there was really a clean and elegant design to be had if we took the time and ran with it
Bcash itself has been in the linux kernel since kernel 3.14 in 2013
now, uh
It is not anywhere near ready today
But he's aiming to add file system features that would match the performance and reliability of extended 4
And have the features of butter fs and zfs
That's kind of the goal right now
Bcash fs supports multiple disk drives today
caching tiering
native zlib file system compression support which
File system compression support is not like file system compression in the 90s and in the 80s
We now have i7 cpus
And massive amounts of disk bandwidth. It is now faster to compress and decompress data off a drive
Than it is to read uncompressed data. It's it's unbelievable, but i've actually done my own tests for writing media
And it is fantastic. If you have a great processor, you know overstreets announcement
He stated some performance numbers for bcash fs compared to extended 4 and xfs and butter fs and he says it's looking really good
so
I was curious. He says it's looking really good. It's looking real good. He says well
I actually put the numbers in the show notes. It's looking fantastic. It's early days, but some of these benchmarks
Because bcash fs in its early state is already outperforming extended 4 and butter fs not by a lot
But a little bit in most circumstances
And yes zfs
Not all though. There are some circumstances where extended 4 is definitely outperforming bcash but uh,
Today right now
It's looking really really good. And these are all based on the early ferronics numbers. So, uh, yeah salt and all but uh,
Uh,
For example on the compile benchmark
That's specifically like when you're compiling something where bcash really sucked but not like worse than anything else
It turns out all these different file systems suck really bad when you're compiling software
It's like a it's like a worst case scenario for file systems. Sorry developers. Uh, and so uh, bcash fs has got your back though
Uh 140 milliseconds is what bcash clocked in and in at uh extended 4 for this particular test 299
butter fs 164 xfs 209
uh, and these numbers are all arbitrary, but they're just
The numbers themselves don't necessarily matter except for within the context of all on the same system all basic a baseline performance here
This system is really really fast
It is really set up to take advantage of many things that we attribute to butter fs and zfs today
and it's good to go and so
I I gotta ask the mumble room
Are we ready for another file system? I mean should we just be waiting for butter fs to stabilize or is uh,
Is it too late is is I mean in my opinion? I don't think i'm gonna try butter fs for years
Uh wimpy, I I let's start with you. What do you think?
Uh i'm cautiously optimistic really
Yeah, well, uh like you i've not had
the best success with
uh btree fs
And this is already in development and it's a fair way along
And i'm interested to see how it develops over time because linux does need
Something to go up against zfs and although btree fs has been around for a long long while it doesn't
seem to be
Ready to compete yet
Joe do you follow the file system stuff as a as a ludite yourself? Do you care much? Do you do you think do you think zfs?
Is the new hotness or is what's your what's your opinion? What's your take and opinion on this?
Well starting with btree fs or butter fs as you call it
I remember you and brian talking about that years ago
And we're still in a position where you're not using it and it's not really production ready. I tried
Yeah, exactly
The thing with the file system is is so fundamental to your operating system and everything you do that
You need something that is truly tried and tested
It's not like using an irc client if that crashes, you know, you restart it no problem
But if you are talking about your file system if that is not a hundred percent rock solid
And you could potentially lose data. Okay, fair enough. It all should be backed up and
Everything but then you potentially talking about a lot of time to restore your backups
And so it's a good point. It's not something that I would be particularly interested in
And another thing is that why pile all of this extra functionality on a file system when there are
Things you could use external programs, you know third
For example like lvm which has been in production for years
Yeah, why try and force that stuff into the file system where it doesn't belong as far as i'm concerned. Hmm
That's a really good point. Uh poppy. I wanted to ask you from a production standpoint
I don't actually know a buntu mobile or touch whatever you want to call it
What file system does that use and when you look at this from like I have to ship this to millions of people?
Uh, is there any is there any room for a new up and coming experimental file system?
Yeah, totally. Uh, we use ext on the phone, but I don't think it really matters largely for us because
Um, the vast majority of the software is is delivered as a read-only image
So it could be pretty much any any file system as long as it works because you're not going to corrupt it because it's read-only
Um the applications and your user data sure you that's that's you know
That's different and you're going to be writing there and turning it off while it's doing stuff and all kinds of nasty things
but I don't think
Butter fs could be considered not ready given yola ship their selfish phones with butter fs
And the first thing the the number one email I always get anytime I say something negative about butter fs now or beatry fs
whatever you want to call it is well facebook uses it
And I mean and i've used it and I actually have I have I have a virtual machine
That is like the most critical virtual machine here in the jb1 studio running on butter fs right now
I use it too
Jupiter broadcasting uses butter fs and it's on a super important server that I would be very sad if it crashed
And and I also have used it on two different production systems that were very critical that I had to dump it and go to
Xfs so take that for what it's worth to me. It's
As somebody and and I know I don't mean to be like this guy and I hate to say this
But before I became a podcaster, I was doing it for 14 years
And one of the and for for the biggest chunk of that I was responsible
For the uh as a as a customer if you have a bank where you can do images of your of your check
And you can take a picture of it or your atm scans it
I was responsible for managing the infrastructure that stored all of those images ocrd them and sorted them properly
And I can tell you that file system reliability is something that I became intimately familiar with
And I I got involved in the industry of data storage and anything that has the track record of butter
Fs is a joke. It looks bad. I'm sorry. It's got nice features
I'm, sorry
It could deliver it could be the future delivery platform of linux software if you listen to lenart pottery
But I have to tell you from somebody who spent a lot of years in in really big iron important data infrastructure
Butter fs is a joke. It is a joke and nobody's going to deploy it
And i'm the the reason why facebook is deploying it is because those systems run in ram
Okay, you guys they run in ram if there's a single problem
They reboot them and they come right back from an image off a tftp server. It doesn't matter
Data integrity doesn't matter and it's very fast
It's a good performance system if you're running your file system out of ram
So butter fs works in that scenario just because facebook uses it and I do not want 200 emails on this topic
Just because facebook uses it doesn't mean it's a production ready file system
It makes linux look bad and that's why I look at these things and you know what?
I just got back from linux con and most of those guys are talking about storing your containers on zfs
Now, how are they doing that? How are they implementing the back end zfs storage?
Are all of those container solutions where they're running thousands of containers?
Are they going to do all that with a zfs implementation in user space? I don't think so
Something's got to give there
so I in my opinion I look at bcash fs and god I
I hope it happens because and I want to take so something else that came out of linux con
Is this linux one mainframe from ibm?
Uh canonical is in on this open suse or sorry
Suse is in on this and I want to play a little bit of this clip because I
I think this this is a good example of how
Big data and and really all of the different applications that we've all heard about all the different open source projects
That we've all we've all heard about can be used at a massive scale beyond anything
We've ever thought of before and why the back end storage for all of this is such such a critical key component to all of this
The linux one server. It's a pretty extraordinary server for analytics specifically for unstructured data
such as live tweets and news
and
Combining the unstructured data with structured data such as postgres maria db and mongo db
Mongo db could be used for customer information in this demo maria db would be used for
financial information and postgres for geospatial data
So for example
In this box, I can I can type any topic such as uh, sessile the lion
And when I do that
What you see are live tweets and news streaming into maria db
And the origin of where these tweets and news are occurring their cities and the countries
Are streaming into postgres at the same time. We have spark analytics running doing sentiment analysis
highlighting negative sentiment in pink and highlighting positive sentiment in green
All right
So what let's let's let's add more load to the linux one server
So what you're going to see are three data feeds
You're going to see postgres maria db and mongo db. This is the icon for the s&p 500 financial data
We're going to start streaming financial data into maria db
And we're going to start streaming trades financial trades
And their point of origins into postgres
We're going to use spark analytics to analyze all this data in mongo db
We're going to have live tweets and news
streaming into maria db
and we're going to add another spark analytics service that
determines how live news and tweet events, uh, uh influence financial markets
This entire infrastructure is written in node.js
It's managed by docker swarm and docker compose
We're using chef to provision applications into docker containers
There's a docker container for postgres a docker container for maria db
And another docker container for mongo db spark analytics is all running in docker containers
So put another way essentially what they're doing on some of these mainframes is they're taking all of the stuff that you might spin up
on your own droplet or your own server and
They're making it all run on one machine and they're doing it all in crazy crazy crazy real time
In fact, i'm going to jump ahead a little bit just so that way we can kind of keep it interesting
And she pulls in real-time sentiment and info and market data for the greek market crash
This is happening live at linux con why she's doing this and what I want you to keep in mind is this system that she's demoing
Is being flooded with real market data and she's not giving an arbitrary query
She's giving a very specific data queries where it has to search through the database and what she gets from this is astounding
What we want to drill into this right? We want to use this information
so let's click on one of these points and what you see here is a globe and
Each of these globes remember where we save that geospatial data for some reason. Where are the trades occurring?
So the red towers is where selling is occurring. The green towers is where buying is occurring
The height of each tower is proportional to the volume of trades that are growing
I want to load up this linux one server. I want to load up this linux one server
I want to get millions of web events to billions events and to do that
You have to type a financial crisis. You let you why not include the trades?
I just want to make sure we understand this we're talking about billions of events now as somebody who processed
All of the customers in washington states image transactions as they're cashing their checks and making transactions
The idea of billions transactions and I used an ibm mainframe running system 390 to do this. This is blowing my mind
So here in europe, um, well, you know
Some some some of the european countries are selling, uh the red towers
But there are some particularly this is interesting again. This is real data in germany. They're buying they're seeing this as an opportunity
So let's spin it around. Let's let's go to india. Okay
India right here the uh, the coastal cities they are selling
New delhi, they are selling they're they're kind of they're kind of pessimistic about uh,
About the greek financial crisis. Let's uh, let's go to china. I'm very interested in china
So china beijing they see this as a buying opportunity. Here's those green towers
shanghai is selling
um
I'm I just like australia, right? So
Here's australia. You can't really see it that well what you see are the coastal cities and they are selling
But as you see this is real-time trades going on at the same time
You see the amount of towers buys and sells proliferating. It's giving the world a mohawk
So let's go to north america. Let's look at the united states. I'll stop right there
So this to me is a fascinating illustration of of where all of these day-to-day open source projects that we hear about
Can have a massive massive impact and if we as linux community as the linux community if we cannot provide the backend storage to this
I
Worry about I worry about long-term relevancy as the platform continues to evolve into containers
As these applications she said at the beginning of this presentation
That all of the different programs are being delivered via container. She also said they're running on top of susa
But if you extract all that out like say you take the vision of the core os project and you make and you make the
App spec such that you can run the same container on a windows machine that has hyper-v on a mac os machine
Mac os 10 machine and on a linux machine and on a bsd machine
Well if at the end of the day what you really really need is a super high performance super well designed file system like zfs
I'm, not sure why you would choose linux as the machine to run the container
uh, maybe i'm just being hyperbolic here, but to me it seems like
Like linux is the most convenient platform because that's where the development is happening the fastest
And people can just jump in and have an impact and deploy something today
But as this matures and the requirements of a container-based environment develop and become more obvious
I don't necessarily think linux is in a good position to actually provide that
That's what i'm worried about
Anybody else in the mumbler want to jump in it might maybe just out of hand
I mean this i'm looking back at this and i'm thinking as a system administrator if i'm going to put all of my
Applications in containers and then once I have them in containers
I can manage them very easily using a plethora of projects that I just saw at linux con
And and i'll really after that all I need is a good back-end storage. That's then i'm pretty much set
Am I missing something here am I getting out of hand? I mean what am I not understanding?
Nobody has any intake nobody hasn't even put on this really
Really? I don't buy that they're gonna that anybody's gonna move their entire stack to like a windows machine
I mean bsd would be the only one that that's what I think that I think poses a threat, you know
But I think it's a so what if I think these problems are solvable ryan
Let me ask you this because you you nailed it. I don't think they're gonna go to windows. I think that'd be crazy
What if though what if what if
Freebsd is kind of I mean, I am totally aware of the timeline of the projects the existence of how long they've been around
The history of them
Just please go with this metaphor. What if freebsd, you know
Like public perception wise is where linux was in that computer chronicles clip. I just played what if today?
People are writing off freebsd as not all that applicable because we have this great superior operating system
That's on all of these systems that has an obvious market advantage with all of this momentum and money behind it. Just like windows had
What if freebsd is at that point? What if it's at the point where like god there's for those people who have who have early vision
For those people that were early on linux that saw this was the way that I should build my info
This is the system. I should build my infrastructure on this is the platform
I should build my product on what if that's where freebsd is at right now and from those of us who are in the entrenched system
We would be the windows users of the 90s right now. What if we can't see it? Is that impossible?
Well, yeah, that's seems like the assumption is that linux is standing still
You know and we're not having things that are like bcash fs
You know, that's that's a attempt to improve
You know upon the file systems that exist under linux and uh, also
If bs if open, you know freebsd wins. So what? I mean, it's still open source
Actually ryan your first point is really well taken, uh, uh bcash fs
docker
cgroups
All of that are actually an indication that linux continues to be the spot where innovation happens
Uh in fact so far linux has moved faster than the rest of the industry hasn't it?
And if you look at where it's gone, there's been a lot of innovation
There's been other systems that have developed containers or zones or jails and you know what? They haven't done a
Blip compared to what docker and containers are doing today. That's a billion dollar industry
Boom right out of the gate and i'll tell you what it's all happening in linux
And the reason is because of the gpl that we all you have it all comes back
I believe to the gpl and I think that is the that is the thing that will continue to be linux's advantage for the
Long term that nothing else has and it is for the long term
I think since the beginning of linux and it is today 24 years later the gpl
That will give it the heads up that'll always keep it ahead of everything else
It'll always keep people when you're investing the next thing when you're planning on the next technology when you're banking on the next platform
You're going to use linux and it's not because of anything else
But the gpl makes it possible the gpl makes that code contribution have to happen
It makes that evolution have to come back to the source and because that evolution has to come back
To the source it always has a little bit of a head advantage of anything else and I I actually I look at where we're at
And I think we're actually regardless of file system regardless of anything else
I as much as I I'm not a richard stallman guy. I'm not a gpl fanboy
But when it comes to our kernel linux made a very very very good choice when he chose the gpl version 2
And I think that continues to be our main advantage going forward and that's why linux is so important
To be our main advantage going forward and and as the market begins to change
And I very very very personally believe that after going to linux con after listening to the things that the leaders of the linux foundation said
After listening to the kernel panel not have a very good response to containers
After listening to them stumble over the fact that they miss c groups to begin with after hearing all of that
It doesn't matter because the gpl at the end of the day, I think keeps the linux kernel more
more competitive
Then perhaps say bsd even though they have a great file system even though they have a great everything else, right?
It doesn't matter
Because if you base something off of the most competitive product in the market today, you have to contribute it back
That momentum just continues to build upon itself
That's what's beautiful about the gpl
So and and there you go get it out of here. So uh, anyways, I that's why I I went
I left linux con and it took me a couple of days. I'll be honest with you
we recorded the linux action show and and I hadn't come to a conclusion on this yet because I was like
shit
What if the people responsible for being like the flag holders of linux the linux foundation?
They're the people that put on linux con
They're the people that called a container con
They're the ones that decided the theme
What if the the quote unquote stewards of linux or the flag holders or whatever you want to call them or the stakeholders?
What if they're the very people ushering in the irrelevance of the platform itself?
I know this sounds really hyperbolic, but i'm just thinking from from like a watching market trends from a very very long term
containerization
and maybe you have to be at linux con itself, but it was
It was in the air
It was unbelievable like uh, the people that weren't delivering their applications via a dock container yet
Were apologizing for it. They're like, yeah, we're really sorry. We're gonna have that done real soon. It's like number one
It's number one on our list like they were apologizing for the fact that you can't get their application in a docker container
I mean it was blowing my mind. I've not seen anything like this. And so I was like geez what if
What if we go to the trouble of putting everything in containers?
And then we just abstract away linux all together
Because these systems these these management systems and there's you know, um, I don't know 55 booths
Literally that are all showing different docker management solutions
And and all of them are basically trying to solve the same problem and all of them
Abstract you away from linux as much as possible. They abstract you away from applications
You could you could become you could become an administrator of these systems never having ever heard the word rpm
Deb or package in your entire life and you could deploy an entire application stack on a web server all around the world
But why is that a bad thing?
I mean we've thought a problem of you know for the longest time people said I don't want to write for linux because I don't
Know I won't it won't run on everything. You know, there are all these different distributions and it's really you know
kind of fragmented and
So a lot of companies said they didn't know what to target and it it probably was a cap
You know a way to get out of creating something for linux but
Um, but now that they have these containers and I think they're only going to become more relevant over time
Continue to become more relevant, you know, this is something that people can target
Linux as a entire platform with a container and not worry about the ins and outs of developing
You know these packages for every single distribution
joe, I don't know if you have any thoughts on containers and docker, but sometimes I
I got the feeling and the opinion. So I'm not exaggerating when I say there's probably nearly 50 booths that all
Were trying to solve the problem of managing docker containers and I started to think to myself
Maybe it's just a mess. Maybe it's not a manageable problem
Maybe that's really just one of these it's going to become like
It's going to become the issue of when you ship an application and you statically link the binaries and all the libraries
You have to continually update that separately from the entire system and all of a sudden becomes a complete management nightmare
Joe, do you have any thoughts on maybe if it's just all hype right now or as a let out yourself?
I'm, just curious because you know, that's your slang. That's your that is after all your brand
Well, it just feels like almost like the dot-com bubble to me all this docker and containerization
Hype and you go to these conferences and it's just what everybody's talking about
And maybe i'm wrong and maybe it really is the future and there is some real
Benefit to it. But to me it feels like the way we were doing things and are currently doing things
Isn't necessarily broken. So why do we need to do it in such a different way?
So I don't know but that's my whole shick, isn't it that I you know, i'm sitting here using xfce. That's why I asked you
Yeah, yeah
Wimpy, I think maybe it's perhaps i've walked away and i've just seen a little glimpse of the enterprise
Maybe there's a little bit of a gap in between the two of you
I don't know if it's a little glimpse of the enterprise. Maybe there could be a mix of traditional and this new
fangled next generation container delivery system
What do you think well if we just take containers out of the equation for the moment this all started with a conversation about
file systems and that linux was not
Competing with zfs with all of the options of file systems. We have we don't have something that competes with zfs
But then there's that presentation there which shows some uh, fantastic analytics using you know postgres
Margo etc. Yeah, we had to change our storage when we had to change our storage back end at work
Um, I couldn't in good conscience build a solution around linux for that
It wasn't the right tool for the job
So we still have all of our processing
Running on linux and it's backed by clusters of postgres and it runs
Uh clusters using celery and all of that is linux
But the storage back end we use was a true nas or is a true nas
Um, and that's obviously, you know free bsd with zfs
and big enterprises
May not know about um true nas and bsd and they would go to perhaps uh netapp
You know, they're they're the big enterprise storage server now
You'll you'll pay a hefty hefty whack for their solutions and I went along to their um sales
You know demo day and it's all very impressive
But it doesn't do anything that true nas doesn't do
And the true nas is a fraction of the price like one tenth of the price for an equivalently
specced system
so the enterprises today will be using netapp and
Give it time
Linux will have a file system that does compete with the likes of zfs
I mean so you and when that time comes it will be it will be the new docker
You know the the fantastic new file system for linux will be the new hot thing in in some year's time
and in the meantime
People are already solving their enterprise storage solutions either by using linux and xfs on lvms
But some are already using uh, betree fs
But I think the file system will be the new hotness in a few years time. Can I just ask what's with the uh,
What's with the dispute between how it's pronounced? I thought it was pretty conclusively pronounced butter fs
No, what do we want to say
I realize it's based on a betree file system. I mean I get that but don't the developers call it butter fs
Yes
Yeah, so it is a betree file system
And betree fs is easier to say than the sort of the bastardized butter fs
So it's just easier to say i'll give it i'll give it I like it and actually
The other reason I like it
The other reason I like it is because I think it's actually good to remind the folks listening what it's based on
Uh, because those of us who are novelle netware admins back in the three days also remember betree based file systems and how many effing problems
We had with them. This is not a new file system hierarchy method
And those of us who had to administer netware
Right good point. Yes those I I know it's funny because you see people listen and they're like, oh chris had file system problem
He doesn't know what he's been doing. Uh, hello
I've been using betree based file systems probably since before you've been using computers most of you out there listening
I had to administer netware systems way back in the day when people still use dost
A dos and they had an auto exec bat file that mapped a drive to a netware server
They had a betree based file system
And you know what? I specifically had to create a file system checker when that server rebooted which
To be honest with you only happened about every 500 days because netware was pretty baller with the uptime
And then they would have to check the file system and do a whole bunch of fixes
And so when butter fs came around or betree fs came around I thought to myself
And my first thought i'm not even kidding you this is years and years and years ago
Like joe said back when brian and I were still doing the linux action show
And maybe I even said this on air. I doubt I did because it sounded like a dumb ass thing to say
But now in retrospect, I think I was right
Really a p3 file system. Is that a good idea because I remember that being
Real bad. I remember that being real bad. Like it was so bad you guys
That I I was happy to move people over to ntfs. Okay
Yeah, that's how mad it was. I was yeah, it's real bad. Okay
I was like, yeah, this is this nt4 server would be better and for a little while it was better
But then I I shook that off, too
uh, yeah
All right
So let's move on and uh, I actually love this next thing because it came from somebody in the community real close to us
And uh, it involves somebody who's been made massive contributions
To uh, the open source community, but first I want to tell you about our friends over at linux academy go over to linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged and get the unplugged discount. That's linuxacademy.com. Slash unplugged
This is a platform to learn more about linux and all of the sort of open source
Platform tools around that. I mean that's everything so as new things crop up. These guys are advocates of open source
They're linux users themselves. So they pretty much jump on it right away
That's one of the great things about the linux academy platform and that's why it kind of keeps its name
A little sharper than pretty much all the other platforms because open source and linux aren't like a bullet point on like the oldest
Make sure we cover how to do nginx. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no as mr
Obama says hey, listen, it's actually what they're all about. They have over
1700 self-paced courses you can go there and learn get deep
Seven plus linux distributions to choose from they've just rolled out a new certified system administrations prep course
It'll be going live very soon and it is the biggest and best they've ever done
And what I love about it is they took people that are super passionate about linux and open source
Which I can completely connect with that
And then they say okay. Well, we have friends that are educators
We know people that are developers and let's create the linux academy platform
And so when you go there you can choose from seven plus linux distributions
And then that when you choose your distrosates like ubuntu or debian or I don't know sent to us or whatever
You choose that and then all of the courseware automatically adjusts to what you want it to be
courseware automatically adjusts to match that distro
And and I can tell you
When we were trying to come up with how to linux like how to like even maybe sort of semi accomplish that like
Yeah, I it was it was an unbelievable task and and so I super respect that
They even just accomplished that part of it
But then to like they then they tied it so that way when the courseware when you need a virtual server
They spin that virtual server up on demand and that virtual server matches
The distro you chose for the courseware
So everything from top to bottom like say you went debian everything top to bottom is debian and then they do scenario based labs
So you actually deploy the entire software stack you're going to learn and so when you go to do it in production
It's not the first time you've done it. That's so critical
I really like that plus if you're doing any of the amazon stuff like any of the aws stuff and they have a lot of aws stuff
You don't have to go rent an aws rig and accidentally pay a whole bunch to amazon for just learning
Learning is just included with your linux academy subscription. So I want you to go to linuxacademy.com
Check them out
They've got a lot of great technologies and they have these nuggets that even if you're a little busy and you know
You got two minutes. You can still get value out of your linux academy subscription. That's what those nuggets do
It's pretty cool
And it's like, you know back up your rig or figure out how to do something really nice in ssh or finally figure out
How to use ip tables come on, you know, you need to do it. It's all over there at linux academy
I mean those nuggets are really nice for a quick deep dive. So if you're like gosh this week or whatever
I just i'm really busy. I don't feel like i'm getting anything out of my subscription
Those nuggets are available to you. They also have an availability planner and you just go in there and say i'm okay this week, you know
You got to be kind of organized but it's kind of slick because you say this week on monday
I'm gonna have x amount of time. I won't have any time tuesday. I won't have any time wednesday
I'm gonna watch tech snap on thursday, and then i'll have a couple hours in the afternoon
And then friday because i'm a geek i'm not going out
So i'm gonna have like all friday evening
And so then you just go in there and you tell it how much time you have available and it'll automatically generate courseware
That matches your availability and including like reminders like hey, bro, you know, you're gonna have a thing on thursday
You better study up
That's kind of nice and then last but not least
It's not really a feature like that. They would put on a bullet point
But their community is stacked full of jupiter broadcasting community members. So if you're having kind of a low moment
Or if you have something to celebrate
There's a lot of your friends over there
That i'll celebrate with you. Um, and a lot of times you'll see me like i'll retweet on on linux academy
When a jupiter broadcasting member gets their certification because they'll often tweet it out and things like that. It's
It's really cool
So and I and I think this is the kind of thing that I would love to see our resources go behind
There's a lot of mainstream larger
educational resources online
That uh, they they really have a limp approach to their linux and open source, you know support. It's it's just a feature for them
and uh
Screw them because they don't understand how important it actually is the linux academy
They get that they they they close that uncanny gap
I think you should go check them out. They're really cool and they also support this show linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thank you to linux academy for sponsoring the linux unplugged program
And i'm glad that they're rolling out all that new stuff. Just go check it out
you'll have your linux foundation certified system administration course online probably, uh, sooner than later linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged linuxacademy.com slash unplugged big thanks to linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
All right, so, uh, he didn't join us today
But producer q5 sis wrote up a blog post about his uh run-in meeting with eric s raimond
He got a chance to chat chat with him for an hour or so at foscon 2015
And uh, he did a blog post about it and it got some traction online
He got some our linux recognition and a few other places
And in there he linked a patreon page for our uh for uh supporting
eric s raimond and um
He's now got up to 40 patrons
But what was kind of weird is the backlash online and uh poppy I know that you saw this. Uh, another folks saw it
Uh, um our friends from the elementary os project saw it
A lot of people thought that it was sort of ridiculous the idea to to pay for somebody
Who's contributing to open source because that's the high the whole idea of free software
Even if it's something really important like ntp
And uh, I look at this and I think this uh, this is kind of this is kind of um
a little sad
Uh eric has got 40 patrons and yet he's contributed to some of the most significant code significant code in in many popular operating systems
Uh, and so poppy did you do you remember do you kind of can you capture the conversation that you saw on google plus?
Because I know you commented on there and and the controversy was kind of sort of being brewed
Yeah, it was uh, daniel foray from the elementary kind of posted that he was sad that uh, someone asking for
uh donations via patreon
Um when that was promoted on our linux on reddit
There were people dogpiling and saying how terrible this was and you know, the guy should just you know
Get a job or whatever or you know, wow, they shouldn't yeah, but but
you know from from my perspective, you know, if that's the
the model that he wants to use in order to
You know put a roof over his head and pay for food for his cat then that's that's his decision
I think it's I personally think it's quite sad that
um
There are people out there making, you know, don't take this personally
There are people out there making video blogs, right? Which is stuff that is somewhat ephemeral
You know that video about how awesome those speakers are or that video about how great that game is or whatever
is very ephemeral and
the stuff that the stuff that eric is making is
Much more permanent and the same goes for any any developer of open source software is way more permanent
you know if you contribute to something especially something as significant as ntp or maybe you contribute to mozilla or something else that's open source and
And widely used that's a that's an investment and people
Long after you're gone long after your contribution is finished will continue to benefit from that work
and it's quite sad that we
value
A bunch of videos posted online over and above a piece of software that we might use under the covers. So I mean, all right
Oh, i'm not I I do follow what you're saying there, but let's be honest
uh
that that's sort of like saying that the document the documentary of
Abraham lincoln are invaluable or the documentaries of the birth of the computer industry are invaluable because i'm not saying they're in
I'm not saying they're not valuable and I you know, I personally back some pretty wacky kickstarter campaigns
Um, just like anyone else
But I think it's a bit sad that someone who is doing such good work
How is code how is code any less infamorable than content?
Because the ntp project is going to be replaced the code
He's working on may very well never even be used. It may be superseded by a completely different project
How many times do we have conversations about?
um, you know in the in the context of a security vulnerability in some piece of software like
You know some mail server or ssh or open ssl or something like that and everyone then takes a
Sits back and take a look and says oh my god that code's been there for 20 years
Right, that's what I mean is someone can make an investment of their time that might take them, you know months
Of their time 20 years ago and that's still being used today that video that someone made about you know
Okay, those those interesting videos that you post at the end of some of your you know, some of your shows
They're interesting, but they're not a massive investment in the future in in
In comparison to something like open ssl or contributions to ntp in my opinion
I and I I actually think that's a pretty common perception. In fact, I think i'm pretty much in the minority here
but i'll tell you poppy what it sounds to me like is it sounds like um
Idealizing developers like they create some sort of unbelievable contribution to society that cannot be replicated in reality. It gets quickly replaced
It's often flawed and not very good
Take system d dash ntp d take any of the new ntp projects being by being created by any of the bsd projects
What what eric is creating is absolutely useful code and very very very much a contribution to the greater open source community
that said
I mean, you know things come and go with code like just like things come and go with content
I don't know if you can attribute a value from one over the other but I will say
In terms the one metric you could maybe value impact is
Uh user use right oftentimes code created something like an infrastructure like like the ntp client
Is used by a great more number of people than content is watched by those people or it is used in a much more important
Scenario, so you could argue those kinds of value. I mean you could say you could say, you know, this particular video or documentary had
You know 50 million people watch it
But you could equally argue that this piece of ntp software has 50 million users
But those 50 million users are using it every day all day in a very critical way
It's not it's not a one-off. It's not a one-off
You know visit the cinema go and see that thing it maybe touched you it's maybe something that you know
Will influence your life in the future, but I doubt it's going any any, you know piece of cinematic
Um, you know is is going to influence 50 million people every single day of their life, right?
Um, and I I don't want to pick on videos. I'm just trying to make the point that some
Developers sometimes get a bit of a bum deal. But what I also think is that when daniel raised this I think
I think he was a little bit glass half empty pessimistic because I think he believes that our linux on reddit
is a reflection of
The community in general and I absolutely don't think it is. Yeah, I agree there and and rotten though
Uh, do you think there's a I I feel like there's a pretty major difference between the user base backing an open source developer
Who maybe contributes to several projects and a company who would only support?
Worked one project in particular here. You can you can come work for us and you can contribute to this project ntp
But only that don't you see a difference there rotten or do you not?
No, because if that person's working on multiple projects and it's benefiting the computer in multiple ways in the community, I mean
Then that's actually a negative. But if they're saying you need to work on this
But they're already working on that and they're benefiting the community in multiple ways
It's better to pay them and you know to say you're continue doing what you're doing
We appreciate your efforts and with like ntp for example, that's 50 million users that are using it every day
That have no idea they're using and have never heard of it. So he's getting no gratitude. He gets no money
He gets nothing. He doesn't even get a thank you most of the time
But all these people are reliant on it and the same thing when when when shell shock happens and heart bleed happens
Why are these companies like google and redhat? They're reliant on these people and these projects helping these people
Why is it a negative that when the community rallies around someone and says thank you
We want to we want to show you we appreciate you
They get crapped on. Hmm. Yeah, that is it's true. You look at the
Exactly the case when something when the shit hits the fan with a project and there's a security vulnerability and everyone rallies around
And you look on something like hacking news great long thread about how oh, you know
You know everyone ringing their hands and how lamentable it is that this piece of software is only maintained by that one guy
In his basement, right and everyone starts throwing money at the screen
But then when someone goes out and actually asks up front and says hey
I'm that guy who's maintaining that thing that you quite you use quite a lot and you quite like
Could you please give me some money? Everyone's like I get lost right, right? Yeah, interesting
Uh, so ryan, I wanted to give you a chance to chime. What are your thoughts on the story?
so
Uh, you guys know that i'm in the middle of a kickstarter and we've gotten shamed
For asking for money to develop, you know our open source project and I think that people need to just
Shut the hell up
and
Stop shaming open source projects and open source, you know enthusiasts who are trying to create something for the greater
good
And for asking for money, I I don't know that maybe they're just like an outspoken
Minority, but it's just sad because a lot of these people
You know are doing it out of the kindness of their hearts, you know
And and they have to pay the bills just like anybody else and nobody's holding a gun to someone's head and saying
You have to give to this guy's patreon page, right?
You know, he's not setting up a paywall or anything to use ntp
so yeah, you know, it's it's they don't have to
uh
Go after him for asking for money
They just don't have to support them if they don't want to whimpy you have this if
This was an nt if this was ntp on an apple on an iphone
Then it would be an in-app purchase to get the clock to be right most of the time
Very nice wimpy you you have a little familiarity with that community contributions. What are your thoughts on the story?
What well I do my my first question was for ryan
Where where are you getting this pushback and reticence? What what?
Medium, you know, is it is it reddit? Is it google plus? Where are you? Yeah, a lot of it's reddit
Some google plus but I hate to bash on reddit because I actually like reddit, but yeah. Yeah a lot of it's reddit. Yeah
uh
it's it's interesting because I
I I haven't come out and said, you know, I want your money or anything like that. I've placed some
options for people to choose to donate to ubuntu mate
And my feeling is that the open source community or the ubuntu community or the linux community because i'm not quite sure who
Who my audience is exactly?
It's probably a mixture of all of those have been overwhelmingly generous and i've not
seen or heard
any
um
Negative remarks about the way we've gone about, you know requesting funding for but it's a bit different for you though
It's a bit different for you though, because you know you you started
Um ubuntu mate while you're currently in paid employment
So you you know, you got a roof over your head and your kids are being fed
whereas
Uh someone like elementary they're trying to raise money in order to pay developers to do the project
Or nathan dire who's trying to make an app or esr who's trying to pay his bill. We don't really even
Where i'm confused because what if we know i'm sorry
I'm, just we don't have to even abstract this where the money's going. This is happening today to jupiter broadcasting. Uh,
You know, um, I I have for a very long time
I have had a vision that I would love to have the primary source of funding for this network be user contributions
So that way I can be extremely selective with sponsors. I can let them go if I need to et cetera, et cetera
Um, and I can make changes that maybe are not appealing to a sponsor but are appealing to audience members if I truly believe
It's best for the show
And so i've set up a patreon
For the network at patreon.com slash today and since I converted the linux action show and since for the last three weeks
I've been experimenting with different formats because not because my co-host has pressured me into it as which is apparently the new dom
would have narrative online or
Because it's too expensive to do video because i'm still delivering everything as video
Or because we're open source zealots, but because I truly believe with the current available technology
I can make the best the best possible show in this one particular way and i'm trying to think well
Geez i've been doing this show for 10 years. What do I need? What kind of changes?
Do I make to be able to do it for the next 10 years so that way I don't burn the f out
And I can make this show not just something that's kind of like a version of itself
But like even better than itself
What kind of changes do I need to make and I make those kinds of changes because I know
As somebody who's been doing this show for 10 years intimately every single hour of the day. I think about this show
I know what's best for this show
And what I get for that kind of change is as I get a massive drop off in support on my patreon
And not only that it comes at a time when i'm trying to ramp up support for other open source projects to fund them
To improve video production under linux and the support drops out from underneath me
so there is very very very very much a downside to going to your community for support because
When you as the creator and wimpy you got lucky this time that you chose to make a decision
That's better ie the drop of a buntu software center, but when you as a creator go to make a change that you know
Intimately because you are familiar with every single aspect of your show because you think of every second of the day
You think of that show you know, what's best for it you get punished for it and you have to continue forward regardless
And it makes me completely rethink going to my community for funding
It makes me completely rethink that and I it makes me rethink all of the emails
I get all the time offering sponsorship opportunities
Because they won't they won't bail on me when I go to make something that I know makes the product better
And I know it's the same thing that I know is the same exact scenario
That open source projects face today because you watch them try to make decisions that are best for the project
And then their community punishes them for it
And then when you take somebody like eric who goes out there and says you know what for a long time
I've tried to fit into different corporate cultures, but it just doesn't work for me, but I still want to contribute
I still want to make a difference. I still want to make a dent in the open source universe
And he goes out there and he asks for support and he gets shamed for it
I I think there's also a
There's another aspect to it in the sense that there's a lot more people who agree with him and think that he should be paid
But they're not as vocal
Yeah, maybe so right the people that just people that
Don't go ahead. You hear you hear the yelling a lot more than you hear good job. Congratulations
Thank you for doing this thing and helping us do all these great features and utilities and stuff
Do you think that people that are criticizing open source developers actively going out and seeking
uh funding to
effectively pay for their time and effort
are people that
Think that because you're developing free software
It doesn't cost
time
And money no, no
Because I I wouldn't be that's that to me is too easy of an answer because it basically
It assumes that people the consumers are dumb
And the consumers are very aware that it takes time and effort to make code and to make software
They're very aware. It takes time and effort to make content
What they don't have is they don't have the entire picture and they have what you are delivering today
They have what works for them today and a concept of that and why it's so great
And that's why they chose you to begin with is because it meets all of those things
but what they do not understand is maybe perhaps a zoomed out 50 000 foot view of that you have and and and and I
I really
I really hate doing this on a linux podcast
but uh, I
I mean he's dead now. So let's just let's just do it. I mean, I think steve jobs was kind of best at this
He obviously often knew what was better for the consumer in a lot of cases before the consumer did and I don't mean today
Like with all the crap they do now, but I mean like when they launched the first imac
I was working at a school district at a school district that had to deploy like a couple of hundred of those things
And uh, I remember the really really big controversy was this new universal serial bus
We didn't even call it. We didn't call it usb back then
It was this new universal serial bus and nobody had it and nothing worked with it
And we thought apple had screwed us because they had just abandoned the adb connector that all of our keyboards
All of our mice that we had spent thousands of dollars for the last 10 years on that we had hundreds of
Used to connect all of our printers everything we had adapters
We could even do networking with these ports and we thought that apple was crazy because not another
Not a single other computer on the market had this universal serial
Bus thing with this weird flat connector
And we thought we were screwed because we bought all these machines. We didn't realize what a mistake we had made
And it was a huge controversy
And now you flash forward and usb is completely ubiquitous. It is completely obvious
It is it is it is it is a no-brainer and it is that kind of like
Balls insight to like i'm going to ship this thing even though I know today's market
It doesn't understand why and i'm not trying to equate any of that to what i'm doing today or what these other projects are
Doing today, but what i'm trying to illustrate the fact of the matter is a lot of times the current market be a distro
Consumer be it a podcast listener or a computer buyer. We we have uh, we are very much aware
You know, we like our lenovo's we like our lenovo keyboards with our track points that are scientifically proven to be more accurate
Than the trackpad and and now the lenovo is going to make a retro unit. That's great because that's what we like
We're going to make something more just like hollywood makes all of the same dumb movies over and over again
That's why we have spider-man three times over again because we like what we like and we just want to stick to that
But sometimes things have to evolve forward and the problem is
It's not always
Always great to be community funded when that happens and I I I look i'm taking my personal experience and I think boy
I think some open source projects could be handicapped by this because you kind of get paralyzed
Because essentially what it encourages you to do is just maintain the status quo
Just try to maintain the status quo and make people as happy as possible with the status quo
But there's no growth in the status quo just like and and wimpy
That's why when a couple of weeks ago when you came on here and and you were like, you're like, no
I know I am staying behind the decision, uh about the ubuntu software center
I I walked away from that episode really respecting your decision
Based on my experience as a content creator and knowing how that can go when you take something away
Because you know the end result will be better
It it can it can be very controversial now. I think this is a particular one. The momentum was behind you
But uh now you're a couple of weeks into it as what do you have any perspective on the the the entire?
Which would it was actually kind of big news for a moment in time?
I know it was bonkers, wasn't it? But um, yes, the the ground swell of opinion
Um in the ubuntu mate community and probably outside it to some extent as well
Is that it was the right thing to do?
I'm getting a lot of requests now asking if synaptic is going to be
The default so what i'm learning from that is is that at the moment there is no
simple way to install synaptic like there is to
Install the ubuntu software or app grid for example
And maybe in the next version I will add synaptic in there as an option for advanced users
to
Satisfy, you know that request advanced users don't need a one-click button
But I think by putting it in there it will appease them now, uh, ryan, uh, can you really blame?
um, you know, uh
projects like ubuntu that put up like a donation slider or
Elementary os that make a recommended donation before you download when they get such pushback on crowdfunding
That's exactly what the point I was making is I actually used to be on the other side of this but
As time has gone on and i've contributed to more projects. I realized that
you if people are really negative when people like ubuntu or elementary try to go to crowdfunding and
Then they have to be ready for the um fallout from that which is
Them trying to find other ways to monetize their project and oftentimes if they make some kind of you know
Partnership with with a company or they try to sell software. That's not maybe the core software like add-ons and stuff
They get pushed back as well. So it's a lose-lose situation. So I guess in the end
The creator should just go for whatever they feel like is the right way to to pay for their
for their contribution
And yeah, I get it some people, you know
Some people do
Contribute in their free time and that's great. But some projects need more love than that. Some projects need more
Focus than that to compete on you know with the proprietary software solutions that are
Oh, oh, sorry. Go ahead. Sorry. Uh ryan finish off the proprietary solutions that are what?
The proprietary solutions that are out there sometimes some of these open source projects couldn't be competitive
If they didn't have people working on them nearly full time ryan. It was making me actually the one I was thinking of
When you were talking it was arduer a little bit and how arduer has community funding
But also kind of gets pulled around by commercial interests from time to time because that's really where it makes the most of its
Money, I think uh, and that's a that's a weird dichotomy for an open source project to find itself in because you kind of get pulled
Around by different priorities. I suspect right and it's like what you said, you know
If these open source projects are going to be competitive, you know, they're going to have a lot of money
Said, you know if these open source projects fight the same thing
They sometimes they get you know, sweetheart deals from companies that use their product
But they say, you know, here's what we want you to focus on
And they you know if they want to be paid if they want to pay their rent
And you know, they have to focus on those things and their user bases might be upset about it
But that's what's paying the bills. Yeah, I think that's fair enough though
I mean patrons have been doing that for artisans for you know, hundreds of years
So I don't have a problem with somebody who's prepared to
Financially back a project to hold some sway
Over what the priorities of that project might be. That's a good point. It is sort of it is a long-standing
Historical tradition in a sense, isn't it?
But one of the things like the core infrastructure initiative, I mean shouldn't they perhaps be expanding that having more companies
Paying into this pot, but then it's kind of shared out more fairly amongst all open source projects
Not necessarily just the core infrastructure
Yeah, I mean at a larger scale these really critical open source projects are being
Taken advantage of by many many large corporations now though to be fair the core infrastructure project
has quite a big list of contributors and they've they are, you know, they just they just announced a new badge program to kind of
Try to give some sort of certification or whatever to to different projects. They're working
I mean they're they're moving closer to that Joe but the point well taken is at a certain point
Why does it fall on the responsibility of us when there's companies out there like Google, Amazon, Apple and and even Microsoft
That are shipping projects and products and making billions of dollars off of them
But that's also
Missing the point that there are other organizations that do exist like SPI
Where people can companies can submit money and donate money to them or users can donate money to them
That and they will decide who who needs the money at the right time and stuff like that and they will help before you
So you just give it one organization just like the core infrastructure thing
The SPI is essentially that but for a lot more like they're for distros there for regular projects
Anyone who actually wants to do it can just join the SPI and get that but I would also say that the
distro point
Is is a little bit different because with when a distro
They some reason for some people look like distros are getting when they ask for money that they have
More work involved and in some cases they really don't but like the utilities and the tools that people use to build the distros
Just get ignored. So I think it's easier for like if you have a thousand people
You and you see the district like oh, they're doing a lot more work. I feel more
Inclined to give them money rather than this one little utility over here and they kind of get ignored
Yeah, and looks familiar points out that in some cases perhaps the backers
No better than the creators
I don't know if I always agree with that but I guess it definitely is worth balancing and I kind of
You know in the case of our patrons I kind of look at the people who comment there as sort of like an advisory board
Not people who necessarily know more or less but people who know more
Advisory board not people who necessarily know more or less but people are maybe slightly more invested. So their opinion holds more weight
That's kind of how I look at those folks. Uh, and I think that's kind of an that's why I think
You know, I mean
Eric uh, eric s raiment is is one example. Uh,
elementary os projects another example, uh, matei projects another example, but I mean there's
There are different projects on there where I think things like patreon make a lot of sense
and you could use people that are slightly more invested as an advisory board and uh,
um
I don't know. I think there's something there but
There's a stigma still after all of these years not a topic that is new to this network at all
Uh after all these years that stigma is i'm surprised when it comes up
I guess and maybe that's what I take away from this is after all these years in 2015
I saw it in that thread and I was like wow
Really we're still debating this
Really?
It's like our version of like the the political debates that never end
But uh, I would love love love to hear your thoughts on this go over to linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Actually any topic you think would be worth discussing with our virtual lug?
I would love some really good meaty discussion topics linuxactionshow.reddit.com
You'll also find a feedback thread for episode 107 over there and you can contribute your thoughts to this episode
And don't forget every single episode has an rss feed in different formats. We've got a I think hd
I don't know. We've got video at least we've got the mp3s
We got the mp3s. We got your augs with your vorbises and we also got yours. Uh, there is a way actually get webm
If you're really super savvy, I bet you could figure it out
I'm, not going to tell you though because it's a horrible format that should die in a fiery fiery pit of hell
And it costs me a lot of money. It takes a ton of time and I hate it. But if you're really super savvy
You could probably figure it out. Uh, go over to jupiterbroadcasting.com
Why do I say that because all of our episodes are embedded with html5 video and uh, well there's to make that work
You got to use webm, don't you?
But we have rss rss feeds and torrent rss feeds available of all of our episodes
We have those linked in the show notes also links to everything
We talked about including the full version of that ibm mainframe video
Is in the show notes and I encourage you to check that out because the demo kind of just keeps getting nerdier and nerdier
As it goes on and what I love about is it's super obvious. She's not doing like, um, easy demo data feeds. She's
Full-on plugging that thing full of really esoteric crazy requests and getting amazing results and you can watch the rest of the video
We have that embedded in the show notes
Also, I encourage you to check out the linux action shows highlight of our trip to linuxcon 2015
I have that linked in the show notes
I also just submitted that to the linux action show subreddit and it's an extraction from this last week's episode and we went down
To seattle and we really wanted to create
What the experience would be like a lot of times we go to these cons
And we don't know if we can really answer if it's something that's worth your money, you know
The flight the travel the ticket is it really worth your time?
And it's something we've always wanted to be able to answer for you
And so we tried to do that in our coverage in this week's episode of linux action show
So I extracted that component of the show and posted I'll have a link in the show notes is also on the subreddit linux
Action show that reddit.com and it's on the jupiter broadcasting soundcloud account. Yeah, we have one of those
And you can listen to the entire thing. Hey, don't forget linux unplugged is live on tuesday
Go to jupiter broadcasting.com slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone
I'd love to hear your feedback jupiter broadcasting.com slash contact or the subreddit that i've mentioned like a dozen times
All right, everybody
Thanks so much for this week's episode of linux unplugged and i'll see you right back here next tuesday
So
Ah good times good times. All right, so, uh jb titles.com everybody. Let's go pick our title jb titles.com
Um, so, uh any other closing thoughts mumble room on the anything we talked about I have one about um,
The you know that they're asking for money thing. Yeah, um, like so in this case daniel foray is right
It's ridiculous that these people are getting mad about asking for money
But it really annoys me when people correlate what he did and what elementary did
To what this guy is doing because they're completely wrong. The reason people got mad
At the elementary has nothing to do with him asking for money
It's the fact that they insulted everyone before they asked for money. No, that's true. Yeah, I guess and it's well in your yeah in that
In your opinion. Yes, but yes
Calling people cheaters is pretty insulting. Yes, you're right. You're right and also never having the balls to admit they were wrong and apologize
Right, that's that's more important because they they have the balls to say ridiculous stuff like that
But they never actually go well, we were wrong. Sorry
You do kind of have to have the balls to be be willing to backtrack if you do say something's done publicly
Uh, you know
It was kind of perfect that joe is here on the episode where we played a clip from lanus from the 90s, right?
Huh kind of fit with your whole stick, joe
That was great. All right jb titles.com. Let's pick our title
Title
Insane in the mainframe is up there. Should we do something? I mean, it's also linux's birthday
We could do something around that old linux clip that we played
um
Butter fs better than beetree, but I can't believe it's not butter fs. Of course, there has to be butter jokes man those
I can't believe it's not butter people have gotten so much freaking mileage out of their advertising campaign. It's ridiculous
It's absolutely insane. All right. So here's our top titles
You guys got to go the votes are wow. Wow. We whoa, we have like a
She's louise. We have like a 20 boat spread here
So you guys got to you guys got to zero these in a little bit
I i'm not going with I can't believe it's not butter fs. We can't do that one
So that's our top one right now, but come on. Come on, uh insane. I like insane in the main. Yeah, that's pretty good
That's tied. Uh, happy birthday linux
Freedom isn't free. That's not bad. I kind of like that one. I'm gonna vote that one, uh linux
It's it's a buck o five and linux in the 90s isn't bad either
I like linux in the 90s and freedom isn't free
But insane the mainframe I wouldn't be too upset if that was our title, but jbtitles.com bang suggest.com vote it up
Hello everybody
I like freedom isn't free because you know, it it's very
global
and it also is like um
south park thing
Hey chris. Yep
I would like to plug something real quick. Uh for those of you following mycroft
There are only two of the reduced price early bird mycroft extendibles left only
two for 129 their normal price is 149 and then we've got still have
427 of the 99 dollar mycrofts left. So
Uh, if anybody is considering getting one of the extendible units
That's the ones with all the ports exposed on the back. There are only two of them at the reduced price left
So if somebody wants to get over there and grab those I don't think they're going to make it through the rest of the day
Okay, i'm so mad. You're trying to plug your open source solutions right now
Hey, uh ham, aren't you going to a ham convention this weekend? Do you want to plug that at all?
Oh, well, uh, it's not necessarily a ham convention
Uh, there's a jet boat races and i'm gonna help with communications. Oh, you're doing ham radio at a jet boat convention
Okay. All right. Never mind. Nobody go to that then that's horrible
Well, that's where my that's where my audio editor is going to be this weekend as a jet boat convention everybody
Future jb jet boat mobile jb3 mobile studio in the works