It's gonna be a special episode, but it's almost too perfect that it was on August 25th, 1991,
that Linus Torvalds at the age of 21 announced the Linux project on Usenet and we'll have a
link to the original email in the show notes. I think everybody's probably seen this one before
where he talks about it being a no big deal OS. Only a 386 OS won't ever take advantage of things
like SCSI. It's just, it's sort of a perfect moment on August 25th. Let's hope it never gets
big and professional. Just a few years later, right? Hello friends and welcome to 368 of your
weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello Wes, good to be connected with you.
Huge show today. Nice to have you in our recording space for a very special episode.
I see you spruced up in here. Yeah, thank you. Thank you for noticing. You know, I put a lot
of work into that. You sure did. Also, I like that you wore a hat. I don't know if a birthday hat is
the right style, but I like the intention there. We have a huge show today. I also want to start
by saying thank you to a Cloud Guru for sponsoring this episode of Linux Unplugged. Cloud Guru is the
leader in learning for cloud, Linux, and other modern tech skills. Hundreds of courses and
thousands of hands-on labs. Get certified, get hired, and get learning. Go to acloudguru.com
and thanks to them for sponsoring the Unplugged program. Now we have some big news to get into.
We have a fun initiative we're launching. Some follow-up stuff, but maybe even more special.
I should sit down for this one. We have a huge showing in the mumble room. Time,
appropriate, greetings, virtual lug. Hello! Hello! Hello! Mumble overload. That really was. I got to
bring that down just a little bit there. That was a lot. We have the return of a bunch of friends.
Popey, Wimpy, it is great to see you gentlemen. Hello guys. It's been far too long. Great to have
you back. Hello. Hello. Hello. Hello to everybody in the mumble room. We'll get there in a moment,
but I also want to say a special hello to Drew, Alex, and Mr. Joe Resington. Hello.
Hello. Good afternoon. I'm back. Hello everybody. So we have so much to get into,
but we had one more special guest that snuck in just before we got started. So I also have to say
a big special hello to Mr. Michael Dominic. Hello Mike. Hello hippies. Hello. Hello. Hello. So good
to have you here too. We have some things to cover you and me as well. How you doing, Wes?
Oh boy, I'm excited. You know, you and I were talking before the show and we thought this is
a special day and it's not often we make the news about ourselves. So that way it's not just about
our big news. We have a couple of things in the second half of the show that I think you guys are
really going to be interested in. But like the Arch users we are, before we do any of that, Wes,
it's time to see if we can update the Jupiter Broadcasting file server. It's been since the last
time we did it on the show, I think, right? That's a yes. It's been a little too long.
So our commitment to you right here on the show is to try to do a live update. Wes Payne,
are you ready to update one of the most important servers for Jupiter Broadcasting live on the air?
Let's do it. We can't have downtime. We can't, no. Wes, don't do it. The last time I was on this
podcast, you were doing this and that was blooming months ago. It's like last year.
I know. It's pretty great. It is pretty great. Are you ready to start? Yeah, let's do it.
Is it a big one? Oh, decent size. Oh, hey, we're upgrading Docker. We don't use that for anything.
What about your ZFS there? What about your... Oh, let's see. Oh, yep, we got a new kernel.
So we'll have that coming down too. All right. So this is going to be one of those download and
build. So we'll let that go in the background and then we'll continue on with the rest of our show.
Check in later. I have a good feeling about it. I think it'll be just fine. I really do. Oh, yeah,
of course. Spikiness can do it. But that's probably all the stalling I can do. I have some really big
news to share with everyone. You know, I've been podcasting. This is unbelievable. And I thought
it can't actually be true. But I checked. I've been podcasting for 15 years. I've been podcasting
for 15 years, nonstop. That's amazing. What I'm about to share with you is probably the biggest
project I've ever worked on in that 15 years. It's one of those projects that I hope sets the
foundation for myself personally, for Jupiter Broadcasting and these podcasts for the rest of
my life. The Cloud Guru and Jupiter Broadcasting have made the mutual decision to separate and
create Jupiter Broadcasting's independent media status. The demerger will allow for Jupiter
Broadcasting and the Cloud Guru to dedicate their resources and specialize in the content they do
best. Jupiter Broadcasting and creating Linux and open source podcast content cater to
enthusiasts and industry professionals and a Cloud Guru in creating comprehensive and hands-on
multi-cloud computing, Linux and DevOps training for businesses and individuals. A Cloud Guru and
Jupiter Broadcasting share many commonalities such as the passion we have for our respective
missions and the investment we make in creating accessible, accurate and engaging content that
makes a difference to our audience. We also share a belief in the importance of giving back to the
open source community. As such, a Cloud Guru will continue its support of Jupiter Broadcasting with
a sponsorship arrangement and we will continue to explore future content collaboration opportunities.
There you have it. It's official. I'm looking forward to the future. A new era. We'll be working
together in a new era. Jupiter Broadcasting and the productions are independent on their own
company again. We have a little Vic Fontaine to celebrate.
You came along and everything started to hum.
Still, it's a real good bet. The best is yet to come.
The best is yet to come and babe, won't it be fine?
You think Westpain is going to pour us a couple of drinks to celebrate. So we may be under the
influence. A little more than that, Wes. So I'm very excited. A Cloud Guru has a lot in the pipeline
and Jupiter Broadcasting has a whole bunch in the pipeline. There's things that are in the background
that are getting worked on, but there's a couple of things that are happening pretty much right
now. Let's start with the first thing. We're going to be doing a little bit of a little bit of
a little bit of everything that's happening in just a few minutes as we're recording this.
Coder Radio returns to the air with its first episode landing. And Mike, I don't think you and
I could be more excited. We are like so full pumped about doing this. It's you and myself again with
dragging Wes in as much as we can. And the show's back. It's back. It's a party Jar Jar style.
It's full Jar Jar style. And we're going to do it live, I think. We decided we want to go ahead and
do it live, which, you know, should be fun. We don't have as many live shows anymore, but I think
that should be fun. And it's just back where it always was. Coder dot show. And you can subscribe
and the new one will be out in about 15 minutes as I record this. Same feed and everything,
I think. Right. Yep. Same feeds. So if you never unsubscribe, it'll be right there for you.
So that's pretty exciting. And I don't know. We have much more to say than that, Mike. Like people
know Coder. It's been around forever. So same classic flavor. New label. Yeah, we have actually
the labels the same. We kept the logo. That's right. I see it's gluten free now. Yeah, that's
what we did. We made it gluten free. So that's great. Mike's also going to be joining us on
self hosted this week. So keep an eye out for that. And then the other thing that I'm very
excited to announce right now is that Linux action news will return in September. And Joe and I are
already starting to work on that. And Joe, you're not thrilled at all about it. No, because you're
making me work on Sunday again. It's like, what, five months or whatever with no working on my
Sundays? Yeah. Yeah, I know. I know. But we looked at it and we felt like LAN is the show that does
the due diligence. It does the work. So it kind of has a special place in Linux media. We didn't
really have a voice in that sort of area. Headlines served us super, super well. And so drew
hats off to you for just banging headlines out. You really own that and took it. Thank you. Thank
you. So headlines is remaining with a cloud guru. And I don't know if they're continuing production
or not. That's going to be their decision. Now that we kind of will have that hole in our lineup,
it makes a lot of sense to restart Linux action news. Oh, yeah. And of course, for me,
it has a special place because it is born from Linux action show. And so to me, it's a sentimental
show for the continuation. Yeah. And so I'm really happy that I'll be back. We're currently aiming,
should we say September 7th for the first episode back? Yeah, I think that's the first. Yeah, we'll
sort of six seventh, depending on where you are, if you're in the UK or in America. But yeah,
that's Sunday slash Monday. Oh, I'm excited. How's your update going over there, Wes? Well,
it's going well. Is it? We're rebuilding the unit RAMFS right now. Now we're not done. We got to do
the AUR updates next. Do we? I think we should. So I just want to take a moment with our friends here
and say thank you to everyone for your support over the last couple of years and for being there
now, helping make this possible. You guys have really made the difference and just a big huge
amount of appreciation for everyone. And I'm excited about where JB goes from here. It does
mean this has becomes a business again and the business has to survive. I've learned a lot of
lessons in this process and I've learned how important that is for the product. The product
is very important. And if that's what sustains the business, you put everything into the product.
With that in mind, we're launching something called the unplugged core contributors. It's
a membership for the Linux unplugged program and I'm launching it today. You can get it at
unplugged core dot com. If you use the promo code founder, you'll get two dollars off the monthly
cost indefinitely. It's only available for the first 100 subscribers. There will also be a link
at the top of the show notes, but you can go to unplugged core dot com. Now, why? Why a membership
for Linux unplugged? Well, let me just say I have I have learned a lot and my intention with this
membership is primarily two things. Number one, keep Linux unplugged as independent as long as I
draw breath. Number two, help reduce adload needed to make the show profitable so we can keep
producing. So membership will offset adload. There will be ads, but it will help offset how many ads
are required. Now, as a perk of being a member, when you become a core contributor, you also get
access to two RSS feeds. The first is an ad free version of the show. Same full production, just
there will be no ads. Wonder where you got that idea from? Who could have thought of that? And if
that's your preference, you know, as Joe offers that for late night Linux and he has as a Patreon
perk and it's for some people, they don't want any ads and it's a great option. You still get
the full high quality produced episode. It just doesn't have any ads. Or if you're like me, you're
just too lazy and forget to listen to the ad free version, but it's a great way to support too.
That's true. Now there's a second feed option. When you become a core contributor, you can get
the full live stream. All of our screw ups, the stuff that never makes it into the show,
the full pre and post shows, which are much, much, much longer than we'll make into the show.
It's basically the extra show that never gets released. So you have two options, ad free or
the full bootleg, which has everything in it, including our pre and post show chatter that
is, you know, maybe sometimes we'll cut a selection of that and put it on the end or the beginning,
the end of unplug. This is everything. So promo code founder for the first 100 subscribers.
It's eight dollars a month. You use that promo code founder. It'll kick it down to six dollars
a month indefinitely. Unplugged core dot com. Help keep us independent and help reduce the
adload needed. I may consider rolling this out for other shows as well. I think you guys have
heard me get on my soapbox before and talk about how important I think it is for a creator
to be funded by the audience. It changes the way you think about the content that you're making.
It's a it's a game changing way to think about it. You don't think about it from grabs and clicks
and emotions and getting the biggest number for advertisers. You think about it from a standpoint
of what would make that handful of members happy. And it is a much more genuine way to produce
content. And in my 15 years of production, I can tell you, I have learned to walk the line
with ad supported media, with company supported media and with member supported media. But if
you were to ask me to pick one model, it would be 100 percent member funded. It's not possible,
especially in today's climate, especially because I'm trying to make this a full time,
sustainable job. But member support does go a long way and it does help reduce the amount of ads.
It's a great way to be invested in the content here. Yeah. I mean, that's why we're doing it,
right? We have a track record here. So it's an investment I think you can count on. You know
that that money is going to go towards producing a show that can go through something like a merger
and a demerger and stay genuine and true to itself and answering to its audience. That's
what you're investing in. Plus my 15 years of nonstop podcasting track record. We'll have links
in the show notes or you can go to unplugged core dot com and use the promo code founder for the
first 100 subs after 100. It will be full price again, but I appreciate either way. And don't
forget after you subscribe, you get to feed choices and you can subscribe to that in your
podcatcher of choice. And then it just shows up in your podcast catcher like every single week.
One thing is nice about the full live stream. It's definitely not as well produced. It's way longer,
but we're really going to shoot to try to get it out as quick as reasonably possible. So it's if
you like the show right away or maybe if you're often a live stream member, but you didn't make
it and you can get that feed and you'll get it as quick as we can turn it around. The next best
thing to be in here. So I'm very excited. I hope we get some support here because obviously it's
early days and I have to make decisions about advertisers and how many to take on. And I hope
I hope that this resonates with you as the audience, especially maybe some of those have
you been listening for a while and you know what this show does. You know what we're made of
unplugged core dot com. How are you doing over there, Mr. West? Are you ready for an update?
Well, I've just rebooted. Let's see if it comes back up. Updates are done. No issues. All right.
Are you pinging it right now? I'm just about to. I'm going to have my first celebratory drink.
I didn't I didn't think that would actually work, but it's already pinging. That's a good sign.
I maintain I think one of the smart things we did here and they were just talking about this
in two and a half admins in the latest episode. Jim and Alan were talking about some reasons
maybe not to use ZFS on route under Linux. And I agree completely with their take on it.
And I think this is sort of proving that out to like, even if something goes wrong,
worst cases, our pool just doesn't mount. But our OS will boot. Right. And that is nice.
Oh, what is it? This isn't up yet. You're teasing me. You're teasing me. Come on, West.
We might have to go check on it. We're going to have to do a console run during the show.
I think so. Are we going to do that? We don't have a wireless mic. But we should, though.
Westpain will take a really long XLR cord out to the garage. I do have mumble on my phone.
Crap. I didn't want to say I told you so. Damn it, Wimpy. No, Wimpy. No, no, it's going to be
fine. Don't you worry about it. Don't you? It's going to be fine. I have faith in Wes. I'm sure
he can recover the firestorm that is happening right now. I do, too. He does look a little
nervous. Oh, no, it'll be fine. Oh, that's never a good look for us. I know. I know. Like,
it doesn't happen. Not much makes him nervous. Oh, oh, oh, some progress. Okay. It might just
be being slow. We'll see. It didn't immediately reject me trying to SSH, so. Okay, so now you're
just getting like the delay thing. Yeah. Yeah, yeah, that does. All right, we'll come back after
this housekeeping break. How about that? You ready? Should we do a little housekeeping and
we'll see how it does? Now, I have a special housekeeping this week. If anyone out there is
looking for a very talented full time audio editor, mixer or master, or a very savvy sysadmin
with 20 years of experience, let Drew know. Drew is looking for work as part of this transition.
His role is no longer available at a Cloud Guru, and he'll be looking, starting right now, for
work. He's still working with us. He's still here. But Drew, this is sort of, you didn't ask me to
do this, but I wanted to get this out there for you. Where could people get ahold of if they're
looking for a killer sysadmin or an amazing audio guy? Yeah, I appreciate it. I am, of course,
on Twitter at Drew of Doom. I'll make sure that there's a link to my LinkedIn in the show notes.
Also, I've got an episode coming out. I was on the podcast engineering show a few weeks back,
and that episode comes out on the 27th. So when that's live, I'll get that in the show notes too.
There you go. Oh, I'm looking forward to that. LinkedIn profile in the show notes,
like he mentioned, at linuxunplug.com slash 368. I can vouch for this guy,
either doing your sysadmin work or making you sound amazing. Drew is the guy for the job.
No kidding. Yeah. But the most important thing is he's not going to make me stay up
till four o'clock in the morning on Tuesday nights because he's going to keep editing this show.
That's true. Yeah. Yeah, that's right. I'm not going anywhere as far as this community is
concerned. We're so lucky to have you. We heart you, Drew. We heart you. I heart you too.
That is our housekeeping there. Was that enough time for you, Wes, to get into the...
Were you able to get a shell? No. Oh, no. And it's not pinging anymore. It is proper screwed.
This hasn't happened yet. Now, I will say I was a little cavalier. I didn't do a whole lot of
checks. I thought, you know, let's try this as the casual admin. You just run your updates.
The updates went well. You reboot. That's why we did this, right? Oh, God. I got so much to do.
All right. Well, I mean, do you want to make a cart crash run while I... I mean,
because we got to get it back up, right? That's what's going to happen now is we got to get it
back up. I wanted to get some take from the mumble room on an idea that I'm percolating on
that I'd like to get the audience's help with. I've been trying to think of ways that we could
improve the quality of life for Linux users, make a difference in projects, maybe help catch bugs
before major releases. And I was toying with this idea of a bugathon, something that would be
scheduled ahead of time. We'd give plenty of heads up to the audience and we'd essentially pull
together a live stream event where we're helping coordinate the group testing of, say, a distro
before its next release or a project before their next release. Try to line it up with their own
internal project testing windows and release windows. So that way we're contributing at the
right time for the project. Try to mentor and work with people that are attending the live stream to
properly do bug reports, format them, give them enough information, go through that process with
people, maybe put it up on the screen and show them a bug report and try to take like a
concentrated couple of hours on the JB live stream with the audience and focus all of our attention
at one thing. And as I was experimenting with this idea in my noggin, I thought, wouldn't it be
interesting to try this with Fedora 33? Because not only are they cramming a bunch of new stuff
into Fedora 33, but as we've talked about a lot on this show, it will also be the first Fedora that
switches to ButterFS as its default file system. Just a small change. A lot of eyes are going to
be on that change, Wes. Yeah. And maybe we could do our part to help test it before it gets released
to the public. Maybe we could catch something as a group, something that's organized. And I've
created a Bugathon room on the new Jupyter broadcasting matrix so we could start coordinating
there. And I'm hoping maybe the Luplug could help me with some of the details as well. But what I'm
trying to get to is something in the end that is useful for projects and maybe distro maintainers.
Because, and Wimpy, this is one thing I was going to kind of pick your brain is maybe I'm too
cynical, but I think a lot of times what ends up happening is we just overburden developers that
already have too much on their plate with a whole bunch of bug reports or problems that aren't
really in the right channel or don't really provide enough context or information for them
to do anything. It's almost like we make the problem worse for them. There's two sides to
that, right? There is the bug report that says insert name of application doesn't work for me,
it crashes, which is of no use to anybody. And then there's the bug report that comes from somebody
who is trying to help solve the problem and does the initial steps of triage.
Now, this is all complicated stuff because you have to, as you say, have to file the bug in the
right place to draw attention to the right people. But I tell you what, I know Frank is in here
listening to this as well. This is manner from heaven, right? If you're prepared to try and
corral the JB community around these release critical periods to do some well-focused testing
and bug reporting, bring it on. That's just fabulous. Because for all of those bug reports
that are of quality and we can action, yes, there will be some that we can't do much with.
But high quality bug reporting, can't get enough of that stuff. That's great.
I'm liking your take on it. I was worried, you know, I don't want to create a bigger problem.
And I think sometimes our good intentions do that. And I also want to do something that's
substantive. Do you know what I mean? Like something that actually could help.
One of the places where it may help before, I mean, I know you're going to talk to Neil
about this stuff and his take on the Fedora community may be different from mine, right?
But one of the places where you can start to help right now before we even get into, you know,
it's nearly the release and we need to report things is improving the documentation around
how you report things, right? You know, how do you actually file a quality bug?
Checking that all of that information is ready for that group of people to come into that process
and actually make a meaningful impact in the QA process.
Yeah. Right. Lower the barriers to entry. Just make it as smooth as it can be.
Right. Brent, I think there's an opportunity here too to just encourage people to learn how
this process works and maybe they do it on their own afterwards.
You know, some of us have been lucky enough to know some of the people that work on the software
that we use. So we've been able to just, I don't know, send bugs over telegram. I do that every
once in a while. But one thing I've always wanted to know is how to write a really great bug report
from the developer's perspective. And so I think if we're able to share that knowledge and create
a bit of a bug squashing army, that's a legacy that'll just continue. You'll have a lot of people,
you know, five, 10 years from now that are creating helpful bug reports that
might be super helpful in lots of communities. Wouldn't that be a great knock on effect? So Neil,
I'm curious to know what your take is and specifically how we could help the Fedora
community. Before you jump in, I noted that Fedora 33 has a test week and one of the last
days of the test week lands on a lup day. And I was thinking we would sort of target this for that
test week for Fedora 33. That sounds great. I mean, as Wimpy said earlier about making
quality bug reports, I completely agree that that is definitely an aspect that could be improved
here. And in the Fedora context, we have tools like our tools that are for bug reporting in general
when crashes happen and stuff like that already tries to guide people to tell us the right things
for being able to reproduce a bug or do something with it. And we've got automation on the backend
to replay the crash and do stuff like that. That's all well and good. What we don't really
have, and this is probably something where if we just solicit some feedback from developer types
who actually work on the software, what kind of information would be useful just in general
for non-crash type bug reports? Because there's a whole variety of bug types. There's the,
well, it just broke. And then there's the, well, this did something slightly unexpected,
but didn't fail. And the latter case is actually the much harder one. I have tons of those bug
reports in my own queue for the projects that I'm one of the developers for. And it's really hard
because people don't give enough information for me to do anything with it. And in a lot of cases,
by the time I can get around to ask for the information, they either have kind of moved past
it and forgotten about it, or just don't think that giving more information is useful or necessary.
And sometimes even worst cases, they're rude about it. So I think setting a better set of base
expectations of what makes a useful bug report helps. And I think also having the ability for
people to realize that there's like things that need to be evaluated and tested and kind of beaten
in to make sure that it works well. As a distro release is being developed like Ubuntu 2010,
which is coming up, Fedora 33, and so on. As those are coming, all these distros that do
scheduled releases often have periods in which you can help and they have documentation for how you
can help make it a better release by testing and reporting and even here and there working with
developers and stuff like that. It just sort of depends. Neil makes a good point there,
which is that the urgency with which people are reporting issues doesn't necessarily align
with the priorities of the developers that are receiving those bug reports.
That doesn't mean we don't care. It just means that we're busy and we have a priority order
in which we can address things. So it's a bit like being in an IRC channel. If you're the kind
of person that joins a free node channel and then immediately demands assistance and then
immediately after asking for assistance loses interest and then leaves, that's not helpful
conversation in an IRC. In the same way that if you file a bug report, make it a bug report that
you actually care about and you're not just being frustrated on that day. Because it might be that
weeks or months later those developers are coming around to a collection of issues that circulate
around a thing that you've identified and other people have as well and they're trying to collate
information around the issue that you've reported. Do expect that sometimes you may get a response
within minutes or hours and sometimes it may be weeks or months later that somebody comes back to
you asking for more information or wanting to follow up on what you've reported.
Fedora 33 caught my attention because of the high profile nature of all the changes.
They're all pretty big. One of the things that's coming down the pipe for Fedora 33 is they're
doing now an IOT edition, which not shocking there that not really a surprise to see that
this is coming. In fact, I kind of wondered if this was maybe one of those things that they resisted,
but maybe customers asking for it kind of made the start. As one might expect, it's meant to
be deployed on devices that are used in the Internet of Things from small, silly devices
to production equipment. You got to put quotes around that's the Internet of Things. Yes, right.
They have a product requirement document and in there it states that Fedora is the default
platform in the IOT space. Anyone starting an IOT project from cute embedded hacks all the way up to
multi-million device deployments will start with Fedora. It's going to be available on x86 and ARM
64 architectures. It's pretty small. I mean, maybe not tiny, but it requires like three gigs of disk
space and runs within one gig of RAM, at least if you're not doing anything anyway. You want to
adjust to a new way of managing packages, though one does not just run dnf install on the Fedora
IOT system. No, no. This distribution instead is using RPM OS tree. Oh, yes, you know RPM OS tree.
It's built around the concept of an immutable base image, perhaps augmented by one or more
overlay images. The running system is never modified by the package management operations
like installations or system upgrades. Instead, RPM OS tree maintains a set of parallel system images,
two of them by default. The running image is immutable and any package management operation
will instead apply to the next image in the series. So, for example, if you were administrator
on one of these boxes and you want to install, say, nano, that package will go into the alternative
image and the action will not actually yield a usable nano command at first. Got to have nano.
Oh, gosh. Of course, you're installing nano. It's got a new release out, Wes. New version.
Now, of course, the idea behind this mechanism is to make system updates safer, which especially
you want if you've got an Internet of Things device that's deployed somewhere out in the field
and it's hard to get to. Since the update is applied to the idle image, it can't break the
running system even if it's interrupted at an especially inopportune time, which, Chris, as you
know, seems to happen a lot with updates. We could have used that today. It's also nice for an IoT
device is it's really easy to implement a factory reset operation with this type of file system
approach. You know, hold down a button and it goes back to the original image. Roll back. And it
reboots. There's other takes at an IoT device image. The thing that made this stand out to me
is interesting for those of you who like Fedora is apparently they are opting out of the normal
release cycle for the IoT edition. Instead, the project has committed to producing a rolling
release with monthly updates with RPM OSG configured to pull down updates automatically.
Hopefully, IoT systems can be kept up to date with minimal effort. And if it goes bad, well,
roll back. This reminds me when we started seeing Ubuntu core and people wanted to build
desktops. You know, as soon as I see that, I'm like, well, now I want to make it a desktop.
Such an idiot. That's my first thought. And yet soon it'll be running in the studio.
I guess they just they wanted to put everything in the end of this 33 release. So it just seemed
like a good one to test. It seemed like this is something that we could apply to other projects
as well. And Minimac, you could see how the virtual could kind of get in on some of this,
do virtual install sessions and stuff like that. I would love to see that. You know,
we have really a good crowd now every Sunday. And wouldn't it be cool to have like an install and
testing party? We could even have a separate room and we could even record that session
and just have a mumble recording. Wow. Or you could use Discord, you know,
upgrade to the 21st century. Oh, jeez. But the matrix is fine too. You know, come on.
Oh my God, it's too much already. Let's build a bridge to everything. So here's what I'm thinking
specifically for Fedora 33 is September 8th for Linux Unplugged. After that week's Linux Unplugged,
let's all just whoever wants to join us stay here. So come for Linux Unplugged and stay and we will
do the bug smashing bugathon session and we'll try to get some guidance on best practices to pass
forward for bug submitting and stuff like that. Maybe bring a computer you want to install Fedora
on. Yeah, bring a computer you can wipe and we'd love to get some testing on the PotterFest stuff.
And we'll just sit here as a group and we'll just try to bang this out. And if it is successful,
if it produces something of use, I think we'll keep working at that model and see if we can't
apply it to other stuff. So September 8th will be the date. It'll be after Linux Unplugged.
It'll be the Bugathon Live and we're coordinating in a room on Matrix called Bugathon
on the Jupiter Broadcasting Matrix server. So this will be good because the beta for Fedora
comes around September 15th and then like they have a backup date to like the 22nd because
maybe they might not make the 15th. There's a lot going on. It gives us a chance to find and get
this stuff in before the beta lands and then, you know, do another round of testing. So that'll be
the plan. I'll remind you about it in the future, but that'll be kind of cool. This should be fun.
I'm excited. And I'm just excited for Fedora 33 because Fedora's great. Yeah, come check out
the virtual log too. We do that every Sunday at noon Pacific time and you can just join the
mumble lobby and hang out in there. And of course there's a Matrix room too. That's right. You know,
Wimby, I do have a special Discord pick for you because I knew you'd be here this week.
Okay, lay it on me. I'm all about the Discord these days. So listener Dylan wrote in and he
said, I'm a big fan of the show. I've been a dedicated listener since I found Linux seven
months ago. He likes to listen on the road. Oh, and he loves a good old fashioned Arch update.
So I'll have to come back to that for him in a moment. But he says, I'm contacting you today
in hopes of having a cool piece of software my friends made highlighted on the show.
It's called FetchChord. Its main purpose is to display your OS in a rich presence way on Discord.
So it gives you like a rich display for your Discord based on your OS. It's kind of like Neo
Fetch for Discord. So it's called FetchChord. Oh, that's fun. Right. So like how it can,
you know, it'll show information about what you're running, what your system is.
Isn't that neat? So we'll have a link to that. It's FetchChord on Mr. Potato Box's, or Bob
Mr. Potato Bob Box. Yeah. Okay. That's awesome. Yeah. Isn't that great? So that's for you.
That's that's for you. Thank you for catering to the current generation. And maybe in a few weeks
from now, you'll realize the errors of your way and you'll bring your community over to, you know,
a modern communication platform as well. I'm actually laughing out loud. I feel attacked.
I feel attacked right now. I'd just like to point out at this point that self-hosted has a Discord.
There you go. That's true. Right. Also, Neil, back in your box, you and I both played Fall Guys
on Linux, you on Fedora, me on Ubuntu. And how did we communicate that evening?
Yes, through Discord. It was actually a lot of fun. Right, there we go. End of conversation.
Hey, I only just felt that. I only just said that because I've been needling Chris for like almost
two years now to set up a matrix server. Yeah, but that was, you started that conversation two
years ago. Two years has elapsed. The world has moved on. Matrix is a science project. It's
wonderful, but, you know, it's not for everyday people and we need to be inviting everyday people
into our world. Ditto, give us give us the awkward fact that's hanging in the room here.
Well, JB does have its own Discord server set up. It's just there's no one in there.
Hey, I'm in there. Yeah, I am too. I think. I just check it from time to time. I, you know,
you might be right, Wimpy. That's why it hurts because you might be a little right, but we'll see.
Wimpy, you are the voice of reason once again.
Wimpy, this is this is why the good developers invented bridges,
my friends. I'll just bridge that Discord. It'll be fine.
No, but that's the worst thing ever because then that's the worst of both worlds, right?
You need the one thing or the other. You're not backing one platform or the other.
Or a disgusting hybrid.
Pick something, but if you pick matrix, don't expect audience expansion. Pick Discord,
the fastest growing messaging platform in the world. Expect audience expansion.
I agree just because I have an unfiltered Discord as well. So we have a self-hosted
Discord and unfiltered Discord, and they're both very successful.
I guess all it means I have to figure out why it keeps crashing on my Linux.
I mean, the thing is, maybe matrix is sort of like the back end,
and then you can have these front ends that are telegram and Discord and IRC and
people can use whatever they want. I don't know. Maybe not. Maybe it won't work out,
but I'm launching on the grand experiment.
Hopefully Google will just make another type of chat and then we'll just use that one.
Oh my goodness.
Oh geez, not again.
All right, Westpane. Let's see how that server's doing.
Actually, it's doing great.
What?
Yeah, totally. So it stopped pinging, and then it started pinging again,
and it's running fine. All our containers are up.
Well done. Well done.
So why do you think it took so long to come back online?
Was it checking some disk or something?
We will have to investigate.
Yeah, that'll be something for after the show.
Now we are on kernel, what was it?
5.8.
5.8, okay. It's fine. I mean, 5.9 is almost out, so we better update soon.
Obviously, can't have an old kernel on our server.
Well, before we go any further, West, good job.
I feel like you get an applause for that.
Hey, I didn't do anything.
It was our minimalist design, ButterFS on the root vial system,
keeping ZFS for the big data pool, and turns out Arch sometimes works.
Yeah, sometimes. Sometimes it works.
Now, we have a cool pick that Alex found for us today because we all love to eat.
If you've listened to the bootleg stream, you know how much we love to eat.
So tell us about Chowdown.
Chowdown, indeed. It's a self-hosted recipe manager.
Stores your recipes in plain text using the schema.
So I don't know if you knew this, but there is a recipe schema over at schema.org.
And this Chowdown application actually stores your recipes
in plain text and you can run it out of a container
and has a nice little web interface with some search.
So when you want to bring it up on the iPad,
whilst you're frying up some steaks or something, it works really, really nicely.
It looks pretty, too. I like it.
I'm liking this display system where they...
I mean, you got to take pictures of your stuff.
Sounds like, Alex, you've actually been using it, too.
I have indeed, yeah, for probably about three or four months,
ever since Chris convinced me to buy one of those barbecue ceramic egg things.
I wanted a way to kind of record what worked
and what didn't on particular cooks and stuff.
So what I use it for is I have a brisket recipe
and then I put some notes underneath the brisket rub
or whatever I did that particular time and said,
I like this about it and I did it at these timings
and it came out a little bit too dry.
And then I have these things in plain text forever.
So the next time I'm planning to do a big cook or something,
I've got that all there alongside the recipe as well.
Yeah. And I like that you can check stuff off,
like individual ingredients and steps of the directions, too.
The display is really clean.
Yeah. Now, one thing worth looking at is in the GitHub,
the author, Clark Lab, I think his name is,
he's actually proposing a complete redesign of the web interface of the UI.
So currently it's this blue thing with pictures
and I quite like it, to be honest.
But the web interface is going to be rethemed as red
and he's rewriting some of the backend and stuff.
So if you want to be part of that process,
he's actively looking for feedback at the moment
on the new proposed UI. So head over to GitHub
and let him know what you think.
Very cool. We'll have a link to that in the show notes.
Thank you, Alex.
Thank you for your perfect pick.
Right on theme for the co-host of Self-Hosted.
Check out selfhosted.show for more of that.
My mom has a quick question about how she fires up a container
with her recipes in it.
Okay. It's Tupperware.
Who said Tupperware? That was blue ingenious.
All right. Fair point.
Yeah. Put it in the microwave, crack the lid, and then you're done.
Don't forget to burp the container.
Maybe sprinkle a little water on there.
Yeah. What does constitute burping a container in modern parlance?
Is that when you like bring it down and restart it?
That's burping it?
You got to rebuild it to get the B in there, right?
Well, let's go around the horn and see what folks are working on.
Mr. Dominic, I know predominantly nothing more important in your life
at all than Coderadio, of course, but what else is going on?
But what else is going on for you?
I'm ashamed to say I'm a full-time Linux user now.
Welcome. Wow.
Took long enough.
I still haven't exactly decided Snap or Flatpak.
And so I would like to put that to you guys.
Why not both?
Hey, Neil speaks the truth, right? Why not both?
I mean, you're more of an app image guy. That's just what I think.
We have standards around here, right?
We do get into this a little bit in the most recent Coderadio.
I'm on board with this change. I support this.
I think you've been flirting with it for a long time.
How much do you think it was distro versus you just settling into something?
I think I'm lazy, as people would know.
And the ability just to buy a Thalia or whatever the name of the laptop is,
pre-installed, driver's work, I don't have to really care about anything,
was the solution.
Also, Apple's OS is getting crazier, right?
I had a lot of issues with Catalina and Big Sur, not trying to diss anybody, but-
You and the rest of the internet.
Right. It kind of looks like Fisher Price.
I'm really interested in this. Is it aesthetics or is there something
fundamental from a developer's perspective that you're unhappy with?
Yeah. So I think the biggest change was I'm not doing a ton of iOS work.
I'm doing a ton of embedded Linux work and mostly Python on the server now.
So I ended up running a bunch of Ubuntu VMs anyway on a Mac computer, which was kind of silly.
Also, you and the rest of the internet.
Right. So at some point, it's like, why not just run it natively on the hardware?
Thank you.
That's what I wonder if that does seem like, even with WSL and virtualization on Mac Arm,
at a certain point, it is just a little bit simpler. There's less things in the middle.
Right. If it works for you, if it meets your needs for development,
whatever you need, yeah, why not?
The disadvantage that Apple has that makes it easier for these kinds of transitions of like,
you're running a whole bunch of Linux VMs and then you're like, well, why do I have Mac OS?
Is that if you decide to make that change, you wind up actually saving money, right?
Because you can make that calculation and see that there is an actual
tangible benefit across the board.
You don't necessarily get that same calculation when you go from saying Windows with WSL to
Linux on the computer, unless you get a computer with Linux pre-installed.
And I think this is what's just been said about how Linux being pre-installed was just the thing
was like, this is it all works.
Everything's fine.
I'm just going to kind of roll with it.
That is the thing we've been missing for nearly 20 years.
And now that we're starting to have that for real in a big way,
like with System76 and Tuxedo and now Lenovo and Dell and so on,
like having these things there makes a huge difference.
It does, but they've been around for a decade.
Maybe I should nail my colors to the mast here.
Obviously I'm responsible for Ubuntu's interests in WSL, right?
But that in itself is very interesting because we're finding an interesting trend, which is
there are people that are already running Windows that now are in a world where they
need to target Linux as a platform.
And they're able to do that from their point of view, the comfort of their Windows environment.
And WSL is an enabler for them to be able to rapidly do the business that they need
to do, which is to build their products on Linux and to target Linux without actually
having to dip into a Linux world.
And this is kind of an uncomfortable place for me because on the one hand,
I represent the Ubuntu desktop.
And on the other hand, I represent Ubuntu's aspirations for WSL.
And they don't necessarily compete with one another.
They do complement one another, but they do overlap.
That set, they are not distinct sets of users, right?
They do intersect.
I like that little microcosm.
I think of the cognitive dissonance we've all had around WSL and figuring out where
does it fit in this ecosystem?
Right.
It's a very similar logic that arrives you at Discord versus Matrix, right?
It's that pragmatic approach to use the thing that gets the job done versus the purest
approach sometimes.
Yeah.
And you have to figure that the Windows 10 user base has got to be at least one or even
two orders of magnitude bigger than the Ubuntu desktop.
Good point.
And sure.
And I don't discount any of those things.
And to some extent, I'm pragmatic too.
I have a MacBook, as both Wimpy and others know, and I also have a Windows PC that I
work from as well, because I do some game development.
I need to be able to do this.
And the thing is, I just I don't see WSL as a driver for getting people interested
in the Linux platform.
I just don't think it will work that way.
I'm not so sure about that.
So you just said to me that you have a Windows computer for game development.
The trend that we are seeing almost exclusively ahead of everything else is game studios that
need to target Linux and are using WSL as the vehicle to do that.
Now, I can't reveal names and I can't say what's going on behind the scenes, but that
is definitely a trend that we're seeing.
Well, that's good to know.
I think it's also the perspective that Jay Tucky in the chat room points out that's worth
considering.
He says, I can confirm that I love WSL and many of my colleagues use it at work on Windows
machines.
If WSL didn't exist, they wouldn't be using Linux.
They just wouldn't be using Linux tools.
So there's that too.
There's like the use of more open source tools, even if it's running on a proprietary platform
is in somewhat a net benefit as well.
Right.
And we're already sort of comfortable with the, oh, yeah, you use whatever.
Maybe it's a Mac or Windows and then SSH to all your Linux servers.
It's sort of just bringing that a little closer to home.
You say proprietary platform, the proprietary platform being the desktop operating system
in this case, which is Windows.
But WSL 2 is empowered by the Linux kernel, which is the Linux kernel.
And in the majority of cases, the Ubuntu user space, which is the open source Ubuntu user
space.
And is the new Windows terminal open source?
Yeah.
I believe it is.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's funny.
So that stack is fairly open source except for the virtualizer it's running on.
It's pretty open.
You know, it's way, way more open than, you know, you would, you know, think in your mind
when you're thinking about, you know, a Microsoft ecosystem, because it isn't a Microsoft ecosystem.
This is Microsoft basically opening up to what the rest of the industry have defined
as the de facto development platform standards.
And guys like Mike, I guess, building applications that he's building.
It just made sense to him to just switch to the platform itself, and which we dig into
in Coder a little bit.
So that's a good tease.
And I think Mike, right?
So a lot of people talk about, you know, oh, WSL is the way that Microsoft is going to
snuff out Linux.
Well, what if it's not that?
What if Mike is actually the example of where we're headed?
You know, that more people come to Linux platform natively because they've been introduced
to it via another means.
Yeah, you get more comfortable with it, you know, eventually a couple of years down the
road.
All right.
I could see living in this day to day.
I wonder if there is brand association power as well.
If you are a Windows user and you trust Microsoft and you trust the Windows platform, and now
they're saying this is a tool that is legitimate, it's sort of a brand association thing.
I wonder if it gives it a more legitimate endorsement.
And that's the word I'm looking for.
Yeah.
And, you know, the thing is, as all of these people have said about the idea of WSL potentially
being an avenue in which people start thinking about using Linux natively, like my own story
in getting in switching to Linux parallels that like WSL didn't exist back then.
I started with DJGPP and using it in DOS and then with Windows using Cygwin and eventually
switching to Linux full time because I liked that platform, that ethos, and that's certainly
something that I think is important and is a good way to go.
The difference between then and now is that we have a lot more strongly de-emphasized
the community and the open source principles at the forefront of how people get access
to open source software and tools.
And so I don't know if people actually get exposed to that open source culture quite
as much now than they would have, you know, like when I started doing this like 15, 20
years ago.
Interesting.
So I would argue that more people are exposed to that because it is the lingua franca of
contemporary software development.
You can't go into an organization and they explain to you that they want to create a
way to distribute some information to the world without them leveraging open source
technologies in order to base the foundation of their product on that, right?
You know, it's your thoughts, your thinking that are unique and distinctive.
It's not the technology that you use anymore.
True.
And also looking at my daughter's generation who are just emerging into this world, they're
brought up on scratch and the micro, or at least in this country, they're brought up
on scratch and the micro bit.
And the whole process is not called open sourcing, but the idea that you share your code and
then you remix it is the very expression of that collaborative open source environment
that I find most compelling.
So, you know, my daughter talks about magpying things, you know, finding something that
somebody else has done that you value and building upon it.
And this is the term that the kids use in this, you know, in my area, they magpie somebody
else's stuff.
I'm just, I'm just smirk, I'm just smiling because that's a wonderful thought.
Adorable.
Well, so there you go.
That's what Mike's been up to.
That's how we got down that rabbit hole.
That's what's sorry about that.
No, no, it's great.
That's like, that's one of my favorite things about this show.
Check it out.
Coder dot show.
It's back.
It should be up now.
Go check.
Is it up now?
It's not yet, but it will be soon.
All right.
It's in the tubes, as it were, doing the encoding.
I'm pretty excited about that.
Mr.
Rastitun, it's been a while since, so we've got an update from you.
I know you got some new shows.
Tell us what you got going on.
Yeah.
Well, since I disappeared, shall we say, I have started a new show called The New Show
with Popey and Dan.
And it's a completely new show.
It's nothing like the old show.
It's the new show and it's at the new dot show.
So check that one out.
And also Jim Salter and Alan Jude of Text App Fame.
I managed to get those two together for a show called Two and a Half Admins, which is
at two dot five admins dot com.
You see what we did there.
Clever domain hack.
And that's basically me just learning stuff from them.
I just kind of introduce it, ask them questions and go, all right, yeah, OK.
And then kind of say, should I do it like this?
And they say, no, you're not doing it that way.
You should do it this way, that way.
You're doing it completely wrong, Joe.
You're a half admin.
And Popey calls that show Two Dot Zero Five Admins to try and insult me.
That sounds about fair.
And Joe, have you learned anything yet?
I've learned tons from them.
Have you implemented anything you've learned yet?
No, I'm still I'm still at the planning stage of implementing.
Next time he rebuilds.
Popey had to drop out early.
So for Popey's benefit, I'm going to plug the Ubuntu podcast, which is humming right
along.
Mr.
Wimperis, I've noticed on my YouTube recently that there seems to be some
Ubuntu Mate hacking going on live on YouTube.
Yeah, so some people during lockdown have decided to get fit and lose weight or, you
know, increase their mental aptitude by reading books.
I decided I'd learn how to flex OBS Studio and learn a little bit about cameras and
videography.
So I've been doing a bit of live streaming.
So not just Ubuntu Mate, but generally stuff around the Ubuntu community or grassroots
projects to try and involve people in, you know, projects, just trying to put stuff out
there to invite people in.
And we've had some success.
So, yeah, I've got a YouTube channel.
It's Wimpy's World.
So YouTube.com Wimpy's World.
Come along, join the next live stream and dip into our Discord server.
We've got a broad, broad spectrum of people involved there from enthusiasts through to
hardcore developers who are interested in making and creating stuff.
And what's the name of that Discord?
It's in the YouTube chat.
So if you go to YouTube.com Wimpy's World, there's linked from there.
Yeah, yeah.
Or Wimpy's World.com.
There's all the links there.
I like your setup.
You've got like a good setup over there with the music going.
And you must have one of, do you have one of those Elgato Stream Deck controls or something?
Because I noticed you're hitting a button and then stuff sliding around and it looks
really good.
So I have lots of things.
It's a bit embarrassing to be honest with you, like how much stuff I've got now.
So I have three mirrorless cameras now.
And I do have two Elgato Stream Decks, although I only use one.
The thing I use for switching the transitions is actually a fairly modest Android tablet.
And go to YouTube.com slash Wimpy's World because I'll be revealing how I've put all
of this stuff together and the tricks I've learned along the way.
And I've been learning how to do this stuff by following like pro level game streamers
and how they're using OBS and then adapting how they're using OBS to delivering like
let's code Linux material.
So I'm going to be going through all of that and how I'm using OBS and all of the plugins
that are available and all of the ancillary bits and pieces.
So come along and join.
We'll go through that journey together.
Oh, wow.
Wimpy, you forgot to mention the snap, the OBS snap.
That's what makes it all possible, right?
That'll be part of it.
Yeah, the OBS snap, it's like, I'll tell you what, it's like a Linux distribution.
So the OBS snap is OBS plus about 20 plugins and filters built in to the snap.
So it's a fully loaded battery included version of OBS and that's what I use.
And everything that's built into the snap of OBS, it includes all of the hardware acceleration
for NVIDIA and AMD and Intel GPUs and APUs and a whole bunch of plugins to do sexy transitions
and interesting effects.
It's all in there and I've learned it all by watching game streamers on Twitch.
Well, you've really nailed it.
I've watched several of them and I think you've put a lot of good thought into just how things
flow when you're making a transition too, which looks really good.
But just the overall look is good.
The green screen is working really well.
The chat integration works great, the music isn't too loud so you can still hear what
you're doing and I can see what you're working on, which checks all the boxes for me.
Taken a lot of fails to get there, but thank you for the kind words.
Definitely needs more star wipes though.
Star wipes?
Yeah man, to make it really professional.
Definitely.
Agreed.
Good Lord.
One day I will hope to be half as good as Wimpy at live streaming.
Hey, look Neil, Neil, the very fact that you are now streaming on Twitch moderately in
influenced by my jamboree that I do is the whole reason I'm doing it right is I think
as a Linux community, we need to get away from matrix mailing lists and IRC channels
and emerge into this whole video production era in order to capture a new audience.
So Neil, it doesn't matter if you're learning as I was a year ago, you're doing it right.
You're capturing a new audience.
Something I haven't shared with you, but I've been doing podcast consulting at chrislast.com
slash consulting and I had a consultation with a developer of a popular open source
project that everyone listening who's used the Linux desktop for a while has definitely
used this app and they've noticed that developers streaming is becoming more and more of a thing
and it was you Wimpy that they pointed to specifically that really impressed them with
the way you're doing it and sort of inspiring them to get their setup going.
I don't know if it's going to be a great idea or not, but I think, you know, it is for them
connecting them with a newer generation of developers who are just beginning their journey
and it's been worth it so far.
So I think you're onto something in that regard.
So I'm blushing a little bit, but the thing is this right video is the medium by which
most information is communicated via the internet these days, particularly since, you know,
the whole, you know, galactic meltdown started a few months ago.
Our community needs to capitalize on that movement.
I don't claim to be doing it right.
I think I've just caught a wave of other people that are also investing in video
as a means to communicate because it's no like accident that I started doing this when
I found myself stuck within the four walls that I'm sat within right now.
Right.
You know, it's kind of a happenstance of, you know, of the world we find ourselves in.
I think video plays a part in this.
I think it's every medium.
I think it's audio, text and video and there's a reach into each of them.
But I have as well really kind of started putting live streams up more on my screen as I'm working.
I have a monitor that I just sort of perfect to just toss a stream on and it's either a
news stream or sometimes it's a community stream.
And it's like, it's like listening to a podcast while I'm at my desk, only instead it's a live
stream.
And so it works for me.
And I think there's probably a lot of people that do that.
I think there's something to that right now.
Maybe that is very much of the now, but you know, my live streams are not short.
And they are an hour, like minimum.
The last one I did was an hour and 45 minutes, kind of staggered that 2000 people have watched
that, you know, in the time since I did that last, this time last night.
What's your retention like though?
Retention is pretty decent, actually.
You'd be surprised.
I mean, yeah, it's like 30, 35 minutes on my channel and most of it is like long form
content and I used to criticize people making long form content, basically streaming hours
long things, but there is an audience for that kind of technical information from our
community.
So we'll have links to that in the show notes.
That's pretty great.
This has been a fun episode.
It's really felt like a party.
Thank you everybody for being here.
So go check out Wimpy's channel.
I have a link to that.
Check out Alex on the self-hosted podcast.
Check out Joe on the return of Linux action news.
And his podcast, two and a half admin, the new show and of course, late night Linux.
Mike's also got the Mike Dominic show and Coder radio.
You can find those.
We'll have links in the show notes.
It's a lot of plugs there.
There's probably more that I'm probably in my forgetting one.
Probably.
I mean, there's a lot to it.
Give me a job.
Yeah.
Give Drew a job.
If you were seriously, if you're looking for somebody who's a great admin or a fantastic
audio master and just a great coworker.
Yeah.
I really, I think Drew, if you had time and you know, could like, you know, just get like
some massive VC funding, you could launch a serious podcast editing shop.
Like it could, you know, Drew's podcast editing, but the realities of the world are that the
man needs a job.
So if you need assist admin or a great editor and sound master, give them a look.
We'll have a link in the show notes to that.
A thank you to a cloud guru for sponsoring this episode and a thank you to our members
unplugged core.com as we sign off West, I'm going to hit the old refresh.
We have 24 active core contributors now.
Amazing.
We haven't even finished the show.
Which means there's still some of those discounted founder slots available for the download audience.
Use the promo code founder, or if you just click the link at the top of the show notes,
it will take you to the deal right there.
Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of the unplugged program.
I can't wait for next week's episode and all the episodes after that.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
The brave souls over at WSL Conf are doing it again on September 9th and the 10th.
WSL Conf on September 9th and the 10th.
Oh, hey, that was a great time last time.
Yeah, maybe we should see if we can get in there again.
I'd be curious.
Diddle, are you going?
I'm presenting.
Oh, fantastic.
Well, I guess you should probably go then.
I guess you should probably go.
Otherwise, it's going to be really awkward.
You know, you know what?
You know what, Diddle Dan, we should fly you out there.
Oh, hang on a minute.
Oh, yeah.
No, none of that.
It's all virtual.
I am actually legitimately missing community events.
I know.
I am now.
I mean, it's getting bloody tiresome, right?
You mean barbecue events?
Yes, I do.
Yes.
I really do.
I'll tell you what, if Linux Fest Northwest is going again by next year, if you come out,
I'll take a group of you out to the best burgers in the Northwest.
The best burgers in the Northwest, if you come out.
That's my commitment to you.
And then the best pizza afterwards at Mod Pizza.
No, Joe, that is not the best pizza.
Stop dissing the Mod Pizza.
Look for us heathens that live, you know, in the colonies.
Mod Pizza is the height of pizza sophistication.
I have to disagree.
No, no, you can't disagree because you don't live in the colonies.
Can I just take you to good pizza just so you can, can we just do that, please?