I can't believe I'm saying this,
but I've switched away from systemd.
What?
I don't believe it.
I'm just kidding.
Hello friends, and welcome into a very special Linux Unplugged.
This is episode 314.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Hello.
How are you doing?
I'm doing great, because we've got a full house today.
We do.
It's a special week here at the Jupiter Broadcasting Studios.
We have the full core team in-house.
And I guess that's my quick way of saying people that are all involved in creating a
brand new podcast for the network are in-house this week.
And that means that we have a whole cast of characters here helping us get various jobs
done.
So I want to say a very happy hello to Mr. Cheese Bacon.
Hello Cheezy.
Hello.
Good to have you here.
Thank you.
It's good to have everyone here.
And hello to Alex.
Nice to have you in studio, Alex.
Howdy, y'all.
Nice to have you.
You're sounding good, sir.
You're sounding...
That sounded nearly real.
Thank you.
Nearly.
And it's always good to have Brent back in studio.
Hello, Brent.
Well, hello, everyone.
How are you doing?
I'm great.
It's good to be connected via real, like, cords and stuff to the studio.
That's nice.
Brent made me breakfast.
What?
Mm-hmm.
Brent made me breakfast today.
He's such a gentleman.
It's so good.
And Drew barbecued lunch.
So...
Pays to have the team around.
Now, of course, this wouldn't be a Linux Unplugged without our virtual log.
Time-appropriate greetings there, Mumble Room.
Hello.
It's really good to...
Aloha.
Aloha, Neil.
Welcome back.
Neil will be giving us his flock report in a moment.
But, Emma, I just have to say, it's super great to see you back.
How are you doing?
I'm doing good.
I will be off crutches pretty soon, but I returned to System 76, I've returned to the
factory.
So I'm moving around pretty good these days.
Man, if people don't follow Emma, social happiness on Twitter.
She recently had a serious medical situation.
Just, I mean, unbelievable to watch from afar, Emma.
So...
It was a safari accident, to be specific.
That is very cool.
We should make that a disclaimer because, you know, other people get injured, but Emma
got injured on a safari.
So that's true.
But it's really good to see you back.
I've been following your journey on Twitter.
Nice to see you back at work.
We have some cool stuff you and I are going to be talking about in a little bit today
too.
So I'm glad you're here.
Let's kick things off with a wee bit of community news.
Did you see all of this hoopla around this horrible bug that was discovered in KDE that
could potentially make it vulnerable to attack?
And then the KDE project responded by just ripping the feature out of Plasma, I understand.
What happened last?
Yeah.
So it's not, you can call it a bug or really it's a design decision because it turns out
you can execute scripts in your.desktop or.directory files.
And why would you want to do that?
You know, the funny part is when they removed the functionality to do that, the words accompanying
the removal were, we didn't really have a use case.
But you can imagine, right?
It's just like a little hook you can run.
You can have a script.
Run a script to set up an environment ahead of time.
I mean, I could kind of-
I've never wanted to.
Yeah.
So that's funny.
So they just ripped it out.
Yeah.
You know, there was a little kerfuffle here.
Defcon was going on.
So the researcher disclosed it in a way that the KDE project was not too pleased about
because it just showed up on Twitter.
And the researcher actually sort of stated that, well, Defcon was coming up and I just
wanted to get this out there.
Man, that shit really pisses me off.
The one thing is when you're doing this is be responsible.
Be responsible and work with the project.
And going on Twitter just to build your personal brand has got to be one of the worst human
being things to do because not only do you make a project look a little foolish because
you don't give them the opportunity to work with a heads up that just about everybody
else gets, but you're putting real users at risk to make yourself look good.
Yeah.
There's just no point.
I mean-
It's disgusting.
We could have got this solved and pushed out before anyone knew.
Now, I doubt that this was being abused in the wild.
It's not a super important vulnerability, but still-
How do you think I have good form?
How do you think I got that key logger on your laptop?
What?
Yeah.
Dang it.
We'll have links though.
You can go read the...
There is a little white paper about the vulnerability and you can go see that, well, that feature,
it's gone.
Finally, ladies and gentlemen, we have perhaps the first modern core boot server platform.
Supermicro's X11 SSH TF, I love the name because it's got SSH in it, is a platform
that supports core boot.
This platform is the first modern upstream core boot server platform on the market with
an Intel Xeon E3 1200 V6 processor, which commonly known as the Kaby Lake DT.
Now, Wes, you did a little sleuthing into why Supermicro would be interested in doing
this and what the motivations are behind this development.
It kind of checks out, kind of makes sense.
Right.
So this was over at the Nine ESEC site.
They've worked with Moldat, which is a VPN provider, and it's all part of the system
transparency project.
And basically the idea is to get as much of this stuff open sourced and transparent as
you can, especially if you're interested as they are as a VPN provider of being able to
guarantee things to their customers about how their systems run.
And it's all well and good to have an OS that has audit logs and shows that you're not keeping
other logs or exactly what you are keeping.
But when you can't trust the firmware, you can't trust anything else.
So true.
You can see from a marketing standpoint, this is a great thing to have on your site, fully
audible platform from the VPN software all the way down to the core boot hardware of
this system.
And, I mean, as you've seen, if you've ever tried to use core boot, most of the time anything
that supports it is way out of date.
But that's just not going to work if you're trying to run a business.
Speaking of core boot, our friends over at System76 and Emma have a little news around
core boot.
It appears System76 are preparing to roll out their first core boot enabled laptop,
which is, I think this news is coming out just ahead of this year's open source firmware
conference.
I bet those two things are not unrelated, Emma.
It is exciting.
And people that pre-order with the open firmware will get to pick up their daughters at the
conference.
Whoa.
Cool.
What kind of work has this taken behind the scenes to make this possible?
Is there like some sort of a crazy mad scientist lab where people are hacking away on firmwares?
Has there been some sort of collaboration with another group?
What has been the engineering side of this?
This has been in-house led by our lead engineer, Jeremy.
He's very big into open firmware and developing in Rust.
And he's been putting it on all the laptops.
They've taken them apart if needed.
They've had to work with Thunderbolt to get proper licensing to include in our core boot.
We've had to work on suspend issues.
Right now, the Darter and the Gazelle both are doing pretty good supporting core boot
fully.
So it's these two systems.
Is it possible for existing purchasers, like people who have a Darter that maybe they got
it six months ago?
Would it be possible for them to switch over to core boot and Linux boot?
Or is this only going to be the new systems?
This should be anyone that currently has a Darter should be able to do it.
And I'm guessing we'll have people reaching out in support if they want to implement that
or test it out, and we'll be happy to give them instructions.
So what's the sales pitch now?
Is it user security and privacy?
How does System76 look at this?
What is the value this adds to the product?
Well, we want to make sure the entire product is open.
So this puts us a step closer to that, moving away from as much proprietary software as
we can.
And this also lets us get to the lowest level of the hardware so we can maximize performance
and just tailor the performance towards the user's needs.
I also noticed the brand new shiny 4K OLED display at our workstation was announced.
And this thing is such a monster that we were speculating last week about what its capabilities
were.
And sure enough, you guys said, well, why don't we send you out a test rig?
So in a couple of weeks, in a few weeks, we may have a review here of the new Adder workstation.
What's your take on this new one?
I bet you must be pretty impressed.
You've seen a lot of laptops come out the doors there.
But this one's 4K OLED, RTX 2070 graphics, 8-core Intel i9, 64 gigs of RAM in a laptop?
Yeah, she's a beauty.
If anyone picks her up, I'm guessing if you're a laptop namer, it's going to have some sexy
woman name.
Yeah, it seems like a lady with that display.
Beautiful eyes, you know.
It's beautiful eyes.
Yeah.
The contrast ratio is actually 100,000 to one.
Oh.
So the contrast is pretty extreme.
And it also has the nits.
It's 400 nits.
So it's pretty bright as well.
That sounds wonderful.
I think we've all been waiting for a laptop like that.
I have a couple of different use cases.
I want to bring it in in-house and see how it processes the drone footage because that's
brought just about every machine down to its knees.
And then set it up as a VM machine, maybe attempt to do some PCI pass-through with it.
When you're talking specs like this.
Yeah, we haven't tried the GPU pass-through yet, but that is on the slate for this week
for sure.
Oh.
Well, I'll let you know.
Yeah, definitely one of the things I would like to test it out and kind of run it through
its paces would be just rendering out video, Blender work, that sort of stuff.
And I mean, they depict it here on the actual landing page for the site.
So with that 2070 in there, you should really be able in the 4K display, you should really
be able to get some high quality graphic and design work done off of this machine.
This also be like one of my first longer term hands-on with a Pop!
OS.
Right.
Looking forward.
I've been waiting.
And then the last thing that I know, I've been looking at the specs of this machine.
The one thing that I really like so far just from the outset is a lot of the big bulky
ports are on the back of the laptop, the power, the Ethernet, the HDMI, the DisplayPort, a
USB-A, NC.
That works so well when you're just setting it up on a mobile desk.
It's so clean.
Yeah.
So I'm really looking forward to it, Emma.
And I'm really glad you're able to make it back and chat with us about the news.
It's great to see the core boot systems.
So what's kind of the timeline for that to be just the default when people order one
of those machines?
I don't have information on that yet.
It's really hard to predict with Nvidia models.
It's an ongoing project, but I do need to mention one other thing.
The Adder is currently on sale for about another month.
So if anyone is interested, we do have a 30-day return period.
So now is the right time to purchase one.
Okay.
Also kind of just saw this slip through the news, but it's probably worth mentioning too,
is that it looks like System76 has been granted a Thunderbolt license.
That seems huge.
Yeah.
We're the core boot, so we can implement Thunderbolt functionality and core boot systems.
That's fantastic.
That was one of the lingering questions I had.
That's great to see.
Well, Emma, that looks like an awesome release.
I can't wait to try it out and kick the tires and see if I can't make it suffer a little
bit.
Awesome.
Well, we look forward to seeing what you think.
Well, Emma, do keep checking in as you're feeling well and joining us because it's good
to hear from you.
We love to have you.
Will do.
Miss you guys.
Glad to see you back.
All right.
Just a couple of items in the old housekeeping this week.
This Friday stream will be the final Friday stream.
Say it ain't so.
As we say goodbye to a crazy experiment that will result in a couple of new things that
we're doing.
So we looked at the Friday stream and said, how could we do this a little differently?
We decided to break it up a little bit.
We'll have more information about that soon.
Live stream, community Q&A's, things like that, that'll be coming down the pipe.
But the first takeaway is come see us on Friday because we have the crew in house this Friday.
If you're listening the week this came out, we'll also release it, of course, over at
Fridaystream.com.
It's going to just be a fun show with the crew in house hanging out and we're launching
a brand new feed.
We'll tell you all about this later on, but you can find it over at extras.show, extras.show.
All kinds of stuff we'll be ending up in, stuff that maybe didn't fit in here, an interview
here and there, a random minimum viable podcast we're trying, extra content perhaps from today's
episode of Linux Unplugged, things like that.
That complete keynote from Thomas Cameron from a couple of weeks back, that's in the
extras feed.
So we've created a new feed of extra content that doesn't quite fit in the other shows,
but we wanted something that you could subscribe to and just get it easily.
Right.
I mean, you know when you run out of JB shows, you're already caught up on everything for
the week.
What are you going to do?
Now we've got a feed for you.
We don't want you to get the shakes.
Extras.show, that's with an S, extras.show, and it's extras.show slash subscribe.
It's just going to be fun, quick stuff in there that gives us an excuse to kind of play
around sometimes, including some stuff that we'll do on the live stream with the community
very soon.
So we'll tell you all about that.
And a nice, nice bit of news on the Linux Academy core side, transcripts are nearly at
100% now.
These are click along transcripts that make it easy to jump around in the video.
And there's a whole new batch of free courses that are available for community members.
If you sign up for Linux Academy community, including some cloud fundamentals, AWS security
essentials, and Kali deep dive, that's worth going, making the free account just for that
right there.
Tell you what.
So check that out.
That's all over at linuxacademy.com.
You can sign up, get a free community account L right here, and our team curates that stuff.
So that's why we mention it from time to time, because it's a good deal.
So go check that out, won't you?
And much, much more.
And keep your ears out on that extras feed, because there'll be a lot of cool stuff coming
down that feed, extras.show slash subscribe for that feed.
Now Mr. Payne, there is a problem out there, and it's getting bigger and bigger by the
day.
It's the only way against, yeah.
Yeah.
Otherwise, Linux would probably be dead.
We'd probably be in a world of hurt, and a bunch of different communities are trying
to solve this big problem that everyone listening to this show knows about, and that's the kernel
is a huge project.
It grows in size and contributors every single month.
On average, most releases have somewhere between 1,000 and 1,500 developers making contributions.
Yeah, that's Major Hayden.
He's a principal software engineer at Red Hat.
And something on the order of 200 to 300 of those are brand new.
They've never made a contribution to the kernel before.
He's going to be joining us in just a moment.
And he's going to talk about a big project they're working on to try to solve this issue.
Major's here to give us some background on this, and it's the continuous integration
project.
It's a really cool idea to kind of try to catch the low-hanging fruit with how fast
the Linux kernel is moving.
There are some challenges there, and I would say Greg Crow Hartman's got a couple of really
good talks on this particular topic.
One of the challenges, I guess the biggest challenge, is that it moves incredibly fast.
The project is large and moves fast.
Last I looked, it was the fastest moving open source project that was out there by a good
amount, even way past Kubernetes.
I think it does, if you take all the commits that have gone into Kubernetes, that's about
two and a half versions of kernel development.
So that's about two and a half releases worth.
So we're talking fast.
Yeah, and so their idea here is, let's come up with something that can monitor this and
send it out across multiple systems, architectures.
Right.
I mean, that's just a wide test base.
The Linux kernel runs everywhere, as we say all the time, and that means you got to test
it everywhere.
And you have tons of different options when you're building it.
Yeah.
Can you imagine doing this by hand?
All right.
I make a couple of changes.
I'm going to go compile that kernel.
I'm going to go distribute it on like six different machines and architectures that
I have to keep in my office to test this, and then I'm going to test it.
Come back, wait, see if anything's changed, and then repeat over and over and over again.
That statistic, the Kubernetes entire product is two and a half kernel versions.
Yeah.
That's amazing.
And you think of Kubernetes as this massive project, right?
Yeah, there was just that review done of it this week, some security thing, and it took
them months.
Yeah, and then you have new contributors, you have subsystems that are on esoteric hardware.
It's really a challenge.
That's where this continuous integration project comes in.
This project came about because there's a lot of low-hanging fruit in the kernel that
can easily be tested.
There's quite a few things that you can test in a VM or you can test on a physical host,
let's say, that are very easy to test internally with just that one machine.
And so the question was asked, why don't we make automation that just runs these tests
to catch the low-hanging fruit?
Because the idea is we want to take Red Hat kernel developers and not have them go deal
with these small, easy-to-fix problems that slow them down and make them have to go find
a solution.
But instead, let's catch these problems before the patch gets merged in the first place.
So if someone says, hey, I'm bringing in these 10 patches, and then we find that when they
do that, all of a sudden memory allocation issues pop up, like you can't allocate memory
like you could before, or it's just not structured in the way that you want to, then you can
call it out.
Someone could say, oh, there's a bug in there.
The nice thing about that is you can find the bug right then when the patch is being
proposed instead of later on when quality engineering is taking a look at a lot of changes,
not just the kernel, but a whole lot of things that are changing and trying to work backwards
and figure out where the problem was.
In our chat with Major, one of the things that he pointed out was that, okay, we can
solve this from a technology standpoint, but there's the human factor as well.
And there's a couple of different projects, but the one that the continuous integration
project is working with to solve for the human factor is called, was it patchwork, Wes?
Yeah, patchwork.
I mean, if you think about it, Linux kernel development is done in its own style.
It's kind of an older style.
You're on the mailing list.
And while, of course, there are Git mirrors everywhere, it's kind of secondary.
So you need to get the culture, understand how to interact with that, and you need a
bridge to actually help the tooling work.
There's a few software projects out that help with that.
There's a big one called patchwork, and it essentially reads through a mailing list and
watches the emails as they come in and tries to figure out which of these patches go together.
So a kernel developer might submit a patch and say, okay, I want to change the way this
works.
It takes 10 patches to make this change.
And so they submit all 10 patches to the mailing list.
And then what patchwork will do is go and say, okay, wait a minute.
This was one contribution from one developer.
It has 10 pieces.
These go together.
And so then inside the web interface, you can go and look at all these patches together
in one place.
And of course, there's an API as well.
So if you have automation, you can actually just pull down the patches or what we call
a patch series when patchwork sticks them together into one patch series.
So that way you can test them.
That way you can report back status on them and that kind of thing.
But it's a software project completely over on the side from the mailing list.
Now think about this for a moment.
They thought they could replace all of this automated stuff.
And they ended up running into this human problem where people have been doing it a
certain way for a long time, have this that works for them.
They got software that archives that it's plain text, it's searchable.
They got filters set up that have been working for them for years.
It's part of a workflow.
And you can't deny the kernel is successful.
So obviously it must work.
Yeah.
And I mean, you're not going to change that, right?
I mean, that's established.
So if you're going to build something to work with, that's your only option.
Spark is an incredible effort to sort of solve a human problem and automate it at the same
time.
We'll have a link in the show notes if you want to know more about it.
And if you'd like us to dig into those kinds of projects, go to linuxunplugged.com slash
contact.
If you'd like us to deep dive into some of that stuff, you definitely can.
Now what's great is the way they're doing this, and even though it requires an incredible
amount of infrastructure, they need system 390s, they need every various ARM system that's
in production.
They need lots of different Intel and AMD systems.
The end result, hopefully, is improvements upstream.
And so as part of this, we asked the question, well, if we do this really well, and we keep
things from getting into the rail kernel that's not supposed to be there, what if we could
do this for upstream?
So what if we could do this for an upstream kernel repository of some sort, and not only
be able to catch it earlier, but then catch it in a way such that we can help upstream
development and help test and help maintainers actually know what's okay to go in the kernel,
what's not?
Okay.
So how many software testers does it need to change a light bulb?
None, because software testers don't make changes.
They will just report that there's darkness.
There are many, many different continuous integration projects.
And OpenQA is probably another very popular one.
We'll have a link to a talk in the show notes.
This talk is about OpenQA.
The heart of OpenSUSE's automated testing.
I'm Ludwig.
I'm employed by SUSE, and still I am one of the engineers behind OpenQA where it is now.
OpenSUSE is a huge project.
And so they're one of many that take advantage of OpenQA.
Yeah.
I mean, think about it.
It's just too complex to test by hand, right?
There's too many little things that can change.
You have a giant collection of software to handle.
So solving that problem, they introduced OpenQA.
One thing that's kind of neat about OpenQA is it replicates things the way a human might
interact with, you know, simulated keyboard and mouse inputs.
So you can test a huge range of software that might not be amenable to other testing methods.
Yeah.
And Fedora, as we've talked about before on the show, considers OpenQA a, quote, significant
part of their release validation process.
That's one of the great things about open source, right?
I mean, one distribution solves a problem and another one can just take advantage of
it.
No, it is.
It is.
Ladies and gentlemen, Mr. Popey is joining us now, mid-show.
Popey, welcome to the Unplugged program.
I know you've messed around with Jenkins a bit.
Is there any kind of continuous integration going on over at Canonical for some of the
projects there that you're aware of?
Oh my God.
Tons of it.
Really?
Yeah.
It's all over the place.
We use a little bit of Jenkins and we also use something called Spread, which Spread
does all the testing for SnapD across a whole bunch of different distros.
So we know that SnapD and Snaps work across different distros before we ship it.
Of course.
It makes perfect sense in the Snap scenario.
And don't we appreciate it.
So you have essentially VMs that are running the different distros that Snap could potentially
run on and then when a new builds out, it deploys to those and tests to see if everything's
working?
Yep.
Does it for every pull request as well.
So the more active they are, the more of these machines get sped up.
Yeah, they get busy.
That's great.
I noticed we had a pull request for the Castor Soundboard project on our Jupiter Broadcasting
GitHub from the app image maintainer.
And he said, you know, apply this patch to your project and every time you do a build
now, I'll just pull it down and I'll automatically build an app image of Castor Soundboard.
Sweet.
Gave us instructions to get it hooked up and then using Travis CI and it'll just sort of
build it for us.
Yeah.
It's a Travis CI pipeline.
It's a good example of how you can solve a problem like developing the Linux kernel with
this unbelievable amount of problem domain or it can come all the way down to a simple
open source soundboard that we use here in the network.
Yeah, the same techniques work all over the place.
Yeah, it's really, it's, it's, you got to solve these problems at machine speed.
It's really what it is.
We use, we use Travis a lot for a lot of the snaps we build and at the recent SnapCraft
Summit in Montreal, we had some guys from Travis CI come along because they want to
streamline how they deliver software to the machines that are actually doing the builds
because obviously they're spinning up thousands of these machines all day, every day.
And you know, it's very noticeable for them when Silicon Valley wakes up and everyone
starts committing the code that they've made and all these Travis CI jobs start spinning
up.
That's a lot of workload.
They're constantly trying to optimize these machines to start as fast as possible and
have all the compilers and all the other build tools, the whole build chain in those machines
as fast as possible.
So they spin up and spin down super fast, super fascinating stuff.
It really is.
Yeah.
I would imagine to be the kind of thing that if I was still in IT, I'd probably be building
probably the kind of things I'd be standing up now.
Totally a tangent thing, but is it just me or do you canonical folk have a lot more of
these sprints these days?
It seems like they went from a couple of times a year to all the time, I mean, one a quarter
almost.
Yeah.
Well, yeah, there is a lot of them.
But there's different types.
We have engineering sprints, which we tend to have every six months and roadmap sprints,
which are every three months and then the snap graph summits, which are like ad hoc.
So yeah, there's a fair number of events going on at the moment.
There's a lot of air travel and getting around.
It's good fun.
Good.
I'm glad you don't.
I'm glad you don't mind.
It can be fun.
But you guys do.
You tend to do them in pretty nice locations.
I've been following along on telecast for poppy recently.
It's fun.
It is fun.
Is there like a URL you give out for that that people if we should give it out here
on the show?
Oh, that's very kind of you.
Yeah.
If you you have to be a telegram user, a telegram user.
But what I did was I exported all of the episodes that I made out and I've put them on by my
website.
So there's a recent tweet flow from me about this.
But if you just go to T dot me slash telecast with poppy, you'll get you'll get to the channel
where all the telegram episodes are.
Learn everything about beer and curry you ever wanted to know and more.
You had the most English telecast the other day where you were walking from home to the
pub to get picked up by your friends to go get curry and I just was listening.
It's so fun because it's like what at most, like seven, 10 minutes ever and sometimes
much less.
So it's like who doesn't have time for that?
That's what I wanted it to be.
It's just like ad hoc, just me having a little chat, whatever's on my mind at the time.
So I don't have to go through the whole episode effort of creating an episode of something
and publishing it somewhere and RSS feeds and all that nonsense.
I just press record in telegram and you know, the thoughts come out of my brain, out of
my mouth and into the phone and I give it a preview list and then hit send and that's
it.
Nothing more than that.
I think you're way ahead of us.
Yeah.
Well, so now my last two questions are, are you going to be back on Ubuntu podcast now
that you're done traveling or is more traveling ahead?
So we just recorded two episodes before I dropped in here.
So yeah, I'm back on.
Martin's out because he's on vacation.
So I'm back in and Martin's out and I think in two weeks time we'll have our first one
with all three of us back for a while.
And then last but not least, um, how, how great is user air turning out?
Did you have any idea how great this would be?
I see it as just like three guys chatting and I have no idea.
Like when you say, when you say nice things, Chris, when we get nice comments, we also
get horrible comments.
Of course.
Mostly on YouTube.
Can I just say, can I just say, not only have I been making podcasts for 13, 14 years now,
but I've been listening to them for just as long and this is one of my favorite podcasts
of all time.
Oh, that's very kind of you.
Say Joe, Joe and Daniel put a lot of effort in, oh, come on.
It's always you.
I'm nodding my head to him.
Always like, yeah, that's right.
That's right.
Well, and I've got kids like he does too.
So it's like as Joe calls me centrist dad, my, my wife referred to you the other day,
Pope is that guy who said something about bedsheets.
Oh my God.
It's also, it's like the only show I get to listen to with my wife too.
There's that.
And I think a big part of what makes it work is Daniel Fore from elementary is willing
to take a bit of, as you would say, a piss, like he'll just sit there and he'll just dig
himself in deeper.
He'll take the piss, Chris.
He'll take the piss.
What is it?
I'm sorry.
Not a piss.
Hold on.
Joe came in studio just to correct me.
Yes.
Take the piss, not take a piss.
Okay.
Thank you, Joe.
Hey, Joe.
Joe's here.
We got all, it's a whole family reunion right now.
We're working on a new super secret show, you know?
So yeah, yeah.
Very secret.
So we've got, we've got so secret.
I even flew drew, drew and, uh, and, uh, L and Joe who haven't been on show.
They're here too.
So we've got in studio, we've got cheese and we've got Brent and we've got Alex and it's
a whole JB party.
Wes and myself, and we're working on some new secret stuff.
It's very exciting.
So one thing I would have to say is if any of the listeners want us to answer any particular
question, they just have to let us know with hashtag ask error, ping us in the, the JB telegram
or in IRC, you know where to find, just ping any one of us with your crazy questions for
us to ask about life, the universe and everything.
They get some great questions.
So whatever medium you like to talk to these guys, hashtag ask error and it'll show up
on their radar and then they ponder them in the show and it leads to some of the best
conversation and discussions.
So yeah.
Well, Popey, it's good to have you here and thanks for giving us the comical side of that.
That's a, it's interesting perspective on how they use continuous integration.
It makes total sense, total sense for snaps.
Well, while we are talking about other great podcasts, you notice we don't do quite as
many distro reviews.
We still do a few.
We do like the big benchmark ones, the ones that we can't not do.
But if you want a review from folks who just can't seem to scratch that distro hop itch,
check out Choose Linux.
Here's a clip from each of them on the most recent distro they randomly tried, which is
one I haven't given a go yet, EndlessOS.
I know that we start almost every single distro hop segment with, well, Elle, I see you had
some issues, but not this time.
This time I'm in love.
This is what I thought an operating system was supposed to be like.
When people tell me about how they use Windows, and it's just simple, and you go and you use
it.
I would say that this is the prettiest GNOME retrofit that I've ever seen, too.
It is almost on par with how good Deepin looks.
I can see what you're getting at, Elle, but it's just too simple for me.
Hmm, EndlessOS.
So it's the man who uses XFCE.
Nice, nice.
Also shout out to XFCE Project had a release this week.
Shout out.
Whoop.
At ShoesLinux.
They're also throwing in a few picks here and there.
I don't know.
I might just stop doing the show and just listen to them.
Yeah, we can learn everything we need.
Mm-hmm.
Just listen to them.
All right.
Well, let's do our pick this week.
Now, everybody's always talking about their tiling window managers, and I'm like, yeah,
I know about your i3.
Yeah, I know about your Awesome, but I like me a traditional desktop environment.
That's always been my go-to line.
Well, Wes, today we are going to have our cake and we are going to have it with a delicious
side of ice cream.
That sounds great.
Yeah.
Right?
It's called QuickTile.
Keyboard-driven window tiling for your existing window manager.
I'm sorry, what did you say?
Existing window manager.
Hmm.
Well, existing X11 window manager.
So everybody's existing window manager.
Hey, hey now.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I don't know, like in Choose Linux, they were reviewing OBS.
And now it's like the reviews are getting to the point where you've got to start making
the OBS disclaimer.
Or I mean, I'm sorry, when you're reviewing OBS, you've got to start making the Wayland
disclaimer.
Oh, yeah.
Like a lot of this stuff doesn't work because-
Yeah, or on Wayland, it's just, oh, it's going to be rough.
Hey, we're getting there.
We're all very hopeful about Pipewire.
So what my plan is is to just hang out on XFCE on X11 for a long time, and I'll just
add a little window tiling key binding magic to my XFCE desktop.
With QuickTile.
Yeah.
So that's where QuickTile comes in.
It's an analog also to WinSplit.
And if you remember that, that was an old school.
There was WinSplit and WinSplit Revolution, which were plugins for Compass.
Now if you don't know what I'm talking about, you're-
You got nothing.
You don't know what I'm talking about?
Really?
Oh, my God.
No.
Oh.
Wes, show them the wobbly windows real quick.
Oh, yeah.
I still got the-
So take a look.
Tell me what you think about these wobbly windows.
What do you think of that?
How far is that fun?
What do you think right there?
Yeah.
Or watch what happens when I close a window.
Watch this.
Come on now.
Now, okay.
Honest, your first impression.
Okay.
The wobbly windows I think is super fun.
It sparks joy.
Oh, yeah.
I can't stop smiling.
You're seeing it.
So I will say I'm a fan of that.
The exploding windows, I don't know.
Yeah.
It felt a little cheesy.
But imagine like you're angry and you want to close something.
Ah.
And you just explode it.
You know what was even better is back in the day they had burn down windows.
You'd close it and it would fire effect and it would burn down.
I'd be okay with like turning the old CRT TVs off.
Yeah.
Oh.
That would be great.
In Plasma, one of the fun things you can do is you can set it so that your windows gray
out when the application crashes, which is kind of a neat effect.
I think I have that in Plasma.
Yeah.
Did you set that up?
Oh, yeah.
No, I didn't set it up.
You could turn on the wobbly windows.
Oh.
Careful.
Yeah.
It's just under desktop effects.
Most of the time.
Right?
I mean, all those engineers work to build that GPU for something, might as well put
it to the...
I don't even notice anymore.
I kind of like I feel bad showing it because the wobble doesn't seem like it's very wobbly
anymore.
You could up the wobble if you want.
Oh, right.
Of course.
It's Plasma.
So you could increase the wobble factor if you want to increase the wobble factor.
Poppy will not be increasing the wobble factor because he did something that is so 2019 Linux
personality that I just I love and also fully appreciate.
So on Twitter, which God only knows why he chose to do this, he announced that he was
switching away from Plasma.
And then was it six successive tweets explaining how it's okay that you're switching away from
Plasma and that everybody else's choices are okay, too.
Yeah.
I don't like this whole, you know, internet Zed list celebrity has switched from Distro
A to Distro B, the sky is falling rubbish.
So I just had to super clarify everything in a complete succession of tweets.
I liked it, though, because you referenced back the first tweet of when you actually
installed KDE Neon.
And what are you on now?
You just on mainline Ubuntu?
Yeah, Ubuntu 19.04 with GNOME.
What was the was it just time for just trying something else or what was the what was the
impetus?
The actual trigger to this was last week's lup.
Oh, really?
When you I came in, and my audio was all messed up.
I've tried so many things, and I couldn't figure out what the hell it was.
So I thought, okay, there's got to be something fundamental on my system.
I don't know what it is.
And I don't know who to file a bug against, or what projects file a bug against.
So I decided, right, let's just upgrade to the latest of everything.
And if it still happens, then then I can start looking for where the bug is.
And it hasn't happened yet, I don't think.
Which is partly why I'm here to test that this actually works.
I'm wondering if your impression not even necessarily from like a technical level, but
my impression is the GNOME audio stack just seems a little simpler.
Like it just seems like it's sitting right on top of Pulse and whatever Pulse is doing,
that's what GNOME is doing.
So I think part of it is that KDE gives you knobs and buttons to switch, so Plasma gives
you like things you can tweak.
And because the GNOME desktop doesn't, it's harder to shoot yourself in the foot.
And I think it's entirely possible that I've twiddled something in KDE at some point in
the last 18 months, which has made this go bad, and I don't know what that is.
That's possible.
But there are lots of other possibilities as well.
Hardware failure, it could be Pulse audio is rubbish.
There's so many things.
I can't point the finger at any one thing, but yeah, the audio subsystem on GNOME seems
to be simpler.
You sound great today.
Awesome.
Thank you.
That's what matters.
I can't argue with that.
Yeah.
I find that I hop about every nine months now.
It's about my...
Yeah.
It's the problem when all the options are so good.
It's all good.
We're going to do some reloading here in the studio.
In fact, we were thinking about having an on-air debate about what we reload to.
I'm becoming less and less attracted to nuking and paving a system.
So I built an arch system a year ago.
It turned one year old on July 27th, and I've got it set up just the way I like it.
And I don't know if this is just because I've now been using Linux for long enough that
I can actually troubleshoot my problems sufficiently that nuking and paving is no longer a requirement
to get a stable system, or whether it's just because I've become so comfortable in this
pair of old, worn-out, comfy shoes that now it's like I just don't feel the desire to
nuke and pave like I used to.
I mean, I have a Proxmox server in my basement that I can just spin stuff up on.
And my laptop and my desktop are work horses now, and they just need to work.
Sure.
There is an element of you have to know enough about a system because half the re-kicks that
happen on our team are, we did something weird, and we've got to start again.
And if you keep doing it every time, you don't ever quite learn what it was that broke it.
But you always have to do that math, like, ah, my time is worth X, Y, Z.
I know it'll take me two hours to re-kick this thing.
I know it'll take me five hours to troubleshoot it-ish, or more, exactly, exactly, exactly.
But Popey said something in one of his recent telecasts with Popey that I had to respond
back because he said, Popey, you were talking about upgrades, and how people are always
like, we almost have like a wipe and pave or a nuke and pave culture that just sort
of is the default answer.
And it's not necessarily always the best way to go.
Sometimes just upgrading for a while actually is the best way.
Yeah, I've long lamented the fact that people will say don't upgrade because upgrades are
broken and therefore you should always do a clean install.
And I appreciate, you know, sometimes they are broken.
And part of the problem here is that people do all kinds of crazy things to their machines
and then forget they've ever done that, and then six months later they go to upgrade and
something they've done is so fundamental that the upgrade breaks.
Now part of that is they then blame us, the distro maintainer, because we make a shonky
distro that can't upgrade properly, yet they ripped out core components of the desktop
six months ago, but they don't remember because this was just a command they copy and pasted
off of a blog somewhere in order to get a new theme or to get a new splash screen in
grub.
Yeah, disable system D or something stupid.
Or yeah, something ludicrous like that, but they don't know they did it.
Did you hear that I've switched from system D?
It's great.
Troll.
Yeah.
But part of the problem is us in that when we leave people in a really horrible state
when an upgrade breaks, you're left with often a black screen or no way to log in.
Or if you do log in, your desktop doesn't load properly or something, and that's horrible.
And when you're in that state as a user, what are you going to do?
You're going to nuke and pave and then you're going to get it in your head that that's the
right way to upgrade.
And so it becomes ingrained behavior.
And see, for me, this is one of the big advantages of building an Archbox is I know every command
that went into building that thing and I had to go and learn why I'm running that particular
command.
Whereas, as you say, copying and pasting something to piping it to shell is very easy and tempting,
but it can lead to problems down the road that you just don't foresee because you don't
understand what it is you did.
I mean, I love Arch, so don't get me wrong.
But here's the context for the rest of the audience.
Before the show, we were discussing what OS we're going to deploy in the studio after
today's show.
We have a couple of things we just need to address.
Some of these machines were either set up as Kubuntu or Neon, and now they're running
XFCE, and we just want to do a clean install, so it's just a base system.
Start fresh.
And we want to do it before there's a lot of issues.
There's a couple of niggly things we've noticed.
And then, of course, because it's a group full of Linux geeks, the debate of what distro
we should use has been the number one.
I can't make this up.
Oh, yeah.
No, it really is the serious point of contention.
So Alex is advocating for Arch, Drew is essentially advocating for Ubuntu LTS, and I'm on the
fence leaning towards Fedora.
You say that, but you want Fedora.
You'll be happy to see Fedora chosen.
Yeah, I would be.
I would be.
More Ubuntu.
So I'm going to make my, I'll start.
So Alex just made his case for Arch.
I will counter that with, we started with Arch.
We started with Arch.
And now here we are.
May I add that one of the additional problems that I doubt Alex has that we would have in
the studio is you like to do upgrades immediately before live shows, because that's when you're
here in the studio working on the machines.
There is a little bit of that.
And it's fine.
Like most, you know, when you do the upgrades, when you have time and a safe space, Arch
is fine.
It's very stable.
I've stopped doing that.
Okay.
If you say so.
Well.
You got tricked.
Okay, maybe I haven't completely 100% stopped, but I've reduced.
I want this to be a soundboard clip.
I've moderated.
That three seconds is amazing.
No, I think for me, it's like, I've always felt like a little bit of like spitting into
the wind, but it is also like me saying my operating system should be able to handle
this.
Like, so you probably saw this week that a canonical announced that the absolute latest
and greatest version of Ubuntu LTS now has like a nice gooey way to sign up for the live
patch service, get yourself an Ubuntu one account, and then you can patch three machines
for free and you can do it all through the gooey and then you're secure through reboots
for some of the more important ones.
That's super appealing to me in a studio environment.
And so initially I envisioned like deploying Ubuntu LTS everywhere, bring it all into landscape
using live patch to manage them, and then I started having sound problems, which we've
documented and we've resolved for the most case by switching up to Jack.
It's pretty much solved our problems.
But now we're sitting here with these systems that are sort of Frankensteined and I've had
a lot of experience in the last nine months.
I don't know.
How long has it been?
Yeah.
Six, nine months.
Yeah, messing with Fedora and it seems like a very clean, reliable system that has good
solid upgrades.
And Drew himself has some good experience with it.
Doesn't hurt that our editor loves it.
And between the two of you, like we can pretty much pull anything off with Jack audio.
So I kind of feel like maybe it's time to just switch to Fedora and then we have Fedora
on the server and on the systems.
And that's the part that appeals to me the most is one common OS, one common environment.
The server's running Fedora, my laptop's running Fedora, the studio systems are running
Fedora.
Everything is the same environment.
And you are, I mean, you're kind of the primary admin.
You're here in the studio the most, you're using the machines the most, so that's not
for nothing.
Right.
But I don't want to do it at the expense of software availability or reduced production
quality.
And so that's where I wonder if Drew has a case for Ubuntu LTS.
So I do.
But before I get to that case, I will say I am already maintaining a group of packages
that do what we need it to do for my own use because I use Fedora on my workstations as
well.
I know.
That's why I think it's funny that you're going to come in here and advocate for Ubuntu.
So I would be comfortable with the studio having Fedora.
To me, it does make sense.
What I like about Ubuntu LTS is the longstanding nature of it.
Fedora 30 is going to be supported until, what, two years after release, right?
And we'd probably bump up to 31 after that arrives.
And it's a lot of upgrading.
And it is targeting a use case that is more agile than a production machine like a recording
studio to me should be.
I will grant you, going Fedora is conceding that we are getting on an upgrade tread machine.
Yes.
So that is why I think the Ubuntu LTS route is probably the better route for a production
machine.
Workstations, those can be great and agile.
And that's what I do at home.
But if you want something to be fairly static and work the same way every time, an LTS is
kind of the, to me, it's the right way to go.
And the Ubuntu Studio repositories are fantastic.
They have everything that I put in my Fedora repositories already in there.
So really-
How do people find that repo?
If you just do a search on the Fedora copper for Drew of Doom or Linux Pro Audio, they'll
find it.
Because it's actually really nice.
Some of those tools have not been on Fedora before this.
So it's actually really nice that you're doing that.
So Wes, here's my argument.
My counter-argument, because everything Drew said, can argue with that, absolutely solid,
especially when you add the fact that we could use live patch so we could actually even keep
the system secure without having to reboot them.
That's super attractive.
And I would only need these three systems, it doesn't need to be more than that.
But you're working on Jack in the Box, which is a project to take a lot of the audio routing
and put it inside a Docker container and sort of normalize the desktop in the OS.
And if we were to roll out something like that, it wouldn't really matter.
Yeah, I mean, that is kind of the flip side of we could adopt Ubuntu LTS, but eventually
we will have to upgrade and that's a long, it's going to be a long time, possibly.
That's good and bad.
If we do go with Fedora, we're going to get a lot of practice following the upgrade path.
Well, and then also, I think we could probably take advantage more quickly of things like
pipeline as well.
Right.
So I think it's kind of the difference between what Drew's suggesting and making them really
appliances like things we'd be, you know, you find in a rack you don't futz with.
Right.
And as much as we do use these as a production machine, they're also content sometimes.
And you know, we are still adapting our pipeline, how we do the shows, and we probably are going
to continue doing that for a while.
Part of me wants to use these shows as a way to push forward the most modern way to develop
audio.
Right.
And like, we're doing some super freaking cool stuff with Linux audio right now.
Alex, I know you want to jump in.
I want to give you a chance.
Yeah, I do.
So I've been looking in the fedoraproject.org website whilst you've been talking, and the
average lifespan of a fedora release hovers around the shortest is 330 days.
So just under a year.
The longest is 420 days, and that was Fedora 22.
But on average, it seems to hover around that 380 mark.
So you are, you know, signing up to get on this train of upgrading at least every nine
months.
Yeah.
By the looks of it.
That's what I estimate.
But having to upgrade, it could be a really inconvenient time because these releases come,
they say every six months with Fedora, but they also have a big disclaimer underneath
that says it will be approximately six months depending, it will be done when it's done,
is the disclaimer.
So it could end up shifting slightly.
So it won't be like, okay, it's May Linux Fest Northwest is out of the way, we can safely
upgrade this box now, you might end up having to wait a bit.
So I mean, for me, a rolling distro, you never really have to worry about that kind of stuff.
I can also see where Drew's coming from, though, with the LTS being a minimum to probably four
years worth of updates and stuff.
I mean, for me, I'd probably go that route, right?
I mean, yeah, 1804 is really in that sweet spot, right?
It's really good.
And, you know, one other option that hasn't been floated, Centos.
If you're doing everything in a container, it doesn't make it, you're not giving up what,
you know, the thing Chris said, he doesn't want to give up software availability.
If you're doing it on Centos, and everything's in a container, then part of me feels like
I'm like, not participating, like I'm watching Linux on the on the from the benches, if I
if I'm using Centos, you have a laptop for that you have.
These are production machines that just need to work.
I have a proposition for you, Chris.
How about you do whatever it is you're going to do now.
And then you'll get it out of your system.
And then in nine months time, switch to 2004 LTS, where you can have ZFS on route.
And then you can do snapshots before you do your upgrades.
And then you won't have to worry about it.
There you go.
He has a point there.
It's very logical.
It's very, that is, as, as the good Mr. Spock would say, logical.
I guess I'm struggling to come up with a reason now.
I think we've made a good case for the LTS, especially since the package availability
is there from the other flavors.
I guess what would you propose is our solution, then, for the variance between production
and workstations?
I mean, we work for a company called Linux Academy, right?
I think it's I think we can solve that problem.
I think it's a good thing to be familiar with multiple different flavors of Linux.
You're right.
You know, I mean, as host of Choose Linux, I ought to be right.
But yeah, no, it's I don't I don't see any reason to pigeonhole ourselves into saying,
we run Fedora only or we run Ubuntu only or any.
To me, I like being familiar with multiple different systems and I feel comfortable administrating
them all.
All right.
So let's do it then.
Let's do.
I think we should use Ubuntu 1804 LTS right here.
That'll be what we reload the system to.
We just got to make sure we make sure it's decent because like there's some some excess
ego in run right now and some of the window management.
It's just it's kind of bare bones.
What?
Are you proposing something else?
No, not necessarily.
I'm just saying, you know, we want to make sure it's easy to use windows.
Well, that wouldn't hurt.
Can I can I tell you about it?
OK, we got to make sure we install a dock.
What about QuickTile?
What about using QuickTile?
Yeah.
You know, it is also Python, so we could probably script it, too.
Oh, yeah, you can.
Oh, absolutely.
Yeah.
You've you've whipped together a couple of hacks using XRender, which has been helpful.
We could expand on that.
But you're right.
The XFC does lack some modern window rules and stuff like that that are super nice and
plasma.
We just I'm just saying we just we should think about those things as we go forward.
Thankfully on the LTS, it really doesn't matter what base distribution we just can't we can
mix it up and install this Wesley Wesley Wesley, Ben, you're coming at me.
You're coming at me with questions, not solutions right now.
I mean, you're to me.
You're just I don't know what you mean.
You mean we can't use Ubuntu like my head's spinning now, like my whole world is falling
apart.
I just want you to trick it out for me.
Adopting a distro like a religion is stupid.
Thank you, Thomas.
Very well.
So what are your feelings on the current iteration of Ubuntu with Gnome as the default?
Like, how do you feel about Gnome these days?
Because I know you've had a actually, I think Gnome looks great.
You know, I don't want to steal anyone's thunder, but one of our team members here is trying
it out.
And I was looking over his or her shoulder and it looks so good, you know, just looks
so good.
It's just not what I need for production appliance systems.
I actually would prefer nothing has a no compositor, no no special 3D effects, no nothing.
I3 then.
I got it.
All right.
Oof.
Chase, did you hear what he just said?
He said I3 on a production machine.
I'm glad you guys I just was just listening to all you guys hash it out.
The reality is, is that Drew is right, is that you should use the LTS because.
Maybe we should do I3.
Long term support, fellas.
Hey, what do you think?
Maybe we should we give I3 a go?
Yeah, if you're down, let's do it.
I mean, I3 is great.
Let's give it a go.
And then we'll say we'll give it a review in next week.
You want to put a cheat sheet on the wall next to you?
Yeah, good call.
Cheat sheet.
All right.
OK.
Well, we'll see how that goes.
So make sure you tune back next Tuesday.
You can join us live over at jblive.tv.
You can burn it at Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar and see you next Tuesday.
It's for people who like to mess with computers, if you and you know who you are, if you're
somebody who doesn't want to mess with it.
I just want to surf.
I just want to buy something on Amazon, send an email to my kids, look at some websites.
If that's you, you don't want to mess with it.
Probably not a good choice.
What was that hesitation before?
Look at some websites.
You know what's funny is Leo actually now is he's a pretty happy desktop Linux user.
That's what I hear.
Neil, how was Flock?
It was awesome.
Aside from being in Hungary, which I've never been to before, which was it was an experience
in itself.
It was great meeting all these people again for another year and seeing a bunch of new
faces do.
Now this is the old Fedora Developers Conference.
And did you did you get anything accomplished?
Did you achieve any kind of kumbaya on anything that you set out for?
Like how was that aspect of it?
So from my point of view, the big thing was I wanted to see, you know, how the relationship
between the new RHEL 8 and Fedora is going to work out and like talk with some of the
people about the extra packages for Enterprise Linux for RHEL 8, as well as the Fedora modularity
thing and its downstream RHEL cousin, the application stream stuff.
So that was that was a big chunk of what I was looking toward.
But there was also some great things about how we're going to handle some of the changes
in the Python ecosystem.
You already know from my previous times being on Live Subplugged, talking about murdering
Python 2 in its sleep.
So there there was that as well as looking forward to the future of where, you know,
in the Python ecosystem is evolving the way that software is developed and shipped and
things like that and stuff like, you know, getting into weeds of it, things like dist
utils and set up tools.
If you're familiar with Python development have been the staple or nearly the requirement
for everything that's going away as a requirement.
And that requires that means that a lot of things about how we assume Python software
is shipped has to change.
And we have the most important part.
Mm hmm.
Did you get sick?
No.
Yeah.
Ladies and gentlemen, congratulations.
Congratulations.
That's moving on.
You know, next your next level conferencing now, Neil, that's what that means.