This is Linux Unplugged Episode 41 for May 20th, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's digging through all of the
quote-unquote big data. My name is Chris. My name is Matt. Hey Matt. So this week by
big data I mean we've got some results from the survey that we did last week in
the Linux Unplugged show. We asked folks to chime in with their home server
setups and I had some like I had some basic like do you have this installed do
you have this installed and then I left like these fields for like leave some
notes and that's where there's some really interesting stuff but I think
some of the other things that stood out for me is the cloud versus home
installation bias we'll talk more about that and then also just the massive
amount of people that listed Arch as their home server distribution.
Interesting. Which is funny. I'm not surprised. We just did an episode on that
right? Yeah we did. And I thought maybe I was going out on a limb but turns out I'm
behind it I'm behind the trend and we've also got the survey from our Linux the
Linux subreddit they do like an annual survey and they got a brand new one that
just came out it's actually it's getting to the size now where I think it's worth
talking about they had over 10,000 respondents from all different walks of
life on the Linux subreddit so we'll cover some of the results from that
coming up in today's episode but first I wanted to tease a couple of things just
let's just you know what like I'm just a hint bomb I'm gonna drop I haven't
showed you this to you Max I wanted to surprise you on the show I don't know if
you have the video stream up but just a little hint I do we have a little hint
now on the video stream of where things are going with how to Linux there is
chase Eric and I down in downtown Seattle on the beautiful Kerry at the
beautiful Kerry Park which is like the most picturesque version of Seattle you
have ever seen it's gorgeous so I won't say what we were doing but there might
have been some shenanigans happening yesterday some scenery some selfies you
know just some weird you know we were we were kind of making asses of ourselves
to be honest with you because it's a pretty busy park because it's so iconic
you know it's so like it's so like classic Seattle yeah and when there we
were kind of goofing around and people were actually to be true to be truthful
about it very patient with us because for the most part I mean every now and
then there was like some dog shenanigans going on and things like that and some
dog fights and and we sometimes like the reflector would fly away and go towards
a crowd of people yeah that was a possibility too so but it was funny gosh
it was a gorgeous day yesterday it's gorgeous day here today as well but
that's so yeah boy I just tell you what man that was that was some nice
shooting but that's not actually all this morning I wanted to talk about
before we get rolling I also have see if you can guess see I'll try to do it
before you see the video version on the stream see if you can guess what I have
in my hot little hands by this audio tone can you guess what I have in my
hands no that's the Intel sound man yes yeah I got the we just got it in studio
today this morning the Intel NUC D 5 4 2 5 0 W Y K H rolls right off the tongue
that's a gorgeous piece of hardware yeah this so this is the I wish I had my
box to join you this is the fatter NUC this this is a big fat on it's and the
reason for that is it can take a standard size SSD you know two and a
half inch SSD instead of that PCI little card you have to use so and it's not
that much bigger to be honest with you but now yeah so we're gonna have a
little this is gonna be a little dedicated Skype machine so we can do
some fancier Skype stuff here in JB one and you know we were really kind of like
okay how do we want to do this what is the best way to accomplish what we want
to do and the at the end of it it was like because we already had the SSD on
on-site it really meant all-in for a core i5 rig with I think it's I think we
get eight gigs or 16 gigs I can't remember eight gigs I think it was like
400 bucks from Amazon yeah 460 or something like that total and it's gonna
make you know it's just perfect for Skype it's it's small Rekai calls it
the glue of the studio cuz now we've got this is our second one and I believe it
these little it's just so much it's so much power in a little compact machine
and Linux is such a slam dunk on the NUC it's just really easy cuz it's all
Intel parts how much do they got well that one that one is yeah like also all
set after we bought the RAM and everything was like 460 or 480 something
like that but that's pretty good this is my five right yeah that's an i5 laptop
i5 with yeah but it has like the virtualization stuff yeah it's just a
really low undervolted underclock yeah I mean you get really low TDP yeah don't
get the most performance like you would if you went with a desktop i3 you you
know we get the same feature set just a little bit less performance but it can
turbo up there sometimes if it's not overheating yeah the one we've got now
in in production is usually around you know 1.8 gigahertz for each core which
for doing for doing HD Skype is more than enough it's really more than enough
so it's it's it's great or you know mumble or whatever that's gonna be
essentially like another call-in box that way we can take multiple Skype
video calls and things like that essentially like the communication hub
yeah and so having something that is low profile quiet like that and so
eventually the other nice thing is we can essentially add more I'm just we'll
just get a little shelf and put them on there and they have HDMI directly out
that goes into the capture machine they have one audio out port and then we use
one of the USB ports to add a USB sound card which we would do anyways so they're
pretty nice little machines so the one that I'm showing the picture on the
live stream is a nut too and this is an arch box run in gnome 312 and it's just
it's it's great it's it's sometimes needs restarted I've noticed that
sometimes these knocks need to be rebooted I don't know what's up with
that I don't know if it's the Intel driver or what have you updated the
firmware chiptap I don't know I don't think so oh because they don't or at
least mine never came with updated firmware so when I got it I updated them
and it seems to be better after about David Rick I might have you know the
thing what we've noticed is the HDMI audio out after like about 24 48 hours
starts to get crackly oh see I don't use the audio at all in mine so I wouldn't
know so maybe that's why I haven't noticed Rekha says he did update the
firmware yeah well what's cool about it is so so so they have an audio out jack
plus then we have the USB sound card so that we can like you know so we have
this so audio comes in over USB or goes out depending on the setup and then we
also have an audio out over HDMI and because it's the Intel Iris graphics the
driver works pretty much flawlessly so after your base install of even you know
and it makes an arch setup super simple after your bachins base install you've
got working HDMI mirroring with audio signal so for us that means one wire to
the capture machine and we can get the desktop picture and the sound from the
machine without having to run any other wires which leaves those other audio
interfaces available for other things and so it it's it's a great combination
I really am impressed with these boxes and I think I wonder why Intel is the
only one selling these because it seems like people could be relabeling these
maybe people are oh I think like gigabyte does so yeah gigabyte uses a
more powerful chip in the brain yeah and then you have that company that makes
the orange box they also do a whole line of nick things yeah those guys figure
what they're called no I'm not they have an i3 version that's only 299 or 289 yes
yeah they do yeah I went with the higher processor just so that way we have a
little more flexibility what we use it for right because a lot of times thinking
for me I maybe just get the cheap yeah you know it'd be great for like a
visuals machine for BSD now because it's super small and it's just out of the way
and I went with the i5 because here in the studio I have found that every
piece of gear ends up getting used for all kinds of different stuff that you
would never expect it and and so I try to just sort of hedge my bets when I'm
buying studio equipment and I err on the side of more power so that way when it
ends up doing something I never planned for it's a capable for doing the job but
if you would like this is always gonna be email web you know it's it's it's
always gonna do like maybe one VM something like that you could go lower
power I think oh yeah I can think of so many uses for those boxes yeah so many
yeah I think calling them the glue is a good description and you know I've seen
some pushback on our coverage of the Ubuntu orange box people are like this
is like there's a thread right now in the subreddit it's like what's the
actual use case for something like this I I think people undersell the NUC and I
think I think it's I think that's why I maybe it's because I've had so many good
experiences with the NUC now I started off feeling like it was a finicky
device and I still think there's some I think still has some esoteric rough
edges but I think it's I think it's gonna revolutionize some production
stuff it's what one of my opinion all on the NUC NUC is a great workstation it
could be a great media center but at the end of the day it's not gonna make a
good data center you can actually exactly a whole portable data center
with that Ubuntu orange box yeah that's just what I'm seeing yeah I could use
that yeah exactly for a data center there's something like the the super
micro iCloud it's like three use and fits ten i3s and it's probably more
practical yeah Alan what I'm talking about is basically people who want to
build their own data center and don't have that much space so right well three
uses enough only like three pizza boxes well yeah that's true you know it's
heavier and harder to carry around whereas the orange box has those carry
handles and stuffs it's super portable in that case so you can take one of
those data center and a truck those half-use sleds and put one in a case like the Nuc
is but it's sorry the orange box rather is but well there were a bunch of places
I used to do this with Mac Mini's I was just gonna say that do that I was just
gonna say the Mac Mini they're still around it's Mac Mini polo dot net I
still haven't made the money back yeah you go Matt you send him a power PC Mac
Mini and you could run things the power on those I mean like because they're
really they weren't powerful but they were real consistent I don't know how to
describe that better they just the power something about the power piece oh the
power PC chip was solid yeah I thought that was a great machine I agree and I
couldn't bring myself to throw it away yeah yeah why am I looking at buying a
NUC right now I'm supposed to be having dinner I'll tell you about something
else you should consider buying because it's mobile that makes sense and that's
our first sponsor this week that is Ting head over to linux.ting.com shout it
proud my friends linux.ting.com that tells them that you appreciate them
supporting the Linux unplugged podcast and that you're willing to take a couple
of minutes and check out their service as a thank you for keeping us on the
air but here's why you'd want to go there once you're there you'll you'll be
amazed at Ting because it's no contract mobile and you only pay for what you use
it's a flat six dollars per month and then it's just taxes and your usage on
top of that so like in my case I have two phones on my Ting account and I end
up paying a very very low rate because both myself and Rekai who's the other
person on my account are very smart about our data usage we're primarily Wi-Fi
users because we're pretty much either here at the studio or somewhere else that
has Wi-Fi and then you know of course when I'm driving I'm careful with that
that makes my monthly bill with two phones generally unless we have a big
day where we have to tether or something like that for you know several days in
row and Comcast is totally biting the dust you know that because that'll go up
a little bit but even in that scenario it was like forty four dollars for two
smartphones that's for a Nexus 5 and an HTC one and that's with everything picture
picture messaging hotspot tethering included with that plan it's just use
it's just your usage they bail they bill on the usage not on the gimmick and
that's what makes Ting stand out so go to linux.ting.com because that's gonna
take $25 off your first device and they've got a whole new slew of devices
including the beautiful HTC one m8 that is unquestionably one of the best
Android phones on the market now one of the big improvements they made over the
HTC one is considerable battery improvements which I think is awesome
and a little sleeker design of course and a few other things they've got
Samsung Galaxy s5 as well they have new mid-range and entry-level phones and I
was taking a look at the Moto X on Ting check this out you buy this Moto X if
you go to linux.ting.com it's gonna cost you three hundred and fifty six dollars
that's an unlocked phone that you own that you're only paying for the usage
you're not in a contract it's $356 that's not the cost where they're
spreading it out over a two-year contract without and gouge you that's
you pay it and you're done and then it's just what you use after that for a
Motorola X and some folks say this is one of the best Android phones ever made
that's unbelievable so go over to linux.ting.com and check out what they've
got to offer and try out their savings calculator put your current bill in
there and then check out the difference and tell me you couldn't go get
yourself a new computer every couple of years on that money you'd save it was
unbelievable for me linux.ting.com and a really big thank you to ting for
sponsoring Linux unplugged getting us into our 40s Matt it's so crazy all
right hard to believe we're in the 40s already I mean it's like where'd that go
I know right that really did go fast so I'm just reposting in the chat room
right now a Google Doc that's it oh hi that's the problem oh you're the problem
you are the Samsung can be hi we were discussing a side conversation well
we're back I'll let you finish it up in the post show sorry I just jumped right
back in I just posted in the chat room if you guys want to take a look at it to
the survey results the Google spreadsheet results from the home
server survey that we did last episode and rocks like everybody has a home
server yeah seriously yeah so rotten I don't what what jumped out at you
initially when you looked at the results the majority of people using the home
for their home server is heavily in backups and media for likes file storage
like media servers and stuff like that but also it's a lot of hate against
using cloud services yeah it was sort of well go ahead that's pretty easy to
explain the average user has like what a megabit of upload baby yeah even even
high-end people like me only have five megabits of upload yeah well try to
upload a couple of terabytes that way well there's other uses in just in file
storage and back yeah yeah right so you know I like knowing where my stuff is
and I this was a home server survey but that jumped out at me too rotten when I
was looking through this essentially like out of out of how many do we get a
hundred and what was it I think hundred fifty five respondents hundred fifty
eight respondents like two of them are using like a host somewhere to be their
home server and like VPN into it and in like both cases like it's because of bit
torrent sync and maybe like plex or maybe more than two but it's like almost
just two and in in all cases where they're using cloud hosting it's for bit
torrent sync and in some cases plex and I was I was surprised it was that strong
of a difference because it's there was a huge standout what about you it what
stuck it what stood out to you when you were looking at the results you know
actually I I see a lot of flex when I look at these results yes a lot of media
serving yeah couch potato and some other stuff I've never even heard of like sick
beard oh yeah well we covered sick beard recently but that does seem to be really
popular yeah which is good it's good and it's ab nzb which kind of goes along with
six beard sick beard and I didn't participate in the survey but a lot of
these people and I are in perfect sync like that with bit torrent sync you know
I use all the time yeah and plex yeah and network backup I a few folks are
using tiny tiny RSS which makes me happy because I think that's a good project
and it was a great Google reader replacement use that as well you know
what jumped out to it jumped out at me is not as much own cloud as I expected
there is definitely a fair amount of own cloud representation but not quite as
much that's just because you know in my opinion I've talked about this before
it's a pain in the butt to set up and then once it does get set up it's like
sometimes it screws up and maybe that's just the database back end or something
I just honestly don't know but yeah there's a lot less own cloud I see one
or two things of own cloud on here but not much I like some of these that some
of these guys gave us a total like like a list out of their drives and all that
kind of stuff if you are considering jumping into a server and you want to
see some of this stuff this is a really good resource we'll have it linked in
the show notes here's an example of somebody who has a DVR running on fedora
20 but he's planning to change it to archie says 2 terabyte hard drive 4
gigs of RAM he's got myth TV subsonic xbmc plex and of course SSH so many
folks so many folks using plex so many plex users very dominant there's also a
lot more arch than I would expect it yes and you know what a lot more arch
almost almost a majority of arch and also a few mentions of free BSD in here
and a lot of free NAS too so here's a good one I liked this one this guy's got
sab nzb couch potato plex uses his network backup and then a git annex
which a git server is a really good idea he says I think the main importance for
the NAS will be enough storage being able to put whatever I would like on
there he says I do monthly ZFS scrubs I do snapshots every day with the ZFS
tools and then I use ZFS send to send my data to another storage device in
another place which I thought was really good he said he likes to do our sinks
for simple backups duplicity for Windows duplications and BUP BUP one of the best
backup utilities out there which sounds familiar but I haven't checked it out I
don't think really cool results I really liked going through this and yeah like
other people have picked up on arch really stood out in in this survey arch
really stood out and I wanted to talk about that a little bit because we just
did us we just did an episode about building the ultimate home server on
arch and before we went on the air I thought maybe I would get a lot of
feedback that I was crazy I was being too on the edge I I was using a toy
operating system for a serious task and I was being irresponsible it's honestly
what I I kind of projected what I thought if I was looking into what the
future what I thought the feedback was gonna be and I would say overall it has
been very positive we had a very good response to Sunday's episode the
ultimate you know a home server arch home server the arch home server
challenge that we did and this the survey results here which is funny I
didn't I didn't want to look at this before I did the episode because I
didn't want to like cheat and like do oh that looked cool I want to do that I
wanted to build the thing I wanted to build and then follow up this on Tuesday
so when I opened this up this morning to look at this I was kind of floored and
then combined with all of the really positive feedback that we got and a lot
of folks saying yeah I run arch 2 that was sort of revealing to me and I
thought I've been wondering if maybe you and I just sort of happened to
serendipitously and thanks to the chat room as I've been reminded to point out
switch to arch it's sort of a time when arch is reaching sort of a mass momentum
and despite I think so yeah and despite how hard the arch project seems to try
to make it hard for people to adopt it seems to somehow keep happening and then
we just got these results of the 2014 reddit linux subreddit is that hey yeah
the subreddit for the linux art is like what our slash linux yeah our slash
linux subreddit and they've done these for a while but a couple of years ago it
was taken over by somebody new and I think he's been doing a good job with
this and so I wanted to cover his results and chat with you guys about
this and you know I mean these are just these were results they were posted on
a subreddit they made it sticky for a while you know so I take it for what it
is they had 10,292 respondents which is up from 7,698 last year and the year
before that it was 4,932 so a lot of growth and it seems our linux itself has
grown a lot in the last year so you combine the growth of linux itself with
the with the linux subreddit and then the fact that the mod stick it it they
had some pretty good results and so they asked folks do you use linux on
non-server computers and of course like 96 of their respondents 96% of the
respondents yes because they're in the subreddit do you use and then they asked
them do you run linux on any of your server computers and 58% of people
responded yes when they asked for fun or profit for fun 66% of people for profit
27% of people so that's all kind of interesting but what I thought really
stood out is this next survey question what linux distro distro do you
primarily use on your non server computer what is the out of all 10,000
respondents what is the number one distribution arch not Ubuntu it's arch
it's arch linux 64% on the server 36% on the desktop overall I just thought that
was pretty stand out here's a couple of bits of differences Debian has replaced
linux mint for position number three elementary OS has quickly gained a
following putting in position number six Zubuntu has dropped to position number
seven after elementary OS and crunchbang has risen above kubuntu and gen 2 for
position number eight and kubuntu has dropped off the top ten making it in
position 11 now I don't know about you guys but my gut for some reason gives
more credence to this survey then the top ten results on distro watch no
disrespect to the distro watch folks but for some reason distro watch is based
on just clicks on their website it's very right right and this seems like I
mean I don't have a strong impression of the user base of our Linux but it seems
to be a wide mix and in fact if anything I would have labeled them as anti arch
Linux to tell you the truth I would have said they kind of hate on arch a lot in
the I disagree I think I think that they're I think you're definitely gonna
have a mix but I would say they're more anti boon to I've seen like a bigger
group of purists for sure but they're definitely pretty pretty set in their
ways yeah also they should have looked at the the survey should have also
included the the basis so they should tell you like elementary OS is based on
a bunch of so they should point out like how much space in a bunch of yeah well
then you lost this place because of fragmentation possible well you could
make that same argument about Debbie and then sure but it's more I think it's
there's the the more important part is that they they did the survey for like
people to fill out the survey like three weeks before Ubuntu released 1404 yes
and that would have skewed the results massively in that pay in that way well
they should have it should have skewed the results towards Ubuntu because the
Ubuntu hype was at an all-time high before the 1404 but people weren't
using it it was asking what are you currently using people are probably
waiting to use it well I know I would think they'd be using a book do don't
you think and don't you think more Ubuntu users would be trolling the our
Linux subreddit for news about the Ubuntu release than normal and there's
a lot of people who went from there's people who went from arch to 1404 and
have been using it for a while there's even a couple blog posts about it but I
know it's just it's not that it's saying that they it's just the timing was
where they could have waited a month I don't know I I think if anything doing a
survey as the weeks leading up to the next major release of anything gives
more attention to Ubuntu and it's getting if anything I think that's
actually more of an indictment of the poor showing of Ubuntu hmm but I could
be wrong our could be nothing you know all of this could mean nothing let's
keep that in mind here's I want a couple more things just to just as for us to
chew on what Linux distro distro you primarily use on your non server
computers so this is fun versus profit number one distribution people use for
fun arch Linux no surprise there when it comes to profit only 15% of them use
arch which is not too surprising Debian does a strong showing at 23% as does
fedora for profit 28% fedora came in at number two for fun at 71% now what did
what other Linux distro do you use on your non server computers Debian played
showed very strong here followed by Ubuntu and arch Linux but through this
whole thing arch does really good now here's here's an interesting one more
people using Linux on laptops than on desktops not by a huge huge number but
by by a pretty good number with that that number though because he set it up
where it was laptops and tablets are the same answer yeah but who's running who's
running Linux on the tablet people could be considering Android or you know a
bunch of touch yeah yeah but you know it does kind of get to the point where I do
run Linux on my laptop but I also run Windows on my gaming desktop for those
windows right games right yeah I think there's some folks that do that so yeah
Debian it's interesting too for server distributions Debian was the top
followed by Ubuntu then sent OS number three then arch in number four or it's
Linux at number four then followed by right at Enterprise Linux that's that's
got to be because of the demo that's got to be the demo I would think yeah
although just because they make the most money doesn't mean they have the largest
install base and then which Linux distro do you primarily use on your
server computers fun versus profit Debian again is up there now I thought
that was kind of funny too they get into the desktop scene and they ask folks
like what desktop and what's your favorite Linux GUI gnome 3 really no
wow that surprised me yeah yeah well I actually went and arched it and
put the good man on it I am too yeah I'm doing gnome 3 on the ultra pro right now
and I love it it's growing on me I'm actually a big fan of gnome 3 except is
it mutter yeah mutter is the it's not it's not working very well for me so
I've had a few crashes just because of mutter and so it may be kind of locked
me down and not be nice gnome 3 yeah yeah but as when I did use it it's it's
pretty awesome Katie Katie that's number two oh go ahead there Devlin make your
point yeah that actually makes me question now that we've been seeing like
the cutie and GTK fight going on if gnome shell is gnome trees being so
successful in terms of usage in desktop wouldn't that mean that kind of GTK 3 at
least is getting some attention there yeah I mean maybe this momentum will
keep them relevant so what what do you guys think what is the most hated Linux
graphical environment any guesses unity by a freaking ginormous margin ginormous
margin which honestly feels a little unfair in fact he even points out that
the hate for unity is actually up over previous years so now I think that
improves so much well that comes to people more people being exposed to it
now because it's it's in the mainline version go ahead there is the second
most what I see here is like it seems like the power users that being are the
ones that are actually actively in these communities and participating on the
voting and stuff and the result is that those are the users that feel that they
got kind of left out yeah the newest choices right and as a result it goes
back to yep pretty much yeah you got it and let me tell you something else I
think what this shows you is and this is my this is my connection here but I
think one of the reasons why arch is seeing such strong performance is
because it's a great distribution to run gnome and what's the number one desktop
everybody loves gnome so what do people run on their desktops in this survey
arch what's the number one desktop environment they're using gnome so it is
interesting that because nobody even though fedora does a pretty good job
nobody has gotten off their dumb asses to make a good gnome 3 implementation so
arch is eating their lunch in the power users and I think I think we as Linux
users need to change our perspective because we always talk about these
magical pony new users who show up from magical land and just want to say please
sir give me some Linux because that's of course how new users operate so we're
always talking about these mythical new users and in reality it is those of us
who've been running Linux for over a decade now that are still here we're
still relevant we're still buying products and guess what we like gnome we
like arch Linux because we have evolved our tastes over time not all of us and
I'm not disparaging anybody who hasn't but I think there is a vast majority of
longtime Linux users who are sick of the distribution crap and politics they want
these kids off their lawn they just want to get a good damn desktop use the
latest software and that's what they want to do all day long and let the kids
fight it out they can go do whatever they need to do and personally maybe I'm
just bringing my own baggage into this but I think I might be representing a
large crowd here and I think these numbers might back that up what do you
guys think I don't think it's your own your baggage I mean when gnome shell
started came out people were bashing at it I looked at what they were trying to
achieve and it pleased me I didn't like the implementation at the moment so I
didn't jump right right away to using it but yeah that's how I was to know
crossroads crossroads do you uh what do you think do you think this is a me
bearing my own baggage well the thing about no gnome 3 and are just arch
doesn't really do a lot there I mean the whole thing is you know upstream and all
that kind of stuff but Fedora really pushes gnome a great example of this is
gnome software still does not run on arch because package kit on official
arch repos is zero dot seven dot six and gnome software requires zero dot eight
dot one I think yeah and it doesn't build as I've tried I can't I can't get
it to build and so it really it's Fedora is pushing gnome Fedora is the epitome
of gnome all right Colonel Linux why don't you play devil's advocate for me
so I don't disagree with what you're saying yeah you make a very good point
but what but taking that attitude of you know we're the power users and and and
cater to us that's great for one desktop and and we have that but that I think
where these companies like canonical are coming in where they're trying to craft
the the unity desktop is we want to want to further we want to spread the idea of
Linux and new users are turned off to Linux primarily because there's people
like us that say well listen I can do everything from the command line and
that works really really well and it's really really efficient I mean you just
talked a couple episodes ago about how efficient crazy efficient it is to be
able to do things from the command line but that scares new users off and so if
we want to reach past 10% of the market share we have to create a welcoming
desktop I think that's the other side of the argument right I agree yeah and that
then and that what that what that means is it doesn't minimize the open seusses
and the Ubuntu's and and the fedoras and the manjias and all of these things
because they obviously have a role to play in this but what I think it does
mean is there I think there has been this group of Linux users who kind of
have just been overlooked because we're so busy thinking we know what's
best for everybody and thinking how we're gonna get more users we're so
we're so worried about getting more people using Linux that we kind of just
forget about this group who I think is is trying to show their voice in these
results and I but I at the same time doesn't mean you cater exclusively to
them I think that would go I think I think that would that would that would
stagnate the adoption of Linux absolutely I agree with you Noah all
right Riley you had a you had a point for unity I wanted to get to that
actually said unity is actually almost underrated because like the only thing
people ever use unity on is Ubuntu and people just don't like Ubuntu for
whatever our reason but if you actually tried it on Arch it's actually pretty
awesome I've been using it for like two weeks now I can't believe how stable it
is are you using the mooo OS or did you just load it on no I just did it I did
the repo method is it the 1404 yeah it's the same version in 1404 it's got
like all the new global menu stuff all that I like that idea we should do a
poll and find out what desktops the chat room and the and the unplugged users use
now there is a caveat with that though cuz Eric installed it he said this week
and his GTK stuff got messed up on the other desktops so if you're you need if
you're gonna use unity just to use unity don't try to use other stuff with it
yeah correct yeah correct yeah it kind of borked my machine and I didn't back
it up before so or that partition anyway so I ended up having to just nuke and
pave my arch install that kind of applies to Ubuntu as well if you use
unity you just use unity yeah that's true you know when I loaded LXQT on my
Ubuntu 1404 install I was a little bummed because the menus were so jammed
full of just all kinds of junk that unity kind of does a good job of not
putting in your face but when you go to something as a more traditional menu
structure oh it was it was like I was feeling the presence of unity and all of
the system setting all of that stuff but you know that's what you get when you
install something over a desktop so that's any no thing you know I should
stop into a spot but it would you mind going to straw poll dot me and making a
poll of like just say what's your desktop environment and just put like you
know some of your some of the top ones in there and give me a link I'll in fact
I'll jump down to restricted casting so you guys can come up with the list while
I tell you guys about digital ocean another sponsor of Linux unplugged and
another company that I am very very happy to be a customer of what is
digital ocean well digital ocean is simple cloud hosting dedicated to
offering the most intuitive an easy way to spin up a cloud server folks in our
audience have been able to get up and running about 42 seconds but just you
know to hedge their bets digital ocean is gonna say yeah we bet about 55
seconds or so you can get a cloud server that you have root access to spun up and
pricing plants are only $5 per month for 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD
which I really love the asset that SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer yes a
terabyte so for like you know a lot of you that's right there at $5 you'd be
surprised at how much machine you can get plus digital ocean pairs up with the
tier 1 bandwidth providers and the best data center locations all over the world
in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam and they're always growing
they're always adding in fact to that end they're also hiring so you might
want to go digital ocean calm and click that we're hiring button and see if
there's a job there for you but while you're there use our brand new promo
well actually it's not so brand new anymore it's getting towards the end of
May well let's let's rock May for Linux unplugged use our promo code unplugged
May and you'll get a $10 credit that $10 credit will let you try out that $5 rig
for two months for absolutely free digital ocean calm unplugged May is that
promo code once you get logged in go check out that dashboard go look at that
dashboard and tell me that is not the coolest thing ever they have managed to
wrap around an entire KVM management system that allows you to deploy virtual
images around the world the different data centers take snapshots and backups
manage the DNS and HTML 5 web console one-click application installs all
riding on top of Linux and KVM through seriously one of the best and most
intuitive but yet powerful interfaces I have ever seen it is worth getting a
digital ocean account just to see a little bit of masterpiece right there
digital ocean calm and use the promo code unplugged May and a huge huge huge
thank you at a digital ocean oh and also I was gonna mention go look at their
pricing plans they have hourly pricing I don't mention that enough and so if you
guys just need to do a little bit of testing you can go get a digital ocean
account use our promo code unplugged May and try the hourly pricing you will
probably be able to run that machine for quite a while with that $10 credit
that is a great way if you just want to run it for a couple of hours I've got
emails from folks that do build projects up there they do some quick
syncing and they shut it down try it out try out their hourly pricing you might
find that works really well for you and also if you get stuck when you're trying
to deploy something go look at their community section they've got some
really good tutorials that people have written up like here's an example how to
use bit torrent sync to synchronize directories and Ubuntu 1404 one of the
things I noticed in our survey was a lot of folks who are using cloud hosting are
using that now as their own method of backup because it's just a really good
way for you to be able to control your data and backup and there's all kinds of
things that are in here it's not just bit torrent sync of course there's all
kinds of server-side applications you might need a little help they've got
tons and tons of pages and their current and up-to-date because they've got a
really passionate community digital ocean comm and use the promo code
unplugged me to get that $10 credit and a big thank you to digital ocean for
sponsoring Linux unplugged loves it so I'll jump back in here how we how we
doing are we working on the pole okay yeah so once you submit it it'll it'll
make a little link that you can copy at the top you just you can drop off the
results a little slash R and then try toss out the chairman we'll have the
chatroom vote and get an idea of what their poll is I'll vote to and we'll put
that out there but I might have too many options it's not good letting me oh
really you guys put that what are the desktops you put in there what are they
oh gosh we put in no Michelle Kate unity Katie e X of CE LX DE LX QT mate i3
awesome ex-nomad Pantheon cinnamon flux box open box TWM window manager e17
that's probably the problem that's just the shell there's a few you can easily
take out like JWM you can take that out yeah this is what happens when a
committee comes up with some of it if also some of them you maybe just
combine a bunch of the very very simple yeah let's do that yeah that's a great
idea XFCE and LXD yes we should just say tiling or something all right UT is not
it's not even final yet let's give you to be in there dear Devlin has something
he wants to add to the to the discussion let's him go ahead even though I
personally use a tree most of the time and I use gnome tree when I go out in
public and if I'm going to a place full of noobs I go with something more that
will be more user-friendly to them even though my personal preference is I tree
in that scenario I think it matches well and I think a lot of us kind of do that
we've seen that at least in the in the Linux best stuff like that people go and
use their technical stuff but when they go into to meet new users it's just that
becomes so simpler to to show something up yeah all right so I wanted to open up
a topic to the to the room here so now everyone is free to move about the
cabin one thing I thought it'd be kind of fun because we are obviously a bunch
of Linux enthusiasts slash advocates we're always talking about why people
switch to Linux I also think it's good though to be real about it so that way
because here's the here's the here's the truth you guys here's there's a lot of
people listen to this show that have a dirty secret they don't use Linux they
run Windows or Mac or whatever it is but they listen they listen to kind of keep
their beak wet they listen to kind of keep their ear to the ground so they
know what's going on because they're considering it and so for these folks I
like to give them the real story and you know I've been thinking about this a lot
because in how to Linux chase is going to be making the switch and you know I
don't want to blow smoke up his butt I want to be honest like when something
sucks it sucks and I wanted to be able to say yeah man that doesn't work so well
but don't worry you can do X or yeah we're still working on that that kind of
stuff so bit puffing the chatroom just came out of the closet he's on a Mac
right now but I thought let's talk about some some Linux switching stories or
when we convince somebody to switch to Linux and it backfired real bad because
maybe we can learn as a group I'll start and then I wanted to toss over to Noah
because I know he's done some client deployment so he probably has the story
but I'll start with mine my like one of my biggest Linux shames like my big
Linux failure was when I got my wife who was my girlfriend at the time I believe
switched over to Linux and it was KDE this is a long time ago and I switched
her photo manager over from whatever she was using at the time on the Mac it
might have been I photo though I feel like this was pre I photo it was
different enough that when she was organizing her photos she was
permanently moving and deleting them and didn't know that because that's not how
it worked in her own program and she I end up losing a whole bunch of her her
photos and that was like you know at that point we were done you know
experiment was over going back to another opera I can't remember was
Windows or what it was and it was no that the switch to Linux experiment was
done no no we're married now so I managed to save the relationship but I
don't know if I had pushed that Linux thing who knows so that's that's my
failure you know I should have I should have probably thought ahead and thought
yeah this photo programs gonna work different for her but Noah have you been
out there have you been to have you convinced a client or a user or a friend
or family member to switch to Linux only to have it blow up in their face or your
face as the case might be yeah many it has it has blown up I want to give a
disclaimer it has gone the other way many many many more times nine out of ten
times right when I install Linux for a client they are much happier and I lose
money right that's that's 90% of the way they're not they're not taking they're
not calling you up for support anymore so you lose money right yes right but
there have been a couple of times one one that I'll tell you one that's that's
comical and then then a true example of where Linux just failed the we instead
we had a hotel it was complete web-based system that they used to check people in
and out and so we walked in this I said well what's the problem well the
computer is really slow and it takes a long time to boot nothing really works
right and I I mentioned this when when we were all meeting at Linux fest but I
have a dirty a dirty little secret when I anytime I try somebody out on Linux
for the first time what I will do is I will use a Samsung 840 SSD because when
I put that drive into the computer all of a sudden not only don't they have the
junk that comes with Windows but that SSD just super fast yeah right and base
next to an actual spinning hard drive it just seems that much faster right so I
put the drive in there and oh my gosh the computer so fast everything works
we're so happy great when I leave the next day I get a call the computer
doesn't work what do you mean it doesn't work so I go back over and I look and she
goes well I don't like see this the icon has changed it's no longer the little
blue e how do we get the blue e on there and I said well it'll do the same thing
just click on this well we don't know which one to click on and all of our
staff doesn't know which one to click on and when you open it everything works
fine but if anyone closes it then we don't know how to get back there so I
actually ended up downloading the icon file and changing it and renaming it
Internet Explorer and theming it to look like Windows Internet Explorer just to
keep them happy oh man now that I don't think that really exemplifies Linux
failing where Linux actually truly and totally failed me was I had a friend and
she called me she said you know what do you recommend I'm my computer's kind of
reaching the end of its life and I said what do you do with it well I get online
and I edit documents and I do this and I do that okay so walked her through
installing Linux all of her music would not pull over because she had purchased
it in whatever Windows uses I don't even know but plays for sure purchase well I
sure she had a zoom okay so whatever plays yeah okay so whatever it is it
doesn't pull into Linux and it was it was a it was it was one of those things
where she'd asked me before can I move my music collection over well of course
you can move music Linux plays music yeah no problem right right no that
didn't work yeah and then she goes well I can play can I play Netflix well we
installed the Netflix desktop but if you don't have a really powerful machine
that running all of that the layers that it needs to run that didn't work yeah
yeah and essentially what it all boiled down to was she could edit her word
documents and she could check her email and that was it and we ended up going
back to Windows oh yeah I mean that you know like that the WMA they were
probably even WMA files they were yeah I mean I think yeah so that's you know
that's a that's a hard thing because that's Angela my wife's mom kind of the
same situation right they use a computer they're on a satellite connection so
they're basically just downloading a few things printing off photos and you know
updating Facebook but they have bought I mean I don't want to speak for them but
it's potentially thousands of dollars worth of DRM copyrighted protected music
and it's just one of those things where I don't have the time to unencumber all
of that music for them so they are on like some ancient you might even be
Vista install like what are you gonna do right all right mumble anybody else in
the mumble room want to share like a Linux deployment blew up I mean again
like Noah said of course it generally goes good I don't have like a huge
detailed one but essentially I gave someone Linux because they were tired of
windows and then they I had to go away for like a couple weeks or so and while
at the time I got back they had given up and bought a Mac that was a quick nut
punch like I was like I thought you're gonna keep going then boom you strike
with that I was going over to a friend of a friend's house it was late at night
we weren't gonna be there for long and I see that he's running Ubuntu on his TV
like right in front of his bed I'm like oh cool Linux Linux Linux and then he
couldn't get the resolution correct and I'm like well hmm maybe you should just
try updating so we do a little pseudo app get update pseudo upgrade and it
doesn't boot and I have to leave pretty soon and he never talks to me again all
right if my microphone works yeah yes yeah we so does it go ahead check yeah
okay actually I have three stories why can I can wrap it up in one because it's
always the same story for all three okay what is it in the last month I just
can't explain how it happened but I guess it's mixture between the XP ending
and the always malware stuff that happens on Windows systems anyway three
guys came to me and asked specifically to install them Linux on their
computers and I must say they are happy with it oh good just happy well that's
good that's great yeah I had my dad on it for years and years and then he ended
up wanting a new computer and the shiny Mac got him and we had a couple we had a
little we had a little bit of a mini disaster that kind of pushed him over
and yeah but my worst story is the photo one all right we've had we've had some
back and forth but we do now have the official oh yeah what we have one more
story before I get to know I just wanted to point out that my story was like a
dropping a bomb with a Mac thing but this is also in like 2005 2006 so it was
it was kind of a mess back then anyway yeah mine mine was mine was way mine
like was before iTunes was a thing I think it before I photo was a thing
that's how long ago mine was but and so like now I would ever use dark table or
something like that yeah really short positive one sure yeah yeah go ahead
turns out my 80 year old staff that actually put Suza on his box on his own
and it works he's happy with it you know and you guys has and I didn't help him
that no bearing on the fact that I'm a Linux user now but my my grandpa on my
dad's side of the family he's he's in his 80s and he's got he's his favorite
distro is puppy Linux that's his he's loved puppy Linux for years and he
thinks this is the best perfect distro for him and he likes putting on low end
hardware but he's also a big Fedora user and he tries out every Ubuntu
release but he always ends up going back to Fedora which I think is hilarious
because yeah he's also in his 80s and it's awesome yeah it's just something
he's always enjoyed tinkering with and I didn't even know until after I started
the Linux action show like a couple of years into it it came up like my dad
mentioned to him that I was doing a Linux show and it's like oh you like
Linux like are you serious like my mind was blown it my mind was it was like I
entered another reality all right so yeah that's more or less what happened
to me as well that's amazing here is the we've had a few iterations of but here's
our latest poll which desktop environment do you use I'm gonna vote
we'll also have this in the show notes we want the download audience to vote
too I'm just curious what you guys use so I'm gonna vote for Gnome Shell for
both of us okay Matt okay sounds good that sounds like me all right so I'm
voting and I guess I already voted on that maybe I already voted voted all
right and the results are hold on survey says I think we put straw poll under
some load here right now Gnome Shell has a healthy 27% lead followed by KDE with
a 22% lead cinnamon coming in at 11% unity 9% XFCE 9% mate 7% and then it
kind of trails off from there this is almost mirroring exactly what we saw in
our Linux that's wild and you know I've kind of lost my love for cinnamon I mean
it's it was fun for a while I just you know it's kind of like watching the same
TV show over and over after a while you can't get bored with it well yeah but
the extensions of cinnamon are not as good as gnomes but they are pretty good
yeah they are pretty good it got my interest at the end of the day for me in
cinnamon and I I think it's great in like for a lot of folks who want a
classical UI but brought a little more into you know the year 2014 man to
cinnamon nail that and it doesn't really well for me the problem is is I think
what you're kind of getting at Matt is I'm just kind of done with that it's the
same thing that eventually kind of wears on me about mate or Mate you know I've
I've played that I grok that UI but I recognize that the paradigm that was
set up way back in the 80s you know is due for some refreshing and I think
that's why I like gnome 3 and and honestly if I spend enough time
configuring my KDE desktop what I like about KDE 2 is I can make it feel like a
more modern operating system it's true I mean now on some boxes I still do use
XFC simply because I'm not in front of them every day I just need I need quick
access to something I've used in a launcher anyways I don't care why run
the resources at that point but for a daily use situation yeah I do prefer
norm go ahead Riley for people who don't want like all the unnecessary stuff that
Katie yes like it still has all your extensions it still has like your
desktop but effects and all that stuff so yeah pretty much 30 ways to get to
the control panel I mean you know that's kind of I would disagree with that but
that's I think cinnamon is also a good source for people who want to a full
fledged DE but can't you know put they can't devote a lot of resources to it
because I've there's been benchmarks that show that XFC Inc and cinnamon are
very close to about the same resource usage and that's actually kind of
amazing when you can say and you think about it came from gnome how does how
does cinnamon work when you don't have compositing does it still work okay you
know it's it doesn't work very well it's very it's very slow it needs a graphics
card it doesn't really matter what kind of graphics card so that would be an
area though where XFCE kind of has yeah that leg up and still you're still in a
GTK environment and I think an area where LXQT is gonna be a strong
competitor for XFC I wanted to go back to something that Crossroads was gonna
mention go ahead Crossroads okay so the thing about thing about cinnamon is that
at least when I but I always thought when I was on unity I saw cinnamon I
thought it was great I thought it was wonderful I really wanted to try it out
I never really got around to it ended up using KDE and used a few things and then
I finally installed the mangero version of with cinnamon and I you know I thought
I was gonna love it I thought it was gonna be great and I used it it was fine
and then I got bored really quickly and I just it never turned me on I think
sometimes too because the options are there to tweak with them you fiddle with
them and then you get bored with fiddling with those options and kind of
sounds so weird it almost sounds like what's it called when like you get
kidnapped and then you relate to your kidnappers Stockholm Stockholm Stockholm
I wonder if gnome gives me Stockholm syndrome a little bit because I'm like
because it doesn't have all these things for me to tweak although they are
tweakable actually like a lot of stuff is surprisingly tweakable but because
like it's not just a right-click it's not right there I generally just leave
it alone like one I essentially I install gnome I spend about 20 minutes getting
like my theme and my icons and and fiddling with different things that may
you know every time I try something new settling on something and then I
generally don't ever change it again unless a new icon back comes out that I
want to check like right so but on KDE it is a daily occurrence that I'm
changing something because it's there and it's it's just right there too it's
right-click boom there it is so it's a long and short if you have any type of
obsessive types I guess that's probably not because I'm that way too um you know
I speak from experience that might not be the best desktop choice for folks
like us I don't know now lion head you just don't get it I understand what's
your point well I just feel confused when I'm using it so I just feel that
no X yeah so I just feel that XFCE is more streamlined at least for my kind of
workflow yeah it just works better on the laptop or on the same time you can
stream it streamline it whatever way you want to yeah all right well before we
wrap up I'll go ahead finish up finishing thought I was just gonna say I
think the the problem with gnome is that people aren't you aren't used to the
paradigm so they expect something else yeah when if they give it enough time
then gnome could actually be it can change your your your preference of the
paradigm and you'll actually like no more than other ones if you just try it
yep very good guys well so if you wanted to check out this the home server survey
I would especially if you're gonna build a home server soon or you're thinking
about or you want to figure out how you want to improve yours go look at those
results there's some great content that you guys supply gals guys and gals I say
guys universally it's a unisex term for me just disclaimer on that and then also
we'd love to hear your feedback I I decided this week we would do the survey
for the feedback we generally read a few emails on the Linux unplugged show for
this week I actually ended up replying directly a lot to the emails and didn't
really feel like anyone particularly grabbed me that I want to pull into the
show but we do love featuring your emails so go over to Jupiter broadcasting
comm click that contact link choose Linux unplug from the drop-down and
maybe you can kick off our next discussion I love having a topic on the
show that sort of inspired by an email that comes it maybe not be the main
topic but something we can chew on is always appreciated so anything in the
Linux space that you would love to hear a good discussion on please send it and
ask your question don't make it too long so that way we can fit it on air and you
never know maybe you will help set the course for the next Linux unplugged show
and last but not least we do have this open mumble room from these fine
gentlemen that you've been hearing from and we don't have any ladies that are
joining us in the virtual mumble room so ladies out there if you'd like to
represent the female Linux perspective we'd love to have you just go over to
JB live TV we do Linux unplugged live at 2 p.m. Pacific on Tuesday just go to
Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get that in your time zone and when
you go to the live page we have an embedded chat room and you can join that
embedded chat room and hit bang mumble and when you hit bang mumble it tells
you the mumble server address now you might say Chris why don't you just say
it right now well first of all dear listener perhaps it's gonna change at
some point and I just want you to stay dynamic or maybe maybe it's a members
only jacket and the only way you can find out is you come to our chat room
put on the jacket we should totally have a Linux unplugged members only jacket I
think that would actually might still have mine I think that would actually be
particularly kind of cool I don't I don't think teespring is gonna be able
to hook us up with that though but that'd be a good one all right is there
any other business we should we should cover before we get out of here well you
might want to mention that bang is the exclamation mark for people who are on
the audio only oh what oh yeah did I mention the bank suggest thing even I
even say bang suggest oh yeah bang is exclamation right yeah and the other
thing so there we have a few commands in the chat room you join us live the other
one is is bang suggest where you can help us title it and then we we vote on
that shenanigans at the end of the show it's kind of like the funnest thing we
do all right guys well thanks everybody for a great show this week Matt if all
goes as planned now you know me I hate to I hate to speak for a guest but if
all goes as planned on Sunday Jonathan from the open shot project will be
joining us to discuss open shot where they're at give us an update on how that
projects doing so I think that should be a good show oh that should be on
Sunday's Linux action show and if it if that doesn't work out if Jonathan ends
up you know right realizing he's about to come on with a bunch of hooligans
like us then we'll come up with something else great we just pull it
right out of our butts we just store it all right there oh he's good people I'm
sure I know I think I think we're all looking forward to it all right Matt
we'll have a great week I'll see you on Sunday okay see you then all right
everyone thanks so much for to this week's episode of Linux unplugged see
you right back here next Tuesday