okay so mr. West that is me mr. West should you choose to accept it I have a
challenge for you to take place during this episode what now for a little
episode yep and in episode now you can say no feel free to say no in this
episode I thought it would be particularly cool if we set up a server
for starbound now I have linked instructions it appears to be a pretty
straightforward process to install on an Ubuntu server the only tricky thing is
and this might be the hard part is it requires a Steam login to download the
binary on the account that's already purchased it now I could provide my
credentials uh-huh because I bought oh but I didn't buy it on Steam I got it on
GOG hmm this is like much as a custom team it's like 15 bucks this is this is
minecraft but way cooler it's space travel you go to a planet there's
multiplayer co-op you collect resources you build tunnels that sounds awesome
caves and we could set up a Jupiter broadcasting server on the Jupiter
broadcasting org domain and we could all play I mean be awesome this is a
time sucker that makes minecraft look like child's play and it just came out
for Linux starbound it was actually a Kickstarter for a while so I don't know
maybe that's where it sounds familiar from yeah so take a look at the link and
let me know if you want to take the challenge we'll find out at the other
end of the intro this is Linux Unplugged episode 155 for June 26, 2016
Oh welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's making sure to
drink all of its water and still leave room for beer my name is Chris my name is
Wes hey there Wes hey Chris boy these look like some great brews you brought in on
the show today with a fun name no yeah well how the narrows brewing that's not
it that's not the fun part what's the fun part the fun part is it's the
galloping Gertie golden ale it's great that's not what we're here to talk about
though coming up on this week's episode of the unplugged program we're gonna go
a little bit down history lane talk a little bit with mr. wimpy about his
travels to the snappy sprint event later on in the show we're gonna talk
about a very important open source project getting audited and ask the
mumble room if you could audit any open source using a set amount of money we
saw there's certain limitations which projects would you audit to see how
secure they really are we'll ask them when we get to there well I'm curious
got some really interesting new code open source this week from a company you
probably wouldn't think is open sourcing code open BSD says they're even more
secure than ever now because they're getting rid of Linux compatibility aka
the Linux vulnerability as they say yeah we'll talk about that coming up in the
show a friend of the podcast here's got a new release we'll talk about that and
last but not least at some point we're gonna find out if Wes can complete the
star bound challenge now he's already begun ladies and gentlemen so Wes you
have accepted the challenge challenge except I think it's gonna be great now I
haven't played the game a lot because I as soon as I saw the multiplayer thing
well how do you do this and there's just not a lot of servers out there yet so
we'll see if it's possible Wes is working what right away over there on his
spotnik laptop you know with a nice unplug sticker too yeah I like that
looking good that's looking really good all right well let's bring in our
virtual love so we can get into the stories time appropriate greetings
mumble room hi there well it's good to see you it is good to see you so I have
I have like some good news I want to start with because it's good news from
the least likely source and it happens to be right on the heels of us talking
about this last week which is always a lot of fun West spotted this particular
story it's called surround 360 it's a project by Facebook to make software
pipeline an entire rendering pipeline to do VR 360 images and they also they have
in here they have the code up on github but also in here they have some really
cool specs it looks really cool and a super cool video of the camera that you
need to do this with and I that is all very fine and you can watch the video
it's got a great soundtrack yeah yeah super inspirational and they are they're
building the camera and they're putting it all together and it does look really
cool it's like a dome with a whole bunch of image sensors on there their
stitching software takes the images captured by 17 cameras in the surround
360 and transforms them into a stereoscopic 360 panorama suitable for
viewing in VR the software vastly reduces the typical 3d 60 3d 360 degree
processing time while maintaining 8k per eye quality which they think is optimal
for VR they say the rendering stereo 360 video is a hard problem for a variety of
reasons it takes a tone of RAM roughly 120 gigabytes of data per minute of
video so that's even double when you go to 60 frames per second there's little
room for error because any inconsistencies in the stitching really
look bad and stand out in order to create VR video practically we need to
be able to process all this data as fast as possible which is often an exact
opposition to maximum quality so this thing the software it is it's really
amazing they talk about the acquire tangular how do you know how you say
this equity or equity I can't even say equatorial equatorial triangular
equatorial triangular basically you know the earth turns out as a globe and it's
that when you start they have a diet I'd ever die I can't even bother to get
into it because I would just fail horribly I'm already beginning to but
that's not the important part what's the important part is yeah they can figure
all that you know spatial stuff out for the camera but check out some of the
interesting details the cameras output raw pattern images right on to like a
Linux box then the image signal processor which is part of the surround
360 rendering code converts the raw sensor data into a standard RGB PNG
image oh cool it applies gamma and color correction then the rendering system
reads the camera images and builds the projections from each the projections
cover a whole sphere with a rectangular structure and texture each camera
captures only a portion of the full sphere but this can then be
represented on the projection they put it all together equal rectangular
equal equal rectangular okay thank you I don't know why I can't I can't I just
simply can't but I like this and also remember we just recently talked about
how G streamer is building in stuff to support so the timing on this is rather
perfect because G streamer just put on a whole bunch of infrastructure stuff and
is beginning to work on more and then Facebook comes along and specs out the
camera and releases a whole rendering pipeline yeah exactly good guy Facebook
I don't get to say that very often I don't really we were getting into a
pre-show topic I can't even remember exactly what it was that wouldn't be
said that made me think of it but it essentially came down to my time is very
valuable and I have to be selective about how I spend it oh that's what it
was it was about setting up more servicing thing yeah we'll put that in
the in the post show hopefully boy that boy have I if I said that maybe a
million times how many times I can't even think even in this show I've said
that and that's that's why Joshua Drake's post over at command prompt inks blog
really made me think now he's part of the Postgres equal community and he's
talking he's writing a post that he titled the fall of open source once upon
a time he says Foss was born about was born it was about freedom it was about
exposing quality within source code allowed everyone equal rights and equal
access technique to the technology they were using the idea was if you were
capable you could fix code you could or you could pay someone to fix it an
ideology that there was something greater than yourself and there were an
inherent right to build what was human I sat in a bar slowly nursing beers with
other community members over a period of hours we spoke of many things we spoke
of never ever doing a new post sequel website we spoke of my disdain for
Amazon Web Services since reformed with the exception of s3 we spoke of life we
argued we had honest discourse and that's excellent there was nobody
complaining of political correctness there was nobody claiming to be
offended there was nobody leaving because feelings were hurt there was a
community member who passed out in his chair and dropped his phone we walked
him back to his room to make sure he was safe and all was good this retrospective
has been digging around in my gray matter since that night six months ago
that is until I began to itch and like any good community member I think I'm
gonna be scratching that itch that itch was my time is precious to me it seems
like a harmless thing to say of course your time is precious to you I would say
that's probably true of most people I know that my time is precious to me I
make a point of working part-time from May to September so I can take time for
my family the problem within the statement is context the statement came
from a well-known contributor and a very smart guy the guy the reference was in
relation to why someone would use software as a service and the general
idea was software as a service is awesome because it allows me to have
more time for me then he says the great compromise a lot of companies have come
up with through the ranks to become dominant players in the open source
industry meetup.com for user groups github for development heroku for
software as a service and slack for communications when when considered
independently there's nothing wrong with these services they offer a great value
they increase productivity and more code gets developed the problem is that not
one single of these services are open the use of these services creates an
intrinsic advocate position for closed source software in turn you see you will
see the use of these services increase whilst the use of open source
alternatives decreases consider slack which widely is considered the hot new
collaboration tool yet it doesn't adhere to open standards its network is closed
as is its software and he goes to argue the worst part is is that we had jabber
which is open source yes similar environment as slack supports voice
video plugins external protocols bridges image embedding video sharing file
sharing and yes chat it also supports Federation and allows communities
communicate between each other using XMPP he says the Postgres community
hosts their own code repositories websites and mailing lists we
collaborate in a true version and vision of open source and actively reject
moving our project and externally hosted facilities controlled by services which
are not open source the community puts forth the effort for the community the
moment that open source becomes primarily about my time is the moment
that open source is no longer a movement it's no longer an ideology it's no longer
about fairness freedom equality rights or the greater good damn Wow Nemo I'll
let you jump in first I see you tagging me and then I'll let wimpy jump in there
go ahead new right I mean okay so what I say is the value of open source is not
you know your time is no longer wasted by or you can no longer trade money for
time it's that no one has a monopoly on support so if if someone else can't
support it you can and which then you're definitely using your time as is valuable
to you yeah that's definitely a value of open source I completely agree good
point wimpy you think maybe this is a little clickbait your thoughts sir yeah
a little bit I mean this there's a point there but all of the projects that he
cites so slack and github for example there are open source alternatives to
those manner most and rocket chat for slack for example yeah and get lab
instead of github yeah and well Gatorius has sadly died gone into bit rot but
yeah I mean the code there somewhere if somebody wants to resurrect it which of
course is what open source is great for right and you know matter most and get
lab integrate very nicely now so it is convenient you know we were just talking
about this earlier on the show you know having to do more of the thing you do is
your job in your spare time is not very appealing so I'm reluctant to do service
stuff in my spare time because what I do all day say that to say that these
closed services are the death knell for open source I think is a little bit off
the mark because the development platform the development infrastructure
is all open source so all of the tools and platforms that are used to deliver
those proprietary services are all open source so consequently while you have
the likes of slack and github creating their proprietary software they're also
inevitably going to be contributing back to a number of open source projects
along the way and if you are you know very much of the mindset that you don't
want to run proprietary services and one of the alternative you know one of the
alternatives like matter most or get lab he's out there and not quite doing it
for you then you can contribute to those projects so I felt I felt the title was
a bit click baiting and I also felt that the pros was a bit sort of flowery and
meandering in that point could have got to the point in about four sentences
rather than four pages yeah I do see what you're saying and I think it once
you've started it's just so hard to stop I think oh I think what a part of
partially it is it is a failure to recognize a division like so for myself
there are moments where I would opt to go with a hosted solution slack might be
an example of that where there's other moments where I'll opt to host and roll
of my own like we were just having a sink thing conversation a little bit ago
yeah and those are just different priorities and sometimes it's there's
it's for it's for ideology and sometimes it's simply for practical reasons and I
feel like we sometimes in this conversation forget that there is room
for both there is actually we can have both sets of users and it doesn't mean
one thing is dying or one group is defeating the other group both sets of
groups exist and coexist and use the software for different reasons and
that's what I that's how I look at it so I carry software is an ethical there's
that well then you can choose any other camp but that proprietary software can
also spin off open source software so for example I was looking for a tool
like slack for the Ubuntu mate team and in the end we went with hip chat because
I don't have to host it myself you know there's we use big bucket for pretty
much all of our source control so there's a lot of good overlaps there now
as it happens I've ended up taking some existing open source code and
improving it because I've created some IRC bridges from IRC channels into hip
chat rooms so that we can see what goes on in IRC within hip chat so
consequently I've taken something old and busted and made it work and that's
now some open source that's out there that wouldn't have been had I not been
using you know hip chat admittedly it supports hip chat so it ties into their
API's but open API's are better than closed API's yeah and you could make the
same argument for a lot of services there that's interesting so I wouldn't
be just totally side sidebar did you try out matter most and rocket chat and just
I thought or was it just sort of the I don't really want to spin up another
server it was that the barrier it's I'm perfectly capable of running the server
infrastructure sure but my time is limited in what I do in my spare time on
open source projects and I would rather that that time was focused on
development and pushing the project forward and that's why it's not the
death of open source right there that's just such a good point and you know why
don't we take a moment and I want to thank digital ocean because when it
comes to spinning up systems in record time nobody beats digital ocean with in
55 seconds you can have a rig deployed and you can ready to go and if you're
if you're gonna work with something like Docker there's so many things that
are Docker eyes now container eyes I guess they have such a nice stack they
have a good they have an Ubuntu LTS with the Docker with the Docker software
installed with the repos added and you can you know there's also one with
nginx for me and I think I've told you guys the story but for me I was working
on evaluating rocket chat and matter most and evaluating how they stood up to
different like you know different testing like how do I use it from the
mobile how do I use it with the IRC bridge yeah they're gonna ask once you
make them use exactly and you know what it's funny we we almost went with one
system I put in production at one point and the thing that I the thing that was
really nice to know was that I could revert back to a core system and reset
it up within seconds to make sure it was done right I didn't have to put together
some sort of hack solution ultimately Sean set up a matter most server for us
on digital ocean that's available right now to patrons and that has been running
really great it's a really good system it's super straightforward to set up and
so far it's scaled brilliantly so if you use our promo code over digital ocean
you get a $10 credit the promo code is snap ocean it's one word lowercase you
put that in your account control panel it'll apply $10 to your account yeah
their pricing is really really straightforward and the value is crazy
high so that $10 will get you quite a ways and they got data centers in New
York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam London Toronto Germany and India they
have a really nice interface the back so if you have really no experience or if
you're an expert you're gonna actually be pretty satisfied also their API is
really nice to work with we integrate it in with our workflow a lot of people do
there's some good open source code already written like an applet where you
can add it right to your menu bar and get the status of your drop nice I love
that lots of nice mobile apps to that make rebooting like on the go nice and
easy and straightforward calling other things down actually I've just used it
to like my causal server locked up on me one time and yeah and I just open it up
on my Android app and just reboot the top it's also nice if you're like well
is it a problem on my end okay yeah yeah and then the other things really cool
and gives you a lot of power if you know how to use it is their HTML 5 console
that watches it from post login yeah it's it's how you get certain real
certain things done that are really cool and advanced at digital ocean I just
think it's a great service use the promo code snap ocean let you do it that's
it's not like a advanced feature you have to admit it's right there and it's
just part of the service part of it is they're just really really really smart
about when they implement a feature they do it right and they just what they
focus on like they just rolling out right now block storage you can get up
to 16 terabytes of SSD storage they do SSDs for everything and man when you
know and then when they roll it out they roll it out with just really good
documentation check out their community section look at their dog they have
speaking of Postgres they have the article on segment Postgres here's
Docker composer or Docker compose I guess doctor so it's fun that you can
just deploy it so easily look at this how to protect your server against the
HTTP proxy vulnerability boom right there man that's good timing check it out
digital ocean.com just use the promo code snap ocean and a big thank you to
digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program snap ocean gives you
that $10 credit arch strike has an ISO that's all I really had to say on this
just you know we've talked to these guys back when they were arch assault I
think Sammy assured which is pretty cool and for those not familiar strike was
arch assault it's still based on arch Linux which is totally as Morris's here
renowned and lightweight and highly customizable distribution however the
goal of the project is be a security layer on top of arch has 1200 security
oriented tools for ethical hackers and security researchers but the thing
that's newsworthy here is they've actually released their first ISO it's
available for download today it's 64 bit and 32 bits as the first of its kind so
congratulations to the arch strike team for getting your first ISO out the door
Wes you you knew this is probably gonna give me a riled up when you link this
one in our chat thread earlier today I do like to rile you up oh man that's the
open bsd 6.0 tightens its security by losing Linux that's that's the pitch
most significantly amongst the latest security related changes for open bsd is
the removal of the Linux emulation support prior versions open bsd made it
possible to run Linux applications via a compatibility layer but the release
notes that open bsd 6.0 indicates the Linux up system was removed as a
security improvement as a call from our friends over bsd now I think it wasn't
much used and hadn't been actively maintained yeah yeah yeah make sense for
them to cut it but the you don't have to do all the poking though they would
make us a fun on Twitter yeah open bsd also has ditched the systrace system
policy enforcement tool for the second security and the removal of the user
mount option which have enabled allowed non privileged users to mount file
systems it's yet another security enhancement open bsd project lead Theo
Durant say that the user mount option allows any non privileged program to
call them mounted unmount system calls meaning there is no way any user can be
expected to keep their system safe or reliable with this feature no user mount
for you my theory is that since Windows started doing Linux emulation open bsd
is like no we can't we can't be in the same campus this and they're out that's
a good theory that's actually pretty solid I like that a lot all right I I
don't I don't really have a lot to say about this but I did actually feel like
it was a little tiny teensy bit antagonizing with the harassing on
Twitter and and then they and then they tweeted out and said the distros what
they say operating systems that now have the Linux vulnerability and they listed
free bsd Linux and Windows or something like that
nice yeah haha I just made my computer more secure you know how how I moved
wine yeah haha it's kind of like that yeah not quite though because it's
something that's required by the kernel as opposed to wine user space under your
own user account so implementing user space you know how bsd loves
re-implementing things in user space right is it though but is it not
installed by default is it installed by default on open bsd and why the hell
would that be I don't know if that's true because it's not installed by
default in their free bsd so I mean I don't understand how those BS you know
what I got to watch the bsd now program because they'd probably set me straight
I'm sure like sounds like they've already been covering the story for a
little bit they've you know they see that stuff come sure do but I did feel a
little like haha we gotcha we gotcha there's been a lot of interesting
security use today there's a security vulnerability that supposedly bypasses
HTTPS on Mac Windows and Linux you see that yeah so security is you know makes
me glad the tech snap exists makes me glad that I've got my Linux mint updates
installed that way I know I'm secure there you go off topic does Alan allow
you to set up no no I don't think he does he should offer that is this hosted
streaming solution so something happened and I feel like I should probably
mention it on this show because it's relevant to the audience's interest you
guys want to know I six months after it happened I finally I have finally gone
off my butt I finally have spent hours putting together a new episode of the
rover log of my trip to scale yes yeah and you can see some highlights of Mark
shoulder worse keynote where he's talked about he this was back in January where
he was talking about snap packages and also Cory Doctorow's keynote kind of
made me rethink my stance on DRM and I talked about that's that's rover log 16
just came out and you know I was I was watching this man that's that scale
thing is a huge looking back at art my classroom that is a huge event it is it
is a monster wimpy are you are you by any chance gonna make it to scale next
year I don't know he's hoping yeah yeah I would love to I mean I haven't made it
by my but I think I'm gonna go anyways if you guys want to see that's just a
little taste of it you can check out rover log 16 which went up recently and
rover log 17 is already posted for our patrons at patreon.com slash today which
is the one where I drove into the tornado which was a lot of fun so yeah
so we'd be willing I would check that one out so speaking of snap packages mr.
wimpy is here and he was not here last week no no he was not because he was at
a sprint event held by canonical to bring people together to talk about snap
packages so why don't we let's tell you what let's open up the next block I'm
gonna mention real briefly here ting go to linux.ting.com to get the discount
for the Linux unplugged show and support the show plus you'll have Linux in your
URL history so that way when somebody starts typing L in your browser instead
of your dirty porn habits showing up Linux shows up so linux.ting.com go
there to support this show ting is mobile that makes sense as my mobile
service provider has been for over two years because I just pay for what I use
and six dollars for each line my minutes my messages my megabytes which means if
I'm smart and I do stuff over Wi-Fi like I pre-download my podcast and I listen
to downloaded and like my favorite Spotify playlist catch those local
suckers over Wi-Fi I do extreme quality too which is and I'm like guilt-free
extreme quality oh it's nice and then I just basically pay for the little bits
of backup data that I use when I do go on the cellular network they have two
networks to GSM and CDMA you get to pick from what you want all their devices are
unlocked they have really great fanatical customer service they're
backed by two cows which is an internet company that's been around since before
the dot-com boom I mean a forever they're really in it for the long haul
which is super nice especially when you want a mobile provider that's gonna be
around for a while when the deals like this they have a savings calculator you
can try go over there and check them out you know I was just mentioning the
rover log that entire rover trip I did down to scale was off a ting Wi-Fi it's
really nice and when you're when you are traveling it's nice to jump around from
GSM and CDMA it's a little tricky because we you end up having two numbers
and it but it's only six dollars for the line it's not it's it's really I mean
plus you get I don't want to put a sip number in front give that to everyone or
what I do is I do Google voice yeah but actually I would prefer I would prefer
the sip thing I think these days so check them out at Linux dot ting dot-com
thanks ting so I wanted to go and do the ting spot right there so we could just
sort of open up because I have so many questions for wimpy that I didn't want
to have to interrupt him so prepare yourself wimpy I I guess I want to start
with head what what the hell is a sprint event and how come I didn't hear
about this and we're only certain like Linux elites invited to this thing what
is a snappy sprint and how did you find out about it and why didn't I hear about
it right it was publicized so it was publicized through the Ubuntu insights
and a couple of the yeah I think soft picked it up right yeah so a couple of
others picked it up as well so I was aware of it from that but then shortly
afterwards the Ubuntu community team contacted me and asked me if I would be
interested in taking up a place at the sprint as a community contributor I
guess what I was kind of getting at is I kind of had the sense that this thing
came together pretty quick you know there was there was a brief announcement
about it but all of a sudden it's boom let's do this and it seems like they
were pretty proactive about reaching out to certain people to make sure they they
could make it yeah I think I I think I heard about it about a month before it
happened okay yeah so I think it's probably best if you have questions you
ask because obviously I was there I went to a lot of stuff my head is full of
things to do with snaps I could fire off in all directions well it's probably
best if you've got questions you focus the the conversation I have in front of
me I have a Trello board with the snappy sprint topics on it so I have plenty of
things to get into with you but if you don't mind and you can only you share as
much as you feel like sharing but probably 99% of the people listening
have never been to something like this before and so I mean could you could you
just kind of paint a picture you had you flew somewhere you had that you know
there had to be like a ticket purchase there was hotel space and what what is
sort of the setting like and the experience like going to an event like
this okay so the very first thing that happened is I was asked if I wanted to
attend I talked to my wife and daughter and said can I take a week off work not
with you and go to this thing and they said yeah all right then so then I let
the community team know that yes I wanted to attend and then I was contacted by
canonicals travel organizers and they basically sorted out flights and
accommodations in the room so I didn't have to I didn't have to pay for
anything in that respect so I had my ticket sent to me and a couple of days
before the event of full itinerary of you know what was going on you know
everything you needed to know the one the one thing is that all of these
events canonical have a policy of room-sharing so I was sharing with poppy
so yeah that was nice so yeah flew out there on the Sunday Sunday morning I
left the UK got to the event hotel mid afternoon Sunday the first evening that
Sunday evening there was a drinks reception in one of the rooms the people
attending had drinks and snacks get a chance to mingle a bit yeah yeah get to
meet people the first thing that struck me is I knew there was going to be about
60 to 70 people at this thing and I reckon about mmm about 18 or so were
from outside of canonical so that was quite surprising you know and that
weren't just flavors they were you know from other distributions and projects
completely outside of canonical so that first evening was nice and I got to you
know obviously over the course of the last couple of years working on Ubuntu
mate I've got to know a lot of the Ubuntu devs through IRC but I've never
met them and the only drawback of attending this event is you know as that
as they do you favors and help you out you idly say you know if we ever meet I
will buy you a beer yes well I was but I ended up buying a lot of beer last week
which is absolutely fine yeah yeah so so yeah my my investment in the trip was to
make sure I paid down my debt of beers to all of the people I owe beers to good
man would be yeah and so in terms of how the event works so you're in it's a
large hotel I think there was five or six rooms in total there was one very
large room which could accommodate everybody and then four or five smaller
rooms which could take between I think about 20 people or so in each room this
is legitimately a mini conference yeah yeah it really was every morning starts
with an opening session that says what we're going to do this day so you've got
the Trello board there they basically explain where the rooms are what's going
to happen and throughout the day there are three tracks running and each
session runs for about 45 minutes to an hour so it's very fast-paced and it's
sort of an introduction to a topic and some discussion around a topic and
actions and proposals are taken at the end of each of those sessions there's a
mid-morning break and canonical provided drinks and refreshments and snacks
mid-morning break and the mid-afternoon break and they provided lunch as well
and breakfast so yeah they looked after everybody and then mid-afternoon there
was the option to go into the larger room and participate in a two-hour
hacking session so if you'd learned something or taken an action or wanted
to progress something you had a couple of hours each day where you could
collaborate and you know and work on that stuff was this one of the times
Frank showed up and talked to people about next cloud and Frank actually
turned up sort of at the end of one of the days so I just happened to see him
sort of wandering around the hotel looking slightly lost and I just
overheard somebody say oh no Frank from own cloud should be from next cloud
should be turning up in a minute and I bumped into him so I said I I said I
introduced myself and then said I know where you need to be art so I escorted
him to the right room and introduced him to whoever he needs to talk to did he
have a camera with him not that I noticed you don't have a bag over his
shoulder I imagine that could have held the camera so a very interesting so it
sounds like a pretty pretty high rated event in terms of a nice room nice
accommodations room sharing but drinks and all kept can't be ignored I look at
the list here of travel stuff which is nice that it's public and I'm not getting
a set a central theme or a central sense of this was with a big focus towards
unity 8 and mobile or a big focus on cloud I'm getting kind of a lot of
different priorities here from individual Internet of Things type
devices to full desktop applications did you walk away with the sense having
attended that there was like a core theme there wasn't a core theme because
as you can see from the Trello there were lots of different topics you know
the things that are marketing red that's the community and cross distro stuff and
that tended to have a desktop focus so that was more desktop focus the plan for
a runtime to desktop snap issues interesting okay and and gnome runtime
was part of that session and arch Linux and the open suzer OBS snap integration
was in there as well and in the yellow sessions those were more specifically
about the evolution of snap D itself and snap craft so the sort of the
fundamental tools and there was a lot of interesting discussions there and then
there were some new tools announced I don't know if these exist pre-existed
but there's a thing called snap web now so that is a a web UI that talks to the
Unix domain socket of snap D and presents a complete UI of your snap
environment so that you can very handy install snap wonderful access the store
see featured apps and it even does clever stuff like if this is on a
device it will show you the components that are specific to that device so
there was some examples of router switches and stuff like that that look
very interesting Wow so that there was a few things that
did come out that surprised me you touched on it there just for a moment
you said gnome runtime I thought that was a flat I thought that was a flat
pack thing so the thing about so runtime I think is this the the flat pack
terminology I think the terminology that's going to come out of snaps is
these will be called platform snaps but you asked if there was sort of a general
theme no but one of the key concepts that cropped up all the way through the
week is what they called content sharing or the content interface so that's a
new feature and that is the mechanism by which shared runtimes or platforms or
things like artwork snaps can be created so that if you are creating
application snaps for the gnome desktop you can now use the gnome 320 platform
snap as a dependency and through bind mounting in the way that snaps you know
integrate that will be a common platform available to all of the things that
require it so an end user implementation would I have a gnome 320 runtime mounted
file system squash fs file system and whatever the application squash fs file
system mounted at the same time two different mounts for one application it
would appear as one but underneath yes it'd be two oh yeah yeah so it handles
the magic behind the scenes and also things like taking the artwork out so
taking the themes and the icon sets out of the applications and even out of the
platform snaps and making those separately available and then there are
mechanisms to then create trust relationships between those snaps so if
they need to move in lockstep you can use assertions to actually say these
things have to move at the same versions if that's if that's the requirement
yeah yeah not just in desktop but also in server deployment it was it was a
particular that the particular conversation around is called gating in
snap speak but that was particularly for devices where you may have a kernel
component and an application component that requires another and then the
interaction between those three and to make sure you can't accidentally have a
snap upgrade in that chain that is not compatible mm-hmm I hadn't really thought
of that particular problem that's that is interesting so did you get a sense of
what is the application that can't be snapped is it or what is the piece of
software delivered for Linux and like I'm thinking of things like Nvidia
drivers or oh yeah what are the limits what where where do snaps stop and you
have to use something else well there's there's two sides to this so there is
the classic system that can install snaps for example and you obviously have
some host requirements and the host can be a combination of the classic system
and the core snap and then you have a fully snapped environment where the
whole device is a series of snaps that build the complete environment so you
only have snaps I don't think that anything was discussed that was an
outright it can't be done there are things that can't be done now but but
all of those all of the things that were discussed were this is the plan and we
will you know cross that bridge when we get to it sort of thing so there's
there's some more complex interactions to consider when like full desktop
environments are snapped in their entirety and how things like display
managers and session managers and setting demons interact with one another
yeah you know so that's a little ways out but in general I didn't know that
requires like a kernel module at boot you know like a like a ZFS snap or Nvidia
driver snap or a VMware snap that has a you know the VM DK kernel module yeah so
on on devices at the moment you can have kernel snaps and gadget snaps so I think
that you know in that fully snapped device platform that's that's a
possibility that's that's something that's been you know solved so I want to
I just want to throw just as an example a question at you that might illustrate
maybe the variety of people in attendance I see a card here for
integrating snap support into the openSUSE of build service is that
actually going to happen or was it just theoretical code that is never going to
be integrated upstream to the build service no it was demonstrated it's
there already and in fact that work the the one of the screenshots I sure saw
was a build log for from three weeks previous so they'd actually done some
work prior to turning up wow okay all right so then the other thing that seems
to be perhaps an olive branch to the fedora camp is I see entries in here for
getting SC Linux confinement now just recap for the audience one of the ideals
behind snap packages is that they are confined to their own space and that
they're not only they're a little safer for the end-user but maybe isolated from
security vulnerabilities a bit more and that confinement is currently I guess
you would say created or done by app armor I don't know exactly what they
with a term is the app armor is used to create that confined environment which
is not really the paradigm that fedora uses red hat is really behind SC Linux
and so is fedora and SC Linux is also capable of delivering confinement like
that but I you know it's it's not losing I don't think snap was created with that
intention so how how how likely is that do you think that maybe they could get
SC Linux support and did you get a sense from people that were there from fedora
that this is something the project might actually adopt I got the strong
impression that support is coming and there was some discussion around how
that can be implemented and one of the lead developers from canonical had done
the initial discovery work and was confident that it could be implemented
and I don't know what the schedule that will be but it was definitely considered
doable and something that will be done at some point the the speed at which the
snap package I don't even know you can't even call it one thing but the whole
ecosystem snap ecosystem is evolving seems to be really fast faster than app
image and flat pack and it already seems to be more feature complete
especially when you take in some of the additional stuff that's coming out when
when you when you arrive there was there anything that changed your in your
mindset after you left for example is there going to be perhaps a shift in how
Ubuntu Mate implement snaps is it going to be a maybe a greater snap investment
is it going to be still only certain applications like is anything in that
regard changing so when I went out there I'd got like three or four things that
I want to understand so that I could better you know think about how Ubuntu
Mate could benefit all of those questions were answered on day one hmm
so I was thinking well this is a good start because everything I came here for
is now being you know I know what the road ahead is so I've now got four more
days to find out all this other stuff so to give you an idea one of the things I
want to do is integrate snap support into the software boutique and I wrote a
prototype Python client that enables you to install and remove packages using you
know the snap D API but whilst I was there I was talking to Robert Ansell one
of the Ubuntu developers and he's talking about actually making a lib snap
DC library and then exposing that via object and QT object so that all of the
other projects can wrap it and use it so you know things like that are just
terrific because that's a way that anyone can then exploit the facilities
of the snap API within their applications pretty much irrespective of
what language you're you're implementing in right everything's got got an
interface to see yeah exactly and other things that I wanted to understand was
particularly this concept of runtime or platform snaps yeah and you can see that
was the first session on day one so after one hour it was like oh right
that's how we're doing it fine so then the rest of the week was was starting on
some of that work hmm and can you help me understand a little bit of the the
security paradigm around snap packages so they have to be granted access to
things on the file system and it looks like from the docs that I was reading
from the elementary team when they're looking at how to integrate snaps with
elementary OS is there could be certain some of their programs that they make
in-house for their desktop might need special access in ways that maybe snaps
don't facilitate now I only I only briefly skim the documentation but it
sounds like there's a limited ways snap software can access the system currently
and some of those might be limiting am I tracking at all yeah so they're called
interfaces so when you use snap craft to create your package you tell your
software what interfaces it can connect to so one example is the home interface
which exposes some of your home directory and I'll maybe we'll talk
about what that means in some expect some respects and that interface is
auto-connected so what that means is when you install a snap package that
uses the home interface it automatically connects that up and that snap has
access to those areas of your home directory that are available to snap
packages there are other interfaces that do not auto connect so you can install
the snap package you can look at the status of the snap package and see that
is requesting that it has this facility and it's down to you to actually
establish that connection manually that's how it is right now there are
there quite a lot of interfaces and that's where a lot of the focus has been
if you look at the change logs on snap D and snap draft it's really been about
interfaces and they're being added a lightning rate and will continue to be
added to support the various use cases but the end goal is to have mediation so
if you've used Ubuntu for devices on a phone or a tablet when that has
permissions that it requires it actually tells you oh this application wants to
connect to your camera do you want to allow that and you say yes or no there's
an interface to facilitate that question not at the moment but that's what's
going to come so so you will tell your snap what it can request and then it's
down to the user whether or I don't know if there's an override because for
example some things you just absolutely have to be able to tell your snap it can
have this thing otherwise it won't work at all so I'm not you know I didn't see
I didn't sit in on all of these sessions so I don't know all of the nuances but
the idea is that there will be prompts to actually guide the user that snap is
requesting this thing do you want to approve that so hardware aside it sounds
like it has it automatically has connection to your home directories like
any user space application might so yes and no okay okay when you install a snap
that has access to the home interface it actually has access to a directory which
is slash snap slash the name of the snap slash the revision of that snap and
that's where the the data and the dot files and things like that so that's the
equivalent of dollar home as far as that snap which is concerned but it can
actually see all of the other directories in your home directory with
the exception of any dot directories or dot files so snaps can't see any dot
files or dot directories except for those that exist within their own data
directory okay so that okay that actually answers most of the questions I
had around the security of it and I'm you know I'm sure I'll play with it more
is it as it comes along so I don't I use any other any other thoughts you want to
share about the trip or about the event itself it seems like one of the things
that I always experience when I go to something like this is the unexpected
collaboration that happens sort of in the hallways getting to meet people like
you mentioned earlier and paying off beer debts I'm just kind of just kind of
picking your brain as far as any other experiences you want to share on the
trip and sort of any elements about that about rubbing shoulders anybody you got
to meet or anything you want to share in that regard yeah I mean obviously the
social track is just as important as the getting stuff done track during it really
was and so a group of people that I got to meet and spent the week with most of
the week actually because we were in the same room a lot of the time was three of
the guys from elementary so Daniel for a Cody Garver and Cortana sorry I've
forgotten your surname so those three guys from elementary were there all week
and yeah Daniel and I exchanged some notes on you know stuff he's doing on
with elementary and low-key coming up and I had a look through what they've
been working on and I showed him some of the new stuff I've been working on so
here's a little tip for you Chris you are talking about the nice high DPI
support in Linux mint 18 you really want to have a look at low-key okay because
their high DPI support actually knows that it's on a high DPI capable machine
that was my complaint automatic yeah and although Daniel showed me the bits
where it needs you know there's a few icons that aren't scaled correctly in
spots yet but by and large it's there and it's looking very polished and very
complete now so and because all of their applications are all you know use that
same design language and they've been through the process of making sure that
you know it's all high DPI they're out-of-the-box default applications that
are all high DPI and it looks looks the business you know I completely agree
with that rei code in the rei code in the chat room elementary OS with those
potential nice touches to detail combined with snapped applications
could make elementary OS a much more viable platform for me so I'm gonna be
really interested to try that out good for them so so three different reps I'm
sure you probably I'm sure probably just too busy to talk to Clem I'm sure he was
yeah it seems like there was an intention to reach out to like open wrt
that's really interesting yeah yeah so so I think that I think it's fair to say
that you know I've talked about the content interface sharing and you're
asking for a theme definitely on Wednesday Wednesday night there was a
meal everyone that was there was in the big room together we had this fantastic
outdoor barbecue and then did lightning talks and most of the people doing
lightning talks were from the community contributors that had been invited and
it was very clear that that community participation and involvement was
important to developing snaps and making snaps work for everyone so you know it
was it was very much a bring this to the wider ecosystem don't just focus on a
bun too it was that was clearly a strong message that came through this last week
that's really great when we thank you for for sharing your trip with us it
sounds like the exact kind of event that needed to happen and it sounds like a
lot of great people are invited and it wasn't just a big Ubuntu echo chamber
which is brilliant and I think one of the metrics that I use to measure that
is reading the blogs of people from arch and fedora who came back and said this
is really something and that's pretty cool and it's exciting to see that kind
of on the verge and from an end-users perspective you know eventually this is
gonna work our way into our into our desktops and when developers and others
and packagers are excited to use something yes get software to us yeah
that's awesome I know and it's gonna give it a clear path for people who want
to bring software over to Linux something to tell Mike finally yeah I
will and so on on that point one of the last things that was discussed on the
last day was talking about proprietary software and the actual discussion was
if I've made a snap for a thing I can't redistribute what do I do about it but
then the conversation evolved into there are these companies that are basically
dodging packaging their software in the appropriate way for the various Linux
distributions because it's hard and there's too many things to target so you
get these dot run files or you get a deb file for one architecture that maybe
only works for one particular version of Ubuntu and there was this whole
discussion about how we could potentially create snaps for those
proprietary applications and then send them to those organizations and say you
could do it this way yeah really and you know that seems like that it's too hard
excuse with things like the shared platforms and snap craft going cross
distribution is going to be a weaker and weaker argument and then on the end user
side gnome software version 3.21.4 will have support for installations of flat
pack repository files in the flat pack repo format and installation of snaps
and then yeah and this is going to be this is going to make the end user
perspective at least on the gnome desktop and anybody using gnome software this is
gonna make this really straightforward also which is kind of neat and now a
relevant thing sandboxing information will be shown for the certain apps along
with the origin information when the apps are available for more than one
source in gnome software which is I mean I can't wait to see that I can I'm
getting really excited about the direction this is going and I don't
even I don't even I'm still like I'm still happy if we end up with flat packs
and snaps like I'm not necessarily pulling for one but I think it's really
brilliant where what canonical has been doing with snaps and I think it's really
great that the momentum they're building behind it is likely to lead to success
it feels like they're really on a good trajectory right now so that makes me
excited we're gonna check thank you wimpy thank you very much that was that
was a great that was that was actually painted a great picture I know I'm
excited we were there mm-hmm you know you're welcome thank you we are going to
find out if Wes was successful in the starbound server challenge which he was
just I like that you were down for it because I didn't warn you at all that's
gonna be throwing this at you and you know before we reveal if Wes was
successful and get to our next topic this would be a great spot to mention
Linux Academy where you could go to get the mad skills to learn how to set up a
server when you are thrust into a situation to do so Linux Academy comm
slash unplugs where you go to support this show Linux Azure AWS open stack
dev ops they have great courseware on all of it
Linux Academy is constantly improving their courseware the existing library
library and all the new stuff super fast they have a great staff now working on
all of this a great community full of Jupiter broadcasting members and
instructor mentoring when you need it they got on-demand servers that spin up
with the courseware that match the distribution you've chosen from they
have availability availability planners that are just the perfect touch when
you're super busy and last but not least one of my favorite things about Linux
Academy is they put you in a hands-on real-world scenario so you get actual
experience which there's nothing nothing that gives you more confidence when you
go to take the test or when you're just trying to improve your skill set check
out all the different features go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged also
did you know they have a blog they have one of their new content creators Terry
Cox is sharing his experience working at Linux Academy yeah which is very
interesting and you kind of see some of the passion behind it Linux Academy
comm slash unplugged go there to learn more and to level up your skill set
Linux Linux Academy thanks guys for sponsoring the unplugged program and
that's the Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
okay all right Wes were you or were you not successful in setting up the star
bound server I believe so I've only just got the client installed and I'm a
little confused on how to point it at the dedicated service so I there's that
problem you have it as well I do I have starbound installed I yeah I think so I
think I have it on this machine yes I do oh so there's a home I see I see
there's a separate server they got installed when I download this from good
old games let's see here Wes checking in now well do I just join a game maybe you
know I'm well I was trying to start one as well so I have a character oh yeah
it's got a server address you have to create a character first okay I see so
maybe what you need to do yeah so create a character hmm cuz do we do we want to
give out that address because once we give it out people gonna be playing on
it that's fine you think I mean we can always tear it down when we and move it
yeah okay so chat room if you want to test it I'm gonna give out the server
info with okay so how do I where do I where'd you get that server info well so
I already have a character so I'm a different okay so I went to join game at
the front at the front page okay and then I checked Stark bold or star ball
or star K bolt whatever it is and then it just brings up the server info after
I select my character oh yeah okay all right so the server is starbound dot
noble pain calm and it's port two one zero two five I'm gonna paste that in
the chat room to noble pain but you have to have accounts I don't know how does
that work oh well we'll have the chat room tested for us so I'll put it I'll
drop it in there because I want to play with some folks I think that I do too
what yeah yeah I mean it's the binaries totally running okay so good job West I
mean if you got the binary running you're probably pretty close so nicely
done sir well done under pressure too I think that's pretty great I'm pasting it
now in the chat room so I had a topic while people are trying that out that I
wanted to throw at you guys I'm so excited I just want to play the game now
I was noticing that the EU is gonna be auditing a couple of open source
projects that some of us may be familiar with the key pass project is one of them
and I think also I think also the Apache web server is gonna be audited and when
SCPs being audited and I think I think VLC I think there's a somewhat there's
some other projects are getting audited in all of this here's the background the
European Union just announced that it will give the source code of the
password manager key pass and the Apache web server a security audit the idea is
to audit the open source code and then it started around December of 2014 when
two members of the European Parliament suggest an audit for free software used
by EU institutions all right that seems like you know anytime we want to audit
something we rely on I'm all I'm all aboard that train put me on there and
take me to out of town so I started thinking what if the EU came to us
Linux unplugged show okay guys sat down with us and it said to us no no it said
to us we're gonna give you a million dollars and you can spend this on
auditing an open source project or two of your choice so we have a limited
budget to work with and we have to be responsible and how we spend it how and
what projects I guess is the better question which projects would we choose
how would we spend it and I wanted to kick it off so I was kicking this or
ww all right ww I'll answer my I'll go less ww what was your idea how would you
audit what would you audit how would you spend the money I would spend the money
to audit I see Linux oh to see if the NSA put a backdoor in there if you're a
security district you need to be audited you need to be known is this secure or
not and then maybe you know publish that information or use part of the money to
to audit it and make sure it's done right and throw and just and then just
publish information this is what we found or we didn't find you know so this
can be trusted for now because it could all something can always change so yeah
I was trying to think too would I wanted when I want to audit something like
telegram or something like Firefox and I don't think so I think I'd want to go
myself I want to go more infrastructure I think if I was gonna pick a project it
would be something that I rely on and think of as secure something like open
VPN or open SSH right I would love to get a real good so although open SSH has a
lot of eyes on it and maybe open VPN does too but the other thing that would
sort of crop up on my radar and I don't know how feasible this would be and it's
not like it hasn't it's not getting looked at all the time but I am just not
a hundred percent solid on tour and they've been a lot of changes in a lot
of news recently mm-hmm mm-hmm there's been a lot of attacks against or there's
been a lot of changes in the board just like true crypt I would love to have
more eyes on tour yes from a from a third-party auditing a lot of a wire
guard yeah that would be good to get done right away yeah yeah wire garden
tink too really that would be good yeah that is such great performance though
it's awesome oh wimpy you have a great one which one
gnu g yeah yeah yeah yeah that's one we all rely upon we've been we've been told
by folks like Snowden that it's solid but I mean who know really knows you I
not to be paranoid but there are if you listen to text now I mean it's we talk
about it quite a bit there are entire industries now around finding these
problems and selling them and they have they have like Silk Road type markets
where a vulnerabilities go for certain prices in Bitcoin and whatnot in Bitcoin
and what's not it really well yeah it really is it really is a growing market
where people are finding these things and holding on to it and and then there's
people out there that know about vulnerabilities and then sell them and so
it these kinds of things I don't know they just freaked me out doesn't have to
be an NSA conspiracy theory where the NSA is hacking you it could just
literally be some jerk hacker who figured something out and like you know
yeah and like part of the benefit of it being open and you know it's it's kind
of everyone and so like if we can all take responsibility get things audited
and have a really solid base to build from you think it's worth auditing like
desktop environments like the gnome desktop or plasma desktop you think it's
worth that or is it just really rely on the enterprise case yeah and but you'd
have to be careful about versions right you have to pick like a fixed point and
yeah yeah and then somebody in the chat room suggested snaps and snap D it's
probably not bad I maybe app armor too yeah good one
Rekai yeah app armor is not bad anybody else in the mom room having suggestions
before we wrap up yeah if we're gonna be her line not more and more here right
yeah yeah yeah x11 well I think that'd be depressing Wayland way to be bad way
with Waylander mirror yeah that wouldn't be bad yeah I'd say go for the
infrastructure stuff and Wayland would know not jb titles don't look there
don't look there it makes j-bot grumpy continuing the audit of let's encrypt I
think is happening or veracrypt yeah that's a good one wimpy free BSD oh oh
oh yeah you know they had to remove the Linux subsystem that was open
BSD yeah so open BSD then yeah okay good let's do that one yeah there they they
they talk a big game let's see how they do open SSL I think that's happening all
the time these days arch Linux I think that's happy you know Google has a
project called project zero where they're literally going in investigating
different projects recently though they've been really beating up on
antivirus companies it's been it's been really fun to watch yeah okay well if
you have any suggestions I'd like to hear your thoughts Linux action show at
reddit.com or leave a YouTube comment if you're watching on YouTube what open
source project would you audit because I have a sense we're probably forgetting
of some because we just kind of came up it's not everybody yeah but on the spot
my my attack would be infrastructure and then go out from there wouldn't it be
amazing I honestly if there was some sort of perpetual crowdfunding platform
for security auditing and not I don't think patreon will be and I don't think
Kickstarter or gofundme or anything like that there's some sort of different
something different where I could kick into from time to time and say I want to
help and then do you remember the infrastructure project that the Linux
Foundation set up if so if they if they ran something like that if it came from
it if it came from a from a foundation like that or a group of people that were
organizing and hiring the right professionals for the right tools and
the right jobs and being very transparent about how they spend the
money and the reported man that'd be such a perfect companion to open source
security is to have a Linux Foundation or somebody like that organized
something like that and I would love to contribute to something like that I
wouldn't be able to contribute a lot but I absolutely would love to you know I
don't know if you guys have ideas let us know you can also go to the contact page
at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact that's where we get that
business done that's our official contact page although really to be
honest with you for this show I it is more of a community experience well
that's kind of where the subreddit comes in probably a little more and also we
have the mumble room and the IRC don't forget them no I can I'm looking at them
right now we always stare right at their face you can find out when we do all
those things at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash counter it'll convert that
lifetime to your local time zone then you go to jblive.tv you plug that into
your machine of choice and join the IRC and then from there bang mumble you get
our mumble secrets you hang out in our community our virtual lugs always
willing and accepting as long as your microphone works and you don't got echo
yeah oh yeah knock that off no it's action shot at reddit.com is where you go
to leave feedback and topic ideas thanks so much for tuning this week's
episode of the unplugged program we'll see you right back here next week
you did it Wes you did it I'm impressed hello everybody I didn't know if you
better get going now do we have anybody connected though yeah I mean I see Rekai
right here he's on there are you in the game oh yeah I'm right I'm in the game
where are you Chris that's the question starbound doctor during the show I like
your I like that you got your name I well you got your online name I should
do I have Wes Payne too I wonder if I could get my name let's just say I have
a little too many variants of my own so do I have it do I just put anything in
there for the server just leave it blank oh man I was supposed to put the port in
the actual they have a specified port box I didn't see that because I was
just putting it in there yeah JB titles calm JB titles calm if you guys want to
you if you don't want to buy this on steam to you can get on good old games
which is pretty cool I would love to mess around with this all right so
assets mismatch between client and server and the override option is not
set oh I thought I did what does that mean what does that even mean is that
because I don't have the steam version oh is yours allow him can you edit your
character how do I do that I think there was like an allow mismatch oh but maybe
that was the start game yeah cuz that just puts me back in my world this is no
good Wes this is no good well okay JB titles calm I boy I'm starting to
escape you need to update it is that why the assets are mismatched I have you
updated we're going to steam oh you have great games I could just go
redownload it I guess but that feels pretty old they need to snap this up
that's what they have to do snap it up okay guys well I want to say thank you
everybody for making it I really appreciate it that was really fun
wimpy to pick your brain all that stuff I find it fascinating and it's good to
hear a story you know from somebody who was there so that way it's not just our
speculation you're welcome thanks for inviting me on wimpy get snappy and so
that's the top title right now oh geez oh man okay I have a question for you
guys I I would really like to consult with some folks that have some
multi-month long experience with sync thing mm-hmm I do what are some of the
key tricks to getting like your discovery between sync thing nodes or
whatever it's called working and what are key things to know if you if you're
frequently reloading machines or setting up new machines and also if you want to
have a pretty sophisticated sync setup like I want to think a lot of things
between some machines but a couple of bits but some of those same machines I
want to sync with other computers only a couple of things like so complicated
setups like that what are like tips to make because I feel like here's every
here's my problem and I don't even know where I've gone wrong because I have
it's been about six months or so but I I set up a sync thing instance I get two
or three systems going usually it's this machine here in studio my machine up in
my office and a digital ocean droplet and I get those three things working and
then at some point I reload one of them and I can never get that third that
reloaded machine to rejoin up or something like sometimes it can see them
but they can't see it we have fully working totally fine DNS here in the
studio yeah I don't really understand what keeps going wrong and so because
because I'm always doing it when I'm super busy and trying to solve a problem
and just get something working I never really spend a lot of time trying to
really figure out what I've gone what I've done wrong and it just it makes
there's there really that much of a difference between the 64-bit version and
the 32-bit oh file wise or something you mean like how many files it can do so
yeah okay I don't know arch that's a good question you're asking about a
array storage array right well no now I'm just asking about syncing best
practices in general to keep a good sync thing like to keep something that's
sustainable for me using sync thing I want to be able to I want to be able to
have confidence that I can blow machines away and re-add them to whatever my was
it called a syncing syncing swarm what's that what is that called I don't know
network yeah nobody has any advice for me I've got one running on my phone it
sinks all my photos down and anything I do on my phone that I want to you know
be saved in my computers and backed up yeah that'd be good that'd be a perfect
use case like a box thinking that I've got a Linux box thinking that and I've
got a server in my data center sinking that and so when you want to when you
want to add your phone what steps did you follow um I just opened all the web
you eyes and all the machines plugged in actually on the phone I did the QR code
thing so like I'd share the QR code from the other machines snap the QR code it
got all the information so I didn't type it all out so when you add a new
computer to an existing sync setup you go to both computers administrative
interface and you add each that you add each other to it right you have to add
each other yeah because they both have to recognize your public key yeah
sometimes you can just add it one way and then the other will start trying to
talk to your new node and it will say like do you want to add this guy who's
trying to talk to you like yeah based on this I have seen that sometimes yeah
okay but I would say yeah it does like but I would just add them on both yeah
add them especially for the links that you really care about okay okay yep I
will also say I've that's what I usually have done but sometimes like I want to
add them on each end like one of them will connect but the other one won't or
something typically what I do is I have it they all connect to the server but
none connect to each other in between how do you define which ones the server
down you just don't allow them to discover each other there's like an
option that advertises neighbor nodes or something oh I try using that thing you
maybe it'll help okay no it might help you it should be fine but just the way I
do it is I have one server that they all connect to and they don't interconnect
between each other okay that seems to work for me I'm not saying that's the
only solution it just seems to work well because the server has ports open that
are guaranteed and the IP address is static yeah I'll say in the kind of in
the same vein I've enjoyed using it when I was with tank for an overlay network
but you could use whatever really network just like you don't have to
worry about anything I was thinking it was tank would be a good use for that
or if you have a VPN set up already that'll add it to your home or the
studio network or you know well I feel that doesn't really make me feel much
better because you guys really haven't given me anything I haven't already done
yeah it does sound like maybe doing a little bit more manually not relying on
the it'd be nice if you could centrally manage the sinking of all those nodes if
you have so many yeah that would be having to set them up on each node is
really frustrating and time-consuming and tedious yeah really the one thing it
really right now needs the tool to yeah that does burn yeah that does burn me
okay so Ben Ben Fitzpatrick is in the mumble room Ben was our feedback
question who was also our aborted runs Linux for the Linux action show this
Sunday what's the what's the update there been well last night my friend
Jamie came by and we I did manage to get arch running on my pro book that I was
showing you guys and I tell you what the problem was was I believe it or not had
a triple boot setup going on and what happened was I had forgotten to write
grub into the EFI boot so oh my god so the whole time was rub was not writing
to the EFI partition probably so I found the command on the arch wiki and then
bang it just started booting after I ran it from the from the EFI boot menu and
then voila I was in and I got XFC loading awesome everything and it's all sorted
so yeah and then my friend Jamie came by and fixed awesome up for me and
everything's all good so yeah and it looks really killer and congrats man
that's awesome so did you go straight up arch or did you go with an arch
derivative or what was your approach there was normal arch via architect and
I gotta tell you okay architect is not being maintained anymore yeah it still
works and I tell you it's it's really very simple even if you're a new user
and you haven't used arch before it really simplifies things down to the
minimum and I've done stock arch before and architect makes it a walk in the
frickin park so cool that's the way to stick with it man good for you I plan to
and I tell you this thing really saved my neck are you enjoying any of the
process I mean I know there's like ups and downs with it but have you found it
just like intellectually enjoyable yes and I tell you I've actually wiped my
windows I'm actually considering dumping OS X on my macbook even and throwing
archon highly recommended well I don't know about on the macbook but go give it
a go and let it report back and let us know how it goes I will thank you oh
man so okay this made my heart sink I just saw this go by the chat room wimpy
says that he abandoned his sink thing set up uh-huh well okay wimpy I feel
like this is gonna be I feel like this is gonna be what convinces me not to use
sink thing because I think a wimpy and I have seen I die on this stuff before so
do you want to tell us what happened you know all those things you just explained
you were trying to get fixed yeah I couldn't fix it oh so it runs along just
fine until you need to change something right is that what kind of your yeah that
the problem I had is that even though there are mechanisms to support key
exchange with multiple devices that just wasn't happening seamlessly and for the
number of machines I have that was a real showstopper so I did things to
tweak the speed at which it would pick up changes but yeah just it just wasn't
working for me and I was bored with keep on trying to poke it and make it go so I
just gave up are you using something else in place or well not really I mean
I had this one use case left which was my dot five talked to get in the past
about roaming profiles and how I was using that just keep all of those dot
files and everything that was in my profile sync across of the machines
which is why I use it on so many machines because I was using it on all
the servers that I you you know my own personal servers and my workstations and
laptops and what have you so I've I use the same tool to manage the dot file sim
linking which is a tool called makeup but now I've just got it hooked into a
get back end because I can't be doing with sync thing messing me about you
know it almost makes me want to throw next cloud on something with just a ton
of desk because really where my own cloud sync issues have gone wrong is
when own cloud has tried to do something clever like keep a duplicate copy so I
could undelete and then runs out of storage because the undelete bin takes
up all my space and when I'm working with unfiltered clips and it's you know
multi gigs per episode that happens within a couple of months even with
tons and tons of storage but if I really you know if I had a lot of storage
sitting behind it what I really like about the next cloud syncing paradigm is
it very is very close to the Dropbox one where I install a client I log in to the
client now in the case of next cloud I pointed to my server I don't do that
with Dropbox but I log in and it begins sinking and it begins just
participating in the sink swarm without having to discover servers that having
to exchange keys and the thing is that's pretty nice for me because any given
week I've reloaded a machine for a show and I have to sync several hundred
assets to that machine and so I'm not always in the same place when I'm
setting them up yeah so maybe next cloud will solve this for me but in the
meantime dropbox enterprise is like super crazy expensive so I'm ready to
just dump it as soon as possible but yeah yeah last time I used own cloud was
own cloud 8 and I'm gonna have a go with next cloud and the other one that I had
some good success with was C file which is what next cloud is using isn't it
under or is it CC I think no yeah that CCC file is right SSEA file right see
yes right and the only thing that puts me off that is um I really don't want to
be adminning loads of servers in my spare time because yeah