So there's someone in the staging area, Marks, he's from Ubuntu
podcast, he's also a prior OggCamp organizer and he's the guy that has a Steam
controller and did our review and everything. Will you pull him in there
Wes? I assume he probably has a working mic. I assume he probably does. Oh I
should start the show. He has an SM58 and a mixer, yeah. Chat room, please bang
suggest our show underscored. Okay I should probably... Hello Mark. Hello Mark.
Hello Mark, hello Mark. So Mark you had a chance sounds like to try the Steam
controller out, what do you think? Did better than we did. Yeah he got farther
than I did, what do you think of it? I'm really enjoying it, I've tried it with
with games with quite a few different controller schemes and I found yeah it's
generally really successful. Have you tried it with Alien Isolation? No I've
not got that yet, I'm scared to buy it because I'm with games like that I tend
to waste my money because I play for about an hour and then I'm just too
scared to carry on. Yeah that's probably my, I bought, I literally bought it
because I've heard from a few people that it works out of the box with the
Steam controller so I thought okay this is the one to try it on, it looks really
visually impressive. It does look very impressive. But no I tried, I just tried it a few
minutes ago and no dice. So okay so what's the experience like? You get a
game and it has controller support and if it just has controller support you
just start playing immediately? Well if it's got Xbox controller support yeah
you just tell it to emulate a gamepad and it works as an Xbox controller would.
Yeah if it's got Steam controller support like Portal 2 does then it's
even better because actually in-game it tells you to press the Steam controller
buttons rather than the Xbox controller buttons and that's really nice.
I wonder if that would have worked for this one. It seems like for me it's like in a
matter of months like a lot of little issues I ran into are just going to be
totally solved because there probably just be just a couple of updates to some
of these games. Like take Race the Sun for example it seems crazy that doesn't
have a controller support yet. Yep. But you give it a couple of weeks. I was playing
that at Mark's house yesterday, it works fine. Well okay good. So when I went in
there it says it says it doesn't have controller support in the big picture
mode and that you have to you know that that's that's the kind of support I'm
talking about. Not that it doesn't work I just mean that you have to more
integration. Yeah it doesn't seem. I've played a ton of Race the Sun with the
Steam controller but I had to use a community config. And that's not such a
bad solution. It's kind of nice that Valve set it up but it can especially be
maybe be a good first wave to you and tell them. How do you know what's up but
how do you know it's a good scheme? You just sit there and try like four or five of them?
Yeah that's my criticism they need a like rating system so the best ones
propagate to the top. But yeah well you can tell like how many people are
using it but just because it's popular doesn't know. That's not a horrible
indication, at least something though. Yeah go for the second most popular. I
would like somebody that needs to upgrade controller schemes for players
that have actually beat the game. So you just want the macro that will walk you through the game?
You know I don't know why I even bother with this controller stuff because the
mouse and keyboard can't be beat anyways and I shouldn't I shouldn't
bother. Because you can hook up a mouse and keyboard to a Steam machine too.
So challenge accepted. For what? You play you use a keyboard and a mouse and I'll use
the controller and see who wins. Have I tried? No I haven't tried replacing the battery so I should try that huh?
See that's the thing you guys is that the Steam controller is working in big
picture mode and like in the Steam overlay and it does work in games when I
go in there and manually map the buttons. It doesn't, what doesn't seem to be
happening is if I select a controller config it doesn't, the game doesn't seem
to be aware of any controller config or button layout that I've selected and
most games are telling me I don't have a controller connected even though I'm
navigating the picture mode and the rest of the UI with the controller.
Are you on the Steam beta? I don't know what I'm on actually I could check but I
don't, I could be. That does sound like something I would do. It does sound like it.
Yeah I've noticed in the beta updates are coming almost daily on the Steam
client lately and the release notes almost always have you know fix this to
Steam controller, add this to Steam big picture mode. So they're
iterating very quickly right now. Yeah I you know I you know what that is
actually a good point is I should check for updates. That is probably something I
haven't done for a few days on this, for more than a few days on this machine.
Yeah the beta checkbox is really easy to find in the account settings and I
haven't really haven't had any. I'm not currently participating but I don't
think I've really done updates either so. Well you'll probably find when you're
when a controller recognizes your you've got buttons but not the actual controller
mapping I found before I had the Steam overlay turned on it just uses the
mapping that the Steam interface uses which is completely useless for any game.
So yeah there is something going on there where it's it's picking up that
you've got the controller in Steam but it's not applying it in the game. Yeah
okay well. This is Linux Unplugged episode 117 for November 3rd 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that just threw out it's
no beer rule that it just made ten minutes ago right before the show
started. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hey there Wes you know it is a tasty
beer too thank you for bringing these in. That's my job tempt you to break your
rules. You're a good man I appreciate that. Well it's a good show to break the
rules on coming up on this week's episode of the Unplugged show. I tried
out Ubuntu Mate 1510 over the weekend gonna give you my follow-up on that.
We're also gonna hopefully hear a little bit of how odd camp went and then we're
gonna get into some new desktop updates and some really great follow-up
especially for those of you that are looking to do some notes in plain text
and have a nice way to organize them. We're gonna talk a little about the
Cinnamon desktop as well and then we're gonna look at the Volkswagen situation
one more time because there is another big update there and it has caused a
whole new round of mainstream press to say this is why proprietary software is
bad it's amazing. It's hard to believe but. We have a showcase in the show notes
and we'll talk a little bit about that later in the show and then last but not
least today as we're recording this very show Fedora 23 hit the internet's
the new Fedora is out we're gonna have our review on Sunday's Linux action show
live on Friday but we're gonna cover what's new how you can get it and some
of the things that we as a group are looking forward to for Fedora 23 big
release with gnome 3.18 in it. Oh yes very fancy very fancy so we have some
follow-up and some things to get into but before we go any further I got to
bring in our virtual log time appropriate greetings mumble room hello
hey there it's a big turnout today too so that's really cool that's great to
have you now I hope I hope some of you are also breaking the no beer rule that
was implemented ten minutes ago and then then also shattered shattered two
minutes ago I hope you're breaking that right now with me so I have a I have one
bullet point in the show notes for this very very important bit of follow-up
this week we have assembled a crack team of on the scene reporters from odd camp
2015 and I'm hoping that I know Pope is here I believe mark is here from from
the by some some other podcast I'm told and some actually all these guys from
some other podcast I'm told although those are probably rumors they're
probably not even in the u.s. and they're gonna they're gonna give us a
round of what happened at odd camp so who should I give the floor to first I
think you should hand on to mark first because I understand Pope is having
difficulty with his PC well you know he you know what that's so funny since he
was giving me a hard time running arch before the show started isn't that
appropriate I actually think we should give it to mark to those since mark made
the special trip here it's his first time here so why not throw him under the
bus right away that only seems fair that's our policy yeah that's that's
though we like nice of you yeah yeah so mark welcome to Linux unplugged and tell
us a little bit for those who didn't listen listen last week what is odd camp
and how the heck did it go well camp is we call it a free culture on conference
so it's an event that's been running for the past six or seven years I've lost
count now but basically we we hire out of venue and then we convince a bunch
of people to somehow turn up and come up with a schedule and give a load of
talks about anything from well anything kind of community driven really so we
have people talking about Raspberry Pi's we have people talking about running in
parks at the weekend we had panel discussions we had some live podcast
recordings hardware hacking all sorts wow that is like a pick your choice
there's gonna be something there to delight any geek that would listen to
this show I think I love the generality you know like it's not it's not so
constrained you can kind of just come and share the cool thing you're doing
yeah and so I bet there's a lot of Linux that works up in that crowd that comes
up so how did it go it was a good event it was a good turnout did you enjoy
yourself I heard rumors of shouting etc. mainly in the evenings we went to some
really cool venues in Liverpool which were converted warehouses and being a
bunch of geeks relving getting up and dancing of course we wanted to stand
around and talk about geeky things all evening and they kept on turning the
music up so by by the mornings we were a little bit horse that's hard still
recovering the reason I think system D is actually a good idea I could see what
it was like interspersed with I'd like another beer so how does it compare to
last year's I like odd camp 14 and 13 oh that's a good question so I'll camp 13
was at the same venue it was mmm probably comparable actually I mean we
had some different things going on in terms of exhibitors but we had you know
a similar sort of variety of talks last year's was in a different venue and had
probably more of a focus on the the sort of exhibition space as well there was
some really cool like we had a load of hack spaces there last year this year we
had we had a few sort of hardware things and we had the Ubuntu stall and the
fedora stall across from each other in the in the exhibition space but we also
had we also had an intro where exhibiting which was really cool with
their Ubuntu laptops that they're selling now yeah I saw a few pictures
online of those and I did I also see a fedora laptop there too you might have
done we didn't have anything to do yeah right yeah yeah I made peace with my
fedora brethren and they were running fedora 23 and gnome 3 on a large a large
panel and then on a laptop they were running fedora demonstrating their
alternate spins and they had the Marte desktop running there so I decided to
to make my peace with fedora and introduce myself to John Archer and he's
a lovely bloke the ability to stand immediately opposite fedora Stan and
power through the day we we exchanged merchandise stickers and pens and badges
and things and made up a football in no man's land nice very good so I so it
sounds like an event that was a well-attended poppy how did the live
tracker end up working out I checked in at one point but I couldn't tell if it
was working or not yeah it was kind of hit and miss we had an Ubuntu phone
polling our position to the website and various people would tell us every so
often when it was broken which was usually because I'd poorly written the
code on the phone and it would run out of memory as it was logging far too
excessively that was my fault that's actually pretty still neat still though
but this is not indicative of other apps performance right yeah exactly a little
disclaimer that's still a neat thing though I like that I think I think we
should seriously come up with a legitimate live tracker app for Ubuntu
phone and then in a future road trip when I go somewhere I'll use that to
track where I'm going because I have this silver cloud thing for now but I
could swap that out anytime anytime all right so I wimpy and poppy or mark
anything else from odd cam it sounds like it was a pretty fun event I kind of
want to go there yeah me too yeah one of the one of the cooler hardware hacks
that I saw was a nerf gun range which someone had set up there was a few years
ago someone had built a minecraft crane which picked up boxes and made them into
sort of minecraft style objects and the same guy had brought the boxes along
made these these sensors which he put inside so if you shot them with a nerf
gun it activated the sensor and then he had that hooked up to this RFID tag
system to identify who you were and it tracked your score and tweeted you wow
and there was a prize for the three top scores the prizes were won by these
three kids who discovered an exploit in the system and and managed to get them
skilled score so themselves scores of about half a billion compared to my
sixteen is there a you know a lot of times when I attend a conference like
this even when there's like you know everything from software to hardware and
community and and just the open culture itself is really the highlight a lot of
times though you can't help but walk away and go boy I kind of feel like
there was a overarching theme or an elephant in the room and is there one
like that at odd camp is there like a something is really kind of the buzz
this year or there's a there's like it feels like a bubble or a trend that you
observed or is it really pretty dispersed there was one there was one
emerged as a theme it wasn't planned but there was a lot of discussion about
online privacy yeah I was wondering they were that was that was the topic for the
panel discussion and Linux voice also recorded a live podcast on the second
day and that was also their discussion piece very interesting audience yeah
that makes sense I was that's actually that was when I asked the question that
was in the back of in the back of my mind mark were you gonna chime in with
something too I was going to say exactly what Martin just said actually privacy
and online and is it is it like from is it from the state or is it just privacy
in general is it is it if you abstract it out from there is it is it like
Snowden type stuff or what is it the overall theme that was that was kind of
what what it came out it was we were talking about whether the cloud is a
good thing or a bad thing basically and then we moved on to basically do people
care about what happens to their data online and should they care and can we
make them that was the where it all really went but it does seem like we
care as a community the people that Linux that the average Linux user does
care and and also the average Linux user seems to be better positioned than most
users to do something about it either from a technical knowledge set or by the
very fact they're using an open system and so it does seem to be coming up
more and more of these conferences because we're the type of user to think
about this kind of thing we're also the kind of user that is willing to live
with password managers and dual you know a factor two-factor authentication and
and and we're also the kind of user that cares about these kinds of things so
it's a really interesting cross-section that I find when I go to these kinds of
conferences so that's interesting up there so yeah one of the talks that is
typical for talks to get composed as a result of a conversation the night
before and that was you know typical of our camp this year and John Spriggs did
a piece about squirrel SQL which is a two-factor authentication Gibson's thing
right yeah is that yes really yeah I know which is why I was surprised John
did specifically say the focus on the protocol and not who came up with it yeah
well that mean that is very true right I mean if the code is good code then
that's and if it's it's if it's a good protocol then that's and it's open and
we can take it to you know so is this so okay be honest with me now be be honest
with me is this something that I should try to make it to next year because
that's a big commitment I would have to fly out there lots of money etc etc does
that seem like I mean how many I mean really come on yeah how many people are
we talking well the first thing I'll say 400 oh that's a really nice sweet spot I
like that size that's you get you know you get more than 2,000 it's just crazy
you're looking enjoy it oh that oh that's all I'll say regardless of how
big the audience is you would definitely enjoy it yeah yeah and although it's a
two-day event so there's the the Saturday and the Sunday this time there's
actually like four days packed into that because there's the main events that
happen during the day and then there's the evening events that start at about
six o'clock in the evening and go on to about midnight or two o'clock in the
morning so there's sort of like four events over those two days oh that is
fun I like that now there's not I can rank is as good as the sort of the event
itself now you know that is always so true especially when it's around three
four hundred people because when you get bigger than that it's just it's too much
white noise literally huh now is there a Spartacus there is there a spot I can
park the rover cuz UK yeah I'm gonna yeah yeah well I know I mean a UK
dedicated UK right right oh that's interesting roads are quite narrow okay
and you might have heard that we actually drive on the correct side of
the road oh yeah I am worried about that yeah that is gonna change my that's
gonna change my world if I have to go over there well I I thank you guys for
coming in here give me the update that is really cool any other things you want
to mention about the about our camp 15 before we soldier on I know I think it's
it's one of those things that at the end of the at the end of the Sunday we all
get together as there's a guy said there's like the end there's multiple
things to get involved with and the very final thing on the Sunday is a few
relaxing beers where we discuss what we're gonna do next year and so we'll
keep you informed about what's gonna happen next year and when it will be and
where it'll be so you can you know you can plan your flight and everything yeah
do let me know and you know it's funny and and I I know I make this point too
often but and even as we sit here with a virtual log which is pretty awesome
like the mumble and Google Hangouts and all this stuff are pretty damn good
tools to connect with people and we can have really great conversations but
there is just there is something about when you go to an event like this and
everybody there speaks your language they know like what a colonel is they
know what you know a cloud what a cloud computer really is when I'm talking
about the cloud they know I'm really talking about somebody else's server at
a data center and you all are on on the same page and is if you walk around in
your life and you're like kind of the technical person in your family like
you're the you're the person that fixes things in your family or you're in the
tech department at your work you kind of you almost lose touch with how amazing
it is to be around other people that value the same things you value and
appreciate the same things that you appreciate and and also want to want to
maybe even debate the nuance with you and to do that in person mumble really
does a great job of this you know IRC and Hangouts do a great job of this but
nothing nothing does it like in person and like you increase the social stuff
yeah yeah it is it's a huge increase in bandwidth between two people or a whole
group of people and it is really exciting and what you realize is we're
not as bad as that BSD community makes us look exactly right we're nice people
yeah we are so that's what I take away every time all right so I just wanted to
really quickly do a little follow-up from Sunday's Linux action show we got
an email in asking how Noah and I manage our notes and I said well I always do
plain text files and I try to write them in markdown and that's kind of my base
requirements well we got a great recommendation and I I'm sorry I did not
grab the name of the reddit user who submitted it but it is a Q own notes
it's an open source notepad for Linux and those other desktops that works
together with the notes application of own cloud it's a desktop app though so
this is what's really cool is it's a desktop application that it's a GTK app
from what I can tell that has markdown support and it has a change tracking use
your own notes you can sync them over to other devices you can then log into your
own cloud instance and edit them with a local own cloud app but even if you're
on like an iOS device you can if you have own cloud and access like to the
file system you can just edit it with any markdown editor like it is not
lost to own cloud so this is really really cool and I've made a big stink
about own cloud before I have you caught that just a little bit yeah I basically
bailed on own cloud you certainly text a few months ago yeah basically I just
pushed it to the limits with way too much data and I bailed but I only bailed
and I don't think I made this point very clear I only bailed for file sync I'm
still using own cloud and that's one area where it has the most competition I
would say right I'm yeah yeah I would agree and and honestly I think same
thing that's a better job I would agree with that yeah so but I'm still using it
for car DAV and Kel DAV what do you what do you see you have a Nexus 5 are you
are you all in on the Google at the moment my main counter is I do have an
own count own cloud instance that needs to be updated and yeah but I've been
pressed with it in the past have you considered trying to transition from
Google services to own cloud or is it just not worth it no I think it's
totally worth it I need to move email emails of the one thing and then I think
I would consider moving yeah moving the rest of my investment so I did you know
it's funny you say that because I went the opposite route I moved my calendar
and my and my access my calendar and my my address book and I haven't moved
email yet and so this is why for me I kind of like this QO notes because I
still have it on cloud instance sitting around that I could use to sync my notes
but on the back end it's all just text files to markdown files which are text
files exactly so yeah I love the text files this is a really cool
recommendation yeah QO notes and it's a it is a as you probably guessed it is an
own cloud app but it really is just a matter of syncing with text files and
also with text to do was another recommendation that came in a lot and if
you haven't caught this Sunday's Linux action show the question was is how do
we manage our to dues and I said text files how do you manage your to-do list
text files and I use task warrior for a lot of my work stuff what yes task
warrior mm-hmm is this a desktop Android app command line I believe they have
some I believe they have some hold on a second did you just did you just change
my life mom or anybody the mom reviews task warrior task warrior hold on hold
on yeah obviously this is a command line to do this sounds like Linux action show
app pick material to me you jerk West how have you been sitting on this and
not telling me that there is a to-do app for the command line wait till you find
out that you can run your own server sync server on a digital ocean droplet
oh I'm very excited all right so this is how you do it yeah okay okay now for
everybody naturally hold on before West goes any further everybody listening
we're gonna play a little game where if Chris makes this is epic on Linux action
show we're all gonna pretend like we didn't already hear about this all right
so tell me about this cuz I'm very excited so you use task warrior with a
digital ocean droplet and you go to the command line to set your to dues yeah
yeah and it really is just like a CLI interface you know like task add and
then you can specify like project you know project at work or your home life
or whatever and then an arbitrary string and they have you know you can set
priorities you can set due dates and then I just task sync and it syncs up
that even there's a Android app called Miracle which does task but it
integrates with the task warrior server oh okay okay you can have the same thing
on your phone okay but without the command line okay all right so now
what's the server setup like is it like so on the scale of a Quasal client to I
don't know smoke ping how difficult is it to set up I would say similar to
Quasal you don't need a database back or quality area right yeah no database so
you don't have a database or anything like that you do have to set up some
primary error private key infrastructure okay but it's really not that bad it's
mostly you know you pretty much just assemble you have to set up a few
configs and set the right config file so that it allows the Miracle app from
your Android phone but once you've got that in place it really just works oh
that's funny so here's another option there's a basically there's a command
line tool called to do to do text yeah yeah right and it's it's a bash script
so it's essentially this it does the same stuff that task warrior does but
task warrior is a lot more like robust and features so if you've ever used to
do that text it's very similar in the way that I mean the main thing about to
do that text is you got to provide your own sync mechanism all right right so
you have to do same thing or really Dropbox is what I think it if you're
gonna use well no if you do the same thing that task warrior does where you
put it on a server you can do the same thing with to do that text put it on a
server and then just oh see so what I'm thinking about so I mean when I say that
what I'm talking about is from the perspective of mobile applications the
mobile apps that use to do that text have always they always want Dropbox
right except actually there's this awesome app I found because I built my
own to do that text app like structure because I don't like the basic structure
I wanted to have a massive customization where one to do that text file is not
enough for me so I currently have like 30 damn dude that's impressive yeah I
have I built my own bash script to to cut to manage all of them too so it has
like automatic archiving from like a huge list of things anyway I'm actually
gonna be releasing it at some point probably well I made it for myself and
then I told people about it and they're like oh wow that's cool we should give
it to me like I didn't it kid for everybody so it's complicated that's
what Linus said about Linux what's he said about getting it still true well
there's the the other thing is that the reason about that I was because there's
a fact because I did this I wanted to find a mobile version and there's this
there's a it's called simple tasks and it has it's simple task wire of cloud
and they're simple tasks cloudless so if someone doesn't want a cloud storage
they can use any sync they want and sync it to their phone directly so I have
like a custom sync thing set up for that but there's also the cloud version you
can choose whatever cloud you want you don't actually have to be stuck to drop
box okay yeah huh so so there's to do that text and task warrior as two
follow-ups to the email we got in the Linux action show on Sunday and the task
warrior thing is really that's fascinating to me I'm gonna check that
out I like that a lot now no yeah go ahead yeah yeah the the to do not text
thing if someone wants a GUI that go for it app that was a epic a couple weeks
ago or a few weeks ago that one is compatible with to got text so you could
have command line and you can also have a nice giveaway if you want it I I don't
make I don't mean to make a popiar token Ubuntu phone guy but I was just gonna
throw this your way poppy because when I when whenever we're talking about like a
task management app or a calendar management app I always think well what
if I want to bail from Android what if I want to bail from iOS what are you
using poppy when you are when you're using your Ubuntu phone what are you
using in that environment for task management to do or he doesn't have to
be like to-do list even just like setting reminders and things like that
what are you using so that's a great question and the reason I use the app I
use is because I always used Evernote in the past so I use Evernote on the
desktop and Evernote on the web and we have a notes client that can optionally
sync to Evernote so I just synchronize all my notes with Evernote and then I've
got those local but yeah there's at least three task managers in the Ubuntu
store so you know if you don't want to use that one there are lightweight ones
it's HTML 5 ones or you could just go and get the task binary stick it on your
phone and open that in a terminal if you really wanted to yeah you know that's
but I want to talk about that that's the elephant the room for me for all of this
and this is something I don't say usually well I've mentioned it before
but for me if I want to if I want something and I don't want to forget it
for a really long time and I'll give you an example like when I know I'm I'm
gonna need to know the VIN number of my truck yes for probably about eight nine
years that's probably how long I'll own that truck and that's how long I own my
last truck and so there are many times when you're getting insurance or you're
setting things up that you need to recall the VIN number of your vehicle
you want it easily accessible so for that kind of info like that really long-term
for remember forever kind of stuff I am still today using Evernote and I'm just
choosing to yeah from a smart device although to be fair the kind of stuff
like that which I would I would think is slightly private like I don't know VIN
number of vehicles probably not that bad because it's probably like that I have
like I have all the other information in there that is like kind of I'm not super
comfortable with it being with a third party right so for those I have a GPG
encrypted text file on my local machine which is backed up in various places but
no you know it's GPG encrypted so I feel okay about that and obviously the phone
you can use GPG on that yeah right I was gonna say I keep a lot of stuff in text
files with syncing as it is now so yep yep and using I've been ever since I
started playing with pass I started realizing why don't I just do this more
often just encrypt this stuff and then sync it everywhere and I don't care
because I'm using GPG and I trust GPG and syncing has encryption as well in
transit yeah yeah I but I fundamentally trust GPG yes I did as well same thing
I their encryption I'm sure is great it's just like that yeah yeah good at
least it's not plain text exactly so you get me you get me I remember many other
thoughts on that topic before we move on yes I do on the subject of notes I've
actually been looking and I don't even know if this exists for an application
that you type everything and mark down for the notes and everything and it
looks like G note or Xim and has support the sync to like a Google Drive or
Dropbox so that you know you know maybe late it's later at some point you can
access those notes on your Android device yeah you can basically accomplish
that today just using G editor Kate or whatever K right or whatever and just
saving it to a Dropbox or sync thing or bit torrent sync folder and then pulling
that up on your mobile device is there a good mobile markdown editor oh yeah a
lot I assume there must be yeah lots I can't remember off the top my head for
Android because I haven't been using it for a while but yeah there are a lot
there are amazing editors for markdown on Android but no the reason that I'd
like something like Xim or G note is because of how the notebooks and whatnot
are organized it's yes yeah yeah having that having that sort of meta
organization with tags and and categories and subcategories this is
really nice and that's you know whatever note provides and it kills me it
freaking kills me just like and I don't want to I don't want to go on anymore on
this but just like we're seeing more and more open source projects take on slack
and use slack yeah anter gross is my favorite or enter gross how do I say it
and Tegra winter got wimpy can you enter to go and Turgos enter goes is
switching from IRC to slack oh really and there was just a sort of well okay
all right well go ahead correct me I'm okay they it's not switching it's both
have using both I'm the split before it's splitting I'm the lead up for the
IRC for enter goes and the developers prefer to use slack so there's a weird
split right now but yeah they it is a slack thing that they prefer slack yeah
so it has become they then they they listed some really good reasons on their
Google Plus page and also you know what I'm gonna say it Jupiter broadcasting
has started using slack but there is a blog post at drew dev vault comm same
you know please don't use slack FOSS projects and I want to dig into that
because I'm gonna be honest we have started using slack here at Jupiter
broadcasting and I have felt like a bastard for the last two weeks we've
been using it it has been driving me absolutely crazy I'm gonna talk about
that with you guys first though I want to mention Linux Academy go to Linux
Academy comm slash unplug to get the Linux unplug discount and support the
show even if you're just checking them out I want to browse around Linux
Academy comm slash unplug supports this show go there and try them out and then
while you're there do the tour take the tour I invite you because I think it's
gonna blow your mind it's kind of amazing actually finally an educational
resource that is really actually focused and dedicated to Linux and open source
and all the technology around that included even like AWS and all of the
major technology stacks like Red Hat open stack yeah it is really fantastic
they have step-by-step video courses and they are really good with instructor
help available when you need it you can download the study guides they're
comprehensive you can listen to them in the shower like listener Seth if you
want and they come with their own servers which is not just nice but the
way they have done it it's like oh yeah they realize you're a Linux user the way
they set up the SSH the way you can get into it and control the system the way
you get complete control over it and seven plus distros to choose from and you
choose the distro the courseware and the virtual servers they spin up on-demand
automatically mass match that choice you get to keep track of your progress as
you go along and they're rolling out new features you know rather than just like
checking how you did after you're all done and waiting for the feedback after
you do something they're now allowing you to perform exercises and give you
immediate real-time feedback you could have done it this way you could have
answered it this way you could have used this command they have scenario based
courses that way you actually deploy and work with the technology in real-time in
production so when you go to actually do it in production in your production when
you're getting paid for it it's not the first time you've worked with it that is
serious peace of mind and they also now have a new professional development
certification platform I invite you to go check out if you've decided the route
for you is to expand your skill set to make you more employable to make you a
little more competitive if you just want to challenge yourself these are all good
reasons to go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and by the way they
also have time availability planners you can tell how much time you have if
you're busy and as a father of three and somebody who hosts 12 shows a week trust
me oh actually this week I'm not hosting 12 shows I take that back but I'm still
hosting like seven shows a week scrupulously honest hosting seven shows
a week right right it's six shows maybe I don't know who knows maybe I'll just
cancel one of them randomly but still trust me I know what it's like to feel
very busy I really do and that's why their availability planner is freaking
awesome I love it plus they have live sessions you can attend they have a
community that is stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members to help you
when you need a little bit of boost and they have live sessions with those Q&A I
really think that's a valuable thing graded server exercises are really great
and then last but not least I gotta say I think those nuggets the name is funny
it's a nugget tasting you put that in some honey mustard West and I'm good to
go good to go honey mustard with I don't care about pink slime um you know what
I'm still here after years and years of pink slime I'm still here but let me
tell you something that's not what nuggets are about Linux Academy kind of
wish they were but are they what no no in fact it's just like you go deep dive
into a particular topic something like you know I don't know an SSH tunnel for
like a few minutes or something really massive for like 60 minutes but it's a
deep dive into a singular topic Linux Academy comm slash unplugged go check it
out it's really great Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and a big thank you
Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program okay now feel free to
let me hear it but yeah am I a am I the biggest hypocrite in the world by
hosting two Linux podcasts a week and then planning for them in slack and I'll
tell you I've gotten a lot of emails because I haven't really talked about it
in Linux action show or Linux unplugged but I have talked about it in kota radio
and in kota radio I've been getting consistent emails about matter most and
other and other alternatives to slack and I I find it interesting that I am
I'm thinking about this at the same time I'm also seeing you know a post from a
lot of different people about slack including this one over at drew dev
vault comm where he says don't use slack it's closed source has only one client
well not really that's not true it's a walled garden requires users to have
different tabs open for each project and requires hacks to do open registration
he says go with IRC which I say IRC is not an open source product it is a
protocol it does not compete with slack or things like matter most but let me
have it am I a huge hypocrite am I a jerk for hosting the Linux action show
and then using slack to planet I wish I could comment but since I'm helping
plan on slack and you use slack for work I do use like for work yeah we I'm torn
yeah part of me part of me says yes you gigantic hypocrite you you should be
using other things but the fact is you're using the best tool for the job
and for you that tool is the best tool for the job and IRC works and is is
relatively robust you know if you we we often have problems can we use IRC a lot
in canonical and we use free node and we have our own internal private IRC server
and when one goes down we switch to the other and and then when slack goes down
what do you do you know you'll probably switch to something else will it be IRC
or telegram or something else right so I I don't know I I'm torn because I also
use non free stuff I use telegram which open source client but closed back end
so you know I'm in the same position I am pragmatic about these things yeah I
find this to be an interesting trend this developing and I think you could
also say the same thing would apply to Google Docs or office 365 or base camp
or Wunderlist or anything really Debbie and shouldn't use Wunderlist to plan
their tasks right anyways it is something this well that's because it's
owned by Microsoft yeah there's that it is and the reason why I brought it up on
Linux unplugged is because it is something that seems to be brewing on
going on in the background and so for my 50 foot view or 500 foot view or
whatever you want to call it my my my intention here is sort of like looking
at the landscape looking at slack and saying does this idea of a way for for
group collaboration because we're trying to solve something where you have people
all over the world and and the things we work on they absolutely without a doubt
take a week you know every single show from the moment we go off the air
everybody that walks away from the show starts thinking about this next show as
soon as you're done you go oh geez well wow I'm done with I'm done with 117 but
oh my god now I have to do 118 yeah you open the net for the next one right so
slack gives us a place for all of us who are doing that to dump those things when
they come up and plan for the next thing and then we start and we pick up
momentum as that show gets closer and the the the and the reason why it's a
little better than IRC is it allows for additional functionality that's kind of
nice to have and it also gives you something that is very very valuable a
it's set up ready to go right now I just want to start I just want to do a brain
dump I do not want to start setting up software I want to do a brain dump it
gives me that immediately and I think that's important be or to whatever it
has large user adoption kind of like Skype or Google Docs West already had an
account you know rotten corpse already had an account right I don't have a new
client yeah yeah so we have people in the you know we have people are ready to
start right already can just get going without that quote-unquote friction that
was a nice thing to have and then and then you know number three or see
whatever that was really kind of great about slack is it just isolates it it's
it's all of that stuff in one space where IRC now can be dedicated to other
things this is dedicated to those things and if I do not as as a person who
sometimes has to be able to step away and have for God's sakes two hours that
don't involve work it is so nice to know that I could open up telegram or I can
open up my IRC client and there will not be 35 questions about work you know if
that if I want to find that I go into slack and so it also gives separation
in space and and the thing is a slack just gives that immediately so the idea
was does this concept actually add value as you know as an organizational tool I
think the answer to that is yes slack does seem to demonstrate there's value
there so now my as somebody who is an open source advocate my question is well
now can I replace that functionality with matter most and it can I convince
the team to switch it's not really my job though to make matter most more
competitive now the Jupiter broadcasting team is pretty much ready to switch to
something that is more open than the alternative like we were all using
Viber for a while to do team messaging and as soon as I said you know what
telegram looks like a way better solution and you know the protocols open
the clients open I'm using I'm using you know it totally open the client right
now let's go to telegram everybody switches to telegram immediately even if
it didn't do absolutely everything Viber did like you didn't do stickers all that
stupid crap at the time and added that stuff later and everybody switched so
the Jupiter broadcasting team and probably a lot of open source project
teams are a little more willing to switch before others would so I can
probably get matter most set up in a droplet up on digital ocean ready to go
and get say yeah it doesn't do everything slack does yeah sorry it
won't quite integrate with Dropbox yeah you can't write the bot that we wanted
to write but you can move over to matter most and it's gonna be a pretty solid
collaboration tool because we've we bored the idea out without having to spend two
days setting up the server first that's true you've you've said you've already
said that you've switched from IRC to Viber and from Viber to telegram and
now from telegram to slack I wouldn't say switched because they're all with
exception of Viber we did totally replace telegram invite like Viber was
totally replaced by telegram but IRC is still used as a secondary tool like
you're right I doubt you'll make that go away because there's loads of us out
here lurking in the IRC channel unless you know I mean even from like a
production standpoint like we have back we have back-end channels that aren't
public that we're still using right and that's what I mean the kind of people
who sit in those channels are the kind of people who will continue to sit in
those channels but I don't know it seems like you don't have that much of a
problem switching from one system to another and when you said that yeah I
would like was easy because other people were already on it that's just first
mover advantage and the network effect because they were the right yes not IRC
but you know something like IRC communication method matter most is the
free software option so when in the same way that Windows has got first mover
advantage against Linux and then this is the free software advantage you you
should be choosing Linux over Windows in the same way you should choose matter
most over slack I I suppose I see your point there and it means that when
matter most is ready or we're ready wouldn't be it wouldn't be a hard
transition to switch yeah we do have that advantage yeah not everybody does
though right yeah I think the the main to pick away from this is that with
matter most there's a lot more setup issues that you deal with so if you're
just trying to test to see if the the concept of slack or matter most will
work they would make more sense to try out slack first just because it's it's
a lot easier barrier to entry if if you re-listen to exactly what rotten just
said and replace what he said about slack and matter most with Windows and
Linux where he said you're right yeah said yeah then this is harder to set up
and that's why yeah you're right using slack and and what I think there is
those see myself out now no no I think what the what the answer there is is and
I in Kota radio this week I linked to and it talked a little bit about there
is a guide now that makes setting up a docker container with matter most on a
digital ocean droplet a pretty straightforward process so it's not
it's getting to the point now where if you are a little technically inclined
and you are you are okay spending a few minutes doing stuff you can deploy
matter most now and that's up I would bet you five dollars that if you told
one of your minions you wanted to switch to matter most by the time you wake up
and have done your hair in the morning someone will have it running sir how
long do you think it takes me to do my hair you know it's funny actually it's
it's funny you say that because so I have a girlfriend and I had to meet her
family right because that's the thing you do and I met her sister and her
sister's like I really like your hair I don't like okay that's awkward but thank
you yeah and she's like does it how long does it take you in the morning I'm
like what and I never stopped and thought about it like do people actually
think it takes me a while to do this look as a guy it does look high
maintenance I really does now poppy what I what I have to assure you is what I
have done is I have routinated and I have I have I have laser factored as any
male would his hair this hairstyle I it is the laziest approach possible it is
so funny like okay here's another story no shit and then we'll move on I the
first like one of the one of the first times I ever like worked with Noah on
location we go to a Denny's and we sit down his wife is there and we're having
dinner and he goes okay so tell me how you do your hair I'm like what tell me
how you do your hair I'm like what are you talking about like I get out of the
shower and then I grab the comb and I like comb it the way I wanted to comb it
and every now and then every now and then I'll put like I have like this this
coconut stuff I'll put in there and that's it that's it I get it from the
grocery store you've completely left out what time you get out of the shower what
time you get out of the bathroom after you've done your hair fantasy aside it
is it is literally here's here's here is literally the trick you just do it you
do it before it dries so no actually puppy what he left out is that he
conjures black magic yeah right okay all right fine I'll tell you about some
black magic that is a cinnamon 2.8 which was released today and of course you're
gonna see it soon in Linux Mint 17.3 Rosa planned for release at the end of
November it has better sound applets and man I gotta tell you I've been using a
boon to matei this weekend it's nice but that looks way better yeah that's
pretty slick I love you would be but it does look really good all right all
right I've got my rhino hijacked so the a lot of nice improvements to this to
version of cinnamon the new workspace switcher is super super slick and it
harkens back to basically what you get from gnome to or a desktop Matei now the
system tray has got a lot of improvements the window list is really
slick with a really nice tightened window thumbnails visual improvements
all throughout including better support for high DPI and they did a little magic
to make sure that if you hook up a 4k television which are notoriously
horrible at telling the operating system what they do much much improved a
support for that including high DPI which is I mean I got to say it again
including high DPI I mean I got to say it again including high DPI I got to say
it one more time high DPI as I have one machine with high DPI and I feel like
I'm constantly suffering a couple other things were true to change sorry cinnamon
now supports a microphone mute buttons the cinnamon settings Damon is more
robust than before and x ran or support was significantly improved many bug
fixes were ported from no shell as a matter of fact also speaking of
interesting things imported into the project cinnamon 2.8 also supports qt5
applications which now look more native and use the GTK theme that you've
selected I don't know exactly how that's pulled off but I find it to be fascinating
I'm curious to see what that looks like also performance improvements throughout
now you use mint don't you I'm still using I'm still using mint at work with
the cinnamon desktop and and how many times does the cinnamon desktop crash
mmm very rarely really good good cuz last time I tried it it was and the only
time I've actually had a crash in the past six months was due to a AMD
graphics card issue are you gonna go to the next mint or what are you gonna do
you know I haven't decided that yet I'm kind of looking to see how the next
fedora release comes out oh find out yeah all right so one last desktop
release while on the other end of the low resources desktop LXDE has a big
update LXDE 0.10 is out this release they say they focused on cleanup and
polishing and quality of life improvements with over 400 issues fixed
and dozens dozens of new translations and also gained two new framework solid
which replaces lib xqt mount and some custom power management code and lib K
screen which replaces the X render calls and is Wayland forward compatible that's
nice to hear actually I don't know why they didn't put this front and center
because the issue the number one update that I like is their new LXQT pseudo
which makes that like when you launch something and it needs to your your
pseudo password it's much nicer dialogue in this release that would have been in
one of my front center features but yeah that is in this new release as well also
new file manager improvements better support for the trashcan whatever the
hell that is and you get ready for this West search functionality oh good old
search functionality functional geez that one thing that one beer that turned
into two beers has made me all kinds of sloppy but congratulations to LXDE the
oh oh this was also this was also really good some other really important new
updates to the new release version 0.10.0 features are ready for this West
replaces all instances of LX lowercase X lowercase T so it's L lowercase X
lowercase T but upper L and Q now everything is uppercase they've replaced
all instances with that with LXQ and then a lowercase T that's important for
consistency so so from right so I'm gonna write this down right now so that
way I remember it right now so it's uppercase LX okay Q and then a
lowercase T perfect excellent work at it as of 0.10.0 that is officially the
way you are supposed to say that I don't I don't even know West I don't even know
but I just want to make sure we get there in fact wasn't there also speaking
of feedback before we wrap up feedback there was feedback on how to pronounce
Mate speaking of our slack chat and I wimpy can you tell me apparently I've
been saying it wrong again do you know about this wimpy am I am I a jackass no
you're very close this time thank you thank you thank you no I I pronounce it
Marte Marte so I don't know that I've I don't know I've got the correct sort of
Spanish you know m-a-h-t-a-y yeah I was told the easiest way to remember is it's
Marte like latte yeah I was told that too but that didn't seem to stick for
some reason damn it I hate that that it's maybe it's
like a used technically you can say it because people pronounce not yerba mate
with a yerba mate as well but Marta is the nor also also I also while I'm
while I'm doing pronunciations yeah may actually pronounced Xiaomi Xiaomi Xiaomi
Xiaomi I believe you know what you know what I hate I hate all of you what's
your addict what about Huawei well what about Huawei is pronounced pronounced
like her next Huawei Huawei yeah it's it's Huawei is how you pronounce it but
this feedback right here says Huawei look right there on the screen see this
is part of the problem before you hate me and judge me for how I do understand
I have I have hundreds of different versions look right there that says
Huawei now you're adding something it's Huawei embrace it it's your quirk Chris
people will love it I bet you don't know they don't love it that that finish
phone manufacturer the correct way that a Finnish person would say you know the
one yala no the the old one that used to make friends hold on I do I know I do
Nokia no no I know that's not it no no that's not it I don't know Nokia Nokia
Nokia Nokia Nokia Nokia Nokia Nokia Nokia Nokia Nokia.
All right fine we know yeah just just just to have a little bit of fun Chris
it's the name of the music player I just posted in the IRC how you say that let's
see here uh oh geez come on Robin that's designed that's designed to fail right
Right there.
That is...
Exactly.
Wow.
That is...
Oh, wow.
Okay.
So thank you, everybody.
I'm sorry for my horrible pronunciations.
But you know what?
I'll tell you what I can pronounce.
And I can pronounce it real good.
You know what that is?
That's DigitalOcean.
Head over to DigitalOcean.com right now and use our promo code of UltimatePowerDOUnplugged.
DO Unplugged will give you a $10 credit over at DigitalOcean.com with their $5 rate.
You can try it out for two months for absolutely free.
Two months for absolutely free.
You know what?
DigitalOcean is super, super flexible, super simple, because they're using Linux for all
of their virtualization.
KVM is the engine, and they all sit on top of SSDs.
You can get started in less than 55 seconds, and pricing plans start at only $5 a month.
That's nuts.
That's hard to believe.
Hold on.
That's nuts.
Five dollars?
That's like less than a single beer if you go out.
That's how much...
For $5 a month, you get 512 megabytes of RAM.
It's like a cup of coffee.
Yeah.
Or you know what?
Like less than...
It's actually even less than a burger from Wendy's.
Yep.
That is something.
Five dollars a month will get you 512 megabytes of RAM, 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte
of transfer.
Yeah.
That's right.
A terabyte of transfer.
If you go over to DigitalOcean, too, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED right now, and you
won't even have to put in a credit card.
They have a very, very solid interface.
It's really intuitive and easy to use, and you can replicate it on a larger scale with
their straightforward API.
Very intuitive control panel.
I love it.
They've got a brand new data center in Toronto, and they've also just rolled out floating
IPs.
Yeah.
I think this is going to take it up to the next level for them.
This is really going to bring you up to the...
Because if you grow, if you're going to need to move things around, this is a no-brainer.
Floating IPs, you can read about it over at DigitalOcean.com.
Plus, I think it's a great strategy.
I mean, I don't really need everything in my life to be high availability, but now that
I can, that's going to probably pick up a few more droplets just to have them on standby.
If I was doing VC talk and I was down, yeah, we have an on-demand Linux infrastructure
that we just deploy, it servers on demand.
Oh, yeah?
What's your cost on that?
It's pretty low.
It's like $5 a machine.
No!
Yeah, it's like $5 a machine, and then it just goes up to like $10 from there, and sometimes
we even...
You know what?
I've even figured out a way to deploy the machine two months for free.
No!
Yeah, two months for free.
Yes, I use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Go try them out.
They got CoreOS, they got Padora, they got Ubuntu.
They even got FreeBizzle.
I don't know why you'd want to use it as a server, because everybody knows FreeBSD makes
the best desktop out there, so you could try that.
But use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, and really, what I would do, screw that CentOS and screw
that Ubuntu, it's between you and me, Wes.
Yep.
CoreOS.
Seriously.
I'm putting my...
If there was CoreOS stock, I would be buying it right now.
I'm just saying.
But you could do whatever.
If you want to do Ubuntu LTS and have five years of patches and have tons of easy access
to tutorials and community, that's fine.
That'd be fine.
You could try that too, DOUNPLUGGED.
But I'm just saying, they also have a lot of really good community tutorials.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
the Unplugged program.
All right, Wes, now, you know me.
I'm not like some hardcore advocate about free software.
I don't sit here and tell you that everything must be free and that if you don't make free
software...
I think that we should all make those businesses fail.
But I'll tell you, something's got me fired up, real fired up recently.
And I'm not even a driver or an owner of a Volkswagen, but this whole Volkswagen scandal
is ridiculous.
And I want to talk about proprietary software in devices that not only our lives depend
on but are just really integrated in our day-to-day lives.
But first, if you're not familiar with the Volkswagen stuff because all you care about
is technology and you're not actually following the news, no judgment, this story, this clip
will bring you up to speed.
So this software, I'm going to stop it right there, this software is specifically designed
by Volkswagen that when it is in test mode, it alters the way the engine performs.
And when you're not in test mode, nine times of some of the most poisonous types of gases
come out of the tailpipe of these diesel vehicles.
Which causes respiratory problems.
In September, emissions cheating was exposed in 11 million other VW cars worldwide.
None of the cars have been recalled in the US and are still safe to drive.
The company could owe the EPA billions of dollars in fines, including nearly $400 million
associated with the latest batch of cars.
The latest batch of cars includes Porsches, Audis, we're talking high-end vehicles.
And this has caused the mainstream press like Cars.com and the New York Times and a bunch
of others that are running pieces that are basically saying that proprietary software
is the blame.
They say outright fraud is possible because of proprietary software.
And I think this is remarkable.
They say it's a bad situation, they get far, far worse.
You throw a perfectly good phone away after two or three years because components goes
bad.
But because the manufacturer refuses to provide parts and code updates, really, as the driver
of an old but beloved car that owns its latest 50,000 miles to the abilities of mechanics
who understand the engine's technology, which is a huge, great point, by the way, they go
on to point out that a day is coming when great cars get scrapped because the automaker
decided it was time to force me to buy a new one.
This is Andy Inocco writing for Cars.com.
In that same report, you know, he touches on the same thing we were talking about the
other week, you know, with Apple users not owning their software, only licensing it.
Here we see that more and more corporate companies, in this case, General Motors, employers have
defended the practice that you don't own the General Motors software in your car.
They do.
You have no right to play with it or tinker it or make sure that it's not polluting more
than you think.
Right.
Nine times more than they say it is.
You go in to get it tested, and it's then polluting nine times more than you thought
it was.
You go in to get it tested.
Yep.
I hope they're revising the tests here as well.
Maybe something you stick in the tailpipe while it drives around.
Pronoun.
You had a comment about proprietary software by law.
Go ahead.
Yes.
I think some law entity in Europe actually had a law that you have to put proprietary
software on cars so they can't be hacked.
Huh.
That is horrible, and obviously this would be an underscoring reason why that would be
a bad idea.
Wimpy, what do you have here from the podcast on season eight, episode 34 of the Ubuntu
podcast?
Sorry.
That was the wrong link.
That's the one after that about the Librarian of Congress.
Oh, yes.
Yeah, from the EFF.
Yes.
Actually, this is kind of where it's going.
We kind of touched on this last week.
Yeah.
Good point.
But there's a particular point in there about how this affects car security, research, repair,
and modification.
What did you catch?
That they've recognized the need for vehicle owners to circumvent access restrictions in
order to repair the fine tinker.
Yeah.
And one of the things in this VW case is that you're not able to actually determine what
the proprietary software is doing or not doing with regard to these test emission levels
and how the car is being tuned is because it's DRM protected.
And because of the DMCA, you're not allowed to hack it.
But under this provision, you now are.
This is a big deal.
Yeah.
This is a really big deal.
The Library of Congress has extended this DMCA, I guess, exemption to also phones and tablets
too.
And I wonder if this whole Volkswagen catastrophe is partly responsible for this.
It seems to be turning the tide in at least some of the public perception.
So here is now, I don't want to be like this guy.
But I just want to put this out there.
So let's be realistic.
The industry is what it is.
It's not going to be Kumbaya, open source, blah, blah, blah.
It's going to be, at best, people reverse engineering and figuring things out.
This software, this stuff is literally going to affect our lives.
It is the stuff that runs our cars, the stuff that runs the trains, the stuff that runs
the drones, the stuff that runs all of this.
Chris, just imagine for a second if SIZA or TTPIP or the TTP was in full effect.
The person that would have found this bug in the Volkswagen software would be going
to jail.
Right.
And, North Ranger, you also kind of wanted to play on the DMCA laws.
Well, yeah.
I mean, what Wimpy pointed out with the exemption granted by the US Library of Congress still
doesn't fix, I wouldn't call it a loophole.
It's a big catch with the DMCA is that the Library of Congress exemption only allows
individuals to bypass circumvention and things like cars and video games with servers.
It's still a criminal act to distribute tools to break those.
Right.
That's a good point.
Wimpy actually has a really good point about how this could be a great opportunity to explain
it to regular users about why DRM and DMCA stuff is so bad.
Go ahead, Wimpy.
Well, you know, normally we associate DRM with content, and if you try and explain why DRM
is bad because it protects video or music content to, you know, your friends and family
outside of the open source world, that's a difficult sell.
But if you explain this story that the software, automated software, is DRM protected and may
be tuning the car differently for its test cycle than when it's on the road, but nobody
can prove that because it's DRM protected, it's a better way to explain why DRM is a
bad thing and we shouldn't have it.
Yeah, boy, isn't that a good point?
And why not having insight into the software is not a good thing.
And I think that is...
Exactly.
Yeah, and I think we are seeing so much, and we have some links in the show notes, we're
seeing a lot of people report on this.
It's kind of encouraging in a way.
I wonder...
So here's my question, Wes.
And is this crazy?
I have a feeling I'm going to say yes.
All right.
As I wait for this stuff to shake out, is it that unreasonable for me to just avoid
all of these things, avoid the automated cars, avoid all of this stuff, and just say, as
a person who is a privacy advocate, as somebody who wants to know how my stuff works, as somebody
who wants to have control and oversight, is it reasonable for me to say, I am just not
going to participate for the next few years in this next way?
Is that actually seriously reasonable?
What that would mean would be, I can't buy a car after a certain amount of time.
I was going to say, how are you going to manage this?
So you're going to be stuck with outdated products?
So here's why this question fascinates me.
It seems like people who are extremely interested in the cutting edge, what's really going to
happen next, but very informed on it, are going to have to face the question if they
want to participate.
If you know how unreliable software and technology is, you're going to be pretty uncomfortable
with the direction things are going.
And you have to ask yourself, am I going to be one of the first in this first generation
who buys into this?
Or am I going to let a generation of products pass me by?
Because this is finally getting to the point where now your life is on the line.
I feel like at the end of the day, I'm probably somebody who wants to just take that risk,
but is it unreasonable to say, I'm going to let it just pass?
Is that just get off my lawn?
No, I don't think it's unreasonable.
I think it depends on your priorities.
You're in a little bit of a tighter spot in that you report on the tech news.
But for someone who's not that involved, who doesn't need to have an understanding of the
latest and greatest, and maybe doesn't have a lot of workflows they're looking to change,
I think that maybe for the next five, 10 years, you can get away with it.
We'll see what it looks like at that point.
Yeah.
Let it play out for a bit.
I feel like you can kind of, I mean, I don't know.
Boy, it is, for me, it seems like it's-
We're definitely coming to that crossroads, though.
Yeah, and it seems like if you're an advocate of open source and open standards, this is
not a great time that we're going into for you.
But I hate that to be a downer, so let me tell you about something that makes me feel
really good.
That's my mobile service provider, Ting.
I mean it, too, because Ting is great.
It's mobile that finally puts you in the position of power.
If you're so sick and tired of all these different companies running you over and taking advantage
of you and milking you, check out Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com.
You know what I mean, right?
I sure do.
Yeah.
Like all of the mobile companies out there, and I have to be honest with you, I am getting
so freaking burned by some of them.
Even the ones that, I'm the un-carrier, and then let me completely screw up net neutrality
for you.
Let me be the un-carrier and completely usher in the era of where pro services pay to be
completely unrated.
They're selling the public on it, and then the tech savvy of us are screwed.
I hate that.
And then on the other end, you have the duopoly, right?
On the other end, you have the duopoly, and it is just the worst.
Ting is mobile, it makes sense.
Here's why it's great.
Flat $6 a month, and then you just pay for what you use.
You want three phones?
It's $6 for each phone.
It's not a complicated thing.
And here's the nice thing, too.
Like, if a couple of those phones aren't gonna get a lot of usage, then they don't cost you
very much.
And if you're even, like, I don't know, a tiny bit WiFi savvy, you can really go nuts
with the savings.
Three lines, $40 a month.
That's what I'm paying.
Linux.ting.com, it'll take $25 off your first device, or it'll give you a $25 service credit.
I want you to try them out and click that savings calculator.
They got a lot of stuff over at Ting.
Try them out.
They got a GSM and CDMA network.
I think this is a ridiculous deal, though.
The LG G Flex 2, it's got that curve to it, you know?
I like some curves, Wes.
Yeah, I do, too.
Yeah, LG Flex 2's got the curves for $237, ships tomorrow, no contract, no early termination
fee.
You own that phone.
$6 a month for what you use.
And then just your usage on it.
$237!
And it's like, that's not for, like, a two-year contract.
That's just an unlocked phone that you own, and you pay for what you use.
They have CDMA and GSM, too, so if you've got a GSM device or a CDMA device, you might
be able to bring it over to the Ting network, and they have a whole range of devices that'll
work.
This is one suggestion.
I'm putting this out there because the LG G Flex 2 is a really nice phone, and for $237
on the Ting network...
It's a great value.
That's a great...
That's just exactly it.
That's just a really great value.
Also, I would say go check out the Ting blog.
If you've been kind of pondering the idea of what you can get by, do you need a good...
You want, like, that sweet spot, an Android device that gets updates, decent performance,
that doesn't cost $600?
Yeah, I know what you mean.
Well, they've got a Ting blog by Andrew over there.
Go to...
Well, no, go to linux.ting.com and click on the blog.
That way, we get credit.
He's been trying out the Moto E 2nd Gen for a month and writing about it.
He's looking for, basically, a sub-$200 perfect Android phone, and he's been blogging about
his experience.
Linux.ting.com.
Go try him out.
It's mobile.
It really does make sense.
Linux.ting.com also supports the Unplugged show and keeps us going.
So a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged, linux.ting.com.
Go try them out.
They are on a mission to make mobile make sense.
Linux.ting.com.
Thanks, Ting.
All right.
So today...
Do you feel it?
Do you smell it?
It's...
Well, that might be something else.
No, the other thing you smell is Fedora 23 released today.
Anybody in the Mumble Room actually have it installed as we speak?
Is that actually a thing?
Don't let us down.
Come on.
Anybody?
Just one.
No.
Okay.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
Maybe we just aren't the right crowd.
No.
We're not the...
And we're not talking to the right people.
These guys in here, they don't like to mess with computers.
There's all the software you'd want is free and available on the Linux platform.
But they don't care about that in the Mumble Room.
Most of the web runs on servers powered by Linux.
Oh, okay.
Tyler's...
Yeah, go ahead.
If it's any consolation, I actually was going to be running it, but I woke up late this
morning.
Well, that's fair.
Tyler in the chat room says he's...
You know what?
Fedora, he's...
Nah.
That's not his thing.
He's going for OpenSUSE Leap tomorrow.
Yeah.
I can understand that.
I actually have it downloaded upstairs.
I was like, well, I'll do the torrent.
I'm going to help contribute to seeding the Fedora 23 download.
It downloaded in like, I don't know, 45 seconds.
It was ridiculously fast.
I've been also following the RPM Fusion drama.
Supposedly, RPM Fusion repos are good to go, but the website hasn't been updated, so people
are super confused at this point.
And also, Fedly isn't updated for Fedora 23, so people are super hurt about that.
People really depend on those extras.
Yeah.
But I'm looking at Fedora 23 Workstation.
I think the thing that jumps out about, to me, is GNOME 3.18.
I kind of ding some of the other distros, like Leap's coming out tomorrow, shipping
with GNOME 3.16.
That was interesting six months ago.
But in today's time, 3.18 is much more interesting.
And guess what?
Fedora 23 ships with that.
You see, that's the difference.
You see how they do that?
That's the difference, you guys.
That's the difference.
They've actually got the current GNOME.
I know.
It's crazy.
So they've also got, along with that, that means they've got Google Drive support baked
into the new files manager.
Also, the new copy dialog box, which is a total ripoff of the plasma copy dialog box,
just saying, is also included now in files.
LibreOffice 5 is shipping with Fedora Workstation 23, which is great.
The new Calendar application, which has been getting worked on for a long time, used to
be called California.
But now it's just called Calendar because California didn't make any sense.
And it is now shipping in Fedora Workstation as default.
The Builder ID also shipping with code autocompletion for Python.
That's exciting.
I've been thinking about giving that guy a try.
It is very nice.
Also, their markdown support is very nice.
And the biggest feature, which I don't know if I'll be able to try between now and Friday,
but I'll give it a go, is firmware updates via GNOME software.
Which device are you going to try to brick?
Yeah, right?
I think this one.
The one you're sitting at.
Oh, yeah.
Why not?
Right?
Yeah.
Then also, Wayland is rocking in Fedora 23.
Oh, that sounds really fun to try.
It's funny because people are like, oh, Fedora 23, hmm, hmm, hmm, online.
And I'm looking at it going, whatever.
It's shipping with GNOME 3.18.
It's got the best Wayland support out of the box of any distro.
And it's looking really tight.
So I'm looking forward to really giving it a go.
They produce very nice images, I must say.
Like their ISOs, they've got the multi-boot all set up very nicely.
Whenever I get a Fedora ISO, I frequently use it as a kind of a helper toolkit because
I just know it's going to load on a number of systems.
And it always looks nice and comes up with a beautiful GNOME desktop.
I agree with you there.
I do.
All right.
So before we go on, anybody in the Mumba Room, any thoughts on Fedora 23 before we wrap up
the show today?
Going once.
I'm going to go twice on that.
Hey, by the way, also, just as a point of reference, in the show notes, there's been
I've noticing in different forms, message threads, things like that.
And in our IRC room, depending on how you upgrade to Fedora 23 from Fedora 22, you're
having different levels of success.
So I've got the official best methods to upgrade from Fedora 22 to 23 in the show notes.
Oh, look at how much brighter, prettier 23 looks in that picture.
Yeah.
You see what they did is they took 22, they took the same exact thing, but they made it
darker.
Yeah.
You don't want to be on the dark one.
No, I want to be on the one that they turned the exposure brightness up.
23.
That's the good one.
That's the one that's got the higher exposure setting.
Wes, you have astutely noticed exactly the same exact thing that I noticed when I linked
to this thing.
It's like, oh, they're obviously like, this is the dim one.
It's no good.
No good.
It's old and busted.
But what if we are creatures of darkness?
Ooh, in the night we lurk.
Many Linux users are also creatures of darkness.
Yes, this is true.
That's true.
Well, hang out in Fedora 22 land for a while.
All right.
That brings us to the end of this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Thank you for tuning in on a Tuesday.
Did you know we did this show on a Tuesday?
You might be listening on demand.
You might not have any idea.
Go to jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar.
That frickin' daylight savings.
Ugh, it's the worst.
Hate it, Wes.
We should just make the calendar UTC only.
Well, we just automatically adjust to your-
Okay, well that works too.
Contrived time zone, you hairless monkey.
Over at jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar.
Go to jplive.tv to watch us live.
LinuxActionShow.reddit.com for feedback, topic suggestions, and more.
Also jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact to send us in some emails.
But you know what?
If you want all of that S, join us in our virtual lug.
Yeah, come be here.
Right?
It's a ton of fun.
Every week.
How many other podcasts out there are like, yeah, if your mic checks out, you can join
us and just like share your opinion.
You know what?
Yell at us, tell us we're wrong, don't know what we're talking about.
Well, I don't love-
Or come and give us compliments.
That'd be good too.
That's what we prefer.
Whatever.
We're open.
jplive.tv, then do bang mumble to get that info and join us live, jupitabroadcasting.com
slash calendar for that.
Thanks for joining us.
See you back here next Tuesday, everybody.
Bye, Zeze.
Bye Zeze.
Man, that was a lot of show, and Wes will attest.
What's the appropriate term?
Because I don't want to say balls deep.
I was deep into something before the show started.
Yeah, you were taking care of business.
You might say life changing business.
Yes.
Before the show started.
You nailed it, you buttoned it right up,
transitioned right into a perfect show.
And you know what, it's funny because I showed up, Wes,
and I literally today, minutes before we go on air,
my life is changing.
And I show up, we do a show.
Same old, same old.
Mark shows up, Mark's never been here before.
Mark shows up, he does a show, right?
And then I go to JBtitles.com
and you know what I see, Wes?
14 titles.
I showed up, you showed up, Mark showed up.
Where's the chat room at?
Where are the titles?
Where's the titles at?
Absolutely unbelievable.
Unbelievable.
Maybe slacking off is the appropriate title.
Or at least the meta title.
Wow.
For the chat room, because everybody else showed up,
everybody else showed up.
You know what, I'm gonna go get a beer.
I'm gonna grab a beer.
There goes the no beer rule.
I'm throwing it out and grabbing a beer.
That was a stupid rule.
Ouch.
Oh wait, he can still hear that.
Wes, I left one beer for you.
Well, I added some more.
I saw that.
You're a good man, Wes.
You come bearing gifts.
You gotta grease the JB wheels.
That's true, all right.
How's our join queue doing?
Boy, still.
All right, okay, I think Ron's on top of it.
Awesome, awesome.
Well, I'm looking forward to chatting with you guys
about Ogg Camp.
Okay, so let me open up this beer.
Never did ask Chris which of the Minnesota brews
he liked most.
Huh, you know, now that I'm looking back at it,
I don't know if I can pull them all out
individually anymore.
I don't know if I recall.
Actually, they were all really good.
Yeah, some of them were pretty strong.
Volkswagen GT9 emissions.
Curious.
Sorry about that.
It's okay, I don't think the mobile room
could even hear it.
So, yeah, we did.
Oh, you did hear that?
I forget that radio's auto-play
in the horrible world we live in.
We can hear everything.
It's too late, we can hear everything.
Oh, okay, all right, well that's fine.
What you got there, Porter Stout IPA?
I'm not gonna dignify that with an answer.
Actually, it is a Imperial IPA.
It's a Pyramid Outburst, a dry-hopped Indian pale ale.
The Pyramid Brewing Company is,
I believe, in our neck of the woods,
isn't that correct, Wes, aren't they?
Yeah, they're from Portland, Oregon, as a matter of fact.
So this is a beer right out of Portland, Oregon,
a local beer for us, and I've seen the Pyramid Brewery
before.
Oh, very nice.
Yeah, I haven't gone in, but I've seen it before.
So I'll give it a, and you've already been drinking this.
I have been.
It's all about the Oregon beers.
We make the best beers down here.
Well, I don't know if that's necessarily true.
You're implying that Washington
would not make a better beer.
I happen to disagree, but I think we can be beer brethren.
We can be beer buddies.
It's brothers in beer.
Yeah, but you can't beat Washington beer.
Come on, let's be honest.
I think Washington beer is some of the best in the nation.
Yeah, that's true, that's true.
You know what?
I'll take you up on that challenge.
Give me a beer and I'll go find it for you.
Well, no, hold on now.
I would have to defer to your local expertise.
Yeah, true.
That's the only way to make it fair.
Yeah, and I feel like, here's the problem is,
I feel like that question
literally changes season to season.
So I would have to go on a all-star brewery tour
to entertain the current best beer to get it to you.
So you would be asking me
to basically go drink a lot of beer.
This sounds like a whole new show.
A lot of tasty beer.
And yeah, so yeah, well, okay, all right.
Well, we'll see about that.
That doesn't sound like a problem, Chris.
Yeah.