Look at this, we got 37 people in the virtual lug.
Imagine all of us in an actual room together
doing a lug event.
37, 40 people?
That's a little scary.
Don't worry, Wes has homemade hand sanitizer.
You can use it as a lotion.
It's great stuff, we have just buckets of it.
All incented.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 400.
Music
Hello friends and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
This special 400th episode of your Unplugged program
is brought to you by a Cloud Guru.
Learn by doing.
They are the leader in hands-on learning.
The only way to learn a new skill is by doing.
That's why ACG provides hands-on labs,
Cloud Linux servers, and much more.
Get your hands cloudy at acloudguru.com.
Welcome in, Mr. Payne.
Congratulations.
400, we're finally here.
It feels nice because not only do we have a lot planned
for this episode, a very special episode,
we have a fantastic showing in the virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, hello.
Hello.
Hey.
Howdy.
Ha ha.
Whoa.
Man, it is great to see a lot of you.
We have some old friends in there
that have spent a little time away,
but made time special, carved out of their busy schedules
to be here for the 400th episode.
And I don't know about you, Wes, but I
think I smell a little bacon.
What?
A little cheese bacon.
It can't be.
Hey, Cheesy.
Hello.
Hey, guys.
How's it going?
Welcome back to the show, man.
It's been a little lonely without you.
Well, I miss you guys, too.
It's been a little bit of a hiatus, but yeah, I'm back now.
Well, you have some news to share with the class.
Some exciting news at that.
Yeah, so recently, I guess this will make the third week.
So far, I've recently moved over from ACG
to work with System76 directly as a content producer for them.
So I'll be doing product photography, videography,
of course, content.
Still working through exactly everything I'll be doing there,
but I'm really excited about it.
A great group of people, excited to be working with them.
Man, you know they're in Denver, not Texas, right?
Yes, which means I have to relocate,
which means I have to figure out how to consolidate 15 years
worth of crap and move what I want to Denver
and store what I can't move.
Well, congratulations.
Thanks, man.
I think she's just out Lennox jobbed you.
I know, right?
It's great.
I'm super.
System76 is such, if I were going
to work for a company again, it would probably like,
System76 would be one of the few on a list of three companies
that I'd consider.
They're just a great team over there.
So congratulations.
Also, it's been a little bit since Ironic Badger,
AKA my co-host from the self-hosted podcast, Alex,
has returned.
Alex, welcome back to the show, man.
Hello.
Congratulations to Cheese on his fantastic new job,
by the way.
Good job, mate.
Thanks, man.
Well, also, a congratulations is due for you as well.
You have some news to share.
Yeah, somebody should have stopped me, but I've had a kid.
Congratulations.
Oh, wonderful.
Alex is a daddy.
That's really cool.
He needed another project, and boy, do you have one.
You thought podcasting wasn't enough, huh?
Yeah, I'll tell you what, Wes.
Project velocity has definitely decreased since she arrived.
Well, it's just been reallocated to something well worth it.
Absolutely.
Yeah, it's a lot more long-term project.
Yeah, it's a whole thing.
So thank you.
Thank you for the little nod.
We have a huge turnout.
Of course, Brent's there too.
Hello, Brent.
Good to see you again.
Well, hello.
I have some little news too.
I'm moving near Denver as well.
What?
Congratulations.
I happen to get engaged, actually,
and my fiance is down there.
So I might become half-American.
Look out.
The JB family has grown a lot in the last year and change,
and it's interesting.
It seems like there's some convergence happening
on the Denver area because Drew, who couldn't be here today
because of the day job, will also eventually
be relocating to that area.
JB Central formation.
Yeah, and Wes and I don't mind us a road trip to Denver.
No.
No, we do not.
When are we going to relocate, Chris?
That's the question.
I mean, I'm pretty much good to go.
I think the kids are down too, so we just
got to pick up the jacks and hit the road.
But maybe we'll wait for the passes to clear a little bit.
I think where I'm going to be located
is roughly 45 minutes north of where Brent will be.
So I expect we'll be hanging out a lot more often.
Also, there's a really sweet flight from Payne Field
here in Washington to Denver that is ridiculously cheap when
you think about air travel.
I just like the idea of thinking and conceiving of travel again.
And that was a huge limitation for our 400th episode.
If we could have done anything, no doubt about it,
my preference would have been some big meetup
where we have this experience in person.
But we're not there yet.
That's just not an option.
But we wanted to celebrate our 400th episode somehow.
This show started as the Linux action show Unplugged,
launched in August 12, 2013.
And episode one was Too Much Choice,
classic topic about are there too many distros,
apparently the age-old question that's never been answered.
Fast forward to episode 100, July 7, 2015.
Mr. West Payne joins me after a barbecue, which was a meetup.
Yeah.
Yeah, so celebrating the show's 100 milestones with meetups
is kind of a tradition.
Who would have thought I would still be here
barbecuing at the studio?
We are barbecuing today.
We are absolutely barbecuing today.
We're making a whole day out of it.
But since we didn't have that option,
we still wanted to do something pretty different,
just really kind of have a different experience
altogether.
If you can imagine doing something for nearly eight
years that is entirely digital.
So we work our butts off every week,
and the end product is intangible.
It's like a 30 meg MP3.
Yeah.
And so it's years of collaborating together
on creating something that we've never really
had the tangible result for.
And we thought, wouldn't it be awesome for us
in our 400th episode to do kind of some sort of show prep that
was hands-on, that was physical, that resulted
in a physical object when we were done?
And we've always wanted to do a episode dedicated to the topic
since really the early days of the show of using
Linux to brew beer and make your beer even better.
Yeah, I mean, beer is often a component that
helps make this show better.
So the reverse situation just makes sense, right?
That's very true, right?
I mean, we'll find out.
And so we kind of stated this intention
about over a month ago or something on the air.
And several of you reached out, including
a listener named Corey.
And Corey seemed to really love an app called BeerSmith.
Hey, I'm Corey.
I love BeerSmith.
I've been using it for years.
And his email kind of made us feel
like maybe BeerSmith was the route we should take.
I mean, I even got so into it I contacted the developer of it
and started having a little chat with him.
And so we thought, well, if Corey's
been using this for like a decade,
let's call Corey up and talk to him
about how we could use BeerSmith on Linux
to plan our special beer.
It's a fantastic tool.
There's a lot of calculation that
goes into producing a beer recipe.
And there's a lot of online web pages and calculators
that you can use.
But BeerSmith does a very nice job of integrating all of that
and helping you plan your recipe to hit target alcohol volume,
to hit target bitterness, to even hit target
color of your beer.
And it has a number of calculators
that you can use as you're brewing the beer
and as you're carbonating it.
So it's incredibly useful.
Sounds like, too, that you could use it to recreate a good beer.
So if we really like this unplugged beer,
we could reproduce it.
Absolutely.
It has, you know, you can store your recipes.
You can, you know, save as and fork your recipes, if you will.
I have some recipes that I've been making iterations of
for years.
I do a barley wine, or at least have been after taking a hiatus,
barley wine every year.
And it seems to get stronger every year somehow.
But I started from a basic recipe
and just kind of modified it to make it work for me.
And you can just keep different versions or, you know,
however you want.
You suggested I contact Brad Smith, the author of BeerSmith.
So I emailed him and told him, hey, we're doing a Linux
podcast and we're brewing a beer for our show.
And he wrote back and he told me that he'd
started using Unix back in 85.
He worked alongside people that were working on Arpanet
back in the day, deploying SQL at the Air Force.
He mentioned that he used Minix, that he
has been developing the next version of BeerSmith
and the web version all on Linux.
And he uses BeerSmith on Linux himself.
Yeah.
Isn't that great?
No, it's really awesome.
And he used Minix.
That's, you know, wow.
So, you know, Brad Smith is this really cool guy
who's been doing this software for a long time.
And he has, he's really big in the home brewing community.
He has his podcast, which is, you know,
sponsored by his product, but he's not
pushing his product in it.
He's just talking about general brewing information.
Very active at conferences.
I've never met him or spoke with him,
but he seems like a really great guy.
And for your use case, also on Linux?
BeerSmith been working just fine on Linux?
It works great.
I started using it probably 2012.
I was on Linux Mint at the time.
I googled, what should my first distro be?
And about the same as it is now, Linux Mint came up.
And I used that for a while.
It worked great.
I think it was BeerSmith 2 I was on.
And now I'm using it on Ubuntu Mate.
And it works great.
The only thing that's not awesome is the dark mode.
It's a little jinky.
He doesn't have that fully implemented yet,
but I could just change the theme from dark to light
and boom, works great.
Well, I got BeerSmith installed and have been sort of poking
around.
And you are not kidding.
There is a lot in here, tons of tools, tons of options.
Do you have any tips for actually getting started?
Because we're kind of relearning how to brew beer
and then also maybe learning BeerSmith.
Sometimes it's almost like taking a dump truck
to go grocery shopping.
It has a lot on it.
So what I would recommend for anybody starting out
is start with a kit where they do all the planning for you
and you can kind of see what goes into it.
And you make the kit.
You kind of get your rhythm down, your process down.
And then you start looking at different recipes.
You can get them from books.
There's a ton of them online.
Homebrew Talk is a very good online forum
that's been around forever.
And there's tons of recipes.
And so you can start trying out some of those recipes.
And then you can branch off to make the recipes taste
the way you want.
And part of this, when you start making beers,
you tend to learn a lot about beer.
When I started out brewing beer, I
knew there was Bud Light, there was Guinness,
and there were things that were different than those.
And that was about all I knew.
And you start learning about different beer flavors,
how the malts interact, how the hops play into it,
other than some beers have no hops
and some beers have all the hops.
And you get a bit of foundation of that
when you're using other people's recipes
and when you're using kits.
And then you start kind of figuring out on your own
and making your own recipes.
The beer I have now, I'm calling it Fieldward.
It's a dodgy part of town outside of Waterdeep and D&D.
It's an oatmeal stout.
And I've formulated the recipe.
And I'm quite happy with.
I like that tip.
We basically could learn from others
by following others' recipes and getting these kits.
And it's sort of like training wheels for beer brewing,
because there's just so much to it.
Yeah.
Well, the thing with brewing is this
is one reason why a lot of engineering types
are drawn to it, because there's the creativity part where
you're designing the recipe.
But there's also a process.
And the process is very important,
because you can have an amazing recipe.
But if your process allows for contamination
or if it allows for oxygenation when you don't want it,
there's all these things that could happen
or a bad fermentation temperature that
could give you bad flavors.
So even with the best recipe with the best ingredients
with the highest quality water, if you
don't have your process down, you
could end up with a beer that tastes weird.
So it's great to use some kits or other people's recipes
to start out with and just kind of figure out your process
and how to make that work for you.
Well, Corey, thank you.
Thank you guys very much.
The other great thing about Beersmith, of course,
is that it's a desktop Linux application that
makes a profit.
And it's nice to see some of those as well.
Mr. Bacon, you had a chance to play around with Beersmith,
I know, in your beer past.
Yeah, so previously, I would say maybe this
was four and a half, five years ago.
Another friend of mine, Chris, him and I would brew together.
And he turned me on to Bruce Smith.
And actually, one of the ways we met
is because we were talking about Linux and then brewing,
and then Bruce Smith kind of came up.
One thing that I really love about it
is that you can plan out your brew day easily.
So you basically can have a log of everything
that you need to do, all of the gravity measurements
that you need to take, where they need to be,
what to do to offset that.
But I absolutely agree with the guest
in that you should start with a kit
or start with some recipes that are already available out
there.
There's a great one, it's a left-hand brewing milk stout
clone that's really easy to make.
I would also recommend maybe making an ale,
and maybe not a lager, because generally, you
have to ferment those a little bit cooler.
And so you have to watch out with your fermentation there.
That's what I took away from our conversation,
is we needed a little bit of guidance.
Because Wes and I had both done this at different points,
but we were part of a team, and some others
had done some key components.
So we knew we needed some guidance.
I'd never done it entirely all myself.
And then I opened up Beersmith, which is impressive.
But I mean, there's just so many options,
so many different recipes.
It was like, OK, I need a few fewer variables.
Yeah, and we were thinking about building
a pretty sophisticated brewing setup
with a few different components that would be running Linux,
which we will get to in a bit.
But you were right.
You're right, Jesus.
And it was a point that Cory made, too.
We had to start somewhere that was defined,
because otherwise, it just felt like just so many options.
And we wanted to walk away with a beer that
was better than what you could get in the store on average.
Because I think that's something that you can really
appreciate, is that home brewing can often taste a lot better
than what you buy.
Well, even if it doesn't, it still
tastes better because you made it.
You made it.
It's fresh.
It tastes like pride.
What's really cool about Beersmith
is you can take it all the way to the level you want.
So you can start with a kit where you basically just
have extract, which is all your grains that have been boiled
down into this syrup that you do not want to get on anything
because it is super sticky.
And then you add that to water.
You bring it to a boil.
But then you have all grain brewing,
which is basically where you have all of the grains.
And you boil the grains together to make that same extract
or that same base for your beer.
That delicious, delicious base.
So we put our heads together, thanks to some help from Corey
and a lot of good email that came in.
And some chats that we had with people in Mumble.
We kind of just brought all this information together.
We were leeching off anyone who could give us tips, basically.
I think we came to a game plan.
Because if you think about it, we had only a few weeks
to pull this off.
We needed minimum time to beer here,
both for episode planning reasons and for our own tastes.
Linode.com slash Unplugged.
Go there to get a $100 60-day credit towards your new account
and, of course, support the show.
I think one of the things I really appreciate
about Linode and I appreciate about our audience
when we get to some milestone like 400 is everybody gets it.
You guys understand that this is a small business,
that we're working hard to pick good sponsors that we think
are going to be really a hit for you.
And you keep those sponsors happy by visiting our promo
URLs, like linode.com slash Unplugged,
because it's a signal that our audience responds
and that we're a worthwhile investment for Linode.
And that cycle has just sort of continued.
As we're now, you think about Jupyter Broadcasting,
we're nearing like 13 years or something like that.
I think that's like 50 years on the internet, right?
I'm pretty sure it works like that.
Yeah, I mean, remember when you started
and there was Ogg files around?
And that's why I'm not sitting here giving
you a read about underwear.
I'm telling you about Linode, which is our cloud hosting
provider.
They're an independent cloud provider.
And that matters more than ever these days.
They started in 2003.
And they have refined what they do down to excellence.
And they make it easy to give your creations
their own personal space on the internet,
no matter what skill level you're at.
If you're an old server salt or if you're brand new to it,
they have a dashboard that's super easy to use
and a technology stack that works with what
you're comfortable with.
Linode will help your ideas come to life on the web.
If it's a personal website or the entire back-end
infrastructure for your point of sale application.
And they have hundreds of guides and tutorials,
one-click application deployments that
make all this stuff really easy to get up and go.
Just go.
Westpac is spinning up machines all the time
for testing here on the show.
Yeah, I just like to make you nervous.
I get these email notifications.
I love the email stuff they have set up, too.
One of the ways I can tell that the PeerTube
has gotten a lot of traffic, because I
have some thresholds set up.
So when it reaches a certain amount of transfer,
I get an email.
And it's like, oh, we hit our milestone.
And that's nice for the lazy admin,
when you can mostly ignore it.
But if something's happening, you know.
And then maybe you can go troubleshoot.
It's a great first sign that something could be up, too.
They also have S3-compatible object storage,
cloud firewalls, super fast networking, 11 data centers
worldwide, and much, much more.
So go get started.
And support the show.
And get a $100 60-day credit, $100.
I mean, you could really try all this stuff out,
the different range of machines, all of it.
You go to linode.com slash unplugged.
That's the URL to go to to get that $100 60-day credit
and to support the show.
linode.com slash unplugged.
I don't know if anyone else has heard
of this application or framework called Cloudron.
But just digging around Linode's one clicks,
I came across Cloudron.
Cloud-o-ron, like?
C-L-O-D-R-O-N, Cloudron.
OK, Cloudron.
It'll allow you to stand up basically one-click installs
for all your favorite things, so WordPress, Rocket Chat,
Next Cloud, GitHub, OpenVPN, basically
anything you could want.
And it's basically containers, right?
They're wrapping these containers in there.
But you manage it all from this one central hub.
Really cool, something I probably
would have never found had I not just been digging around
on Linode's one clicks.
Sweet.
We'll put a link to that in the show notes, Cloudron.io.
So with our brew planned, we were ready to start.
But we realized we probably needed some help.
And we realized we were going to have
to move quick to get this ready for 400,
because what's the point of doing
this if we don't have the physical thing
by the 400th episode?
That was the thing we wanted.
And we thought about it for a little bit.
You know what would be kind of a cheat code
is if we could learn off some experts.
And so our first idea was to go to a local brewery
and just sort of spend some time there.
Then I realized that with COVID and all of that,
they probably weren't going to be
cool about a couple of jerks doing a podcast,
calling up and asking to hang out in their brewery all day.
It was dicey to start with.
And now we have an extra hard sell.
Yeah, exactly.
So we found a local brew-your-own beer shop.
And that was, turns out, an ace's move,
because they had smart people who could help us
when we needed it, but were otherwise very hands-off.
And of course, they had top-of-the-line gear,
which would have been quite the initial investment for us.
So Wes and I are out here outside of Gallagher's
Where You Brew in Edmonds, Washington.
Are you ready to learn how to make beer, Wes?
Oh, yeah.
We figured we'd learn from the pros directly.
And also drink beer while we make beer,
because they serve beer, too, let's be honest.
This sounds like a recipe for success.
And the nice thing was is they were totally chill.
They let us get in, kind of get acquainted with the space.
And they also were really great about just giving us
a crash course on some beer basics.
But the yeast, the yeast will get up all the sugar,
turn it on to CO2 and alcohol.
After about a week, there'll be no sugar,
so the yeast will fall out of suspension, right?
After that happens, we'll take it back here to the cold room.
This is a beer nursery.
Go ahead.
The athlete and cold room.
Yeah, really.
They had this perfect setup that we were gonna be
totally taking advantage of.
So we were pretty set, but we knew since we were drinking
beer as we went, we'd probably need some brain backup,
not to mention a designated driver.
Sloppy idiots that we are.
I think it's best that Adia do all the precise measuring out.
What do you think, Chris?
Definitely.
Gotta bring the wife in.
Well, it did take precision, but at least it was fun.
Yeah, she's always bringing in the puns, too.
She insisted.
Then we get to work, and we have a recipe
that we've planned out.
We've kind of run it past these guys.
It's essentially a Belgium triple,
but we wanted to make some modifications.
And like all professional brewers,
we made those modifications at the absolute last minute.
In what may prove to be our undoing,
we've made a last minute recipe adjustment.
After all of our planning, all of our considering,
literally here at the last minute, we decided, well,
let's change it up.
So what do we do?
It's a last minute malt swap.
Turns out we had a lot of lager going into this already.
Nine liters.
We decided eight was probably enough.
And instead, we're sticking with originally,
we were called for one liter of wheat.
That's up to two.
That's right.
Two fancy liters.
After all that special planning, it was just sort of a whim.
And I think it paid off.
I think so.
But the moment really came to West.
Like, if I were to think back of that day,
there was one moment where you saved the day.
Touch and go Westpain just saved this thing from boiling over.
He jumped up like an agile lion out of his seat
and pulled the, what do you call this, massive wizard staff
that he's stirring with.
It's the beer wand.
He saved it with the beer wand.
So now it's time to add the bittering agents.
I mean, you got the boil just right.
You added the bittering agents just right.
I was getting a little too beer happy by that point.
Well, it's hard when they sell delicious beer at the spot
that you're making beer.
But I mean, they had such incredible equipment
and like steam power in this.
So it really got up to a boil pretty quick.
And it did almost boil over.
So really, once I think you had the confidence
of saving the brew, like the gazelle that you are,
I kind of felt like it empowered you.
And you sort of went into full artisan mode.
We've officially entered late stage brewing.
And the craftsman in Westpain is really emerging.
Tell us about the special care you're taking.
Well, it's really important that we infuse
as much cracked coriander and orange peel in here
as we can.
That's what makes it so tasty.
I mean, you really, you know, you took charge.
You really made it special.
And so I think you earned the final honor of releasing it
and storing it.
Our time has arrived.
It is time to transfer it to the primary fermenter.
Westpain will be in charge of the transfer valve.
It is a responsibility like no other.
Hey, good sir.
Go ahead with that warp.
Perfect.
Warp's coming your way.
Wes has flipped the warp valve.
And now our beer is going down a series of tubes
and into what can only be described
as a vessel, a sacred vessel, that will hold our beer.
Here it goes, Wes.
Here goes our beer.
Cool.
Look at it flow.
That is pretty great.
All right.
Want to go down the hole?
You can watch it drain right out of the kettle.
From the kettle into the storage.
And then we come back in two weeks and we bottle.
It felt kind of like somewhat anticlimactic to walk away
because then you don't know what's going to happen.
Like, did we mess something up?
That last minute tweaking?
Did we drink too many beers?
Only time would tell.
We had to wait.
Yeah, and so it was indeed a bit of a wait.
But we will get back to that.
We had lessons to learn in the meantime.
But before I get to those, I want
to say hello to Drew, who's making a last minute
appearance.
Hey, Drew.
Hey, guys.
I leave for, what, like six months
and you're out here brewing beer?
Good Lord.
Hello, hello, sir.
How are you?
It's good to hear from you.
Doing well, doing well.
I didn't want to miss episode 400.
Well, we appreciate you being here.
I was just telling everybody earlier
that we felt like for 400 we wanted something tangible.
You work on something for like almost eight years
and it's always a virtual product.
It was nice to do something that we could sit here
and actually hold in our hands.
So empowering.
I think you know what I mean.
I sure do.
And I hope you save me a bottle for the next time
I'm out there.
Oh, you know it.
You know it.
Yeah, that's absolutely happening.
Yeah, so don't you worry about that.
In fact, I have more on that in a little bit.
But we figured we'd spend the time while we waited
for our beer, anticipating what would happen next,
learning how to take this to the next level.
Because I think even before we were done,
you and I agreed we were enjoying this.
Yeah, we were having a good time.
And sure, yeah, we pressed the easy button to start out with.
But we liked learning about this.
There was more to learn and we were interested.
And the entire time when we were using their equipment,
we were like, OK, if we were doing this at the studio
or something, how would we do this?
And we would look up gear on YouTube or online
and look at equivalents that we could use.
And the guys at Gallagher's were really cool about saying,
OK, if you're doing this at home, you would do it this way.
And so that was really handy to help us picture
what it might be like if we wanted to keep doing this
and maybe brew some beer on a more regular cadence.
So we put our heads together and thought,
if we're going to do this long term,
we need some tips from a pro.
And so we caught up with Late Night Linux's Graham Morrison,
who has a full Linux-powered, full-timers brewing setup.
So Graham, before we go too far, could you describe to us
your current brew setup?
So my current brew setup is that I use a closed fermentation
system to basically turn the wort into alcohol beer.
And then I transfer that under pressure to a corny keg
when it's ready to basically drink.
It's almost ready to drink after that.
So it can take 10 days, two weeks,
which is a lot quicker than bottling.
I was surprised by that.
I guess I thought part of the brewing process
involved putting it in the bottle
and then having it sit in the bottle for a couple of weeks.
That actually improves the beer.
Certain beers, kind of Belgian beers, are very strong beers.
Or beers that take some time to mature
or their flavors to mellow can really
benefit from being in a bottle.
That's interesting, Wes.
We should take note of that.
Indeed.
But it's a lot more hassle.
You have to clean the bottles.
You have to individually prime them for carbonation.
And you have to then transfer the beer to each bottle, which
almost you may even have to transfer from the fermentation
bin to a secondary fermentation bin to let all the trube leave
at the bottom of the first bin.
Whereas transferring under pressure
from the fermentation vessel to a corny keg
is a single step process.
And you only have to clean the corny keg.
And it carbonates.
And you can adjust how much carbonation you want,
which for me is important.
That is a good tip.
So what I like about your setup is it
feels to me kind of getting into this again for the first time.
I feel like I'm totally starting over.
And your setup feels to me like it's, I don't know,
about a long-term setup.
But it's sort of like lessons learned
have gone into creating something that lets you just
brew beer whenever the fancy strikes you.
How does Linux play a role in that?
I used to brew beer with just a fermentation bin
under the stairs at house temperature, basically.
Yeah, that's what I'm familiar with.
Yeah.
And the quality is like, I don't know,
can I say it's like a 1970s porn film of beer?
I mean, some people have a thing for that.
Yeah, and it's fine.
But it just makes me think of rainy caravan holidays.
Whereas what really made the difference,
the quality increased like 1,000%
was when I controlled the temperature of the fermentation
process exactly, which is where the yeast is doing all its work.
And the yeast has to work at this optimum temperature.
And to control the temperature, I basically
used, in the beginning, it was this open source project
called BrewPi, which actually ran
on a little bit of firmware running on an Arduino Uno
that actually did, if you're familiar with PID,
like PID controlling, I think it's
like proportional integral derivatives.
And they basically, one sensor measures the temperature.
And then a couple of relays either turn on heating
or they turn on cooling.
And the PID part is the fact that because this big volume
of liquid, it can anticipate temperature changes
according to environmental conditions.
So you get within a tenth of a degree accuracy
of temperature controlling.
So you can basically, with the BrewPi, with the RaspberryPi,
and an Arduino, control exactly the temperature
of the fermentation process and monitor it.
So it's pulling in a weather API feed to monitor that?
The original BrewPi did it all on its own.
It was this self-contained unit.
BrewPi actually was so successful
as this individual project, they spun it into a business.
And they sell their kind of bespoke hardware
and closed source firmware now.
But the platform was popular enough
to be integrated into something called Firmantrack, which
is an open source project that integrates
a lot of that old open source BrewPi software
to work with the same hardware.
And more importantly, actually work with the ESP8266 devices,
low cost microcontrollers, and expands it.
It dumps PHP and makes it all modern REST frameworks.
So that all operates over a REST API,
which you can integrate with Home Assistant,
or you can push to the cloud, do whatever you want.
But it's basically the same PID algorithm
that's controlling the temperature of the fermentation.
Wow.
I got to just sit with that for a moment.
A REST API for brewing beer.
Yeah.
So it really sounds like what I'm
getting from what you've kind of described
is that controlling that temperature
is the secret to unlocking delicious great home
beer versus beer that's OK.
Yeah, it really is.
There are some yeasts that a yeast will
have an ideal temperature.
In centigrade, it could be like 21 degrees.
And you might even start low.
Like with a good pilsner, you might start at 18 degrees C.
And then after a couple of days, ramp it up to 22
and then drop it.
You might cold crash when there's no sign of any further
fermentation.
And you can check the amount of fermentation
that's going on with something called like an iSpindle, which
is it's not quite open source, but it's
a DIY project where the firmware can be downloaded and installed.
The code is accessible, but it has
one of those weird licenses attached to it
so they can try and make money off it.
Sure, you got it.
Have you experimented or done any kind of visualization
or graphing of the temperatures over time
just so you have something to look at data-wise?
Yeah, so Fermentrack does exactly this.
So there's usually two or three sensors involved.
And these are really simple $0.50 sensors.
They use like the one-wire protocol.
They do nothing extraordinary other than report
the temperature.
There's one for the inside the beer.
So you normally use a fermentation bin
with what's called a Thermowell, which is like a cylinder you
put straight into the beer.
And then the sensor goes right into the middle of the beer.
So you get the exact temperature inside the beer.
But you can also use the temperature on the ice spindle,
which can sit inside the beer.
That's the temperature of the beer.
Then there's a temperature inside.
Usually, you use an old refrigerator.
So you put the fermentation bin inside the refrigerator.
And so you get the temperature inside that and then
a temperature of the room, the environment outside that.
Those three temperatures together
are mulched in the algorithm to control
the temperature of the brew.
That is fancy.
Mulched.
That is so great.
Yeah.
And it turns that I put a little heater in the fridge.
This is all that I've done is there's two relays.
So a relay with a simple 5-volt signal from the Arduino
will turn on something or turn off something.
Two relays.
So one turns on the refrigeration.
The other one turns on the heating element,
which is just what in the UK you get them
for like summer houses or greenhouses.
It's a small, low-cost thing you can bolt
to the bottom of the fridge.
And so all of that, sorry to answer your question,
in Fermentrac and in Brusella before it, you can see all
of that in a chart to monitor exactly all the temperatures,
how things are going, and also put on top of that
the gravity of the beer, so how well it's actually fermenting,
how strong it's fermenting, and the alcohol content of the beer
as you go through it.
And then when that starts to flatline,
you know then you can dry hops the beer
if you're going to do that, or you can transfer it
to bottles or a keg.
All right, so then I have really kind of one really ultimate
question.
Looking back at the last decade or so of homebrewing,
all of these different things that you can do,
features you could do, what has helped the most?
And what would you tell past Graham if you could?
What advice can you pass along to us?
The thing that's really made a difference, I think,
with lots of things is the quality of the ingredients.
So the wort kits that you can get,
you can buy them separate with the malt extract
and with the kind of boiled down wort.
Don't kind of skimp money on those kits
if you're going to do it.
And of course, if you're going to brew and mash your own beer
even better, that's like the first step.
Get that right.
Follow the instructions for the yeast
because that's really important.
And then really bottle the stuff that's
really important, that's going to keep, that you want to come
back to.
But otherwise, the keg was the big innovation for me
because it speeds up.
You can set carbonation exactly as you want it.
You can speed up the fermentation under pressure.
So I brew everything under pressure.
I like that tip.
That does seem like a good one.
I actually wrote that one down on an actual piece of paper.
I'm like, I got to make a note and talk to Wes about that.
So looking back at it, do you have a favorite go-to beer
that you brew?
Well, I actually got into this after going
to Portland in the US and really getting hooked.
You know, there's got an amazing beer scene.
I've really got to taste that hoppy kind of West Coast
Portland IPA.
And in the UK, you just couldn't get it.
But I could buy the work kits.
I could ferment them here, and I could bottle them here.
And it was as close as I could get
to getting a pint of those West Coast IPAs on tap
here in the UK.
And that's what really got me into it.
And so I still really love going back to them.
But right at the moment, I've got a New Zealand Pilsner,
which is perfect as well.
I'm really enjoying it.
And the nice thing is you can change,
and it's a bit like being at the pub while the pubs are closed.
Indeed.
You're exploring the world while you can't travel through beer.
Yeah.
I love it.
Graham, thank you.
No problem.
I want to tell you about a special course
from our friends at a Cloud Guru.
We will have a link in the show notes.
It is the SUSE Linux Enterprise Admin Review and Exam Prep.
Is it time to become a SUSE Certified Administrator?
Well, they have the prep course for you.
It'll get you ready for the exam and final exam courses.
And they have all the information
you need to become prepared to get certified.
Exam prep courses are designed to be a review of the content
from each of the courses proceeding
to get you really kind of just set on the important points,
tips, and areas that will be an issue for an exam
in particular.
That's what these are kind of tooled for, including even
how to register and go get the final exam and all of that.
It's all covered.
We'll have a link in the show notes
to the course for our Cloud Gurus,
SUSE Linux Enterprise Admin Review and Exam Prep.
Graham has such an awesome setup.
After listening to that, I was like, yeah, we're definitely
going to be following some of this advice.
It was really nice to get his decade's perspective
on how to do this right.
Yes.
And I think he's hit a nice kind of sweet spot where it's,
you know, much like with audio, you
can kind of invest as much as you want in beer brewing
equipment, it seems, but we don't really need to do that
or have the space at the studio.
So finding the, like, dialed-in setup that just works,
gets good quality beer, but doesn't have to go crazy all
out with, like, six different containers and systems
and setups and transfers, that's what we were looking for.
Yeah.
So, you know, time passed.
We let about three weeks go because we were planning ahead
for LUP 400, but we didn't have a lot of time.
And so we really didn't know how things were going to be.
So Saturday came rolling along, and we showed back up
at Gallagher's in Edmonds, Washington.
Hello, Wes.
It's been three weeks.
Here you go.
We got you a beverage, I guess.
Look at that.
Yeah.
A beverage.
That's colorful.
Looks tasty.
Clementine.
Probably should have something besides beer today.
I suppose that's true.
And once we got in there, we knew, like, some things we were
just so grateful were already set up,
like their whole bottle washing system.
Wow.
Very nice.
Made it way simpler to get up and get going.
I'm going to get these started washing.
You guys get those going.
And over here, I'll bring you some more bottles out as well.
All right.
Thank you.
I was doing the math last night.
It seemed like we were clips, but I wasn't sure
how many bottles we had.
All I can think about is we got kegs.
I'm so glad we got kegs.
Me too.
Why?
Because it'll make this so much easier?
Well, yeah.
And then, like, we have kegs.
Boy, did it make it easier.
I mean, we didn't even have to fill the kegs ourselves.
They just did it for us.
I don't know if we would have thought of that if Graham hadn't
said something.
But one of the advantages of using Gallagher's really rad
setup is we could dial in the carbonation in a way
that we wouldn't have been able to do with a newbie setup.
We're trying it out for the first time
before we bottle and keg it.
And I want to get Wes' first impressions.
Smooth.
There's definitely booze in there.
And it's tasty.
I think we decided it needs a little more carbonation, maybe.
But other than that.
I like it.
I like it a lot.
I think once we get a little more carbonation,
it'll be perfect.
But the flavor, the color, it's a beautiful beer.
Look at that.
Golden, it takes the light well, lights up the glass.
I got to snap a picture of the first look at this beer.
And with the help of their brewmaster,
who kind of encouraged us to dial it up just a little bit
more.
Happened to be a Belgian fan himself.
Yeah, we did it.
We took the plunge.
It doesn't look any more bubbly.
So we're not going by appearance.
We're going for that bite on the tongue.
This thing minimizes the amount of turbulence that it gets.
So you won't be able to see much of the foam there.
All right.
There you go.
Let's give the updated version a try.
Cheers, Wes.
Cheers.
And they had such a nice system, because what?
It was like a carbonation stone they use?
Yeah, they had a way to just force carbonate it.
So you could dial it up as you want, right?
Like, oh, you need a little more carbonation?
Add a little bit more.
They just run it right back through the system.
And in, I don't know, five minutes, we could test it
again.
Yeah.
And we did.
Once we had it dialed in, first thing
was to get the kegs filled up.
And then we got to play with their super cool, like, beer
wand to fill our bottles.
So we're about to bottle, and we're benefiting from this cool,
like, beer gun that they have.
Yeah, it's hooked up to the CO2.
It's carbonated.
You can purge the oxygen from the bottle
before you put any beer there to protect our precious brew.
But surely one of us is going to make a mistake.
Yep.
Now it's just a matter of putting beer in bottles.
So let's get to work.
And we did.
Nice that we kind of came up with a system.
We traded off, on and off.
You know, you filled it for a little while.
Then I filled it for a little while.
We would trade off from the box.
It worked really well because they have everything plumbed.
And so they had a sink there and towels there.
That, I think, was the biggest experience difference for me.
It's like, it's no longer me having
to make a siphon and spilling beer all over the kitchen.
It was just beer into bottles.
I don't think we spilled at all.
A drop.
No, I was really proud of us.
It saved all of that beer for us to drink later.
And after slowly filling our bottles, which
we had we got these swing top style bottles,
we heard the most rewarding sound.
That right there is the end of our batch.
We nailed it perfectly.
Two kegs, we got 27 bottles, and we ended up
filling 26 because we drank a little bit of it.
More than a little.
Can you believe, though, we nailed it just right?
And we did not plan this at all.
That's pretty great.
I mean, you did the math, but let's be honest,
you're more like Python hacking.
So this is perfect.
We brought exactly what we can carry out,
and it's just the right amount.
Two kegs, 27 bottles later, or I guess 25 bottles.
So we had a margin for safety.
Now what we thought is we need to come up
with a label and stuff for it.
But now we've had a couple of days to try it out,
or let it sit.
It's been sitting in the bottles.
And I think Belgium does kind of,
you know, it benefits from sitting
in the bottles a little bit.
So you want to do your first honors?
Oh, yeah, let's try this.
So here, Wes, here, cheers to 400 more episodes.
And let's give it a try.
That tastes like delicious pride.
I mean, it's legitimately a very delicious beer.
It's something like 8.5% alcohol by volume,
but because of, I think, dialing up the carbonation,
you don't taste it that much.
No, but it's not too carbonated.
It's just easy to drink.
Not too carbonated at all, which was so great about it.
Because I was a little worried we might have overdone it,
but absolutely not.
I've done that in past beers.
So yeah, I was a little worried, too.
And it's not too strong.
It's not crazy malty.
It's just a nice, tasty, balanced beer.
I really, really like it.
Now we each have a keg, so that's great,
because we had two kegs.
And we have some bottles that we're
going to be sending out to friends of the show
and whatnot.
But I want to name this thing.
You know, for our 400th beer, because I
think we're going to do this again.
I thought we'd like to, each batch,
have its own unique name and addition.
So this is the 400th edition.
And the 400th edition needs a name.
So I've just opened up a straw poll.
If you're watching live, it's strawpoll.me
slash 42-89-57-61.
Strawpoll.me slash 42-89-57-61.
Go there and vote on what we should name the LUP 400 beer.
We have a couple of contenders already we've selected for you.
So you only have to pick from what we've already put there.
Number one, and these are kind of randomized, I think,
but on this list, the Unplugged Lugger.
Now it is not a lager.
That's why it's a lager.
Yep.
The Chug-a-Lug, the 400.
Oh, classy.
Yeah, sophisticated.
Or maybe it's a Cadillac.
I don't know.
And then the See Ya Next Tuesday, because of the 8.5%
alcohol by volume.
So if you would, go over there and vote.
And whatever the results are at the end of the recording,
we will officially name our beer and then try
to get some labels printed up.
We need your help.
So right now, the votes are open,
and we will come back and see where things lie.
Wes, this right here, what we're holding in our hand,
you know what this is?
This is a real physical product that we created.
We did it, buddy.
There's a lot of it, too.
Yeah, cheers again.
Yeah, we wanted to get enough that we
could send some to friends and stuff and do fancy bottles.
And then the kegs, of course, which we can refill.
And I could totally see us do this for the next Linux Fest.
Oh, absolutely.
Just a good supply of beer on hand.
So we'd have a Linux Fest Northwest batch
that would be kind of more of a Pacific Northwest early spring
beer.
Yeah.
So I thought what would be great is
if you want to have a virtual beer with us,
we should have something special to celebrate LUP 400.
It's a special occasion.
It's a beer-themed episode.
So go grab a special 400th edition beer stein
at luplug.beer.
Luplug.beer.
Go have a virtual beer with our lug and Wes and I,
and enjoy.
It's just something to celebrate 400.
It's not a challenge coin, not yet.
But it is a nice-looking beer stein.
Yeah, something that can join us all together as we share a glass.
Also, how great is that, luplug.beer?
I mean,.beer.
Can you believe that's a thing?
It's like the one good thing to come out
out of all these nonsense top-level domains.
It is definitely a great one.
Look at that.
Isn't that great?
So when is beer is tasty coming back, huh?
This was it.
This was it in spirit right here.
This was beer is tasty in spirit for sure.
So yeah, we did it.
And it turned out fantastic.
We're very happy with the results.
And I think we're going to keep doing it.
So we've been kind of collecting various used pieces of equipment
to help us do this.
Right, piecing together what we need.
And then we're going to have to try to mix in as much Linux as possible.
Yeah, I mean, Graham gave us some great tips for that.
And then I think, too, like the sensors and some
of the automating of the heat on and off and all of that
can probably be tied into Home Assistant.
Right.
So there'll be some fun Home Assistant action there, too.
Absolutely.
There's all kinds of things we can do.
And we probably will continue to play around with it.
I also want to thank our members.
Those of you who are part of our Unplugged Core,
you make this possible as well.
Thank you very much to our members at episode 400.
I'm going to have something special for you in the near term future.
So if you're not a member yet, you could always go to unpluggedcore.com
and become one, because there's going to be some special benefits for our members
in the near future.
And we appreciate all of you out there for joining us.
Wow, look at that.
41 people in the Unplugged is incredible.
Unplugged, you guys, thank you so much for showing up and being part of this.
When we started this 400 episodes ago, it seemed a little crazy
to just open up our virtual lug and let anybody chat.
And then over time, a community developed to help moderate it and do mic checks.
And then now, even we have the weekly Unplugged meeting
that happens every Sunday.
I mean, it's taken over.
It's the show that isn't the show, and it happens every Sunday
at noon Pacific in our Mumble Room.
You can find it on our calendar, though, to get it converted
in your local time at jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
And the info for our Mumble Room is at linuxunplugged.com slash mumble.
Mr. Payne, I think that's 400 right there.
We did it.
Can you believe it?
Dang it, I think that means we have to start planning episode 500.
Well, here we go.
Here's the episode of 500, and here's maybe even 400 more.
Thank you, everyone, who's been listening for even more than a couple of episodes.
I don't know how you put up with us, but man, are we more grateful than ever for it.
Thank you for listening.
It really is humbling, but the community is the best part of the show.
For reals.
All right, everyone, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode
of the Unplugged program, and we will see you next Tuesday.
Al Roker, see you next Tuesday.
Bart Kopper, see you next Tuesday.
Ben, see you next Tuesday.
I'm Bennett Mears, and I'll see you next Tuesday.
I'm Brent, see you next Tuesday.
I'm Mike Bitten, see you next Tuesday.
This is Carl, see you all next Tuesday.
Hey, it's Casey, see you next Tuesday.
Computer kids, see you next Tuesday.
This is Neil, see you next Tuesday.
This is Ben Two Hands, see you next Tuesday.
My name's G severo, and I will see you next Tuesday.
This is Ironic Badger, see you next Tuesday.
I'm Jero and see you next Tuesday.
I'm Limbo, and I'll see you next Tuesday.
Hey Minimac here, see you next Tuesday.
I'm Cheese Bacon, and I will see you next Tuesday.
I'm Parker G, see you next Tuesday.
I'm PhoenixLandPyro, see you next Tuesday.
I'm PyGresh, and I will see you next Tuesday.
I'm Eric Nance, and we'll see you next Tuesday.
I'm Simon, and I'll see you next Tuesday.
I'm not Orange, but I will be here on Tuesday.
I'm Thor, and I will see you next Tuesday.
I'm Three Boots, and I'll see you next Tuesday.
And I'm Bert Nuda, and I'll see you next Tuesday.
Thank you, everyone, thank you.
Let's go to JB Titles and let's name our 400th episode.
I thought before we wrapped up officially, though,
at the end of the show, I wanted to kind of capture
what we'd love to see by episode 500.
We'll create a 400 time capsule right here.
So Mumble Room, go ahead and tag me in the chat room
if you have anything to add to our time capsule,
starting with category number one,
our aspirations for Linux.
Now, it's off the top of your head,
but our aspirations for Linux by episode 500.
While you think, because I know I'm just throwing this at you,
I'll say a richer, thicker, more vital
third-party desktop app ecosystem.
Well, it's a nice thing to hope for.
What do you got?
You got anything?
Maybe hardware or something?
I would hope that Linux has continued to develop
on mobile devices independent of Android,
that whatever happens with Fuchsia,
there's still Linux on phones,
and that whatever we've got sort of nascent now,
it's just a lot better by episode 500.
Maybe, maybe I've got one in my pocket.
Casey, you have one?
Yeah, I think that we should be striving
to completely deprecate X11.
Ooh, yeah.
That is definitely one.
I was gonna mention it,
but I'm thinking 500 weeks from now, we better.
We really better.
One would hope.
Barker says better gaming, I agree.
Number two, number two for the time capsule.
Wes Payne, I'm gonna go with you first on this one.
Where is Flutter?
It's everywhere, it's everything.
I mean, we're gonna be doing the show
in an entirely Flutter-based environment.
Okay, I'll go the other way and say
that it really hasn't gone anywhere, I guess,
because that's the only other angle I can play on that.
Okay, but it's canonical, still using it.
I mean, how long is five, give me an idea.
500 weeks, that feels like a whole nother 50 years
of internet time, to be honest with you.
So I gotta say, no.
I mean, that's 10 years.
Yeah, I'm gonna say if they are, they're winding it down.
That's what I'm gonna say.
That's what I think.
We'll see, though, we will see.
What do you think, our podcast?
What would you put in the time capsule?
So I'm hoping that by the time we get further along
that we have great tools for media production already,
obviously OBS and all the podcasting tools
and PipeWire coming on, but just making it easier
for new users to get on board more quickly
and making Linux a first-class citizen
for streaming and media production.
Hear, hear, what can we develop on PipeWire now
that if PipeWire really does unify things, right?
I want easier audio routing.
Yeah, I mean, you're starting to see it, right?
Carla is annoying.
Well, you don't need Carla.
You don't need P-A-C-T-L.
You don't need QJack Cuddle or any of those things
because you now have this unified interface
in the form of PipeWire.
The standard stuff that desktops have now have
the opportunity to integrate those workflows.
Neil, let's say you, by episode 500,
will Proton be merged with Wine
or will they still be kind of these two separate projects?
There will not be a Proton project in 10 years
because everything will be integrated into Wine.
It may even, like, if I'm being super hopeful,
we will need it a lot less.
Yeah.
Pycrash, you want machines loaded with Linux.
Yes, I want to buy my next machine
and to be loaded with Linux from the factory.
Yeah, I know a place.
You're here.
I know a few.
Smooth cheese.
Smooth as Velveeta.
Okay, what do you guys think, Mumble Room?
You can kind of just jump in on this one.
Will JB have switched to Matrix
as their primary chat platform by episode 500?
Yeah.
Yes.
I hope so.
I just need JBot and it's done.
We're an IRC bridge, of course.
Everyone just says yes at the same time.
Yeah, IRC bridge.
We need a JBot rewrite.
These are the things that I think are holding us up.
I mean, we could probably bridge JBot to Matrix
using IRC and just keep the IRC around as legacy.
Yeah.
Yeah, the IRC bridge is fine.
It's just the thing is you'll have to get GeekShed
to agree to it.
Or move to FreeNode or something.
So what do you think the desktop pain points
are gonna be by episode 500?
So this is a while out.
What's still gonna be something that is a pain in the butt
to get working on Linux?
Okay, so there's some confusion going on here,
at least in the chat room.
Okay.
Are we talking about in 500 episodes?
No.
Or are we talking about at?
500. Okay, so that's only two years away.
Okay, oh yeah, right, right.
You're right.
Yeah, that's only two years.
You've been saying 500 weeks,
and I'm like, that's 10 years from now.
Well, you did that.
You gave me that.
I was so confused.
Dang it.
You said 500 weeks, and I'm like, that's 10 years.
Yeah, you're right.
Well, yeah, in total, it'll be 10 year run for the show
at our 10 year run.
So two years from now.
Desktop Linux, main pain points.
Adobe products on Linux.
Yeah, Adobe products on Linux
is gonna be the big pain point.
I think it's gonna be more likely
that Office comes to Linux
rather than Adobe coming to Linux.
By episode 500, I think there's gonna be Outlook for Linux.
That's what I think.
I think in two years, we'll have Outlook for Linux.
They're just gonna rebase everything
on like an Electron type thing.
Yeah, it's gonna be Electron.
It's already gonna move to Electron
irrespective of anything else.
So then they'll bring it to Linux too.
That's exactly the fear I have.
There'll be more and more Electron apps
that will be really CPU hungry and resource hungry,
so if you, it's flattened out, then we'll see.
I think Flutter will only be on Android.
I just want Python GTK for documentation
because I can already see how much better it is.
There's just no docs for it.
Right.
Cute though.
Look at that.
I'm like figuring it out on my own
and I can't really get anywhere.
I think it's fun to think about these things
in a two year time span and then a 10 year time span.
Like if you took, so that's also like,
what if you doubled the run of the show?
Then we're like, we can do a whole episode on this,
but we have a couple of good, we have our aspirations,
a guess where Flutter is, Proton gets merged into Wine,
JB is switched to Matrix,
which I think we could do in two years,
desktop pain points still include Adobe products
and multi-monitor.
Last but not least, is the LUP LUG
still self-organizing in two years?
Oh, it will.
And we've been still using Mumble.
The Mumble developer should somehow, some way,
be capitalizing all this clubhouse nonsense
because it totally validates Mumble.
And Mumble's a better way of doing it too.
We just need like a web interface
to drop into a Mumble room.
There is a Mumble web interface.
It's beta, but it is a thing.
You need a nice trendy iPhone app too, right?
And that Mumble doesn't have the same apps.
Ideally, some VC money, I think, right?
Yeah, and some of that VC cash.
All right, thank you Mumble room.
You're the best virtual lug.
Thanks for joining us for episode 400.
Wouldn't be 400 without you.