Bad news Wes. I know you were really looking forward to this as a space enthusiast
I know you're really looking forward to this, but Pepsi is dropping its plans to use an orbital billboard
Powered by Linux no more Pepsi in the sky
That was the plan the publication futurism reported on April 13th at Pepsi Co's Russian subsidiary
Was working with a startup there called star rocket to advertise an energy drink called adrenaline rush
Using satellites the whole idea is it goes up, and it makes like a billboard in the sky
So you just look up and there's this annoying advert in the sky filled with cola ads. What could be better?
Spokesperson though for Pepsi Co Russia said that the company had agreed to partner with star rocket on the campaign
They said orbital billboards are the revolution on the market of communications a revolution on the market
There is some confusion though because Pepsi Co in the u.s.. They did confirm that this happened
But they're basically saying this was a one-time exploratory event. We're not really we're not really doing it
Actually star rocket was founded only a year ago and has not deployed any satellites as yet
So some industry experts are a little skeptical like today
Do they actually have the expertise and even the funding to do it there?
They're working to get 25 million in a funding round, but haven't haven't got it yet
What do you think Wes gonna invest?
No cold 25 mil so the other part that's important here is actually in the US federal law prohibits what they call
obtrusive space
Advertising right although it's just a technicality like they can't approve the launch in the US at a federal level
But you could just launch it from say Russia and then park it over us guys sure good
Yeah, and so the the satellites involved in this tech we covered inside bite years ago, and they do actually run Linux
I mean, why else would you want to run it in space? I do not like the direction of this
We got to act fast. We got to be one of the first obviously
You know how big we are about advertising these days here on the podcast Jupiter broadcasting
I mean that that fits in space way better than an energy drink
This is Linux unplugged episode
298 for April 23rd
Well, hello there and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, mr.
Payne good to see you. It is the calm before the storm right now, man
I can't I'm having a hard time even conceptualizing the next couple of days
I know we got to do this show kind of quick today because if we're not careful Alan Jude's gonna show up in studio
He's gonna crash our so show with me flashing everything with free BSD. I know it's gonna just ruin it
So we got it
We got to hurry up because the crowd for Linux fest Northwest is assembling right now Alan Jude's one of the first in but then many
Many more and that is the crazy Linux fest Northwest just after this show pretty much people start arriving like during the show
That's crazy. This is our last moment of peace Wes
Haha, well before we go any further, let's bring in that mumble room time appropriate greetings virtual log. Hello guys
Hello, hello Brent. Hello code. Mr. Badger mini Mac the geek tweets this geek tweets and turf is in there and of course
Coming in on the studio line. We have cheese and L. Hello you two. Hey, hey
So glad to have everybody here today and our inner during our last moments of sanity
I thought let's let's ask about something. I think many of you forgotten about I sure have did you? Oh, yeah
The story is like all right, but it's totally slipped my radar. Okay cheese. I'm gonna put you on the spot right now
Can you tell me what the Atari VCS is?
Yes, it's
Linux based console damn to
Some classic games and I think they also
Don't they have a couple of the devs from some of the original Atari games working for them as well. Yeah
Yeah, I was hoping I was hoping to prove a point
I mean, I think a lot of people that had kind of forgotten about this story
And of course, I'm a backer not because I really think it's gonna be great
But just because I kind of wanted to see if they'd get there
I wanted to have a stake in the game to be honest with you
But it's not looking great. Like we don't have a lot of results. Yeah a little bit of a reality check
There's no prototype. There's no Ubuntu based operating system prototype
And there's not even a convincing demo of any of the games which will run on it
Yeah
The thing that kind of made news this week and Joey over at OMG Ubuntu caught it the estimated shipping date on their Indiegogo
Campaign page has been revised from July of 2019
Which is not too far away
To now December of 2019. Mmm a little bit further away just a bit
I mean you want the extra polish so that you can make a prototype, right? But that hardware is so pretty
I hope it ships just because I can buy one secondhand. Yeah, it would look nice on the shelf for sure
Yeah, I would I mean it would and that's why it's like if they get it, right
I'd really love to see Linux be used for something like that
So I had to throw in but we'll see well speaking of companies that have received their funding via crowdfunding and other mechanisms
purism
Kind of been wondering what is the state of the Liebman fives application stack? Oh, yeah, and how are they getting a lot of those applications?
We got a little peek behind the curtain this week when Christopher Davis blogged about a new contract
He's under to create a fractional scaling UI application for a matrix chat client. Is that right?
Yeah, it's his existing application that is pretty neat
and he writes over the past year or so I've been a regular contributor to fractal a
matrix chat client for gnome
My contributions have allowed me to take on a bigger role in the gnome community including maintainership of a few apps
I'm pleased to announce that over the next week. I'll be working to make fractals UI adaptive for the Liebman fives launch
There's a whole mix of terminology, which I'm kind of machine up here. So fractal is the applications name
which is a matrix chat client and
He is making it an adaptive UI
Which is something that these gnome apps are doing where you can rescale them down from a desktop application to a phone sized application
Much like the convergence apps were on you don't call it convergence. No, it's not it's it's adaptive
And it's really kind of a neat trick
He has videos embedded in his blog where it really is coming down pretty nice and it looks pretty sharp. Yeah, absolutely
He also writes he's just he's just really excited that purism accepted this and he's gonna get to work on it and someday
Hopefully soon actually run fractal on his phone and we might get you to so this is I think the real story and and I
Think this is actually one of the more positive things
I've seen about the Liebman fives development is they are paying the existing maintainer of this application
To make it compatible for their platform
Yeah
Really working with some of the existing community and people that they want to bring into the community and something tells me this is probably
Not the only case
Now if that's how they're gonna get some of these apps onto the phone, I got nothing wrong. I see nothing wrong with I got
no problem that is
That's great. That's taking some of the crowdfunding money and some of the money that they've they've earned from selling their laptops and
Redirecting that into the hands of current existing open source developers now
This Christopher Davis character is gonna be able to maintain the other applications, too
That aren't even related to this just because it's a viable thing for him now. Yeah, this is interesting
Well, it's early days of trying to build in this way and in other communities. We probably wouldn't get to see any of this
Yeah, it's nice to see a little peek behind the curtain
And I haven't seen purism make a big stink about it. They haven't been really clear that they're doing this
I think it's been implied, but I don't think they've been super clear. So it's neat to see this
Okay, so there's there's some interesting news now. Let's talk about something. That's a little kind of sad these things happen
It could result in a black hole ripping through our universe simply because
Now the large hydrogen collider is going to be running an unsupported version of Linux
I mean, there's a possible negative side to this but scientific Linux is
Coming to an end. There'll be security maintenance, I believe
67 right
But as a distribution they're wrapping up scientific Linux which for those of you that don't know is it's essentially like a cent OS
It's a it's a remix of upstream rail with the branding removed focused for the scientific community
Yeah, you know, I haven't I don't use scientific links really but from my read on this
It seemed like it kind of arose from a darker time early on maybe in the early
2000s where like before before redhead had bought
You know merged with sent us and all of that stuff and where like Linux wasn't quite as dominant even in the sciences
And so it was it was hard to assemble a distribution something that had all the right tools
And as anyone doing like machine learning type applications, some of those science frameworks are just ugly to compile and get going
So I think for a long time scientific Linux could fit in that niche and just provide a standard baseline
Especially if you're doing stuff like what Fermilab was doing high-energy physics
Possibly one nice way to view this story is just that you know software availability is better these days
So they can just run on the latest cent OS
I think that's what it is
And that is what they're going to do is they're just gonna migrate to sent us and I think it is exactly that the software
Availability is there now. They don't have to have a boutique specialized distro that requires maintenance flat pack install black hole beautiful
thing for real
No, I thought it was an app that'd be good
I'd be really good like just just large the whole large hydrogen collider tool set just one flat pack away
My point was that their tool sets and tool chains now are available. Yeah other ways. Yep
So hopefully some of the effort they've been just you know
It takes a lot to just maintain the distribution even when it's you know, based on open-source centos red hat packages
Hopefully that can just go into improving all the other applications people are using in science. I think so
You got to be easy on me Alex. I'm my mind is a blur from this whole Linux fest stuff
I was telling Brent earlier today. He's like Brent says how are you doing? And I said well
I don't really know anymore because I've entered the blur phase. I know this happens every year
There's a blur phase where it becomes such a storm of things that are happening concurrently
You can't hold them all in your head
No
just sort of cascade in there they're in there for a minute and then they run away and something else replaces I actually kind of
I kind of collapse a little bit and I like I become less confident. I become less capable
I can do less things like I can only do one or two things and
I really really lose sense of how we're doing but going into the blur zone before it really hit
I knew we were positioned pretty well like we we've been planning for a while. This is the most organized we've ever been
Yeah, right. So I feel felt feel like we were pretty good. But now I've I've lost all perspective
I think that the it is it's very true by far the most organized we've ever been but the flip side of that is we're
Also doing the most we've ever done. Yeah, like way more than the most we've ever done. We've got a booth
We've got a we've got a dedicated room where people are giving talks both days. We've got tons of new swag
We've got the new logo rollouts. We've got the largest crew we've ever had there
We got people we got multiple people flying in from out of country
Which is coordinating several different flights and runs to the airport. It's a hell of a thing. It's a hell of a thing
Cheese and L are gonna be here pretty soon. Oh, that's exciting. It is exciting
I'm looking forward to all that new swag that cheese has been working on. Mmm. Yeah. Oh, yeah
Yeah, the shirts just arrived the shirts just arrived. Nice. So I just had to bring them all
Did you see them stacked outside the studio boxes? Yeah, I'm glad they weren't dropped on us by a drone
Yeah, they were like 30 pounds each I think
I was looking at the tracking. L, what day do you get in? I get in tomorrow. Oh, wow. Is it bad you didn't know?
No, I'm just losing track of everything. I just everybody gets in a different day. So I just asked repeatedly. It's my approach
Need little nametags. Yeah, my name is L and I get on on Wednesday
I wonder if she'll I wonder if Alan will be so Alan's gonna be in studio tomorrow recording BSD now
That should be interesting L shows up and we're doing BSD now
Well, let's update everybody on the Debian project leader election. Remember we first covered like nobody really stepped up
Well that problem was solved
And now we have ourselves a new winner and it looks like
Well, it looks like if if any kind of process to get like this is gonna be run by geeks. They have charts
They have flow diagram like a directed graph of explaining how this all works
Statistics and formulas everywhere. Yeah. Yeah, it's pretty it's pretty impressive
So our our new Debian is it DPL the Debian project leader is
Done. Hold on here. Hold on now. Come on now. We got to do this, right? You ready Wes?
Ladies and gentlemen, the new leader of the Debian project is
Sam Hartman
Congratulations him. It's kind of anticlimactic there, isn't it?
There you go. There you go. Give them that and a little applause
Welcome Sam Sam joined Debian back in 2000 and has been around for a long time
He says when I'm not working on Debian or my day job
I'm writing reading or learning to sale or just trying to live life to its fullest over the past year
I've been learning how to DJ that ended up starting with my writing of my own DJ software because
What's out there is too visual for a blind DJ to use easily?
Interesting. It's not packaged for Debian yet because I need to get one patch upstream and write enough
Documentation that someone would have a chance to actually use it
Like that you can tell he's um intimately familiar with getting things going and packaged in Debian
He also writes that one of my key goals as Debian project lead
We'll be to make sure Debian is a community where we can be heard and where we have the opportunity to reach
Understanding regardless of whether our ideas are chosen
I will do this by personally participating in such mediation and recruiting others to these mediation efforts
Eventually, I hope many of us will get better at seeking to understand and avoiding escalating discussions on our own
You know on that same vein he's writing here
Which I thought was interesting because well, there's been a bit of the hubbub about it and we covered it
Mm-hmm. We've lost a number of developers because they were frustrated with our tools and processes
One of the common complaints I've heard is that the wide variety of Debian workflows
Just gets in the way when you want to contribute to a large number of packages
I know that for myself and I find that our processes make it difficult enough for me to go fix an RC bug in a
Package that I don't maintain that I'm just less likely to do so. Yeah
Yeah, I'm glad he's all I'm glad he's aware of the situation there
Yeah
I mean it seems like he's got a decent read here on on what the Debian community has been talking about and that's a good
Thing for a new lead and and part of his platform post here
He wraps it up with I hope to find ways to reduce the stigma associated with bringing important issues to a wider audience
I think it will always be the case that overriding a specific decision will come with a high price
however
Often when we do face a controversial decision
We realize that there are broader policy questions that could be answered that would inform future decisions
Once we get some distance from the original decision. I think answering these policy questions can be valuable
Sometimes it will be useful to answer policy questions in a form broader than a group making the original decision
Broadening the form like this should not be seen as a lack of trust in any of our teams or decision makers instead
It is working together in a broad community. I like those words
Yeah
I think this is a good reminder to and perhaps why no one initially volunteered that first round in some ways
This is something about thankless business position, right?
I mean, it's a large complicated open source project a lot of people with opinions and here you are trying to herd them all together
I think it's gonna be a little different though than it has in the past because classically when you ask
Well, what does the Debian project leader do a lot of times? Oh, he travels around goes to conferences represents the project
But he writes here in his platform. He's not gonna do as much of that
He might try to outsource some of that to the community and he's gonna be participating directly in conversations
I'm curious to see where Sam takes this or mr
Harmon takes this the new Debian project leader
So welcome and we have links in the show notes to more information about the vote anything in the data
You thought was worth calling out. No, not really just that I like it
I think it's all pretty well presented and interesting and I kind of want to spend more time digging into just how it all
Works, you know, I have thought about doing like a week on Debian
I'm wondering I'm wondering might keep an eye on things
Might might consider that idea right now. I'm right now. I'm uh, I've got a new thing. I'm into
Oh, it's ridiculous. I can't help myself. I feel like I'm slipping into old habits with distro hopping again
I don't know what happened to me. I thought I'd finally fix this issue and yet here I am
We'll talk about that in a moment. But first
How about a little housekeeping? Oh, yeah, there's so many things to talk about so we're gonna go them go through them in
a bit of a chronological order
First off being this Friday this Friday on the live stream
We'll have a very special Friday stream because we'll have a bunch of folks in studio
It'll be in here fighting for mic time hanging out with us and chatting on the live stream. I
Something special we're doing for a little while
May or may not stick around after Linux fest. So come join us
Friday 2 p.m. Pacific you can get that converted to Jupiter broadcasting.com slash calendar if you like this show
Well the people from this show them and a bunch of the other crew get together and just hang out and chat
But in a flavor all its own. I mean, it's Friday. May I ask where this will be jblive.tv, of course
No, physically, I mean, I'm gonna be in Seattle on Friday. So it'll be at the studio. Yeah, come to the studio on Friday
Oh, yeah. Yeah, that'd be awesome. Yes slip in get on the stream a little bit
This should be a hell of a stream. It'll be quite the mic rotation important question
Will there be any smoked meats smoking those meats? Well, we may have to we may have at this point. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, we should probably Mike makes you hungry. There's gonna be a house full man
It's gonna be a house full of people
Yeah, it is it is Friday is gonna be crazy because then after that we head up to Linux fest
Which is part two of the housekeeping so Linux fest Northwest is finally here
It is this weekend if you're coming to our barbecue. We have over a hundred people now on the meetup what?
You might want to bring a chair if you're local. We're gonna bring some chairs. I should remember to do that
I'm local Emma and crew from system 76 are bringing us bringing some too and they're bringing a ton of meat
We're gonna we're gonna be feeding a lot of people cooking outside the lady jupes
that'll be
Saturday after Linux fest Northwest and if you are looking to carpool or whatnot up from ctac
Jupiter broadcasting comm slash Linux fest as our telegram group
You can go there and coordinate with peeps or if you just want to know what's going on
What's the fest has started? That's where we'll be chatting with people
So go check that out then
After that, it's Red Hat summit May 7th through the 9th in Boston cheese
Wes and myself are going to Red Hat summit. So if you're in the Boston area, you're going to that summit
Let us know tweet us come hang out. Oh, yeah, it'll be fun. I should be really good
We'll just be there for a few days in and out getting all the Red Hat we can handle
Yeah, we're gonna get the low down get the scoop all that kind of stuff
So check out Red Hat summit if you're going we'd love to see you there
But if you're not going to have summit, maybe just maybe you're going to Docker con
Like Wes and L. Look at you. That's just out. I was like Wes is coming. Oh
Kubica's what Wes is going to that's right. Okay. Oh, right, right. This one is in California, isn't it? Oh, San Francisco
There you go. So go say hi to L. If you're going to Docker con in San Francisco
You get maybe she might maybe have some swag. Oh
It's in route. I'll make sure to steal some if I don't bring it down. Yeah
Yeah, we'll send you with some swag either way, but we may have very special swag for doctor extra special
Yeah, hopefully go find out. Yeah, hopefully we'll see we'll see depends if the delivery gods
If they cooperate with us and then last but not least
Huge deal going on right now for Linux Academy. Go to Linux Academy comm slash join to sign up for a
Yearly promo that's 33% off. It's a great deal
You can see how learn by doing makes a huge difference at Linux Academy because it's it's more than just videos
It's more than just guides. There's little hands-on labs and for right now, that's a fantastic deal
It's going just for five more days seven hours. Check it out Linux Academy comm slash join for the
33% off deal. That's a heck of a deal there West. That's a heck of a deal
All right that I believe that's all the housekeeping. Yeah, that's it. Let's do it
All right that way by the way that track there that we're laying down Joe Rez original no way really
Yeah, I was really enjoying it. If he doesn't want people to know that you can cut that out
It's all on you Joe
All right. So I got a confession to make
I've been a real jackass. I I
This year has been a rough one for me
I've had a lot of I've had a lot of eat my hat moments on the show this year
And this is just another one of them, but I got to be honest. I got to come clean
Man I fucking love XFCE I
Love it
Love it. I am I I love it so much
Have you ever experienced something where you're so happy and excited about it?
Like when you go to bed like your mind is just racing you're so excited like you're just thinking about all the possibilities
That was me with like a hard high school crush on XFCE right now straight up straight up XFCE
Are you kidding me?
I'm not kidding and I I have been the biggest naysayer because I have this whole been there done that mentality with
with XFCE and the whole like Windows 2000 kind of desktop paradigm and you moved on you were in the new world of the
Linux desktop. Yeah, and
You know XFC was for Luddites and guys like Joe Joe is listening to this, you know
Oh, he already knows he already knows
You know
I really started it really started when I went back to gnome shell on 1904 and the performance was a lot better
But I was still having issues with my two vertical ASUS 27 inch monitors and my built-in laptop screen
I was trying to find a window windowing environment a desktop environment that
Would work properly with my screens and plasma got pretty close, but it had issues sometimes
Gnome could get one screen but not both screens working and I came across XFCE just in you know
Cuz Joe kept you know, just in the back of my mind, you know kept telling me try it. Try it. Try it. Try it and
I decided to give it a go
It was like getting a brand new computer where it was like taking your own machine that you've had for a long time taking out
a spinning rest drive and putting like an MV and MV and Ian and MV me in and
Or an SSD and and then in doing a fresh install on that SSD and just getting incredible performance
Literally felt like that
And what I did is I I've I've taken I started with taking a couple of my 1804 installs that are running
Kubuntu
And plasma desktop, right? You just switch those over and just install those into desktop meta package
So it was the same install and yet I noticed
significant application load time differences
Windows would move around the screen faster the whole like using the Firefox and Chrome felt
Significantly faster and I'm not alone Jason Evangelo from choose Linux the writer over at Forbes
He's he just please he just posted an article on the 17th. He and I same trajectory recently
Completely completely just connected the common. There is a common factor. Yeah, and
Jason writes. I can't believe I'm writing this Linux article about loving the XFCE desktop environment
And he writes in here every time I looked at screenshots of the XFCE
Even from the official website. It reminded me of something from the days of Windows 2000 gray and blue
Uninteresting which I agree like the project does not put their best foot forward
You know, if you just install the stock stuff, it's pretty dated. It does it does
He says he says when he uses XFCE and drags windows across the screen
It feels like you're using a monitor with AMD FreeSync like it feels like you're using a hundred and twenty Hertz monitor
I
Have I have like grabbed a tab off of Chrome and gone to take it to my third monitor and I have the tab is ripped
Off and moved across the screen so fast that I thought I must have missed grabbed and just grabbed the title bar of the entire
Browser it moved it is it is
Voraciously fast. It is addictingly fast. It is a
Different computer now and so I thought okay
well if this if this is what it feels like when I load sort of a and a good implementation but not with the
Lot of the the youtubers consider peak XFCE if you look around on YouTube
Everybody says it's man jero
You got to use man jero XFCE edition. If you look at Linus link tech tips there in their recent video
They're using man jero for their virtualized Mac machine when you look at the latest video from Wendell
He's talking about Linux gaming man jero
Everybody it's man jero and pop OS right now is what everybody loves in the gaming space and I thought okay
Well, let's give since I since I'm not interested in gnome shell pop OS is fine, but I'm not interested in gnome show
Let's give man jero a kill
so I downloaded man jero XFCE edition and it was
Exactly what I expected in that the installer was a bit of a hot mess crashed on me once really see I was gonna say
I was really impressed with the installer and had a great time not bad. It couldn't partition my disk
So I did love the partitioner and I loved because I was installing it in a weird West way
Uh-huh that let me just easily skip installing a bootloader at all
I thought it was a dream one of the best Linux installation experiences
I've had in a while
So I didn't mind the look of the installer or the functionality of the installer
but I had two issues number one is
I think this is and maybe remember one cause number two when I was doing the disk partitioning
I decided you know what? I want to hibernate
I'm gonna go ahead and have a swap file when I chose swap file the installer crashed just completely dumped out on me
and then after that it couldn't partition the disk and I think because maybe the partition table was thus in use by the
Kernel at that point and so I had to use the command-line installer to go wipe out the partitions
Reboot and then I could use the installer and after that point it was fine
but you're right it is otherwise a good set of features and
Once it loads up the XFCE desktop is nice
It's got a bar at the bottom really good set of the themes nice launcher. Everything's really clean
Yeah, I don't think it's be the style
I would I would settle on or keep for my own personal aesthetic choice, but it felt very consistent even just from the start
They say it's a lightweight desktop
And it is it is remarkably lightweight. And here's what here's what I realized it isn't I ended up
enjoying my stay with mangero, but I just went back to
my
1804 installs with this Ubuntu desktop because
XFCE is XFCE and it's in a way because it's not like gnome shell where
Fedora has a slightly different implementation than Ubuntu does and they have slightly different patch set all these vendor patch sets
But it's very current right and it's like you got to get the latest version of
Fedora or listen to Linux podcast to find out that there's these new changes you might be missing right
But if you get 1804 or 1904 or you get mangero or you use straight arch or whatever
You're kind of just getting the same XFCE that's available for all of them
And what's what I think makes XFCE a better desktop environment for me possibly than plasma
Although plasma still has been great. I'm curious about this because I mean we're running here. It's been fun. It's powerful
Yeah, what I think I prefer about XFCE is they're trying to solve a smaller problem domain
There's they're not trying to make this entire comprehensive
Platform they are making a desktop environment
That is a minimal implementation and the end result is less things break things are faster cleaner
Simpler and more straightforward for the user and I can I can I can conceptualize how the XFCE desktop is put together
I can't really fully wrap my head around though
I spent I'm sure if I spent more time, but I don't really fully understand all of the components the way the KIO slaves
Were whatever if they're even there anymore like I don't know how any of that works really in plasma
but with XFCE I can clearly conceptualize how this works and
I still get to ride the wave of modern GTK apps that are sort of the peak
I think of UI design and features that are shipping for gnome shell and
They still look great at home on my XFCE desktop
Have you not found any compromises because knowing you I mean you also spend some time on other platforms
Let's say that that are known to look nice and be visually polished
And I think you're hitting on something with with plasma and gnome. They're like our there are flagships, right?
There aren't there are philosophies that we're projecting about how Linux can do desktops
I mean there are many of them, but they are the prominent one, right?
And because of that they've you know, they've tried to make themselves look nice. Do you yes
I like I get that you want things to be snappy
But how many times you're really opening an app, you know, like I start my computer
I launch Chrome and a few electron apps. That's it. I don't think about it
so the electron apps I noticed the least difference, but I
Feel consistently like all of the native applications like Chrome and Firefox and the terminal and the file manager. Holy crap the file manager are
Consistently faster like them somehow I the menus open faster the web pages render faster the applications
Launch faster they show up on screen faster. I don't know why maybe maybe because they're not going through some sort of 3d rendering pipeline
I don't know what it is in the way
but so the the the end result is the consistent use of the desktop even once things are loaded still feels faster and
More memories left over for my other things that I want to do. So there's those things but I have had to make
modifications to make the sucker work for me
Number one thing I had to do is I went and got you launcher
Which I think is a very good launcher. If you guys are looking for a nice desktop launcher, check out you launcher
By default control space just brings up a little prompt and you can you can type in
Terminal commands directories or just the name of applications hit enter and they launch. It's got some nice auto film reminds me a lot of spotlight
Yes, or Alfred. Yeah, Alfred or gnome do it's a more modern version of gnome do those things quick silver is another one
I was a little disappointed just running it on plasma and I kind of still like the built-in plasma launcher more
I did a better job of finding the right things that I wanted krunner is better in plasma
but but you launchers nice. Yeah, you launchers great on XFC super quick and
Really easy to get installed. So I once I got a launcher
I like the whisker menu, but I needed a quicker launcher that just was a keystroke away
I had to make that fix
Another way to make XFC II a little more pleasing to me visually was I installed the arc theme and I use the art
I think it just looks great. It just it I I should have brought it down here for you
It looks just I think it looks just as good as the dome shell Wow
I mean it and I've got a nice transparent panel launcher that I think looks really good
I've got all the applets that I want right there in the thing. It's
It's just like yes, I was like I do really like some of the XFCE suite of applications
Do you like you mentioned like thunder? Great. Yeah, great XFCE terminal mouse pads good. Yeah
So I installed the arc dark theme and then I installed the system 76 pop icons. So I'm using pop icons
Which give it a modern?
Trendy look would you say they make it pop? They can make it pop
So and there's you know system 76 makes the pop theme available for free up on their github
So you can just go grab it. So I got that and then then it was sort of like the edge case stuff
And I think maybe this is because I didn't install
Like zubuntu from the ISO. I just did the zubuntu meta package
Yeah, so it's still technically a kaboom to install too. So I got plasma on there still so I could always bail
But what I'm wondering is maybe I didn't get like my notification stuff set up right for the XFCE desktop
I started having this issue where slack would lock up and
And then I just essentially would get bored and kill the process and relaunch slack and the respond to the message
Yeah, then a few more a few minutes later would lock up again
And I'm like looking around trying to figure out what's going on
I did have my machine rendering on a massive project which I'll talk about here in a minute
But I thought maybe that was the cause of it. Maybe I was just running out of resources, right?
I got a ton of RAM. I got a ton of disk. That's not it
Now my desktop doesn't use any memory. So it wasn't that and
It just kept happening for a day. And so this morning I'm looking around I'm looking around. I'm like, you know what it is
It's every time I get a message and a notification
Comes up would come up my application freezes
When I discovered is there wasn't a notification demon running in the background of my XFCE desktop
That was taking these notifications from applications and for whatever reason electron apps just respond by locking up because you know garbage
So I installed dunst d-u-n-s-t. It's a lightweight
Notification Damon which works with most desktop environments. It's very customizable. It's not dependent on any particular tool kit
It takes very little memory and it just now receives
I think it's a debus client or something receives those messages and displays them and now my slack client doesn't lock up
So I saw that problem and it makes me think you're already learning about some of the pieces of the modern death
Yeah, which is good, but I'm curious too. I think we experienced this yesterday troubleshooting a totally different Linux related thing
The flip side of that is it kind of just didn't work right like you had to dive in in plasma
Probably wouldn't been a problem. Yeah. Yeah, I wouldn't I've never had that issue
And I'm you know if I'd be surprised if I run into more things like that. It's possible
I suppose yeah
I guess that is that's the point right is is how many one or two for an experienced Linux user who wants a
Optimized desktop not a big deal. I'm also I'm
Unfortunately
Not getting a perfect hit rate on my monitor still so all the monitors light up, which is great
but
Sometimes it like reverses the primary and like it makes
They like I have two verticals and now what I've done is I have two vertical 27s the Asus 27 monitors
Which are 2k monitors?
They're just I think one of the best desktop monitors for Linux because it's that sweet spot of a nice wide
High resolution screen, but it's not high DPI. Okay, right?
Yep, and then I so then I bought a third one and I put that right smack dab in the middle
So now I've got three 27 inch Asus monitors to a vertical. It's great. It's really great
But sometimes it moves my desktop around to like the vertical screen and so everything sideways
And so I don't know if it's the order in which I have them plugged into the video card to the display ports or what?
So anybody in the audience has had that issue where you you wake your XFCE desktop up from sleep and all of the monitors
Have rejumbled themselves like back in the day
I would just go like write a custom XOR config and I think that would solve it
But now I don't even have an XOR file. So I
Had that I had some daisy chain displays for all it also had three screens
Mine was the reverse right to regular and then one rotated and I was always using a R&R. Okay. Yeah
And I'll just generate you some X render sort of commands save a little script. You can make it launch that start
So sometimes it would you know, just have that as I log in it just sets it. Yeah, that's a great idea
Yeah, great great tip Wes. I use it all the time a decent workaround at least
Okay, you throw a link to that in the show notes, you know the cheese
You're also a man Jaro user and you run an XFCE, right? Yep, and on a lot of other distros
Actually, I've had to use the X R&R
For it's a Dell and spirit on I think it's like a 3000 series a little 11.6 inch two-in-one
But yeah, because the screen would be rotated because it's a touchscreen as well
So the screen would be rotated on a lot of distros out of the box
Ah, so but no, I mean man Jaro dude out of the box X XFC has worked no problems
You know if I flip if I flip it into tablet mode keyboard, you know is disconnected
Everything works fine there. So I haven't had any problems with it. Obviously not the best
touch interface, but
You could get some work done with it for sure
What do you think about those tools that manager makes available like the the tool to install different drivers?
Like it's easy to switch between Intel drivers Nvidia drivers or bumblebee. Like have you played around some of that stuff?
Yeah a little bit. I've also played with
Just messing around with Steam because it comes right all out of the box
And so if you're doing that and you're you know working with a little machine like this with integrated graphics
I mean it works flawlessly man. I was able to jump on and pull down
I think it was faster than light and play a little bit of that
No problem was impressed with how different it had been ages since I'd used manager because mostly I just you know
Regular arch gap and how different it feels from regular arch. Yes feels almost like a real stable
It's on this row and the weird part of us just having 1904 out
That that was a newer kernel than what I got when I installed one jar. So it's just like a what's happening here?
Yeah, that is impressive how different it feels, you know, the ISO has all the stuff
It just dumps it right on the disk and it's still like it's still doing those sort of like gray zone thing like you can just
Choose the non-free driver right there at boot and just start right out of the box with the non-free stuff
No problem have at it Haas. They are clearly thinking about you know, it's a it's a cohesive experience
And it's the distro of choice in all of these new
Linux gaming videos from Linus tech tips and
What's the other one Wendell? Yeah them and pop OS
It's like these these two distros are standing out in the gaming community
Solace almost had that really it was for a hot minute
But they it kind of proved it out and then you know, these other ones came along and executed it
Yeah, well, and I'll agree with Wes in that it
Definitely feels it feels more stable
of an arch just based distribution
I don't know
I mean, I've had no problems with any updates breaking anything having to go back and tinker with anything just out of the box
Everything's worked
And and you know, I get the latest and greatest for the most part
to you know, which which isn't really a big deal as far as graphics drivers go for this machine with integrated graphics, but
For for those desktop rigs out there running it. I think they'd find benefit
At just the pace at which it's updated. I will say it was really nice to be an arch again for a bit
I still on the ThinkPad. I left it on
I think I'm gonna run it on the ThinkPad for a while. I just haven't Pac-man right at your fingertips
So fast good. It's so good. It's so good all my other rigs
I'm gonna keep on Ubuntu 1804 and just put Zubuntu desktop packages on them because it's
They're all working fine. Like 1804 is proving out to me to be a really good solid super solid LTS
Mm-hmm, like getting it's getting that machine up there reset up on Zubuntu and going to get some of these things
You know, it's the software is everybody makes a package for it
Everybody there's a package always available and especially when you're on the 1804 LTS
Yeah, it's a PPA or even just an in GitHub right like the build depths. Well, they're the Debian packages
So that 1804 build is is really quite appealing
I've just switched my main server from Debian over to Ubuntu 1804
Simply because it has ZFS compiled in hmm
It's it's better than that DKMS stuff and I'm having a the gnome UI
I can just remote in and use is it's actually kind of nice sometimes
Yeah, so guys aren't ever supposed to admit that though
Yeah, don't worry nobody will hear you
You know
So now that now that Joe has gotten me and now that Joe has gotten Jason
The next target on his list is gonna be L. Oh, you know it. Yeah. Oh, what's your current Linux desktop setup?
I was sitting here thinking that exact same thing
I'm like, I'm gonna blame Joe for this, but I'm running pop OS right now, and I don't want to leave
Oh, that's right. In fact, you have the successful upgrade to 1904 last week. Yeah, everything went so smooth
I haven't had an issue with anything including all of the tools that we use like everything has just worked
Mmm, that is a heart. Well, then I'd say stick with it. I I'd say stick with it
If I was gonna I think right now I would like to try out if a gnome shell if I was gonna try out a gnome
Shell implementation. I think it would probably be pop now. That'd be my next hop. I'd recommend it
I give you three months though before Joe wins you over he got to me eventually. You'll get bored of stability, too
Who wants that I hate to say it but I think he's right
The way you talk about XFCE it sounds almost like a window manager without a desktop environment
But that could be the next logical step. It really does get out of the way. So it's once it's up and going
What's great about it is like Thunar for example is it's everything I love about Nautilus
But faster and for me in my personal experience, it's network browsing works better
So I was like just randomly decided, you know, I need to go back to my old laptop
It's like just randomly decided, you know, I need to grab a file off of the computer down in the studio
Go to the network section boom easy all listed right there. Would you want to SFTP in?
Do you want a Samba in do you what do you want? Have at it? It also doesn't change its UI much nice CP though
No, no, definitely not
Don't get me going on that. Don't get me going people miss the reference. Go listen to Linux action news
Episode 102. I think I was judging a book by its cover for a really long time now. Keep in mind
I had been an XFCE user for many years back in the past because it was great for Linux terminals over project
But I kind of looked at it from that same vantage point from many years ago
I think the math in my head was the project moves slow the screenshots look like ass
Ergo, I mean, I know I've been there done that. I don't need to revisit, you know, but I was wrong
I just think it's a matter of time Chris before you're back home
with name
Do you ever try out some of the the i3s and the sways and the the window managers that don't have a full
Desktop environment and that might be where I go next I suppose
Because I've been doing kind of the same thing with that for a long time
The only reason why I really haven't made that like a jump to like a week in i3 is
I have been using a window desktop environment since the 80s. I've used different
Graphical desktop environments that had multiple windows. And so I I grew up
Like I instinctively when I sit down at a computer I arrange my windows in a stack
I enjoy it and I mentally lay them out very visually the way I the way I the way I'm working and so
For me being able to do that is is an efficiency booster and I feel like I would lose that if I went to something
That arranged my windows for me, but I'd be willing to give it a go for a little while
I tried out i3 for about two weeks six months ago and
it required quite an investment of having a cheat sheet open next to me the whole time and
it's an investment to learn all those commands and stuff, but
It's fast, you know
Like XFC's fastness
i3 is probably up there with it and you might find that you once you've adopted the paradigm and depending it might not be
I three might be a you know, a different tiling window manager that it gives you that control
More so than other desktop because you know, they they acknowledge that people are picky about where their windows go
It's for people who like to mess with computers
Very nice, sir. And there are also static window managers that give you even more control. Okay. All right. All right
I mean you guys you guys gotta let me hang out for a little bit. I could give me whiplash
I'm moving around so much. I I think
what what something about it is touching a
Like a
what what I felt like I unlocked was this sense of relief that I'm gonna be able to just use my computer to work now and
That was so exciting to me like this, I'm not gonna have to screw with this now
I'm just gonna use my computer to work and the fact that XFC you move so slow to me is
Is kind of a nice thing because now I've got kind of a moving fluid base with frequently updated apps
And then a desktop environment that takes quite a few years to really progress in any way
That's gonna alter the way I work. So devil's advocate moment
I've heard you make this pitch
Numerous times over the years
What happened to the iPad Pro or is this just augmenting it? I feel like the iPad pros role is more like communications
I really am NOT crazy satisfied with
Mail applications on Linux because we at Linux Academy use the Google Mail Suite the Google App Suite
And I'm not a big fan of using Thunderbird or Kmail or mail spring for any of that kind of stuff
I've tried them all and so what I'm doing right now is I pretty much do
The majority of like the zoom calls and
Slack meetings and emails on the iPad and the reason why is because I batch those things at certain times of the day when I'm
Not on air anyways
And then I use the desktop for like real work. That is like my more productive work
I do have some of those applications like I have zoom installed on the desktop and I have slack installed on the desktop
But that's like supplemental so that way if I need to open up a link or something on the desktop. I've got it
And the mail is really the weakest spot in my opinion
Because when you have the Google app integration you you really want something that works tightly with calendar invites and can look people up
in the directory and
It works well with doc links and stuff like that
And that's where a lot of the desktop Linux application applications fall down
And so I've either used wave box, which is an application that lets you have a bunch of different cloud accounts in one app
Wimpy's talked about that before or I will use nata fire and I'll just natify Google Calendar and
Google Mail
For Linux Academy, and then I just have those as essentially desktop applications
And it works, you know
And the nice thing is both those apps work really well in a vertical layout so I can put them on
My vertical monitor and then pretty easily see all the information. I need when you're talking about XFC
I would also say that
One of the good things about it is that it like you said earlier it gets out of your way
so whenever you do want to add these other bits and pieces from the Linux ecosystem like a
new launcher a new dock
All the all of it seems to play nice together. Like you never really have an issue where just
the theming is extremely broken on this one thing or
That something won't play nice with XFC and that's I'd say that's one of the best advantages of using XFC
Yeah, and to that point I was able to load up quake and I'm able to use the tilde key
Which is my preferred key to to summon the quake terminal
because nothing else is using that on XFC and control space is available for you launcher because
Nothing else is using that on XFC because there's a again
I think this is what's key about it is they're trying to solve a more limited set of problems
it's a it's a smaller problem domain that XFC is trying to solve and
And therefore what they've limited themselves to they can do really well. It's just simple and consistent. Yeah
It's nice and it's exactly what I want
and I think I'm gonna hang out here for a while and watch where gnome goes because there's the the development rate on gnome is just
It's incredibly impressive and see where plasma shell goes because I think it's got some of the best technology out there in a desktop
Honestly, you do seem a little refreshed though because I mean we have to talk about those things
It's part of what we do here on the show in the network, right?
But you you're off you're off the hype train you get to like just take a little break. You're not on the roller coaster
You're watching it. I'm an observer of the two desktop environments now remove myself
Like if they don't do something right or you know, we had this problem the other day here in the studio
It's not a big deal
But we had this problem the other day where for whatever reason plasma shell was using like 700 megs of RAM when you combine like
All the different components. It was nearly a gig of RAM and we've got a rig here. That's got 64 gigs of RAM in it
64 gigs of RAM and we had to reboot our OBS machine before Coder radio because
100% of the RAM had been used up with the machine just sitting here
That was less than ideal 64 gigs 100% used up
So we had to reboot and you know, we can we can see like actually we're starting to have an issue, too
We've already had 59 X runs. I bet you if I were to look at the memory usage
It's starting to creep up right now. It's not too bad. It's not too bad
Let's see
You know, okay, we're using four gigs right now. That's not too bad. It's a little much but it's not bad and
I guess I'm I'm I'm discovering as we've as we've learned really really how to work with the Linux audio stack
As we've really learned like there's a couple of things that are a little odd about it that we have to compensate for
some applications still use also and
Then the also software will talk to the sound card and the stuff that's using pulse audio will be completely unaware of the changes
the sound card is made say say you go from 48 Hertz to 44 Hertz or from 44 to 48 if you don't tell the
Pulse applications that you've made that change
They sound like Barry White or like a chipmunk depending on which direction it's gone
And then we do too and we have no way of knowing because we haven't changed anything
It's just there's two different audio stacks and one of them has talked to the card and hasn't told the other stack because they're completely unaware
Interpreting the same data stream differently and that just happens and it happens to us frequently
It was happening to us very often. It was a ritual we'd go through on the live stream
and there's other strange things like when the system boots up it enumerates the sound cards and
It assigns them sort of at the order that they were enumerated to the operating system by the motherboard
Not by like a physical ID of the card
So for some strange reason
The motherboard which can happen were to enumerate the sound card devices in a different order
Maybe they're USB devices that boot up in a different order for some reason one day or that whatever even if they're PCI devices
they will get different IDs in the also level in the pulse audio level because it then inherits what also set and
So you can actually have sound cards that are your in-and-out sound cards on a machine change
day to day when you reboot the system because they will get different IDs in the system because they assign ID at the time the
Motherboard enumerates them instead of like reading a device ID and saying okay, this is sound card one
This is sound card two and it'll always shall be
Doesn't do that. It just takes whatever the motherboard gives it. Okay, it's a sign now. Let's go
Good to go and these are crazy weird things that when you add an additional
Complicated desktop environment on top of it like plasma that also has its own audio stack phonon
Which is then sitting on top of pulse which is then sitting on top of also which is then sitting on top of the driver
stack which is then sitting on top of the hardware and
And so with something like XFCE you essentially remove one of those layers
You just have a simpler setup and I mean
I think it's kind of just a turning the question on its head right it some people you might need a fuller richer desktop
I think some of this exploration is just deciding like do I need those features and are they worth worth the cost because eventually if they
Aren't working you're gonna have to debug them. There you go
So I only have one last issue that I haven't solved yet that I would love to get the audience's help with
It's a real it's a real humdinger speaking audio
Everything plays audio just fine except for Firefox. I've got no audio in Firefox
Don't know what it is. It's the strangest thing if VLC Chrome
MPV audio is just fine. It's just in your zip on to install. Yeah coupon to turn
Yeah, thanks. Otherwise working great, but no audio which in some respects is actually nice. Yeah, that's your silent breath
Yeah, it is. It's like I never have to write that silence
But
Other times like I click a link and they're like, oh, yeah, right now
I got good now I got a copy the link go open up Chrome and listen to it
I don't know what the hell that's about speaking of audio issues, but I'm sure I'll solve it eventually
And if anybody knows let me know at Chris la s. Alright, so before we go
Man, that's a lot. I just dropped on you guys. I'd really like to know what you think
I know I feel like I'm hopping again. I feel like I'm distro hopping again, but this one I'm pretty excited about
I'm really still happy like these machines here in the studio
I don't really see us going off of plasma anytime soon. It works fine
I think we would switch out to XFCE if we had a reason to touch these machines and do a bunch of other stuff, right?
So maybe next LTS will reconsider maybe or if we decide like, you know, we're gonna like I don't know spend some time like
Restandardizing or if we were making some other large change
I might consider because it's such an easy transition to go to XFCE
but otherwise all the systems here in the studio, which is a good number of systems right now are all still running plasma shell and
It's it's great. So I
They're all getting pretty good. You know L's happy with pop OS and gnome shell plasma shell works great here. There's tons of great
It's just XFCE is better than I was giving it credit and I feel like if you have been in my camp at all
It's worth giving it a go if you want to see a pretty solid implementation man. Jero does have it
I don't know if you need to run man. Jero though to run XFCE, but it's not a bad place to visit
Might give you a template something to something to base your own. Yeah. Yeah and show you you know
a more modern interpretation of a classic desktop paradigm and
Yeah, I'm just really happy with it so far. I'm gonna stick with it for a bit. All right
Pick times West pick times
I have a disclaimer to make with this pick and I hate to even I hate to even have to have a pick where I
Feel like I need to make a disclaimer
But you could use this I suppose for
nefarious purposes
So don't well, I am a long time like since since
Since forever audible subscriber. I really enjoy listening to audiobooks, especially when I'm driving, you know
I do a lot of road trips and so audiobooks are great
Hadeah my wife and I we share audiobooks
we just love it just my preferred way to consume lots of information when traveling and
It's a nice way to supplement since I don't get to read as much as I'd like
I and I I tend to find certain stories even work better in audio
But the biggest problem with audible books is they're in a proprietary
DRM that is not playable on Linux or other free software devices. That's where open audible comes in. Oh
Open audible org now. I am a longtime subscriber
I own all these books and I will continue to be a subscriber. I'm just going to back up my collection with this legitimately
I know people say that as a euphemism for stealing, but I am honestly using this as a backup. I'm backing them up to my
Server and then just have I will have an awful something offline media
So what open audible does and it is a clunky Java application
I will warn you but god bless it if it isn't performing the Lord's work here
It will download view and convert to mp3s. It will manage all of your audible.com content with their desktop front-end application
It's kind of weird the way it works because you launch the application assuming you've got JVM running
they're set up and
You then go to the menu to browse audible and you log into audible through their like Java
Browser implementation thing and then you sit there and tab through your audible library pages
Which I have like 17
And if you try to like set the sorting to 50 at a time
It'll lock the application up eventually on about page 8 and then you got to start all over again
So you got to keep it at the 20 and then you go through it page by page and as you go through it
The application is basically ingesting the HTML. I ran it. I ran it from the terminal so I could actually watch
It's just taking in the HTML stripping out the links and it is building your library locally in the application
Once you've done this you can export the list
So you don't ever have to do that again and as long as you properly exit the application
It will save the list if the application crashes. It'll lose everything. It's added. So
Avoid crashing as you can tell I had to crash a few times and by default
When you click a title in there and you can also just by default tell to download everything it will download and then convert
The entire audiobook to a high-quality mp3
See that seems nice, right? Then you have that file you can take it with you
Wherever you are plays on all your normal devices. Yeah, and that's it. That's pretty much it in a nutshell
You can there's other various things you can do with it
but for me
It was just a way to get all of my audible books that I've never been able to access on my Linux desktop and I have
Many occasions where I've been listening to an audiobook on the road and I get back to my desk and I just want to finish
It up and I can't play it on my nice desktop speakers
So hopefully this is all yeah, this is interesting
I've kind of stayed away from audible just out of some of those very same concerns
So I might I might have to reconsider now things have come and gone in the past
So grab it while you can and again
Please don't use this to like throw it up on a torrent side or something like that
I I debated not even including this in the show
But I decided since I know as a longtime desktop Linux user
this is something I've struggled with for years and
It was only made a bit better because they have a decent mobile app and that's where I do the majority of my listening
But in the back of my mind have always wanted my own copy somewhere on a file system and so and I wanted to play
Them on my own desktop. Mm-hmm, and I actually first started audible. I
Got my audible subscription then I canceled it and in there
I told them this because they don't support Linux and then when they released the mobile app even like the very early betas for Android
I signed back up and I've been a user ever since so this is really nice to find
I I my library is like 70 gigs of mp3 Wow
It's a lot of books. It's a lot of books
So I'll be I'll be tossing those on the old free NAS and then Wes found what looks like a really nice web UI
For setting up wire guard VPNs a wire guard VPN GUI a West. Mmm. Yes, indeed
I like the name too. Yeah over from the people at portal cloud. Looks like they run their own sort of VPS hosting
Company and if you just want to you know, you're confused about wire guard or you just want to give it a shot
The configs on the command line are admirably simple and easy to understand it as you've seen Chris
But you know, that's not always enough especially as you're scaling, you know, maybe maybe you're supporting a small company
You've got 30 different people that you're all you know trying to manage their stuff now
I haven't used subspace yet. Although I do have it running. I just haven't integrated it into my system. So bear that in mind
subspace
It's nice to see this stuff taking off though because these are exactly the kind of supporting applications
We need if we really want to see why our guard be as successful as I think we all hope it will be
Yeah
And this gives you a simple web UI that almost reminds me of the early UI of bit torrent sync where you go in you add
A device right it does and you see all the different devices there
you can delete and revoke their keys or you can create another one and like this would be perfect for the
Wire guard machine that we have here in the studio to just to add a few of the staff's
Yes
Mm-hmm. And the way it works is it's a Docker image that assumes you have wire guard set up and running locally
They also walk you through if you want to toss this on a VPS like a like a digital ocean droplet to you know
Get a white your own custom wire. The nice thing is it's it should be really easy to test out
Yeah, that's true
Or you just throw if you have a wire guard set up on your own local machine and then you can deploy the Docker image
And you're off to the races. It's pretty nice looking. I
I really think we'll probably get the set up here pretty soon subspace
Which is also just a great name for something like this and more power to wire guard
Yeah, you know it also was neat about it
Does hey it has integration with using let's encrypt right out of the box because of course it does so portal dot cloud is the company
Huh? This is this like another
Commercial wire guard hosted solution. No, I think they do
Next generation open source hosting yeah look at that hmm add great open source cloud applications to your account in seconds I
See yeah, they've got a couple other available open source apps like they got a simple blogging platform web analytics server stuff like that
So I haven't tried any of these before but an interesting development
I gotta say they look you know what guys if you listen get in touch
They are they're really stressing data portability they free software is like bullet point number two on their site here
That's not bad. That is not bad. I love to see that kind of stuff anyways
But that's neither here nor there if you want to check out subspace
We'll have a link in the show notes
And you can go deploy your own wire guard gooey and get people added to your wire guard instance nice and easy-sneasy
Get to it all right there you have it now. Oh
Man, oh Alan Jude's gonna be here any minute now. Oh my goodness better prepare ourselves. Oh geez all right
We better get out of here
Linux fest is nigh if you're gonna be there come say hi meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting for that event and future events
Love to see you there join us live next Tuesday for this show and join us live this Friday
If you're listening the week this came out for a hell of a live stream
Love to see you there anything else we need to plug um you know if you're gonna go over to our Jupiter broadcasting meet up
Meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting you should also stay tuned
Oh, I know L has been so hard at work with all kinds of exciting study groups
Yeah, command-line threat hunting very soon definitely do that all right see you back here
Yeah
Our next study group
Command-line threat hunting how to figure out if your box has been owned on the command line
How great is Tony right? Oh? He's amazing we have we've had we've had a little sneak peek at the material
Let's just say and we we know it's gonna be really good
I'm excited to get to watch the whole finished thing
Mm-hmm yeah, we got a little interview for Tony to run on the show here a little bit, too, so
Yeah, it's gonna be good all right
So guess what we have a couple of bits of housekeeping to get out of here in the post show to all right
You want to hear okay number one?
We got to get the title so JB titles calm everybody go boat and then number two something major happened this weekend
This is a historic event
Probably up there with Skynet as of this weekend April 2019
The cheese cloud has gone online
Yes, yes, so mr.. Bacon has set himself up a next cloud instance come here over here the cone of science
We don't want to share any details that might get your box bone, so just between you and me
Would you do did you do this on a droplet you do this?
root password, please
Mmm, it was a snap setting it up on oh, but on okay, but come on you see what I do
But I want to know setting it up the box is it a is it a droplet is it a physical machine is it a is
It a raspberry pie. What are we working with here? It is it is a droplet
I just went that route region for years and
Jeez, I don't know everything
NYC okay all right, so it's an East Coaster I catch yeah, well I've got I've got I've got a couple of droplets
You know because they're just so ridiculously simple to 1804
Fedora ok 1804 base
1804 base
Basically just installed it with the snap
Setup was ridiculously simple
Went through set up with what is it next next cloud dot HTTPS? Oh? Yeah, so you got a cert on there
Yes, or something like that, so you know just pull down this your automate your let's encrypt cert and everything so it works
flawlessly out of the box
I've got one of the lower end droplets, so I'm running like one one CPU two gigs of RAM
And just like 60 gigs of storage one of the things. I haven't quite figured out yet
Well, I just haven't really dove into it, but is relocating some of that into block storage
Which one of the things that I've learned about?
Specifically digital ocean I'm sure a lot of the others are the same
that you can only move that block storage within that Center, so
Basically I if since I do have a server that's in LA and I do have one that's in NYC
Then I could not move that block storage between those two this geek tweets has been using you're still on 1604
Did I know that yeah? I've been running the next cloud snap on 1604
Yeah, now, and it's it's you know. It's been absolutely rock-stable
It's on a VM at home back in the UK and used it all over the place
I've got two or three Android phones backing up photos to it in real time, and it's been absolutely flawless
How do you handle your your storage is it hosted on the same local machine, or do you yeah?
It's just one big virtual disk. I probably should sort out gotcha Brent's got a pretty clever title x-ray Fox trot
Charlie echo for the spelling out of excess that that's I like that's pretty deep Brent
I'm impressed I had to look it up
Board of stability damn it Joe blame Joe those are good, too
Blame Joe's pretty good, so I think it's between Brent and blame Joe right now, which is Wes's suggestion
JB titles calm not a lot of boats today not a lot of boats
Come on guys go boat go boat blame Joe is pretty good, but would people get it
No, I mean it wouldn't tell you what at all the episode was about
But it would be a slight callback to a tiny bit in the episode it is so his fault