Yara.io? What do you think, Wes?
Yara.io?
Yaro!
What, no, you're, no.
But this does look pretty cool,
and it's yet another Raspberry Pi handheld device.
This one takes advantage of the Raspberry Pi OS,
it just uses their OS.
It's a handheld that I'd say hearkens back
to the Game Boy 3DS Flip-style device,
but it has a full-corded keyboard and a trackpad,
so it's slightly larger.
Let's just say rugged and durable.
Yeah, it does have very much like you could take this
to a construction site kind of look to it.
It's got a five-inch resistive touchscreen
that runs at 800 by 480,
and they say the display actually has
pretty decent color representation.
With the keyboard on there, you know,
you could type out into an SSH session,
you can run XFCE on this thing,
you get access to the Pi's GPIO connection,
so you could hook it up to devices on the go.
And it's kind of neat how they've wired it all together.
It looks, when you open it up,
the way they've integrated the battery and the wiring
and all of that, it really looks like
a legit consumer product.
Yeah, right, and at the same time,
they've spent a bunch of work on hackability,
making sure that, like, you can actually source
every single component, no custom PCBs,
and just a bit of soldering required,
which, that's pretty cool.
Little bit of soldering, maybe 15 hours of labor.
That's all it takes.
Hello, friends, and welcome to 370
of your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Wes, I love it when we hit, like, the 10 mark,
you know, the new, when we click over, love it.
Just feels right.
It feels like we did something,
even though it's totally arbitrary.
Thanks, math.
Well, also, I want to say thank you to a Cloud Guru
for sponsoring this episode of Unplugged.
So many career possibilities in the cloud, so little time.
ACG's learning paths help you take the right courses
to prepare for architects or developers, security jobs,
and many other high-paying cloud jobs.
Get hired, get certified, get learning at cloud.guru.
Also, hello there to Drew.
Welcome back in.
Hello, hello.
Hi, Drew, did you finish up the sausage,
or are you still munching on that over there?
Eh, no, I'm done with it for now.
Did you bring enough for the class?
Just under the wire.
Too bad you guys aren't here in person today,
because I'm rocking a blazer today.
Mm.
A blazer.
I can hear how fancy you sound just in the voice.
Right?
It's the shoulder pads.
I think they do something for the acoustics.
Classy Chris.
All right, before we go any further,
let's also bring in the virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Howdy.
Good evening.
Hello, all 32 of you.
We also have a couple of special guests
who will be joining us in just a couple of minutes
to give us the story directly from the source.
So we'll get to them in a moment.
But we start out with some news that I bet a lot of you,
if you follow the last couple of episodes,
are maybe aware of, I hope.
But I'm very excited to say that Linux Action News
is back with episode 153.
It has a special place in my heart, that show.
But also, I arrogantly thought,
oh, we'll pick up a lot of the slack here in Linux Unplugged
and cover all of the news, and it'll be fine.
And didn't really pan out.
It just didn't really, it was too much of a lift.
There's too much news.
That's right.
And it deserves its own show.
But also, there's an analysis aspect to Linux Action News.
We do our homework for that show,
and we try to do the research
and often reach out for contacts
and try to get the story from people
and then incorporate that into the commentary.
And it's just the sole focus of that show,
and that's what makes it special.
And that often means it's less than 30 minutes.
So linuxactionnews.com, go grab that.
And as these new shows start back up,
because we just also relaunched Dakota Radio,
as we bring things back,
the best place to really stay in the loop
is the All Shows feed.
Because as we relaunch these shows or bring a new show on,
that's one of the first places it'll show up
is the Jupiter Broadcasting All Shows feed.
So you might search for that in your podcatcher
or go grab it from the website,
because that's really your best solution.
But do check out both those,
Koda Radio and Linux Action News is back.
This first story, that's not about us,
brings me back to the old days
of me trying to use Linux in a corporate environment,
an all Windows corporate environment.
Oh gosh.
I couldn't imagine news like this,
but it appears just under the wire,
even actually after the feature freeze,
Ubuntu 2010's Ubiquiti installer,
which is used by the Ubuntu desktop version,
is gonna see Active Directory integration.
The feature freeze exception was sought and granted
for adding this optional Active Directory support
to the Ubuntu desktop installer.
How is this actually gonna work?
Well, during user setup in Ubiquiti,
there'll be a little checkbox
for enabling Active Directory logins.
Once it's checked, a user can log in
to an Active Directory configuration on their network,
while, and this is probably key for some people out there,
still creating a local Ubuntu account
for administration purposes.
The installer will then allow,
specifying the domain, the administrator, the password,
and a nice little test configuration to go test
to make sure that your domain connection
is actually up and running.
This is great to see.
This is really wonderful.
I'll tell you, the first time I ever saw this,
and it's always been hit and miss over the years,
although I imagine now it's gotten nailed down pretty well.
First time I ever saw this was baked into Yast,
and Yast also had the option
to launch an Active Directory server itself,
and there were a couple of cracks at this
with Mandriva and Xandros as well,
and one of the reasons I even used Xandros
for a little while, which is based on Debian,
was because it promised really good Active Directory support
with a back then, what was called a KDE desktop.
Now, this is looking like a pretty good release.
2010 is gonna have Open ZFS improvements,
it's gonna have Kernel 5.8,
and GNOME 3.38 as well as what Wes just talked about,
and a bunch of other package updates.
Something to look forward to.
Isn't it nice to see that kind of stuff landing,
and it really helps Linux be a first-class citizen
in a corporate environment.
Right, that's kind of what stuck in my mind,
as clearly Canonical has seen this,
has talked to folks out in the field
who are trying to use this awesome Linux desktop,
but still have some classic legacy administrators out there,
and once you've got this big Active Directory setup,
you're not just gonna toss that by the side,
you're still gonna use it,
it's got all of this information in it,
so if we can just play nice,
all the easier to slip Linux on it.
Yeah, and it's not just about the authentication
for logins, which we talk about a lot,
but in an established Active Directory environment,
those user IDs are tied to groups
that may be very possibly your email distribution groups
are based off of.
Certainly the file rights on the company shares
are based off of these Active Directory accounts.
Lots of applications for enterprise
integrate with Active Directory,
so you can even manage security key card access
via Active Directory account status.
The list goes on and on and on,
and so when you get access to that,
you become part of that ecosystem,
because that means also now the Linux system
that you're using will understand
that this group ID on the file server
translates to this actual group,
and yes, you are a member of that,
and you can get access to it,
and you can change file permissions,
and you can actually participate in this broader ecosystem,
so it has a lot of knock-on effects.
There's always a lot of knock-on effects
when Debian makes changes, talking about Ubuntu,
and there is some news out of DebConf 20,
which concluded last week.
Debian project leader Jonathan Carter gave his talk
at the event as well as an overview
of where the project is today,
and some of the problems that he believes they are facing.
Debian's finances are sitting around
a healthy 896,000 US dollars.
Thanks to COVID-19, actually,
there was less travel and conference expenses.
I wouldn't call it a surplus,
but they haven't spent as much as they expected.
Carter also noted as part of their fund,
Debian is in the process of acquiring
two new Lenovo servers.
They were able to obtain a discount, it appears,
to help in their efforts.
As for the health of their archive,
well, Debian is up to offering
around 61,000 AMD64 packages, oh my,
and around 31,000 source packages.
Another exciting item moving forward
is the possibility of Lenovo or other OEMs
offering a Debian preloaded system,
but before that can happen,
there are still some support concerns
and other technical issues to work through.
Now, that's interesting, huh,
because we're seeing that Fedora
has launched on the X1 Carbon,
and we know that Ubuntu, not too far behind,
and now it sounds like maybe Lenovo's even open
to the idea of straight up Debian.
Now, the other thing they talked about,
and this always gets in my craw,
is needing to improve quote unquote marketing.
They say it's an issue common to many open source projects,
but Debian especially, often saying it's an unsung hero
underneath the likes of Ubuntu and Steam OS.
Now, I'm not gonna get on my whole soapbox
about this, we have too much to get into today,
but I really hate when we do this to ourselves.
I think it's a lack of perception and perspective
of where Linux is and its role in the marketplace
and the type of consumer that's drawn to it.
I think it is a lack of understanding the dynamics
of the wider ecosystem.
It's a good comparative to understand this to
would be Android.
No one who buys an Android device quote unquote no one,
going by the numbers,
knows that Android is using Linux under the hood, right?
But we all do, just like everyone listening
and you all in the mumble room,
you all know that Ubuntu is based on Debian.
This slice of the market knows that.
And that, as a technical project,
is your best chance of who you're gonna market to.
You're not gonna-
I wonder though, maybe that's,
is that what they're getting at here though?
Because I feel like maybe there is,
I agree on the larger part, like marketing the Debian,
the nitty gritty to the wider user experience,
but maybe even amongst the Linux in the know folks,
sort of take Debian for granted, we forget about it.
I mean, how much do we even talk about it here on the show?
I think you could argue there's reasons
beyond marketing for that.
There seems to be certain areas
that the project doesn't engage in
and other areas that they seem to engage in.
And they seem to spend a lot of time spinning internally
and a lot of energy spent doing that.
I think they do have a perception problem,
but none of this is actually marketing.
So marketing implies that if you could buy a page
in a magazine or buy some banner ads on a website
that people would be flocking to your distribution
and give it more respect for what it does.
But that's, even when I just verbalize what they're implying,
it sounds ludicrous.
Well, that's like a general conception of marketing,
but couldn't it also mean just having more resources spent
at, well, once we're doing that again, at meetups,
at mentioning all the things that Debian is used for
at better integration with partners that are using Debian,
better representation in cloud marketplaces perhaps?
Yeah, I think that is an area they will invest in.
And that is totally an area that makes sense.
But if you think about who you're reaching there,
you're reaching probably that kind of tier of the market
that I was talking about.
People that already know about Debian,
but maybe just don't think about it a lot.
Right, that could be a good way to go.
When I look at Debian as like an outside observer,
I see something that I have a deep appreciation
and respect for, borderline love fest for really.
There's a few things out there
that have been with us for so long.
And so for me, Debian was the distribution when I used it,
I realized, oh, I can switch to Linux.
Like I had used Red Hat, which was, you know,
the good old bad days of RPMs
and manually solving RPM dependencies.
Like we're going way back here, right?
And then I switched over to Debian and apt came along
and it changed my mind
of how a computer can help me manage it.
I have a deep appreciation for Debian,
but when I try to think of what they're doing in the space
that gets people to talk about them,
I can't really enumerate much.
Like I don't see anybody at Debian
pioneering arm development and champion that.
I haven't heard about any big OEM deals with Debian.
And I'm not saying these things are necessary,
but if you do want chatter, if you want buzz,
you kind of have to do something
that people will talk about.
Yeah, that's a good point.
And maybe we should note too that Carter believes
that they need two to three times
their current volunteer levels
to accomplish all of their goals.
He also feels Debian is too lacking in the area of diversity
and not catching up fast enough.
Partially the blame there is, you know, large regions
of the world not being represented
and the people making and maintaining Debian
and maybe failing to put together a timely message
regarding Black Lives Matter and other recent concerns.
That kind of raises off the mark to me.
If that's what they think is not driving contributions,
again, I don't think they're properly assessing the market,
but I may be wrong, what do I know?
I'm just some dumb podcaster in the Seattle area,
so don't listen to me.
It's fascinating in either case that we sort of get
to watch this discussion going on, right?
That's true, and at least it's happening.
There's that as well, so that I appreciate.
I want to talk about PipeWire.
It's been a little while since we've done an update
on PipeWire, and it looks like over the late summer
and before, there has been some significant developments.
PipeWire is increasingly getting ready
for more user testing, and if you recall,
this is the Red Hat project for better audio
and video stream management on Linux,
and it's increasingly getting close to shipping time.
Yeah, PipeWire lead developer, Wim Tamens,
feels that the code is at a state where PulseAudio,
Jack, and also backends are usable,
I mean, if not 100% feature complete,
and actually, it's in good enough shape
that he and others at the Red Hat desktop team
are hoping to see more user testing happen
with the latest PipeWire code.
It now has a fully functioning session manager
with Wire Plumber, human readable handling of audio devices,
hey, that's pretty important,
support for creating audio sync devices with Jack,
hey-o, and support for creating devices with GStreamer,
among a bunch of other great improvements.
Well, to talk about all of this is lead developer, Wim.
He joins us now.
It's been a little while, Wim.
Welcome back to the show.
Hi, hello, everybody.
Hello, and congratulations
on the continued work with PipeWire.
It sounds like we're getting pretty close
to production ready, is that right?
Well, pretty close is a lot to say,
but it's ready for testing.
Okay.
So I expect at least six months of testing.
You know, I was looking back,
you were on the show in October of 2018,
and one of the things that we focused on a lot
in that conversation was the need for a session manager.
In fact, I think it was maybe the bulk of our discussion.
Would you mind explaining what a session manager is
and what we have now with PipeWire?
That's an interesting thing.
So if you look at PipeWire itself,
it's kind of like a blank canvas, basically,
where you can put like devices and stuff like that
and link them together,
but in itself, there's nothing there.
So you need to have a session manager
that puts things on the canvas,
like for example, creating all the devices
based on also what is detected with Udef
or like Bluetooth devices that appear or things like that.
So the session manager, it's basically like presents
all of the devices to PipeWire.
So PipeWire is basically the IPC,
the apps that connect to PipeWire
see the graph of all these devices
that are basically managed by the session manager.
So the session manager as well,
it looks at, for example, when a new app appears,
it looks, oh, what does it do?
What is its role?
And things like that.
And then it tries to find out where to link it to
and it manages the links.
If a device is removed, it relinks it to another device.
And all of that logic is done by a session manager.
It's Wire Plumber, right?
That's the name of it, pretty clever.
Yeah, we're not exactly using Wire Plumber yet.
It's on the to-do list for soon.
Currently, it's like an experimental
internal session manager,
but basically all of that code is moved
into a nicer code base that is Wire Plumber.
This has been a project a long time in the works.
The announcement about starting,
I think you made in 2017, if I recall correctly.
And it sounds like we're at the point where
if someone's willing to take a little risk,
they could turn this on, say if they're on Fedora 33,
and start using this as their sound system?
Yes, I've been running it for a while as my main desktop.
For today, with the mumble session I did in there too,
there was some weird bugs still.
But otherwise, it sort of works for regular desktop use.
There are some things that need fixing,
and we will fix them, but you can use it for basic things,
like watching YouTube and playing movies.
So exciting.
What is the more challenging desktop application?
Is it web browsers?
Like, what is it that is vexing you?
It's mostly the PulseAudio API.
So I actually need to emulate all of the PulseAudio API
with all of its timings and all of that thing
for apps to actually work well.
Because a lot of apps are programmed in a way I do this,
and then I set the time of that,
and it's very specific to how PulseAudio does things.
So I need to emulate all of that.
So that is currently the biggest problem.
Like, for example, if you look at jack apps,
they are much more, that's a much more simpler API,
and they work a lot better out of the box.
And so last time we spoke, I believe that was the plan,
is to essentially implement the jack API.
And so if I'm a jack user, which we are here in the studio,
am I in a better position?
It has more chance of working well, yes.
Like, for example, if you run Ardour or something,
it works fine.
Hey, lucky me.
Yeah, I actually did some testing myself
just a couple of days ago to see kind of where it's at.
And I did find a couple of bugs,
like Carla, when a device would disappear,
Carla wouldn't, you know, reflow the canvas,
and I'd end up having to close it and reopen it.
But I think that's actually a Carla bug
and not a PipeWire bug.
But that said, the jack implementation
is working really, really, really well.
You know, you do have to go into a config file
to change like the sampling rate or something like that.
But everything I threw at it really just worked
with the exception of Flatpak,
which I know is not yet supported.
So I'm really impressed.
So far, it's looking really, really good.
Wim, I'm kind of curious,
when we talk to you about this a lot,
we're primarily talking about Fedora
because we kind of know it's going to be there.
And Fedora has been very aggressive
on getting to Wayland and creating solutions
that work well with contained applications and whatnot,
which PipeWire checks all those boxes.
What is adoption outside of Fedora looking like right now?
I think it's being important in distributions.
Well, mainly PipeWire is used for the screen sharing.
So I think that's on top of Wayland,
that's basically the de facto standard.
So once the version gets updated to 3.10,
the audio bits are there too,
and you can basically use the audio bits there too.
So, but yes, I think everybody's watching a bit
to see how it goes in Fedora first.
And we can't really enable it by default yet.
I guess that makes sense.
But you are taking a pretty sensible approach,
nice and slow and steady.
I hope so.
I hope so too.
It's a very big undertaking too.
It's three APIs that need to be moved to something new.
Also, Jack and Paul saw you.
That's a huge undertaking.
I mean, you're kind of redoing in a sense
or reformulating how the entire media scape
on the Linux desktop works.
Yes.
Yeah.
He says with a big sigh, yeah.
And we're very grateful.
I'll tell you what I'm really looking forward to
is when Fedora Jam and PipeWire are both working in sync
and we finally have like a low latency kernel
available for Fedora,
and it becomes sort of the go-to for multimedia production.
That really is my dream of where I want Fedora to go.
Ooh, seeing the work that's going into PipeWire,
it feels closer than ever.
Thank you very much, Wim.
You're welcome.
So Wim, as a takeaway for the audience
that runs Linux on the desktop,
in a year or two, as these things stabilize
and adoption increases,
what's the primary benefit do you think end users
will notice?
Well, we will have enabled audio in a secure way in apps,
but that's not exactly user friendly.
Right, it's good for them,
but it's not something they-
Hopefully they never notice.
It just works like they expect.
So I just hope that we will be able to do new things.
Like for example, in GNOME,
have a panel where you can put like filters for your syncs
or like make more configuration panels
for doing stuff with your audio,
like what you have in core audio.
Oh yeah.
And then there's like, for example,
you'll be able to run Ardour,
which is not exactly for average users,
but at least you can run it and it runs out of the box,
like something that you actually should expect
from an operating system,
that it runs these pro apps out of the box.
Right, in a way it's the groundwork
to enable a more powerful generation
of production applications on Linux.
Yeah, and for what it's worth,
even some proprietary stuff,
like I threw Reaper at it
and I encountered zero bugs using Reaper with PipeWire.
Whoa.
That's good news.
Boy, we're looking good.
We may be early PipeWire adopters right here.
You know, I am curious though,
one of the big things about PipeWire
when we last talked to you about it, Wim,
was that audio and video,
at least in the backend, weren't too different.
I'm curious how video support's coming along
just in the current Zoom dominated world.
I've seen a lot of folks messing around
with loop back video devices
and getting OBS things set up,
all sorts of stuff that the PipeWire model
might make a lot easier.
Yeah, we're not there yet.
So you can capture from a camera, but that's about it.
There is an internal format for doing video filters,
but there is no example.
I have a Vulkan source, but that's it.
So, and the synchronization with audio
is not really worked out yet.
It should all be internally there,
but it's up in the air.
Still gotta tie it all together.
Yeah.
Well, we're gonna send you a beer and Red Bull
and you can pick which one you want
for until this thing's done.
Well, Wim, thank you for coming on and giving us an update.
You could tell it's a project we follow
with a lot of passion.
And we thought it has been too long
since we've done an update.
And it seems like it's relatively simple
in later versions of Fedora to flip on and start testing.
Yeah, should try it.
I think we might try it in our Bugathon
on the live stream later today.
Well, Wim, thank you very much for joining us.
Thank you.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go to Linode.com slash unplugged
and get a $100 credit for 60 days on new accounts.
$100 for Linode is fantastic.
Linode is simple cloud infrastructure with lots of options,
block storage, object storage,
and they have a really easy interface to use it
or plug it in with a wider orchestration system
like Kubernetes or Terraform,
which is something we've been playing with.
They have shared plans starting as low as $5.
Go for it.
I mean, with $100 credit, go for it.
They have dedicated GPU compute plans.
Or if you're like us and you just want
a decently priced system to mess around with,
like we did something I think middish tier
for the matrix server, and it's fantastic.
The thing runs like a champ.
And with 11 data centers all over the world,
there's probably something close to you that works.
They also have a really fast next generation network.
40 gigabit connections to the machines.
I mean, it's super fast.
With industry leading CPUs, a revamped cloud manager,
and root access to your server,
along with their API that is super cool
if you'd use nothing else
but the Linode command line application.
That's what I use on my rig.
And Wes, you should check this out too
because it's great for show notes.
You know how we'll sometimes use the object storage
to embed audio in our show notes for like a clip?
Oh yeah.
Well, with the Linode command line application,
once you get things like your account set up
and your API key in there,
you just point it at a file
and tell it to just upload it to the object storage
and flag it as public and return the URL.
Just all one command, it uploads the file,
puts it in object storage, makes it public,
and gives you a shareable URL
to embed on a website or something.
That sounds so easy.
It's super great.
The command line app is actually one of my favorite things
about Linode, although the web UI is fantastic too.
So linode.com slash unplugged.
Get a $100 credit for 60 days on a new account.
That's linode.com slash unplugged.
And a big thank you to Linode
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
So Academy 2020 is rolling on right now.
It runs from Friday 4th, the 4th to September 11th,
which is just a little bit after we record this episode.
And Alish joins us.
He is the president of the board of directors at KDEV
and the co-founder of the Linux App Summit,
and also a bruncher.
He did brunch with Brent on March 27th,
which I'll have a link in the show notes.
Alish, welcome to Unplugged.
Hi, thanks for having me here.
Hey, thanks for joining us.
And how's Academy going?
Well, it's going good.
Like everything in 2020 is a bit special, right?
But first, Virtual Academy, it went really well.
No big technical problems
that would have rendered it impossible.
I think that everyone who wanted to participate could
and still can.
We will be having sessions over the week,
so still ongoing.
So what we do is on the weekend,
we have talks that would be more,
well, what you expect from a conference kind of talks.
And those are done.
Actually, you can find them on the internet.
I guess that we can put the URL somewhere later
if somebody wants to take a look.
Everything is online.
Okay.
Actually, this year was easier
because, I mean, everything was recorded
because it had to reach, and it was streamed, of course.
Or you recorded them as you did them.
Yeah, we were using something called Big Blue Button,
which is a conferencing tool.
And one of the features that you have right there,
like you have chat, but you have a button to record
because, I mean, the stream is going through it, right?
Right, that's nice.
So my question with that is,
do you think this is a format you'll adopt long-term?
Because I imagine it made it possible
for a lot more people to attend that couldn't.
Or do you feel like the lower bandwidth aspect
isn't really long-term sustainable?
I think that there's definitely goods and pros
in making it available on the internet.
I'm not going to be here, the one to convince people that,
well, offering contents on the internet
makes them less available or something.
There's a big component into a conference, though,
the social component that is kind of lacking.
And I don't know if we're going to just,
let's always do virtual conferences
and forget about meeting at all, right?
Yeah, maybe a mix.
Yeah, hackers, we are already known
for being not all that sociable
if you remove the conferences.
It's your only time to get out.
That's my problem.
Exactly.
Yeah, but RSI is so bad
because I'm not going to events this year.
That's what I'll blame it on.
Well, so before Academy is even over yet,
you're already talking about the Linux App Summit,
and I believe the call for papers ends pretty soon,
so it's probably the time to get the word out.
Yeah, that's right.
I mean, we've been working on the LAS 2020 since last year,
and it will happen in November, like you said, I think.
Call for papers ends in the 1st of October.
This week, we're going to announce the first keynoters,
which are quite special, so stay tuned.
If you're interested in talking about applications,
which I think that is something
that is actually quite close to end users,
I think that it's a good forum to do it.
It will also be the first time that we do it online
and strictly virtual format.
Right, I've always wanted to attend.
You always should have.
I know, I know, but it always was,
it always conflicted with something else.
There's also, you have a name conflict.
I have LAS in mind, and people are going to think
I'm Chris Libre Application Summit
or Linux Application Summit,
but maybe this is the year I can make it,
so maybe I will, that's pretty great.
So we'll have a link if you want to submit papers
or if you have an idea,
and what kind of things are you looking for for the summit?
For one, we want to encourage all kinds of organizations
to create applications and contents in the end
that are consumable for people using Linux.
Actually, the concept was started by Gnome,
and they called it the Libre App Summit,
and when we started doing it together with Katie,
we decided to like, let's talk about Linux specifically
and let's do it in a way so that when organizations come,
they know what we're talking about exactly, right?
And why it's about having a free
and open source operating system.
What we want is that all of the contents
that people expect to have on their devices
are available to them.
And we don't want, well, technical reasons
or communication reasons to be why these aren't happening.
So we invite the different organizations
to reach out to us and hear from the people
who have been developing the operating system.
I think that was a nice transition
when it moved from something that was for the Gnome folks
to something that's for Linux users,
Plasma Desktop, Gnome Desktop, i3, whatever it might be.
We want applications for Linux,
and I think that's a good focus.
In the broader case, does that mean more standards?
Does that mean coming together and deciding to do things
as a desktop standard?
Or what do you think ultimately will be action
from something like this?
Well, in general, to find what solution
you need for a problem, you need to get people together
and agree, right?
Right, right, absolutely.
That's why we needed a space
where to have this kind of conversation.
And it's definitely part of that.
Something also that is kind of related,
but not exactly like we were talking
about developers talking, but on LAS,
we also believe that you need to have
a lot different kind of profiles
to approach the Linux community
that goes beyond just the hackers themselves.
And we want to find ways to make sure
that they find the space to collaborate
on the different projects.
And we want to, if you look at the different topics
that we're suggesting people to talk about,
you will see things like legal or promotion.
People need to be able to know
how these are gonna work on Linux on the long run.
Besides, well, the APIs that people are using,
which in the end, I mean, if you're a developer,
you will be able to find the APIs
that you need to use somewhere on the internet, right?
But is all of the content really available
for people to consume?
Well, let's make sure it is.
And that's what LAS is all about.
I think it's a great idea from the concept
of a place to send developers who are Linux curious
and they don't have all the answers.
They don't even know maybe where to look
or what the language is to speak.
And this is something they could attend
and get a pretty good sense of the lay of the ground
and maybe get an idea of how to start developing for Linux.
Yes, for sure.
That's a good way to come from.
Also, if you're coming from a region
that is not very represented on the different communities,
it's a good way to get introduced into the whole concept.
Most free software communities that I know about
are very Western world kind of centric.
And it's something that I think that LAS also
can help a bit to solve by not targeting everyone
into a solution, which myself as a KD person,
I would be happy with getting everything implemented,
but just having this common space
where people can approach and see
how can we bring the Linux things you're creating
into my language, into my locales.
The world is much more complex
than many of us think sometimes.
There's lots of scripts.
There's lots of different perspectives
that we need to make sure that are taken care of.
And we need to have places that they need to feel like
they're not excluding anyone, they just want solutions.
And we are offering a space for there on LAS.
Absolutely.
Well, let's keep up the great work.
Thank you for updating us
when you're in the middle of conferences
and doing all of that.
Don't work yourself too hard.
And here's to a successful Linux app summit.
Oh, thank you very much.
Thanks for joining us.
We'll also, if you wanted to catch the platform,
it's big blue button, we'll have a link to that as well
in the show notes.
Those are at linuxunplug.com slash three seven zero.
We'll have a link to the stuff we talked about
as well as the call for papers.
And now it is time
for a spot of housekeeping.
Long overdue.
You know, it's been getting a little dirty, Wes.
You know, you didn't show up so I didn't bother cleaning
cause you're doing it remote today.
So I thought, oh, I can just let it go.
No, no, housekeeping must go on.
You're right.
It is my fault.
I was trying to make it your fault,
but I just couldn't, I couldn't work the angle.
Now listen here, it's important.
This is important.
We're moving the recording schedule
for one week next week.
We're going on Sunday, this Sunday coming up, big change.
I don't know why I'm saying it weird.
What I'm trying to say is Sunday the 13th,
we're pre-recording for the episode
that would normally be live on the 15th.
I'm taking that week off, trying to do a little downtime,
trying not to do the old burnout thing.
And so we're going to record on Sunday
around 3 p.m. Pacific, which that means 6 p.m. Eastern.
We'd love to have you there.
Show up, hang out in the lup lug at noon
and then just stretch that thing out.
Now tonight as we record,
we're doing the Bugathon for Fedora 33.
We want to explore this idea further
and maybe see if we can't take it to future projects.
I don't know.
We'll probably talk about it tonight actually,
but I'd like to call on the community in the meantime
to keep joining the Bugathon room on our matrix server.
I want to make a persistent space
where developers can reach out to willing and able testers
in the Bugathon room.
Essentially a spot where they can search for it.
It's a beautiful thing in matrix and they can find it
and they can go in there and boom,
a group of people willing to help them test something.
Imagine just even that as a resource for developers
where they can reach users
when they need another set of eyes.
Also taking future projects
that we could do as a Bugathon in that room.
So that'll be the place to stay up to date
on future developments.
We'd love to hear from open source project leaders
or developers who have any ideas
on how we could utilize this community powered
bug testing better.
All of that, you can either email me,
chris at jupyterbroadcasting.com
or join the Bugathon room on our matrix server
and chat with us about it in there
because I think this is something,
I've got a lot of big ideas,
but I want to do it the right way.
Measure twice, cut once
and do something that truly makes a difference.
And I think I'll also just plug while we're wrapping it up,
Wes joined us on Coder Radio this week.
So check out Coder Radio,
they'll be releasing just like a day or so
after we publish this episode.
Yeah, that was a lot of fun.
Yeah, thanks for doing that.
That's what Wes spent his Labor Day doing.
It was podcasting.
I can't think of anything better than debating the merits
of C++ with you and Mike.
That's exactly what we did.
So check out coder.show for that.
Thank you to our unplugged core contributors
who are making these shows possible really.
This is our core.
This is the foundation of the show
that makes it possible to continue production
if we lose sponsorships
or help us offset the need for sponsors.
And it keeps us independent.
So I really want to say thank you to the core contributors,
unpluggedcore.com if you're interested in signing up.
You get access to two feeds.
Feed one is the ad-free
or maybe more appropriate, limited ad-free feed
because there are some ads that are short
but contractually obligated to be in there.
But there's otherwise, it's the fully produced show,
fully mixed and just less ads.
We cut what we can.
Yeah, and you get the clean audio.
So if we have somebody on,
Drew works on spicing that stuff up and making it sweet,
that's all in there.
But if you'd rather have just the bootleg copy
of the entire stream, which is often much longer
and has lots of interesting conversations
that are a little more of the off-air variety,
that's feed two, the full live stream.
All our screw-ups,
the stuff that never really makes it into the show,
that's all in that feed.
So you get feed one or feed two,
and that's available when you become
a unplugged core contributor as a thank you.
And that's at unpluggedcore.com.
The real question is, do you want the Drew magic
or do you want all the mess-ups?
Yeah, you know, or do the AB thing,
which it would actually be a really,
I think it would help people appreciate
the work that goes into it,
is subscribe, get the live version feed,
and then compare it to the version published on the website.
And I think you'll see quite the difference.
Also still taking input for Linux Prepper,
I should mention that too.
But I wanted to get into our feedback
because we've gotten some good ones recently
and we wanted to get through at least a batch of these
and then maybe hold another batch
so we can also do picks.
Let's start with a mention with a community book club.
Yes, a community book club.
The group will do a read of Jono Bacon's people-powered book
with a discussion on Slack
and a weekly QA session with Jono.
The book club, which takes place entirely online,
is free and will run from October 6th to December 15th.
So you do the math on that.
Q&A calls every Tuesday at 9 a.m. Pacific time.
Wow, that's quite the day.
You do your book club Q&A,
then you do your unplugged live.
Sign-ups are open until October 2nd
and further information like the Slack group and stuff
will be emailed to participants closer
to when the Q&A starts.
But if you're interested in community
and making your existing community better,
Jono's kind of become the source on this stuff.
So I'll have a link to that in the show notes.
And I guess it's a freebie way to listen to the book, right?
Yeah, and I mean like talk to folks
that are interested in other people
working at building and maintaining communities.
Sounds like a good resource.
Yeah, and troll Jono.
So that's totally worth it, really, if you think about it.
Well, that's why you'll be there.
All right, our first email comes in from Jake,
and he says, hey guys,
congratulations on becoming independent again.
Whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop, whoop.
He says, I was curious if you've ever considered
trying Alpine on the garage server.
It has Docker and ZFS availability natively.
And he says, thanks for hanging through
what must have been some trying times, Jake.
Jake says we should use Alpine.
What do you think of that?
Ooh, you know, I didn't realize
that it had ZFS easily available.
That's never a bad thing, is it?
I didn't realize that either.
Now, that would be taking things
to the next minimal level, I think.
Certainly, we've used tons of containers powered by Alpine.
As a full-fledged server, I don't know,
maybe it's worth a shot.
Well, it doesn't have that same kind of,
doing 85 on a motorcycle down the freeway
with no helmet on kind of feel that our Arch server does.
Right, well, and the other thing too is,
using Arch, you gotta piece it together.
But we often fall back on that there Arch Wiki,
which is a huge resource.
I could see it though.
Especially for something like a Raspberry Pi
or a really low-end NUC that is just an appliance,
that could be the OS to go with.
I could definitely see it making sense.
Daniel writes in with questions about remote office.
He says, sorry in advance for being a noob.
On one of your shows, you talked about
how you linked your RV to the studio's office network.
I have looked for more info on this
and I'm hitting a brick wall.
I have satellite internet at both my office and home
and I'd like to get SSH access to my work computer
and access some shared drives.
Both my desktop and my laptop run Pop OS
and I've never looked back.
Without going any longer into my background,
this is all to say I have a pretty good understanding
of basic programming and networking
from about the mid-90s, but I've been a little out of touch.
So my question is, if I have a droplet
that's running a mail server,
could I use that for this project?
I know I haven't given you a lot of information,
but maybe you guys can help.
Well, Wes, I think he's just about onto it.
I think you just need to connect the dots
for Daniel on this one.
Yeah, right?
I mean, we're doing a couple of things.
Probably primarily would be leveraging WireGuard,
which is just sort of our own VPN of choice these days.
And then also something you and Alex talked about
in self-hosted episode 24 would be that handy little
remote forwarding SSH where you forward the SSH port
from one of your pies in your mobile RV
up to a droplet that we've got running
and then you can access that from anywhere.
That's really the trick.
And I love it so much that now I've set it up
on my son's computer, I just put on everything now
and I just have it right there as another port
and I just change ports and one port number
equals this machine in my head,
one port number equals my other machine in my head
and it works so well that I use it on the regular for SSH.
Now, WireGuard ultimately would be the simpler solution
if that would work with your satellite internet provider
because then you could talk to the machine
with just with anything, like if you wanted to do SFTP
or if you wanted to do Samba,
you could do any kind of file transfer.
So WireGuard might be the preferred solution
but you could totally do it with SSH jump hosts.
Yeah, and if it wasn't clear, that's what we're doing here.
I would definitely argue
for a virtual private network myself.
I mean, that's what they're for.
Yeah, that'll give you full,
it's like you've actually joined the networks together,
you're on the same network.
The SSH thing is really just sort of
an convenient little hack when all you need
is remote SSH access and you've already got
a public VPS somewhere.
I mean, you could also do a little port forwarding.
You could do some things.
But yeah, WireGuard really would be the way to go.
Check the show notes too,
Wes is dropping in a link to a secure SSH tunnel
as a system D unit, which the trick there
is when your system comes up,
it just automatically establishes that tunnel for you
on the back end and leaves it persistently connected.
And if your network goes out,
it can also help reconnect that automatically
without you having to do anything.
So Daniel, when you're looking for
that remote office solution,
do check out that link Wes just dropped in there.
Yeah, it's also pretty handy for remote support.
Maybe you don't need to establish a full VPN tunnel,
but you've got a family member whose laptop's running Linux
and you need, occasionally you gotta jump in there
to do some troubleshooting.
That's a handy way to do it too.
Yeah, I think it was just a month or five ago that,
oh yeah, it was a little bit ago.
But my son was preparing for school from home
and he needed a dependency to install some app they use,
it might've even been Zoom.
And I just didn't really feel like walking him
through the process of app installing
when his mom's standing there over the computer,
they want it done, the teacher's waiting.
I just fired off the SSH connection through that tunnel,
jumped on his box, pseudo-app installed the package,
got it all going for him in seconds
and they were able to just launch the app.
It was really a quick resolution.
And that's just a high level of support
you could offer with Linux if you use the tools.
Like it doesn't have remote desktop RDP,
I couldn't RDP into it,
but I sure solved the problem awful quick.
All right, well thank you
for going to linuxunplug.com slash contact
and sending those in.
We have a couple of more for next episode
since we're doing a prerecord, we're saving a couple.
So if you didn't hear yours answered, stay tuned,
but you do get a taco either way.
All right, why don't we do a few picks before we go?
Because everyone needs this first pick.
And I think it's kind of a essential service
to the community that we call this one out
because I know this is what you've been waiting for,
a spreadsheet program that's end curses.
Yeah, right, who doesn't want that?
Tired of loading up a bloated GUI all the time,
you just need to calculate a few rows here and there?
No longer, at least with SCIM.
You really got a good pitch down for that.
They should contact you.
Tired of those bloated graphical spreadsheet programs?
Go back to the days of Lotus.
Well, I mean, you know,
a spreadsheet's just like a 2D interface anyway.
For sure.
A bunch of columns of text and numbers.
That's kind of perfect.
And don't we always love a good end curses pick?
Yes, always.
We should have an end curses jingle, actually.
We love it so much.
Now you might laugh, but you should stay around.
Check this pick out just enough
to see their charting support
because that kind of blew me away.
Oh, you're right.
That's legitimately rad.
All right, well, you'll have to check the link
in the show notes to see that one
because while we're talking about things
that you always are going to want to do
on the command line, obviously,
that would be presentations, of course.
You want to present on the command line.
And that's where this next pick comes in.
It's simply called present.
And well, I mean, it supports as schematics.
So you could have some animations, I think.
Yeah, I mean, it's got colors.
It's got effects.
It's honestly one of the best.
I've been looking around for a quote unquote full feature
at least as far as you can get presentation tool
for the command line.
You know, sometimes you got to demo stuff.
You're making some changes.
You got a new project you're trying to show off.
If you're going to be doing that stuff
on the terminal anyway,
why have to switch back and forth between like,
you know, whatever you're using Google services,
or maybe you've got the LibreOffice presentation suite
installed.
Nah, none of that.
This is just a simple Python app pip install present
and away you go.
You know what, Wes?
It is no less ridiculous than all of your core applications
being different tabs in a web browser.
No, exactly.
And I mean, it's powered by Markdown, right?
So if you're already familiar with writing stuff
in Markdown, that's kind of how I plan out my notes
for presentations anyway.
And if I can just leverage that without having to copy that
and reformat it, drag boxes around in a GUI
and just have a basic presentation,
no, it won't work for everything.
But for just simple internal facing presentations
with a bunch of other nerds,
I think it might actually be useful.
So everyone on the Zoom call, I am using Wayland.
So I can't share my screen.
So please SSH in and join my team up session.
And we will look at this presentation together.
There's only one organization I think that would fly in
and it would be JB.
That would be the only place we'd be like,
oh yeah, cool, no problem.
That's really neat.
How are you doing that?
Am I dating us, Brent, by talking about Lotus?
You know, the good old days?
Yeah, I think a little bit, but many of us,
well, I say that.
I'm just trying to make myself feel better.
One of the first, first applications I ever used
was a spreadsheet program on the fan line
with Commodore 64 stuff.
My father tracked our allowance when we were kids in there
and we had to use it otherwise we didn't get it.
So that was quite nostalgic.
Wow, tracked the, you know,
I kind of remember something similar back in the day
as my dad tracked the family finances
in a DOS-based spreadsheet.
It just, it all looked like wizardry to me.
See you next week.
Same bat time, same bat station.
Well, this would normally be the point
where I'd plug the live stream next week,
but I'm heading off into the woods or maybe the coast.
I'm not sure yet.
Taking a little downtime.
So we're pre-recording, like I mentioned,
on this coming Sunday.
But if you're subscribed, like 98%, 99% of you that listen,
almost making it not even worth me mentioning right now,
nothing will really change for you.
It's pretty much gonna be the same.
So linuxunplug.com slash 370 to go get more of that.
Thank you to Drew and Wes
and thank you to the Mumble Room.
Thank you to Elish and Wim for joining us as well.
And thank you to our core contributors
who are helping make the show possible.
And thanks to all of you for listening.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
fait.
I wanted to get the Virtual Lugs take on a blog post over at HawaiiGentech.com about
why I, this is the author, why I linked to the Wayback Machine instead of the original
site.
They write, when linking to a page for the purposes of reference, like we do in the show
notes all the time, it seems better to me to link to an archive version of a given page
rather than to the original site itself.
This ensures that after some years have gone by, my article is guaranteed to be consistent.
Due to the changing nature of the web, there is a chance that after some years, the link
could lead to a 404 not found, changed or edited content or entirely replaced, content
that has been due to a rise in popularity is now shielded behind a paywall demanding
a user account or even pay for it.
Whereas linking to the archive is probably more authoritative than linking to dynamic,
changeable web content.
And then the author sites where some new sites on all sides have made changes after the fact
with no notice of updates or anything and then it made their article irrelevant they're
referencing to.
And archive.org is a great way to just kind of link to an official always will work version
of a website.
Think about it in the context of our podcast.
So instead of linking to Foronix or OMG Ubuntu or LWN, we would link to archive.org's Wayback
Machine version of their thing.
I've used Wayback Machine a couple of times, but it doesn't capture all dates, right?
Can you manually trigger to capture a website?
Yeah, I think there is a way to submit something to the Wayback Machine and it grabs a capture
of it that day.
Okay.
Yeah, that Yeah, right.
I would agree with you that linking to a Wayback link indeed is more secure.
I've had oftentimes I remember now for school we were using an API framework called loopback
and we had to push it to IBM cloud and they also use that from documentation on a different
website.
And when you were Googling for instructions or something was going wrong and you were
Googling for stuff to help you out, it would link it to a forum.
And when you click on that forum, they were mentioning, oh, this is the old link.
We've moved to this forum, but all the old posts were archived.
They no longer exist on the new forum and having a Wayback Machine link would have been
handier in that case.
Yeah, I'm a big fan of the Wayback Machine.
I mean, it's been around forever.
But in my experience, every time I go to use it, there's, you know, there's some text there
and some basic images and stuff.
I remember looking at one of Popeys old websites with cats on it.
A lot of the usability kind of goes away.
There's some fancy features in, you know, modern web that don't always translate it.
I think maybe that would be a bad user experience in some cases when, you know, some websites
were looking to have some pretty neat stuff going on.
I just wanted you to know that I did catch that you're using the Wayback Machine to look
at Popeys cats.
I did catch that.
All right.
That's all.