This is CNN Breaking News.
We're learning this now in the Jupiter Broadcasting Studios, Linux 5.8 is out.
Wes, you're on the scene right now reporting outside Linus Torvalds' house.
What are you learning?
Oh my, Chris!
We've got AMD GPU trusted memory zone, TMZ, support for encrypted video memory, also some
new user space patches for Mesa.
Wes, I can't believe you let me get away with that.
Hello friends and welcome into 365 of your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Wes, quite the show today.
Not only are we going to make you an online audio pro with our favorite headsets, but
we're going to tell you why everybody's making a big deal out of BootHole, some other
community news and your feedback, as well as some follow-up stuff from a couple episodes
ago.
It's a well-rounded episode and to help us sort through it all, Drew's joining us here.
Hello, Drew.
Hello.
I like that you brought your own chair today with all of those nice stickers and stuff
on it.
This is a nice looking chair.
You should leave this here.
I just really wasn't feeling the chairs that you provide, man.
They're just not good enough for my butt.
I understand.
You could make them out of just scraps and boxes, so I can appreciate that.
The people that really got the best chairs, that's our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Salutation.
Aloha.
Howdy.
Hello, everybody.
24 of you in there and we've been having a good pre-show hanging out on the live stream
now for, well, we were actually live for an hour and a half, but then we had a fantastic
Comcast outage, which brought us down for a bit.
We're limping along, making do, making possible.
Yeah, so there's stuff going on.
There's a lot going on.
Kernel 5.8 just landed, of course, everybody's already excited about what's going to be in
5.9.
5.9 will probably be what ends up in distributions like Fedora 33 and there's supposedly some
nice improvements for ButterFS in 5.9.
So we'll leave links to that stuff in the show notes, but let's follow up with some
of the RSI feedback that we got on the show.
I just want to do this briefly, won't become the RSI podcast, but I just wanted to say
thank you.
I heard from a lot of you who are also either just now learning to deal with this or have
some tips.
I got lots of gear suggestions, so I'll put a link to some of that in the show notes.
I expected a lot of you to just yell exercise, exercise, exercise at me, but instead I got
a little bit of that and a lot of gear.
David wrote and he says, hey Chris, sorry to hear you're battling repetitive stress
injury and I'm wondering if you're still using a mouse and have you considered a trackball?
Now he recommends one of them thumb trackballs, but I'll come back to that in a minute.
He says, I find that I need to take a break from time to time and also that I have to
keep the trackball clean about every three days, so consider that.
Best wishes.
I love Linux unplugged and self-hosted.
Well, thanks David.
So David recommended the Logitech M570, which I actually have right here, M570 here in the
studio and it's a thumb trackball.
And I don't know if that's universally considered the best route to go for RSI.
I think something more like the Kingston trackball.
Now Wes, I don't know if you remember these.
I grew up with one of these.
My mom was a graphic artist since Photoshop 1.0 and as soon as these big trackball mouse
came out, it's like the size of a pool ball, like from playing pool, not like the swimming
pool.
Yeah, much bigger than the thumb version here.
Huge, Wes.
It's huge.
Like it takes your whole hand.
And so it seems to be the people like those Kingston style trackballs for RSI and Drew,
I think you recommended one of those too.
Yeah.
The Kensington Slimblade and it has that gigantic pool ball right in the middle and four buttons
surrounding it.
You twist the ball to scroll up and scroll down.
I think it's much better with the thumb trackballs.
My thumb will get tired and will just kind of get fatigued and sore.
But with this, you know, my wrist is nice and supported and I'm able to roll the ball
with my fingers.
So yeah, my RSI went considerably down to the point where it's pretty much gone.
I decided this time around, I think I'll have a variety of gear because I think one of the
things that helps is changing up what I'm using to work, like not using the same device
for eight hours a day, but moving between computers that have different MES.
And so one of the MES I got is the Logitech MX Vertical.
MX Vertical.
They claimed to have done a ton of research on this and it keeps your wrist in a better
position.
I've seen this in the show notes.
Oh yeah, I've seen these.
Yeah.
It does charge over USB-C, which I'm kind of looking forward to, I think.
It has gotten a lot of positive comments from the audience.
It's a pretty wild looking mouse.
It's like, you know, it looks comfortable.
Just imagining using it, putting your hand in the shape that it is.
It seems, yeah.
All right.
I'm going to give it a go.
I know the big old huge trackballs.
I've used them, you know, as a kid.
I bet I could probably pick it back up again.
I also got wrist pads for the studio keyboards and the one upstairs and that's helped.
I'm trying not to buy a ton of stuff to fix this.
Like the real solution isn't buying stuff.
There's two other things I've done and I'm just kind of hitting pause after that and
seeing where things go.
And the other thing is it's something I've needed to do five years plus is I've decided
to replace my desk and I've ordered a standing desk.
Oh, look at you.
Yeah.
Autonomous.ai has, I don't know why that's the name, but they have a bunch of cool standing
desks.
So I got one of those on the way.
Should be here middle of the month.
This is, I assume, one that you can switch between modes, adjust the height and yeah.
Oh yeah.
And I'm trying to take stretch breaks, trying to get up at least once an hour and move around
and stretch my wrists out and that has helped.
Additionally, and this is not medical advice, but this has just been something that I've
noted has helped is a couple of weeks ago I started trying to take these pill form CBD.
I'm not a medical doctor here, so don't follow my lead.
But over the last two weeks, I started with a couple of pills and now I'm on like four
of them and I'd say it's taken my pain from an eight to like a three and a half.
I was telling Wes, you know, over the years I've tried vitamins, I tried all these different
things and I always end up just stop taking them, but I have not missed a single night
of this because it really, I feel like between the stretching and the increased water consumption
and the breaks and these CBD things, it's helped a lot.
And you know, I don't get like, I'm not all like wacky stoned or anything from them.
It's right.
I mean, all of these are just like, you know, aims to help you work better, you know, be
able to continue to work.
I gotta be honest.
I wasn't planning to come on air and mention that I was trying CBD to help because it feels
embarrassing and makes it, it's very vulnerable for me to even admit that because a lot of
people will take that the wrong way.
But if it's something you've considered, I'm saying it's helped for me.
I did a very, very loose and fast kind of check on research.
Some stuff out there of course says that studies have been done that look like they have really
positive indicators, but you know, you gotta, you gotta follow your own medical doctor's
advice on that kind of stuff, not some podcasters advice.
But for me it's helped and a lot of this gear I've ordered hasn't arrived yet, but I'm hoping
combining it with the vertical mouse and, and trying to come up with a system of stretches
and breaks every morning, I hope we'll do it.
Yeah.
It seems like you're just trying to get in some good habits, you know, just to support
things.
Change the bad habits.
It's so easy cause you know, we have to, you have to be at the computer pretty much all
day to do work, to do show prep.
It's easy to not take that seriously.
But if you were going to do, you know, some, some job where you needed to operate equipment
or you're training for a sport, well you use the right tools and I don't think it's any
different here.
I'm an extreme computer user.
Not always for the best way.
Anyways, I just wanted to kind of put an end cap on that because we've been getting a lot
of feedback and I want to say thank you to everybody.
And please do continue to send it in.
That doesn't necessarily mean you have to stop, but it's been a couple of weeks since
we addressed it.
So I wanted to touch on that.
All right, Wes, let's get into what everybody really seems to be focusing on this week.
And that's boot hole, a rather nasty looking security exploit that involves our good friend
secure boot.
And there's a lots of explanations out there on the web.
We've consolidated some of them for you in the show notes.
So absolutely do feel free to look further, but you found a really good one over on Debian's
website.
And the security team has written a very readable write up.
The readable write up.
Yeah, you know, I just really impressed because there's a lot going on.
You know, the first vulnerability here, there's actually multiple that was found.
There's a white paper out on that.
There's going to be a webinar, all the usual stuff you get when a big security firm finds
stuff.
But they didn't stop there.
You know, the researchers found this problem and kept going to actually turned up a number
of different problems all happening.
But if you remember things about secure boot, it was a big deal.
We talked about it here on the show.
You know, it's kind of a big kerfuffle in the Linux world as that was happening.
But I think we've kind of all forgot about what it is and, you know, why we care.
I got to be honest, that is true because I really rarely deal with it because I'm not
typically buying Windows machines now and trying to put Linux on them.
But my understanding was, is that ultimately Microsoft has to be involved in the signing
process.
And the way this works is only signed code is going to boot in a secure boot environment.
Yeah, you know, it's a way of helping secure the whole boot process of loading up your
computer.
If you imagine the old days, if you didn't have a BIOS password or anything like that
configured, you just walk over, plug in a USB drive and the firmware is happy to, you
know, just into dumb BIOS, just jumps over there, starts running the code and away you
go.
But in the UEFI world, we've got secure boot so that, you know, in theory, maybe you're
at a hotel and someone unscrupulous comes and wants to try to steal information off
your computer.
Well, with secure boot, you've got a chain of trust and you basically tell your firmware,
these are the keys of, you know, people I trust uses public key cryptography and then
it will only boot into stuff that's been signed by those keys.
So in theory, totally fine if you were paranoid about your devices and not that you need to
be paranoid, you know, in use by corporations, anyone who's trying to have secure devices,
you would roll that in the bootloader and only your stuff will run.
But of course, I mean, what, regular users?
They're not going to do this.
So by and large, the implementation and the most way we run into it is that Microsoft
worked out deals so that all the major manufacturers, well, they've enrolled Microsoft's key in
there.
Now, you could remove it and most firmwares allow you to do that, not on ARM, but, you
know, on x86.
But they ship it with Microsoft.
Microsoft is shipped.
And that also means that, you know, in the Linux world, we were like, well, we don't
want to have to tell people to go turn secure boot off as the first step in how do you install
Linux.
That's an awkward thing.
That's already a barrier to entry when we, you know, they already got this far.
They've figured out that they want to try Linux.
All that stuff is no good.
So many of the major distributions worked with Microsoft and got Microsoft to sign with
the Microsoft key, some of our boot infrastructure.
And that way you can just take, you know, your regular old Ubuntu ISO that's signed,
plug it into your new laptop that you picked up from Best Buy, not have to fuss around
with secure boot.
Essentially then in that case, transparent to the end user.
Right.
So that's what was involved and really to respect the standard here, it's all about
maintaining that sequence of boot.
So the firmware is told to trust the keys and then it will only run stuff that's been
signed by those keys.
But everything after that needs to follow the same rules, right?
They have to have a system in place.
Doesn't have to be the same key necessarily, but that needs to have their own set to maintain
that security.
Otherwise, all of it's basically for nothing.
And that set has to be signed by a trusted set.
Right.
I mean, you've got to have trust at each layer so that you load a trusted bootloader, which
then loads the trusted operating system.
And then there's even some, you know, stuff that you have to think about in the OS level
and Linux has these where you lock down the kernel a little bit more so you would only
load signed kernel modules, for example.
Right.
So there can be implications, especially for folks like in the Linux world who want to
go run a bunch of custom stuff.
But if you think about it as an average end user, this is just an added way that at least,
you know, this has been signed by, in theory, an organization you trust because you're running
their operating system.
All right.
So that's a secure boot recap and sort of the value it seems to provide.
And then what happened here is various vulnerabilities in grub, which meant that you could get arbitrary
command execution as a result of grub loading its config file.
And there's some other ones too, but that was the first one figured out.
It's a bug in grub itself.
Right.
So it's parsing the config file, you know, does some bad stuff in memory and boom.
Now the person who maliciously, you know, modified that config file, they've got control
and it's running in a trusted way.
They can load unsigned code.
Okay.
So this is, you know, this would be one way that you might see it is to install a root
kit that you wouldn't notice, you know, secure boot still on.
But because this happened, they were able to take over control of grub for a bit and
install whatever code they wanted.
So this could affect more than just Linux boxes because you could take a live environment
with this vulnerability, plug it into a Windows 10 workstation, a high security Windows 10
workstation, and essentially exploit secure boot.
Even though that machine never ran Linux, never used grub.
But if you just brought a vulnerable grub in a live environment, you could have at it,
right?
Interestingly, there were some issues found in Linux too.
Several not necessarily verified, at least from what Debian writes here, but possibly
could have interviewed to also allow secure boot bypass.
But our friend Jason Doenfeld from the WireGuard project, he managed to fix those.
This is kind of tricky to patch too, because unlike most normal security vulnerabilities
where you just sort of get the new grub or whatever, it doesn't have that flaw anymore.
Some versions that are signed still exist.
And so as part of mitigations, at some point you basically need to take out the old Microsoft
key and add in the new key infrastructure.
And anything aligned with boot updating these sorts of trusted components is tricky.
So is it basically a firmware update for these machines?
Right.
At some point you probably will need firmware updates, things that fix the keys.
And then a whole bunch of components had updates too, right?
So like the FWPT infrastructure, because there's signed versions of those if you want to operate
in a signed way, right?
So you're going to do, there's also the shim that works that fits between EFI and grub,
new grubs that are out without this vulnerability that have to get re-signed.
For most of us, it's not a big deal.
You might not even have secure boot turned on for your computer.
But there's a lot of thought and infrastructure and planning and ceremony that is involved
in all of this.
And it's kind of just embarrassing that our, you know, obviously the Linux community takes
security seriously.
We've sort of had outside parties, in this case Microsoft, it's unfortunate we have to
have that arrangement, but we've sort of had to convince them that, look, we have a secure
stack too.
By trusting us, we're not going to let a bunch of your Windows machines get hacked.
And while I don't know that that's actually happened in the wild or that will happen,
it's just kind of embarrassing.
I am imagining a scenario where there's Windows machines out there that are no longer supported
by the OEM, be it HP or Lenovo or Dell or whoever it might be, and they'll never get
a firmware update.
The other tricky part, too, is once some of those changes happen, old install media that
you might have laying around, well, that won't work anymore because that was signed with
the old key that's no longer trusted.
Oh, right.
So it's just somewhat tricky all around.
You don't have to freak out about it, eventually do these updates.
But, and we'll have an article linked over at ours from our friend Jim Salter kind of
breaking down some of the patches, some of the updates.
Some users have reported problems because, I mean, you know, anything happening, changing
up your boot is tricky.
So just maybe don't rush to apply those or at least do so in an environment with backups
and with time to troubleshoot.
Yeah, this has been a tricky one.
It has left some systems unbootable.
Jim did do a good job of covering that.
I just kind of imagine a parallel universe where the relationship between open source
and Microsoft isn't super cozy and we have serious egg on our face where a flaw in grub
plus some compounding problems in Linux led to essentially a bypass in the secure boot.
Not perfect like intentions or whatever.
Like I've never been a big fan of secure boot, so I'm not like crushed by this.
But it's embarrassing nonetheless.
It's still embarrassing.
It's not like the world ender, but it's embarrassing.
And I'm imagining a scenario where the relationship with Microsoft isn't quite as comfortable
as it is right now.
And Microsoft responds by just saying, we're not doing this anymore.
Or I mean, you could imagine there is some other vendor out there who suddenly, you know,
we have a relationship with a provider who, you know, we want to add this distros key
or whatever.
And it's just harder to make that case now.
Yeah.
We should we should probably also point out that grub is used all over the place by tons
of people.
Probably another one of those projects that really deserves more appreciation and funding
than it gets because it's very useful and critical.
Yeah, I think that's an understatement.
And I think really well put.
So boot hole is really it's this ability to bypass this chain of trust and secure boot
and run untrusted code on any system with secure boot right now that hasn't been updated.
Right.
If you've got a version of grub with this flaw and a computer that's trusting that version
of the Microsoft key, then, yep.
Once you've got grub loaded with a modified config file, you can run whatever you want.
All that work, all that signing, all that fuss for nothing.
Shucks.
Yeah.
So it's it is an interesting story and you can see why it's getting so much attention
right now.
And like Wes said, there will be more information in a in a like a video webinar webinar, thanks.
It hasn't happened yet, so we can't link it to it.
But keep an eye out for that, because by the time you're hearing this, it'll probably be
posted on YouTube.
Yeah.
Another one, too, where, you know, I'm sure at some point they'll have figured out some
of the problems with some of these updates and just go check your local distribution
for more info there.
Well, some interesting valve news has percolated up on the interwebs, and that is they've hired
a full time developer to work on open source graphics for Linux.
Senior developer Tony Wasirka has announced that he is going to be joining Valve to work
on the open source graphics for Linux as part of a general push on improving graphics.
I like to hear that.
Yeah, it seems maybe specifically he's trying to make an impact on the open source AMD GPU
driver project.
He's been a major contributor to the GameCube and Wii emulator Dolphin in the past.
And you know, that really stands out.
That's for a long time there.
The blog has been one of my favorite things to check out just because, I mean, I don't
do graphics programming in that way at all, but workings of these consoles, the intricacies
of the graphic stack.
It's fascinating.
It's so awesome.
And there's a lot of challenges there, so this guy probably knows what he's doing.
I mean, the people that pull those projects off are like some of the elite of the elite,
and he maintained the GPU subsystem and implemented the Direct3D 11 rendering engine, which has
to be some of the hardest work there is for this.
Pretty neat.
I wonder if he's going to do some work on Proton and if the AMD graphics drivers aren't
just going to be seeing a whole bunch of improvements.
Some just landed in 5.8 that came out today, Linux kernel 5.8.
You've got Valve that's hiring a developer to work full time on Linux drivers, including
specifically calling out the AMD graphics stack.
You've got even more improvements coming to the AMD graphics stack in kernel 5.9.
Wow.
I think I need to build myself a new AMD gaming rig.
Yeah, I'll be interested to see where Valve takes this because last time Valve did some
of this, we ended up with Proton.
So we'll see.
That's the Valve news.
While we're kind of talking about gaming stuff, though, Nvidia is making some news that looks
like that deal that we hinted at recently about them snatching up the ARM division from
SoftBank is like looking real serious right now, looking close, like it's actually going
to happen.
And a principal analyst over at Trius Research said that if the merger goes through, it will
be a disaster.
This will defect from ARM and more ARM customers will start looking at RISC-V, to which I say,
yes, please.
All right.
Maybe we're fine with this.
How do we feel about Nvidia snatching up ARM?
I don't feel good about this at all.
I think that what we're going to see here is people are going to get very, very concerned
very quickly about ARM being owned by a primary licensee.
I mean, it could be a history repeats itself kind of moment, like what happened with Intel
and x86.
I mean, because in the 80s, there were multiple 80s and early 90s, there were multiple sources
of x86 CPUs.
Today there's just AMD and Intel.
And that's only because they have each other at gunpoint, essentially.
And Nvidia is not a good player in the ecosystem.
They generally do not help contribute to the advancement and the development of standards
to support applications in gaming, as well as in professional GP GPU cases and things
like that.
After 10 years, CUDA is still a closed thing.
It seems like a clear move for ongoing licensing revenue, first of all, and maybe cornering
the market a bit more and a turning point for ARM as a platform, I think.
It will not change the current momentum around around ARM.
It just won't because one of the problems that the industry has is that they like to
capitulate to the strongest tech company.
And when you look at that with even in the hardware space, you know, people talk very
highly of Nvidia because their technology works, quote unquote, the best.
But that's largely due to a lot of work they've done on the backroom side, making everybody
like conform to their protocols, their standards, optimizing for their drivers and stuff like
that.
And it has shorted out all the competitors in the graphics space.
And I think the same thing would essentially happen with the CPU space with the ARM ecosystem.
But the thing is, nobody can peel back that investment.
And moving to risk five would be a recipe for disaster for most companies, because the
hardware industry, unlike the software one, operates on such tight margins that redoing
everything would take literally years to figure out the investment profile, much less try
to actually do it.
I think that's very true.
I think the existing momentum that people have invested in ARM isn't going to change.
It can't change.
The phone mobile ecosystem isn't going to change.
I think the turning point will be in considering ARM as a platform that you're safe to build
your business around.
I think that's a shift.
Once it changes again, once it changes hands like this again, something, I think, changes
in the way people perceive it.
I don't know if it's going to change really much in terms of how many Samsung phones ship
with an ARM processor.
I don't think that'll be affected one little bit.
But future projects, things people are tinkering with, I wonder.
I really don't feel very positive about any of it right now.
Part of me kind of just hopes Intel pulls out of this downward spin, and we just move
into an AMD Intel world.
I'd be OK with x86 for another couple of generations.
At least let me get to my 50s.
I just can't get that image of Linus making a certain symbol when referencing Nvidia out
of my head.
Yeah, there's that.
There's that, too.
I think there's that history there.
Maybe that might be informing a bit of my reaction to this news.
I think that's very likely.
Maybe if I was a RGB gamer and I had three Nvidia cards in my extreme Twitch gaming box,
I would feel differently about it.
But sitting here right now looking at the momentum around AMD graphics and AMD CPUs
and the challenges like we've covered just recently in our ARM episode, I'm not feeling
particularly great about it.
Something though that does make me smile is Pine's invitation to get some input on a physical
keyboard, a Nokia N900 style keyboard, if that invokes a certain image.
What?
Yeah, it's really kind of a neat idea of a little QWERTY keyboard that's totally portable
that would make an SSH session really practical on a mobile device.
And it can be integrated with a case where it slides up or down.
I think this is neat.
And they say they're in talks with a number of hardware vendors regarding this N900 style
slide-out keyboard design for the Pine phone.
It won't be thin enough, Chris.
Yeah, I'm really glad that they're not hung up on that at all in this because there are
so many of us out there that are perfectly happy throwing an extended battery pack on
their iPhone.
I haven't done it with this one, but iPhones in the past, I go get the big old fat battery
pack and it like triples the thickness and weight of the thing.
Or people are putting the pop sockets on the back.
You know, there's all...
It's not super minimal.
And actually, in a way, it's kind of perfect if you can pop it all off and then you have
a fairly thin...
I mean, you have the Pine phone right there.
That fits in the pocket just fine.
Totally fine.
It would be like having a Nexus in your pocket.
It's like the small Nexus size, like the Nexus 6-ish.
And your pocket's big, but it's not too big.
But then you can snap these accessories on that actually make it a functional device.
And as these things get more powerful, and as in the case of the Pine phone, the operating
systems are more sophisticated, I love seeing these kind of things.
And so I think it's early days, as a lot of this stuff is when we talk about this, but
they're looking for feedback and they have some suggested design ideas and they have
a form thread set up on it.
So we'll have a link to that in the show notes.
I could see it.
I could see it one day all kind of coming together.
It just makes me so excited that we've got, you know, manufacturing capability in a manufacturing
company that's interested in thinking outside the box, making some of these projects that,
okay, maybe they don't appeal to a wider audience, but then we don't need that.
We'll find out.
Maybe they'll sell millions.
Maybe.
I don't know.
I mean, if you think about it, anybody that has infrastructure they need to maintain,
you could make the case at the price point for the Pine phone, if it is your day job
to keep systems online, you could make the case that you could have a daily driver that
is your Android or your iPhone, and then you've got this with you in the bag or in the pocket.
If you need to just bust something out, that's got a mobile data connection, that's got a
fully complex operating system with terminal and all that and a keyboard, people walk around
with Mac book and iPads all day.
Maybe us Linux users will do something similar, but just thousands of dollars cheaper would
be our style.
All right.
Well, a little bit of housekeeping here before we go on.
Join us next week live if you can, because we're doing another classic chat room attacks
episode.
We've come across the old JB device from the hardware archive, and we're going to give
it a full refurb, load it up with a modern OS, and then open it up to the chat room for
quote load testing and quote.
I love these.
So join us next week if you can, because you'll get a chance to punish one of our machines.
We need your help.
Right.
And now if you don't know when we're live, you can get it converted to your local time
zone via robots at Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar.
It's over at JB live dot TV noon Pacific, and you can just come on over.
We start the show up usually like the live stream usually starts 20 30 minutes before
the actual show.
We get music playing and we get on there, start chatting.
Sometimes like this week we started like 15 minutes late because we were goofing around.
You get to hang on all of that and then also get to help punish the system and name the
show.
Like a whole extra show.
It is.
So check us out over at Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar for the time and JB
live dot TV is where it's streamed at.
And also a reminder for the luck lug.
I was hanging out in the luck lug this Sunday while I was out working on the storage bays
of lady jupes.
So I'm like, I'm carrying the phone in my pocket and I'm like spraying stuff and scratching
down rust stuff and painting over stuff and chatting with the luck lug about cellular
antennas and all the kind of stuff.
It was pretty good, pretty good couple hours with the chatting and I got a lot done, took
a break during some books.
I ran out of Rustoleum and then got back at it.
It was good.
So you can join us too.
The luck lug is on Sundays at noon Pacific and it's in the same mumble room we use for
the show.
We just do it up in the lobby.
So you just have to have the open source mumble software.
Pretty easy to have it for the phone too.
They have for the phone too.
Don't tell anybody though.
We don't tell people about that.
No.
All right, well this week we're going to tell you about our favorite headphones on Linux
for like meetings or joining the mumble room.
This would be, these would be great headphones potentially to jump into the luck lug on Sunday.
I also wanted something.
That's actually why I bought mine.
I bought mine specifically for the luck lug and then I wanted to start using them for
zoom meetings and whatnot and the requirements were something that works really well with
Linux and I think for you and I at least, we'll see where Drew falls down.
I think that's going to be an interesting one, but where for you and I, I think we both
wanted wireless.
Right.
So you have the newer version of ones that I tried a couple, like maybe a year and a
half ago, the Jabra Elite Active 65Ts.
These are no bigger than AirPods.
Right.
That's it.
I mean then they're very much marketed as, you know, competitor Android version of the
AirPods.
Although of course they'll work with iOS too.
Yeah, they're not bad.
You know, they, there are newer ones now.
There's also the 75T.
I don't know why they don't make the, you know, the version in between, but that's not
my business.
And we should probably say the price upfront, they're $120.
So they're cheaper than AirPods, but they're not like super economical.
Yeah.
You'll see them on sale sometimes.
Or actually I bought a refurbished pair just because, hey, why not?
Even though they might've been in somebody else's ear balls.
Well, and then I immediately dropped them on the floor and one of my dogs tried to chew
on it.
I was like, these are not, these are not necessarily pristine, but that's kind of the point is
that, you know, I've already gotten some nice audio equipment, nice headphones and nice
microphone.
And I just wanted something that was a little more convenient where, you know, maybe I'm
not the star of the show for this particular meeting, but I want to be able to get up,
walk to the kitchen, make myself a snack or go deal with the dogs barking at something.
They're not bad.
I was definitely inspired.
I think I'd seen you and some other folks I know with AirPods and that looked very convenient.
Audio quality.
Well, you got to make sure you switch it, you know, into the high quality audio playback
mode, which I will say having used it both on a Mac and Linux sort of struck me as just
how these things go with Mac and Linux because on Mac it figures out if you're recording,
you know, it figures out like, oh, are you trying to talk?
Do you have an application that needs to, it needs an audio input?
Oh yeah.
Okay.
Well then you'll be in headset mode.
If not, then you'll just automatically switch to high quality playback mode.
Although sometimes it gets that wrong.
So it's perfect.
Beautiful.
When it works.
On the Linux side, there may be ways to make it automatically switch.
I've not investigated that because you just go in pulse.
It's an option on the device, super simple, easy, and you can configure it yourself.
So I like that.
And I was actually kind of impressed.
They're a little bassy for my taste, but the audio quality just for playback, watching,
you know, watching a YouTube video at my desk or just listening to stuff.
Totally fine.
Yeah.
For listening.
Totally usable.
Yeah.
Where things fall down a little bit.
Come in Levi.
This is Charlie.
Repeat Levi.
Come in Levi.
This is Charlie.
I found the truth.
Okay.
I'd say that's phone quality.
That's it.
It's phone quality.
And it's definitely noticeable if, you know, you're switching from a different mic or honestly
these days, even just like the phone on my pixel three, the microphone built in, I mean,
to the, to the handset itself is better.
Is better.
Yeah.
And that's a little embarrassing.
Although if you're, you know, for me and I think for you too, I wanted something that
was totally just like, I just got to chime in a couple of times in a, in a work meeting
and I'm not running the meeting.
I'm not talking a whole lot.
I'm doing a lot of, yeah, or I think so's or yeah, we can definitely look into that.
Exactly.
And it does totally work for that, for something you just really easy to pop in.
So when you pop them in, does it auto connect or do you have to go into the Bluetooth settings
in like say Linux and connect them each time?
You know, it depends on the operating system and how you've configured it, of course.
But yeah, for the most part it just, it just automatically connects, no problem.
I did run into an issue and I think this might've just been an issue with the device itself
is I paired it from the same machine with the same Bluetooth hardware ID and everything,
but from two different distros.
And after that I had to keep repairing it with those though I was able to do like a
factory reset on it that fixed it, which makes me think it was a problem with just being
confused about all, you know, all these devices, which made me having repaired it a whole bunch
of times before I bothered to do that, made me suddenly have opinions.
I really actually kind of liked Gnome's Bluetooth settings more than I do in the plasma world.
I'm going to jump ahead to mine because mine is about accomplishing a lot of that and totally
avoiding Bluetooth, which I think is now the way to go.
I wasn't sure I was, these were recommended to me by the Luplug and I went with the Corsair
Void RGB Elite Wireless Gaming Headset.
That's a horrible name and RGB, I don't know about that.
It does have a logo on it that changes color.
But the thing that is fantastic about these is, now these are not earbuds, I will disclaim
they're full over ear headphones, but Wes, no Bluetooth, but they're still wireless.
How does that work?
Well, Wes, it's good old fashioned RF and I think they sound lovely.
Let me play you a little audio sample I recorded this morning here at the studio, just to give
you a sense of what it's like when you're outside a studio environment, you're just
in a, in like a working office environment.
Here's the audio quality.
Ah, the freedom of true mobility.
The Corsair Void RGB Elite Wireless Gaming Headset for the connoisseuring pup who likes
to game a little bit, but maybe also has a pup day job.
The Corsair Void RGB Elite Wireless Push Hard on the gaming angle, but I don't really see
it.
They're all black, nice design, very comfortable to wear, and everybody needs a good headset
and microphone from time to time with today's video calls and whatnots, and this certainly
seems to fit the bill.
I really like the way they feel on the head, not too tight, but they're not going anywhere.
If you got the zoomies, they're not flying off.
But additionally, they sound fantastic.
Music sounds incredible on these.
But let's talk about the real feature, RF wireless, true mobility.
I'm up.
I'm moving.
Let's do a live demo.
I'm in my studio office upstairs in the JB One studio, and I'm going to walk out into
the foyer and move about.
But now as I continue to move across the foyer, I'm into another office space, multiple walls
between us, yet we are still communicating.
But friends, let's be honest.
If you're an entrepreneurial pup, easy for me to say, and you're going in and out of
zoom meetings all day, like I find myself, you want something that lets you sneak away
for those important moments.
Well an RF wireless headset means if you've got to go potty during a meeting, no problem,
because one of the features that I absolutely love about the Corsair is the way the microphone
mutes.
You can push to mute.
So when you're ready to flush, you can just simply push up on the microphone, notice,
and no one's the wiser that you were just flushing.
It has a nice little chime when it mutes and a nice little soft chime when it unmutes.
So you can sneak off and do nature's business without anybody knowing.
Ultimately, while the mobility is great and I can sit here and yack my face off while
walking around the studio, I think my favorite feature is how fricking easy it worked with
Linux.
I'm going to throw this thing that right there was me throwing the box because it works so
damn good.
I plugged it in.
Linux sees everything, even the full name of the device, Corsair wireless gaming.
And it shows an analog connection and a digital connection.
So if you want to try messing around with that seven point one surround sound fake audio,
you can.
If you just want things to work, you just want a simple stereo audio device that's available
to both show up to pulse audio.
And I think that might be my favorite part.
Plug it in, turn it on, and it just goes.
And because the USB dongle is always persistent, Linux always sees my audio device.
Even if I don't necessarily need to hear sound, I don't want my headphones on.
It's still there.
So my settings aren't changing all the time.
The USB device is always there, even if I'm not using the headphones.
So if I have, say, like something start playing and I want to hear it, I just grab the headphones,
turn them on, and everything's already going.
No settings to change, no Bluetooth device to connect, none of that fussy stuff.
It's just always on.
It's always working because it's a physical USB device that's the actual sound card.
And then it does all the RF magic for you.
I think these are keepers.
These are going to be my go to headsets, gaming or not.
I really got to say, the thing that I love about them is that the device is always on.
It's always there because I leave the dongle plugged in 24-7.
So there's essentially the pulse audio.
The sound device is always there.
It's always there.
No crazy change in a default, no switcheroo.
It's none the wiser if the headphones are on or off.
So I can just have my sound device always available, and then I just flip them on.
The other thing I like about it, and you could hear a little bit there in the clip, is because
it's analog, it actually tends to degrade a little bit more elegantly.
When I'm walking to the other room, you can start to hear a few pops and drops, and there's
actually a channel switch pop in there towards the very end of that clip.
So you have those analog drawbacks, but at the same time, it means instead of my cutting
out audio, you just sort of get slightly degraded.
Continuous degradation.
Yeah.
And I do really like the fact that when you flip up the microphone, the little blue light
on the microphone turns off and has a really soft little tone in the headset that it plays
to let you know.
You stop.
Yeah.
So if you've got to take a potty break, no big deal.
It's right there.
You just flip it right up.
You don't have to embarrass yourself.
And it's comfortable.
I can wear it all day long if I need to.
It is also slightly cheaper because it's not fancy earbuds, right?
It's a big over-ear.
Yeah.
What are we talking about here?
$99.99.
Oh.
Yeah.
So I would probably, I've got to imagine I'll use these for five years, and I would buy
these same, these, when it comes to headphones, if you find the right headphones, I try to
buy the same one.
I know it works.
Yeah.
Why change it?
These are my go-tos now.
I hope they don't drop them.
I did think you sounded pretty good, although maybe a little congested.
Yeah.
Is that, you think, the microphone?
I mean, it was just a couple hours ago.
It's a small capsule, so I would imagine it's, but it's not awful.
I think it's a step up from yours.
Oh, definitely.
If you're doing a lot of the talking, or you want to sound really professional, I don't
think it's adequate enough, and I bet you that's where Drew could probably help us out
a little bit.
Yeah.
My impression is that it wasn't a full range signal that it's pushing through, so you're
definitely missing some frequencies in like the high mids.
They're just gone.
So that's why you sound so nasally is because you're not getting your full voice.
Now one thing that I will say is that in the pro audio world, when you see people walking
around with like wireless mics on stage and stuff like that, they're all RF.
So this is using technology that is tried and true in the pro audio space, which is
great.
You know, RF is also going to go through walls a lot better than Bluetooth, as you demonstrated.
It's a great technology for audio.
I highly, highly recommend RF if you're going to go wireless.
You know, Bluetooth is fine for super short range stuff, especially if you have like a
good strong connection, but it's not going to beat RF for straight audio.
Yeah.
And then also you don't have all of the Bluetooth pairing trickery or management that you have
to do with it either.
Just plug it in and go.
Do you do anything below a professional grade microphone?
Does Drew go out and buy a cheap headset microphone ever?
No.
Well, for this, I actually did dig out my old collarbone set like Logitech.
It's an old one.
They don't even sell it anymore, Bluetooth headset that I used to use on mobile back
when I would have to go visit clients and stuff and, you know, be working on computers
and answer a call.
So I had, you know, this hands-free thing and I wanted to see how well it would work
on Linux connecting over Bluetooth.
I did get it paired.
They're just fine and playback worked fine.
The audio quality was great, but the input didn't work.
I could select it in Pulse and as soon as I hit record, the application that was trying
to record would just freeze up and I tried this out in multiple different applications
that record straight from Pulse Audio.
Every single one of them had the same issue.
Just hit record, boom, it's done.
The application is no longer responding.
So total fail on recording for that.
So the microphone did not work and I don't really think it's a Bluetooth issue.
I think it's a headset issue.
I think it's just too old because I've had issues with it on the phone recently too.
Last time I tried it, I had to, you know, stop using it and go straight to the handset.
These days for me, I've got a professional mic in my booth and at my desk and I've got
professional grade headphones in my booth and at my desk.
So yeah, you do have noticed what reason do I have to have yet another headset just for
hands free wireless, blah, blah, blah.
I don't.
So no.
Well, and it's something you were saying in the pre-show and I think it's worth considering.
One option is to just buy one microphone by and buy it once and get a good one and use
it for everything.
I specifically was looking for something that I could get up and walk around with because
I mean just so many of these now and I'm trying not to sit there at my desk all day.
But I like that point that you made.
And there are, we'll link to some microphones that are quote unquote professional grade
that are like a hundred dollars that are a good starting point.
You know, it's funny.
That's basically what I've ended up doing is for calls that I want slightly better audio,
but I'm still not having to talk all the time is I just plug in my USB mic at my desk and
then I switch the headphones to just high quality playback mode so I can still go get
up, you know, refresh my beverage.
I just have to sit at my desk if I actually want to talk, but I sound great.
I will try to remember to put a link to the USB microphone that I like.
They're all in the same range and we'll put a link to a professional grade mic that starts
about around a hundred dollars and then links to these headsets.
I really liked this Corsair for just using my computer as well.
I actually edited the audio for it on there just to hear what it sounded like and I thought
it did a pretty decent representation.
Oh, that's great.
I then listened on my studio monitor speakers where there was a difference, but you know,
in terms of just like enjoying music and playing video games, these headsets are really good.
I really liked it.
So, and the sound was better than I expected.
So I like it.
It seems like a kind of a sweet spot and you know, just usable.
You can use it for multiple purposes, comfortable, sounds good, and a good audio quality on
long recording.
Boy, listen though.
Like what is really sticking with me is the beauty of these RF devices is it's a USB audio
interface that's detected by Linux and it's always there and it just works.
No pairing, no Bluetooth involved at all, just works.
Well, you know, I had to learn in this experimenting that I guess we've switched and now the Bluetooth,
the main Bluetooth implementation is done in Pulse and not in Allset.
You can still set that up if you want, but of course I was planning to record with Jack
and things got more complicated than I want.
So I've been down in the bowels pulling around with Pulse Audio loopback devices and virtual
syncs trying to get what's a simple, you know, simple mix situation and Jack going in Pulse
Audio so that I can play music while using my Bluetooth speakers on a Zoom call and it's
been way more direct than I anticipated.
So tell me a little bit about that because I think ultimately are you saying you could
send music into the Zoom call?
Yeah.
You're sending systems.
You know, playback a YouTube video and then have that and my mic go into the Zoom call
as me.
All in Pulse?
No Jack audio?
No Jack audio because again, I would have had to figure out some routing between Pulse
and Jack.
Right.
Pulse can do this?
Pulse can do this.
What's the secret sauce there?
Well, you kind of have to bust out the command line and start loading Pulse modules yourself.
That's not too hard.
Zoom makes it a little more complicated too in particular.
So you can basically make these virtual syncs, which is kind of what it sounds like, a place
to send audio that doesn't have to be a real device, and then you can use loopbacks to
connect them.
I'll have linked to a nice blog post that was written up with the intention of recording
from a video game while you were talking.
That works fine.
In their case, they were playing it back through a Google meeting, you know, of RTC in the
browser and that's not as picky about what it treats as a microphone.
But Zoom wants to see some kind of thing that isn't virtual anyway.
So I was able to find a great Stack Overflow write-up that actually uses an audio cleanup
filter inside Pulse to get rid of echoes that Zoom accepts.
So it sets up another layer of abstraction that basically tricks Zoom into thinking that
you're sending it from a real stuff, but it totally works.
I'm surprised to hear that Zoom even has any facilities to detect virtual audio devices
on Linux and then choose which ones it accepts and which ones it doesn't.
That seems like more work than I would expect.
It lists it, but won't let you choose it, and if you change it in Bavu Control, it just
changes it right back.
Oh, yeah.
It's a...
Really?
Uh-huh.
I was surprised to see that.
They've put thought into this.
They don't want you using it this way, I don't think.
No.
That's interesting.
But you could use the same trick, I guess, to do only Pulse audio routing to, say, take
a video game capture and send it to OBS for streaming.
Yep.
And the guides are really nicely done.
The one aimed at video games has a neat diagram and a sort of method you can apply to work
out.
Like, you list all your devices, you circle ones that are actually hardware, you draw
some arrows between them, and then connect all the arrows.
You basically open Bavu Control and assign, like, okay, this goes to this virtual sync,
this one goes here, and at the end, your audio routes correctly.
And so, ultimately, Zoom is pointing at virtual devices that you could change what's going
to them at any time.
So you could switch out microphones or whatever you want and never have to change Zoom.
Yeah, and then Bavu Control is just a mixer console where you can, you know, slide things
for the virtual stuff.
So you can either lower your mic or you could lower the mix, you know, the one that has
both of them.
Yeah, it worked surprisingly well.
I kept wanting to play back sound clips when I was in the meeting with friends, right?
Of course, who doesn't?
And I was just playing them on my phone in front of the microphone because I didn't have
a better solution.
And I just kept thinking to myself, like, in Jack, this would be so simple.
You know, I already have it all set up.
So I was just neat to see that Pulse is more capable than we give it credit for, even if
the ergonomics are terrible.
Yeah, I'd love to hear others' audio tricks or solutions they've had to come up with for
more virtual calls that everybody is doing.
Telegram is probably the best place for it.
Jupiterbroadcasting.com.com.
Join the group there and chat with us about your audio hackery.
So how long did it take you to wire all that up?
I mean, that was definitely...
I was very distracted for the first hour of that call, let's just say.
You're doing a dirty call.
Well, I wanted the reveal, you know, where it just like comes out as me.
Because you can share audio in Zoom, but then it shares to everyone and only the host, you
know, they can configure who can do that.
No rules for me.
Nobody ever...
Who wants a soundboard, right?
So we have some feedback from Marvin, and he points out about a neat little tool in
MX Linux that I don't think we've ever shared with the audience.
And it seemed worth talking about.
He says, hey guys, recently you mentioned the snapshot capability of Fedora and how
it nearly protects against OS killing disasters.
Well, there's no facility for that yet, but there could be one day.
OpenSUSE works to have that and so is Ubuntu with CFS.
He says, I think your listeners would benefit to know that MX Linux also has a snapshot
feature sort of like this.
With MX Linux, an ISO of the complete installation can be made on demand.
In the event of any trouble, your system can be reinstalled exactly as it was at the time
of making the ISO.
This saves a ton of time.
And all the customizations and software that I did are instantly available again.
I think it's just one of these awesome features that are making MX Linux so popular today.
You know, it's really interesting.
I find myself thinking to myself, gosh, I would hate to have to do that, like just not
wanting to do it that way.
But at the same time, that seems great for just a consumer.
And you know, here's a simple backup step you can do, save this on a flash drive that
you know, or two of them that you store in a drawer and somewhere else, now you've got
your backups.
You know, what I used to do for family is I would give them a Linux box.
And then essentially something kind of like this.
And it's first it was I would tape a CD in a sleeve to the inside of their PC case.
And then towards the end, it was I'd tape the thumb drive inside the case.
And then in case of emergency, you break the seal and you restore.
And so you could easily accomplish that with this feature.
And I really like that because that's sort of the my Hail Mary remote tech support solution
back in the day was break the seal, reload the machine.
And I knew because I had made that custom snapshot that it would get them back to a
state where I could remote support them.
You could do that with this.
It'd be a pretty good way to go.
He says also, he threw this in at the end.
He says there's so much to like about Fedora, I agree.
But DNF is a total deal breaker.
It's so slow.
They just can't stand it.
They need to work on that before anything else, in my opinion, he says, glad you made
it home safely.
Keep up the good work, Marvin, them fighting words about DNF.
I love it.
It's slow because it's sound.
All right.
It's doing a good job of updating your system.
I'll tell you what.
It's slow because it gets it right.
And if you want to see you want to see painfully slow, check out brew on Mac OS.
However, I'll also add this.
We always talk about how fast Pac-Man is and yay in those tools.
But when you stop and pay attention to how many frickin questions by default the arch
tools ask you, obviously you can configure them or flag them so they don't.
But by default, like you're getting 20 questions before you install like five packages on some
of these things.
And so if you think about the actual time it takes, I think DNF may not be so bad and
probably would have fared better when you upgraded that box, not in a team accession
the other the other week.
Probably would have.
And then also there was I was doing an update upstairs just the other day when gnome crashed
on me.
Right.
And I ended up reloading my machine.
I've had some bad luck recently, Wes.
I'm just going to skip updates for a while.
I'm just going to just let things take more snapshots.
I'll just let them sit, I think.
Well, you know me.
That's not true at all.
In fact, I come in on the weekends and I update machines.
I just something about it.
I love fresh, free software.
I always have.
And it's kind of like, you know, something you cross off the list.
Oh, yeah, I updated all my machines today.
It does feel like I'm taking care of stuff.
I'm doing my maintenance.
I'm I'm being a good custodian, if you will, of my systems.
Well, that brings us to the end of today's unplugged.
We'd love to have you join us live next week for that live punishment test because we need
as much traffic as our little Comcast connection will handle.
We actually got pretty far last time, so it has fared fairly well.
Did you know this show is on Twitter for new release announcements and other things at
Linux Unplugged.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
I'm at Chris Lass.
He's at Westpane.
Right.
Or is it at Noble?
I can't remember.
It's at Westpane.
Why don't I remember that?
I should just have it on a sticky right here.
Really?
I could just put it on a sticky.
Remember, Wes is at Westpane.
Or you just ask me.
Could do that.
It could just be a bit that we do now at this point.
Who really knows?
But I do know this.
I'll see you next Tuesday.
Bye.
Now, I definitely saw in the chat room while we were talking about MX Linux's ISO restore
mode that several people were mentioning other distros like Puppy do this as well.
So what's a what's a pretty well-known tool?
Is there one that all these distros are using or they all roll it themselves?
So the Mandrake family had Drac Snapshot, which evolved into its own tool called Make
Live CD, which became My Live CD.
The current descendant of the Mandrake family that still uses this is PC Linux OS.
So you can respin from a PC Linux OS system.
You can respin the whole system as an ISO that you can then use somewhere else.
So that one exists there.
And of course, Puppy Linux has its own tool.
The problem with making one that's generic is that since every distro does their plumbing
layers a little bit differently, well, every distro family, that is, of course, yeah, every
distro family does their plumbing layers a little differently.
These tools generally cannot be shared.
I still just really like using my friend Clonezilla.
Clonezilla is just recently been updated back in May.
It's still a project is still going strong.
And it is like my universal like go to for when I for when I receive a review machine,
I try to do a Clonezilla.
Right.
Also, with regards to DNF speed or whatever, DNF is getting rewritten into C++ for DNF
version five, which is coming hopefully this fall.
Boy, Fedora is going to be getting to be a spicy meatball.
I tell you what.
Why not in Rust?
Oh, no.
No, no, no.