Okay, I've been waiting since we hit the record button I wanted to ask both of you what your naming conventions are for your home
Machines on your land and drew I want to start with you. I
Named them after astronauts
so the laptop that I'm using right now is Aldrin and then I've got you know Grissom is my phone and
Lovell is my tower. That's clever
That's pretty good and not too far off from mine
If you want to switch it up, like say you've got some servers off somewhere. You can just choose a different mission
That's pretty good. Okay, Wes, what about you?
Star Trek ships, of course, and I always make sure to name my admin account
Oh do mine feel kind of boring now in retrospect because I don't have a ton of machines on my land
I named my machines after the moons of Jupiter of which there are many
So the computer I'm talking to you on is just really simple
I oh just I oh and so it's like one of my favorite host names to connect to because it's very short
Hello friends and welcome in to get another fresh episode of your unplugged program. My name is Chris. My name is Wes
Hello, Wes and hello drew. Hello. Hello
Oh gentlemen, we have a fine show today. We solved a problem. They said would cost thousands of dollars
This is one of those episodes where we'll often talk about the pros and cons of commercial platforms
But this is one of those things that Linux does that the other OS is can't touch
Wes and I have come up with a couple of clever ways to use a Raspberry Pi to bond multiple LTE connections
into either a load balanced failover or we'll even talk about a way you can completely bond them and
To sort of prove a point. I am broadcasting from the woods today
So we'll talk about that plus we have community news and all of that to get into I want to say
Thank you to a cloud guru
This episode is brought to you by the all-new cloud grew the leader in learning for cloud Linux and other modern tech skills
Hundreds of courses and thousands of hands-on labs get certified get hired and get learning at a cloud guru
Com and also made possible by our core contributors. Thank you to our members
I'll give you an update on that a little bit in the show as well. But also time-appropriate greetings to the mumble room
I was late on the draw there. So I wanted to get you get you guys in before we went too far
I appreciate I appreciate you being good sports about it. Hello everybody good to talk to you
Let's start off with some community news that I'm pretty elated to talk about and that is Lenovo has begun rolling out
Their Fedora Linux laptops and Ubuntu ones are coming soon
The first models are appearing with Fedora as an option. The first one being the ThinkPad x1 Carbon Gen 8
Not only has it rolled out with Fedora, but it's right there front and center and it's also the best price and
Best of all, it doesn't come with a whole bunch of bloat as to quote the Fedora team Lenovo respects our open-source principles
The only software they will have is from the included repositories. No extra fluff now so far
It looks like you'll have to be in the US to get one of these but fingers crossed that more markets come soon
I love that. It's vanilla Fedora. I think that's really great gaming on Linux has a great write-up and
Liam writes we also know from what's already been said to expect Fedora Linux to be rolled out to the ThinkPad p1 gen 2 and
The ThinkPad p53. It seems like Ubuntu is not too far off either and will probably land on the ThinkPad x1 Carbon
Gen 8 soon and then other systems as well
Love this. This is pretty exciting
This is like the moment, you know where we start to see real Linux adoption happen at the OEM level
Neal it's available in other places outside the US you're saying so when I talked to
Mark Pearson who's the Lenovo guy who's managing this relationship with Fedora?
He it's it's a matter of getting all the web teams for each of the individual regions to update
There's the websites to get them showing up
It is available in the web portals for the United States and Canada today
It is available through
Telesales or basically if you call them it's available globally. It will show up in the web portals are in various regions
I think over the course of the next couple of weeks or so, but don't hold me to that
I don't know for sure. I don't work for Lenovo. Yeah, sure. No, no, very good
Good to know it does remind me drew that there's been some background
Projects getting in place to kind of make this a first-class experience. Yeah, I think it's worth mentioning that
Lenovo were some fairly early adopters of the LVFS project, too
So this has been a long time coming and they've been fairly good community members in my opinion
Just in the fact that they did launch into that LVFS system so early in the process
It's nice to see you know, like some formal support too because what so many of us have been using these as great Linux
Laptops for years and seems like Lenovo's finally caught on that. Hey, yeah people love this stuff. Yeah, there is that aspect
It's like yeah catch up guys. Come on
but what do we think this means for the vendors that have shown up for Linux and been here for
Maybe like a decade like system 76. Is this gonna hurt them? Do you think I don't know if hurt would be the right word
I think it's good for the overall community that we have more choice
but it does
Maybe say a little something about the vendors who have been doing this for a long time
Are they going to be sidelined now that you know Dell and Lenovo are both offering, you know, first-class Linux support. I
Don't know. I'm hoping not because I'd like to see things like, you know, tuxedo and system 76 continue to thrive
and
I kind of doubt that that's really going to impact them too largely just because
Well system 76 is still a big player in our community, you know, and I looked at these laptops
There's like the advocate in me. That's like I need to put an order in
my Linux laptop was supplied by a cloud guru and
So I need you know, I'm like I would really like to have a Linux laptop
I would very much like to have one but when I look at the lineup
Even though I'm compelled to like support this initiative. I've always believed in voting with my wallet, you know right now
Like these first three months of JB being indie or like the just most critical
Like if I can survive these three months and then make it the next six months and then make it to the year mark like
That's gonna be a real accomplishment. So I it's like I really I'm really in a hard spot
I look at it and like it just doesn't quite do enough for me
Now this isn't an ad. This is totally just my opinion, but I look at something like the oryx pro and I think
That's a lot more meat on that bone. And if I'm only going to be able to spend my very limited funds once I
Get a lot more for that dollar from something like the oryx pro
Maybe it'd be maybe because for me like a GPU is kind of important if I only have you know one machine like that
You're probably also going to get you know things like a better support experience. Yes
Lenovo is now supporting Linux directly on these systems, but you know
It's a big organization with supporting multiple different platforms and operating systems versus, you know
A smaller shop like system 76 with where Linux is what they do and they're all passionate about it
Well and Lenovo is pretty new to supporting Linux, too
So, you know, what's the quality going to be I'm not saying it's bad. I'm just saying it's an unknown, right?
They're gonna be figuring some of that out still
Yeah, and I tend to agree with you here. I've been a longtime ThinkPad user, but especially lately
It feels like you've been getting less bang for your buck with the Lenovo models than you would with say a smaller distributor
I still think it's significant because it it is a brand legitimization
It is an option that a lot of developers are going to be comfortable with and enterprises
But there should be some knock-on upstream effects that might help the other OEMs as well right now the advantage of having a big
OEM like Lenovo directly and properly supporting it
Linux in a very direct way
Across the globe is that they are directing all of their suppliers to also support Linux the right way
That is driving them to move work upstream
Contribute to the correct projects get their drivers in there make sure the hardware enablements there it shifts the prioritization
For their suppliers to like, you know, I I still hold out a tiny flame of hope
You know
It's very small flame of hope that Nvidia could be convinced to make their open source drivers for Nvidia cards work a lot better and
and my hope is that because
Lenovo is such a big user of Nvidia cards on all of their professional lines and
Two of the professional lines that are going to come with Fedora later on are going to have Nvidia cards in them that it might help
You know drive this case towards we should better support Linux out of the gate rather than you know
this crap situation that we're all stuck in right now and
That's good for Lenovo. That's good for the Linux consumer
But it's also good for all the smaller OEMs that just don't have
The purchasing power and the might to get a part supplier to respect them and then to be frank
I love a lot of what system 76 does
But they just don't have that might that is required to force the supplier to do things the right way and Lenovo does
And like I hoped, you know ten years ago when Dell was starting to do this project Sputnik that they would do the same thing
It hasn't panned out to the degree that I'd hoped for
It will be interesting to see if we see any messaging from Dell in response to this
Poppy I feel like I want to go to you to get some historical thoughts on these think pads and these Lenovo's
Officially launching these Linux lines and if we zoom out in in a few months, we'll have Ubuntu versions as well
What do you think about all this? Well, obviously I love the idea that my preferred laptop vendor of choice you
Yeah, I know right I'm making it easy for me to make that purchasing decision and later this year I get my
Laptop refresh money from my employer and I get to choose which laptop I'm gonna spend my money on and obviously I'm gonna spend my money
on a laptop from a vendor that supports Linux and so there's now choice I get a laptop refresh
amount of money every three years and
Every three years there are more places that I could spend those dollars. I'm delighted by this obviously that is an interesting
Measuring stick, you know when you come up for air every three years to start shopping again
And you could kind of take a poll on what's come since last time and you're right it it's more choice than ever. We're also seeing
Distributions work closer with hardware providers, too
So I think we're gonna see more stuff there. Yeah, when it does come time for me to get a dedicated Linux machine
Thankfully, I have my Pinebook Pro right now, but honestly, it's I'm a performance maniac
So when it does come time, I'm gonna have an even harder choice, which is a good thing
I think that's code for you break systems. I
Just am a demanding user
Thankfully speaking of upstream knock-on effects
performance on the Raspberry Pi 4 could be looking a lot better for those of you using SD storage a
Manjaro developer has brought to light that only the single data rate mode is currently being used
for micro SD cards and
Em MC storage with the Raspberry Pi 4 a model B, but get this ready with a two line
Yes, two line kernel patch
The double data rate mode can be enabled yet Tobias Schramm sent out a kernel mailing list post
Identifying that it looked like the controller in the board circuitry appear to support double data rate mode just fine
He also checked on the signal integrity on the data lines for the micro SD card slot and so far
It hasn't found any issues now so far no one from the project
It's really responded to the patches yet, but it was just posted this weekend
I think so we'll see but it is exciting
you know not everyone has the time to set up some sort of external hard drive or you just want to you know a
small form factor and
SD card makes the most sense. Yeah this machine. We're using today for this little tester
Roo that we're gonna tell you guys about we're running it off the SD
I mean, it's not great, but when you when you just want to get a pie going it's it's pretty nice
and
If you're running Manjaro on your pie, I think they're gonna patch this on their version of it, so
Those folks will get it take advantage of it. Yeah right away
Yeah, you know Manjaro is making a very compelling argument for the ARM platform however for these devices that we're using I've stuck with
2004 because I kind of use them for a little more like reliable like server type work
I want the LTS 2004
But I also want something that's built to be server grade and as much as I love arch and I've put it on our server
In the in the studio
I don't actually want to run arch on my raspberry pies that are right that are acting as network routers
Turns out one arch server is more than enough yeah
Yeah, really, but this is a great little thing to see and you know one of those little improvements by code
Which I love updates that make your system faster, right?
I mean like if hardware is just sitting there and suddenly with a little bit of tweaking you can make it better for everyone using it
That's really exciting all right. Well. I have something pretty exciting. I am very excited to announce that
We have one of our first sponsors since going independent has come on board the unplugged program
and it's a company that I've wanted to work with for a
Very long time and they were one of the first on my list when we started talking about going independent again
And I am thrilled to say this URL for the first time
Check out for a special offer for linux unplugged podcast listeners and new linode customers visit linode.com
Slash unplugged and receive $100 towards your new account. You know these new ads. We're doing they're gonna be tight efficient ads
this is not representative of what the ad will typically be but I wanted to take a moment with this first one and
Tell you personally that for me. This is a milestone in my career because I've I have followed Linode from afar for a very long time
and
When JB stopped doing all sponsorships
I wanted a pretty clear separation of church and state and so about two years ago for all my personal projects
I started spinning everything up on Linode because I thought you know nice and clear and separate all of the work stuffs on one all
Of my personal stuffs on the other and I watched I watched them become an extremely competitive
Company where they really have evolved their product over the last couple of years to the point where it is
It is extremely sharp. It is extremely well put together
And the best part is they have been deep in the community for a long time
So they're one of those companies that is part of the Linux community
I have gone to many events and I've seen them at those events talking to people
So check out linode.com slash unplugged they have plans starting as low as five dollars a month
They have dedicated CPU plans. They have GPU plans. They have block storage
They have the one-click app marketplace that I love but something else that's really cool something
I played around with a lot with setting up different WordPress and I was able to play with different styles of WordPress setups is
They have these stack scripts that will deploy a stack for you and you can just audit the script
You can see this is where it's installing Debian. This is where it's deploying this package
Really easy to write your own as well native SSD storage 40 gigabit network connections industry leading processors
they have data centers all over and
They have job postings as well, which I want to mention for those of you
They're looking for work right now linode.com slash careers. It's not related to the sponsorship
I just think that's something you should know about if you want to get that $100 credit and you're a new customer at linode.com
Slash unplugged go spin up a box on Linode's infrastructure
It's really cool. And I am so happy to have Linode on it as a sponsor, but also
To have them here just as we're going independent again
So they're one of the first companies helping make that possible. They started in 2003
So they've been around a long time just like Jupiter broadcasting. They support the Kubuntu folks and other members of the community
I've wanted to work together with them for years
And so when when this deal worked out, I had a real moment
I had a moment where like okay this decision to go independent is gonna work like
It's it's really thrilling and I would encourage you to support our sponsor because they're making what we do possible right now
And I think this is a great fit linode.com slash unplugged get $100 off and a big
Thank you for Linode for sponsoring the unplugged program. I just recently set up a wordpress instance
I did it in seconds. I was I was seeing what I could do to just do a self completely self-contained self-hosted podcast platform
It's awesome. We'll be telling you more about it linode.com slash
Unplugged I just signed up. I just your code
I just signed up for Linode because I actually needed a quick and easy VPS to sign up for and
Having $100 thrown in was an absolute bonus for me because money is tight and I really appreciate that. So thank you
I've just signed up. Yeah. Thank you to Linode to do it. I'm looking at doing the same
They're really cool company and they're one of those that as a businessman
I've wanted to work with for years, but then there was like another relationship that kind of made that impossible for a while
And then we weren't doing ads. And so this is just a bit an opportunity that it's really exciting feels pretty great
It feels like a great fit for the show also
Want to say a huge thank you to our unplugged core contributors. We are already halfway to the goal of essentially the revenue of a
Single sponsor. We're about 50% now. It's like 48% the way there which is incredible. That's an amazing first response of the founder
Discounts went away super quick, but the membership is still available at unplugged core comm we have two feeds for you one feed
That is the entire bootleg live stream lots more show lots more show than what makes it in
Typically, the other version is an ad free feed with some there is some small ads in there that are contractually obligated
but it's like just the main fully produced show ad free and you get that as an as a podcast feed in your podcast catcher you
choose either one and
it's a great way to support the show and
Not only keep the ad load down, but let us be picky and choosy, too
So that's an unplugged core comm and thank you everybody who has become a core contributor
it has been a very emotional week for me and
That's one of the reasons I'm out in the woods seriously is just so I can kind of process everything that's happened and that support
You know, it helped me feel like I was gave me some confidence that I was doing the right thing here
The audience got your back they do they do they do let's also mention something else
We're working on and that is coming up next episode
So we're we're doing a fedora 33 bug-a-thon to test fedora 33 on September 8th
We're gonna do the show and then we're gonna just move over into testing
I want some people to show up and throw some hardware at the butter FS install
Let's try to find some issues
And if we do let's work with each other to do informative helpful bug reports
Our idea here is we're trying to line this up with a testing week with fedora
So we're doing this while the project is in a mode to receive these and we're gonna try to do
Well done bug reports that actually help them and hopefully we'll have some people advising us and guiding us on how to do that
And we'll be on the live stream working with people and can help bounce things around in the mumble room
I'd like to do some brainstorming in the uh, lup lug this sunday
And if you haven't tried it yet, maybe it's good time to go get fedora 33 and start banging on it
The test week is going on right now as we record and it wraps up on the 8th, which is the last day
So and that's the that's when lup is
So that's next week as we record this episode september 8th 2020 if you can make it to jblive.tv
Join us for the live show and then stick around to do some bug smashing or show up when you can
It'll be a live bug-a-thon. I don't expect this to be a tremendous success or anything like that
But i'm trying to learn how we can do this best so we can make this something we do a little more on the regular
For other projects and distributions try to do something
That targets the project schedules that can kind of land when it's most beneficial. So we're not overwhelming them with low information
Low value bug reports, but try to get it right and that's what this is about
And we're kind of doing our first tests with this next week september 8th, and you know how we love fedora
Yeah, we love to give those guys a you know
A good community test because the butter fs switch is it's a it's it's a huge switch
And it's a very public thing and if we can maybe help avoid some issue that comes up that causes people heartburn
That's a win-win for everybody
Okay, so that's uh, that's everything let's talk about the little trick that wes and I pulled off
Using two separate internet connections with linux. We are using myfis
But in theory you could combine this with say a home broadband connection and a backup cellular connection. That's
Tethered to your phone even doesn't have to be a dedicated data device
There's a lot of ways you can actually mix and match this to bring maybe
Fairly reliable connectivity to an area that maybe is having an issue. I am utilizing it because
Uh, well, let's see how to put this you're a hill person
Yeah, I am out in the woods and I don't I don't have like a broadband internet connection. I don't have like
Comcast comes doesn't come to my rv. That's not that's not a thing. I thought you were going to say
That's not a thing. I thought you were just like dragging a fiber cable out the back
Yeah, right, uh, or I have a big satellite pointed at elon's starlink array
Maybe someday. Yeah, maybe actually but right now
the most practical approach this is crazy, but the most practical approach is
I track down old grandfathered truly unlimited data plans
And I contract with them and I have an at&t. I have verizon
I have others too. I have actually have ting back in the mix now, but I have I have several others but
For this I wanted to see if I could take a benefit if there was any benefit
From using both my at&t my fi and verizon my fi at the same time and use a raspberry pi
To sort everything out in between and there's issues here that have to be accommodated for like, you know
My fives are pieces of crap that often requires stupid interaction
Uh, you know and those kinds of things but there overall the idea was these are two very expensive connections
Can I leverage them at the same time instead of traditionally connecting to one using that and then speed testing it?
Connect to the other one use that speed test it and then okay. Well i'll use this my fight today
And then tomorrow i'll use that my fi instead let linux sort it out and just use them both
Just use them both and there's there's a lot of ways to crack this between like vpn bonding
Which would require uh, like a node on a on a linode somewhere or some kind of remote gateway that would combine your connections
But that's not the direction we went for this so you could
And some have even talked about doing with wire guard didn't we see that as well west? Yeah, you know
There are a few ways to make this happen because well it's linux and and that's how these things work
Especially with networking and I think this would work really well for a lot of places
Especially if you weren't like chris and constantly roving around this large country
Because you do need a vps at the end and you basically, you know
You've got your two internet connections and then you you set up a tunnel
To the vps over both internet connections and then you just use the regular kernel, you know
Interface bonding support that exists just right in the kernel itself to bond those together on your local side
And since they both end up at the same place
It just works and then the vps acts as the final gateway to the internet now a big plus with this too is
Is you only show up as one external ip address, right? You just show up as the ip address of that vps
But it's a little more complicated
You also have to have a vps in play which not everyone does
And it might be tricky for you because where you are in the country might not correspond to where that vps is
And you know if you the latency there dominates everything maybe that's not so great
So before we talk about what we did instead
To accomplish what west and I were able to pull off just using free linux and a raspberry pi
There is a commercial product made by a company called peplink. And these are the products you'll usually find in buses trains
Um boats and in this product is called the max transit duo
And it combines two lde connections and it has external antenna connections and it's a little router
It may even be running linux itself. It has a bit of a ui to manage all of this
It makes a lot of what west and I did simple the catch is
The product is like eleven hundred dollars
Hundred dollars. Whoa. Yeah, and then the bonding service to bond the connection is about a thousand dollars a year
Wait, what? Yes, that's a little more than a vps
Yeah
So when I looked at those prices, I said I bet we can figure out a way to do this for free with linux
And sure enough so the approach that we went with is it's it's more I guess akin to load balancing
Wouldn't you say it's like a policy routing solution? Yeah, you know, um
If you're still using if config, well, that's just fine
But you really should check out ip route 2
And the ip command because it exposes a whole bunch of really neat kernel facilities that you might not otherwise be aware of
And one of those is more advanced policy routing now normally when you're you know routing packets
It's kind of all about the destination
But in our case if we have two outbound gateways two isps that are connecting us to the internet
Things can get rather confused if the connection comes in from one and then goes out on the other
Yeah, tcp doesn't like that. No, no, right. I mean, I wouldn't like that
But thanks to policy routing you can set things up
So that never happens if it comes in on an interface it goes out the same interface and the kernel actually has built-in native support
To have different weights and to load balance between those connections
So you can just set up multiple routing tables one for each of your different isps
then you set up some ip rules the command is ip rule and that sort of you know sets things up so that
You don't run into those confusing problems of things going out the wrong interface
Make sure if it comes in on one goes out that same one
And then tell the kernel how you'd like to preference them either give them the same weight and it'll just split the traffic equally
Or if you want to wait one more than the other because it's faster. Well, you can do that, too
now
This isn't perfect in a lot of ways right because for any one connection
It's not going to use the bandwidth of both links
But if you've got multiple users on your LAN say or you're just downloading for things from multiple sites at the same time
Well there it will work. And so this is something that we played around with because here where i'm parked in the woods
Amazingly, there's a tower not too far away and I get
95 ish megabits on one connection and about 60 megabits on the other what yeah, it's great
So we thought well, let's wait the 90 megabit connection a little heavier
And then that'll be the primary connection and then the 60 megabit connection is the one that gets used when the other connection is busy
and the next level kind of trick to this was to set up that little raspberry pi as a router for the LAN and then
Just set the default route on my boxes on the LAN to point to the raspberry pi
Yeah
What's also nice about doing this yourself with linux is it makes it pretty easy if you wanted to say like
Let's say you've got the kids at the rv
Chris and you want them to use the slow connection because it doesn't really matter for you know, whatever video they're streaming
Well, you can use the faster connection to actually get some work done. Well, you could set that up too
Now drew tells me that there's something similar to this that the ubiquity products do. Yeah, so you can do
pretty much all of this in their edge max line and
It's running viata, which is essentially just like debian but
Repurposed for routing. Oh cool. So you can buy like a little edge max router
Some of them are only like 100 bucks. That's what I use at home
And literally log into a shell install debian packages adjust the routing manually do all of that
Within a little box that's designed for routing already has multiple ports, you know
Whichever model you buy is going to determine which port how many ports you have
Uh, it's really cool tech that is neat. Okay, I would definitely check that out
Well, like all great things in linux, so all this stuff is like built in but there's also some projects
Projects that sit in front of some of these tools like the one we were using west was if I recall net isp balance
Right. Yeah, and so where things you know
You might might want a little more support and I should also note that um some other linux firewall based projects
Like open wrt or shore wall. They've got tools in place to kind of manage this for you, too
We didn't want to go that route. We were kind of rolling it ourselves to play with the underlying technology
But if you want to get fancier
You want to make sure let's say that one of these mi-fi craps out and just totally drops off for a while
Has to be power cycled and come back online. You want to make sure that those cases are handled in a robust way
So there's a couple tools out there. Um, we'll have them all linked in the show notes, of course
one of them was just an easy link status monitor that
Did the hard work of sending pings out your various interfaces and then running external scripts?
When something changed and that seemed super useful really nice to customize
But I think for your case we wanted something that was a little more plug and play and just forget about
That's where net isp balance came in which is basically just um a fancy pearl script that sets all of this ip based
Policy routing up for you and has a few ip tables tricks up its sleeve too to make this automatic
It's also got a nice failover mode
So if you don't want to load balance, you just want to say have a backup connection
Maybe that's maybe that's a mi-fi and you have a regular cable connection or something that works, too. Yeah
That's the part where I could see it being really useful for
Remote offices that are maybe have connectivity that have a broadband connection, but it's a little flaky
I've definitely had clients that have been in that situation before or people at home
That always want to be able to have some connectivity
Maybe it's for their alarm system monitoring to their camera system
You could have it fail over to something like a ting mi-fi that you're only paying for when you use the data
Um, or what i'm doing here is google fi is like the third backup if for some reason I have no verizon and at&t
It's unlikely that i'll have google fi but it'll give it a shot and that's pretty neat
And you just have this really easy to set up config file and it makes it simple
I assume you probably have to have mailing set up on your machine, but it makes it very simple to generate alerts
When an event occurs as well, which is really nice
So you don't have to sit there and watch it. It'll just send something to like an email inbox, right?
You can get an email saying like hey, just so you know your main connection went down
I'm now using your more expensive backup connection just to be aware
Yeah, so that's net isp balance
And it's it's one of the it's just one of those great open source tools because a lot of the heavy liftings actually being
Done by the kernel and the os tools
But like west said this this pearl script really kind of wraps it all up and makes it nice and approachable for you
Yes, and it it'll handle some of that monitoring for you too, right?
So it's going to be doing you know
You can configure it with endpoints that you want to test it's going to send out periodic pings
You can also configure it to say like oh well if packet loss exceeds a certain threshold well
Then consider that link down all kinds of options like that and another sign that I really liked
I mean as you said chris, it's just basically using a whole bunch of you know built-in stuff to the operating system
It's got a debug mode
so if you want to go investigate what commands it's running or just use it as a script to orchestrate this and then
Customize it run those commands yourself. That's possible, too
Mm-hmm. Yeah, good point. So, okay. Let's let's talk a little bit about
Uh policy routing a bit more because that was kind of key to make this work
Traditional ip routing systems just route packets by comparing the destination address
Against a predefined list of routes that it can go to and at certain points as well
I've got nowhere else to send this i'll send it to the default gateway and that's my understanding of routing
So how does that differ from policy routing? Well policy routing is just more flexible
It lets you it lets you use other information that's available. Maybe the source of the packet. Maybe the protocol that's going on
basically a whole bunch of other options instead of just the destination and usually the way this works is you've got you've got basically this
Set of rules that you can have and then you can add additional routing tables
this might be familiar for folks who are used to you know, maybe more network grade routers that have a
vrfs virtual routing and forwarding tables that exist
And it just adds a lot of flexibility because originally you just have that one main routing table
But actually under etsy ip route 2 slash rt underscore tables
Just by adding a line in that file you can add to basically as many as you want
And then once you've got these tables set up they act as little routing namespaces
So you can configure default different default routes
You can set up access and then you can set up some rules that make sure things
Based on either the source or the protocol or whatever fields that you have access to through policy routing
go to the right table and then those tables just have
Routes that work as normal and then direct the traffic on so you can make sure that say like if you have different lands that
You need to get to you can set it up. So those go the shortest hop possible
And in our case, that's the magic that says oh look you came from this interface over here
Let's make sure that you choose the routing table that sends you back out that same interface
And in the past you could do this too. Um ip tables has a marking facility
so you could use ip tables that would set a mark on a package if it came in over that interface and then I
On the outside it would identify that mark and then know how to send it. But this is just a much cleaner approach
Now from like the totally other end, uh, this is something we didn't play around with but we did come across speedify
which is a commercial graphical user application that promises to combine multiple connections on your linux desktop or on
I think other os's as well including maybe mobile and and it also include vpns in that potentially and it
It combines all of the connections into one vpn back to their server. It's a commercial product. It's like three dollars a month
Um, but they kind of promised to do this only you don't have to have a separate device
It's acting as a default gateway
You just like throw it on your laptop and you connect a couple devices up
And then this this app gives you a gooey to bring them together didn't try it
But it's certainly from the screenshots looks pretty decent
So that's something if you're interested if you're interested in this but don't want to go through all that rigamarole
You could give that a go but for me it was worth all of the rigamarole to get a linux box set up
and and get all this done and and and figure out how to do all this because that's sort of like
Um the groundwork for a good edge device that then I could say make a wire guard endpoint
Or perhaps I could put a squid proxy on so that way i'm not
sending as many web requests out over the myfis and instead i'm answering them locally from a cache and
Setting it up as a local dns cache seems like a no-brainer as well
And maybe it's an edge cache for steam possibly as well if I throw a usb hard disk on there all of a sudden
This little raspberry pi that's managing these multiple connections
Can start doing other things that are clever to take the load
Off of my myfis and make the overall experience faster as well
And so that's why I thought it was worth the effort, right?
And you know, I think it's a good use case here too because you might ask
Well, is the pi really up to something like this? But since you don't have a fancy, you know gigabit fiber connection the speeds on your
On your outbound really aren't too bad. So it seems to be working nicely
Yeah, I think it's a good point to make is if you were if you were maybe connecting to something considerably faster
You might want a faster machine as the router
I also want to clarify here too that you know net isp balance was really neat to find also because
While policy routing is not too complicated in the simple case that we were talking about and
Um, we'll have linked in the show notes just the sort of the basic guide that we followed when we were setting it all
Up by hand, but if you're new to networking or networking with linux and this all sounds a little bit over your head
you don't really have to worry about that with net isp balance because
Basically the bare minimums that you need are you got to have your multiple connections?
They got to have ip addresses in our case. That was just dhcp
To the myfis and then it literally took care of the rest
I mean you did have to set up in the config file. You've got to tell it
What type of service you got, you know, like which are your lan interfaces and which ones are isps and which device does that correspond?
To then you can also that's where you can customize the weights and like what ip to ping to check if the connection is up
But that was all we configured and it set up everything else. Yeah, and it's really simple because it refers to stuff as lan
Isp one isp2 and so it's not confusing at all
You know exactly what connections you're dealing with which I thought was really nice and it made it super simple to read
I could see us doing other things down the road to accommodate the fact that these are crappy myfis
like
using tools like full sm to
Monitor the links of them and then when it detects that some sort of link has failed triggering another script that does a usb
port reset to reconnect the myfi I could I could see little workarounds needing to come up because
Really for me ideally like the one thing that the peplink device has is the the sim card slots
Are fully integrated into the actual device. They're not these usb myfi devices. They're running their own crappy oses
That's probably the biggest limitation here is yeah, it's not like a real interface or anything or a fancy high-end sim interface
It's just a chromey myfi. Yeah, another thing that came to my mind
That would be a neat stretch goal here is uh, you know set something up to do speed tests across the various links
And then shift the weights as those speed test results change. Yeah
That would have been useful today because before we started recording
I did all the tests and the at&t connection was far and above the connection to use for our remote voip setup here
15 minutes before we went on air the at&t connection was unusable
It was dropping packets to our voice server like crazy for some reason out of nowhere just every second or third packet gone
Sometimes multiple packets in a row gone
And the verizon connection out of the batch all of a sudden was the best connection
And it got me thinking like boy it'd be really cool to have some sort of health check script
That just does a sanity check back to the studio and then picks the connection
That performed the best in that health check. Yeah, wouldn't that that would just be so slick
So pro it'd be so pro. I tell you what, uh colonel points out that there is the uh,
G il or g g g g i net devices like I have their little mini slate
They do have one with dual sims and I saw that I was looking at that one actually
So i'll probably eventually switch this up in the meantime. I kind of want to see how far we can take it
So we're going to play with it a bit, but it was it was really fascinating to get
I would say at least the core functionality of that thousand dollar device for totally free with linux, right?
That was one of those things like windows can't really do this mac os can't really do this
This is pretty awesome. Like the fact that the kernel is just totally
Helping us out by keeping track of the routes and it's easy to bond these connections
And then it's easy for an open source developer to create a pearl script that sits on top of all of this that
I mean, it's it's pretty awesome stuff and like the policy routing is like you're saying it's like enterprise grade routing stuff
So it's and I have it right here on a tiny little 40 pie. Yeah, that's what that's what's really exciting to me
Is it's just like the kernel has a really rich networking stack and yeah, okay if you've got, you know
Crazy high line rate speeds. Maybe it's not going to cut it for you. But for anything we're doing
Totally more than enough. Yeah, so we'll have links to the projects and some of the other projects that we saw that could be useful
Uh in the show notes if you're curious about maybe setting up a backup connection or combining two connections those resources
Should be a good starting spot
Well, mr. Payne, uh, what do you say we move to the feedback and uh, we have something submitted by jay that we may adopt
We may fork this ourselves
This is a getting started with the jupiter broadcasting matrix guide a quick start including
A video walkthrough to make it super easy, but also just a step-by-step guide for getting on the jupiter broadcasting matrix
And uh, we have a link to jay's blog where he wrote all this up and he said you guys feel free to take as much
Or as little of this as you want and I just wanted to get it out there right now
We may combine that with a guide that we've already started
But uh, we're kind of doing 100 things at once right now
So it's just great to have somebody write that up. So thank you jay, and if you'd like to join us on the new
Matrix server check that out. We have a link to it the linuxunplug.com. I think this is just a great
You know just enough of a guide to where I found element decently easy to use and get started with but for folks
Who've never tried it before go check out the video
It'll have you up and up and chatting with us on matrix in no time
Let's talk about this pick that we've been
Sitting on for a couple of weeks because we've been super busy
But this pick is really special for for one reason and one reason alone. It's written in rust
For for one reason and one reason alone. It's written in rust
So i'm going to give a i'm going to give a guess west it's pronounced ton shell
Because you know, it's like tunnel and shell. Yeah, I think you got it. Okay, it's pretty neat
Um, it's a simple secure method to remote shell into ephemeral environments
And I like that they've got this question right at the top of the readme
Why would I use this over my well-established ssh client good question
You wouldn't the use case for ton shell is predominantly quick ad hoc remote access to hosts
Which you may not have ssh access to so let's say you've embraced the craze
You're using aws lambdas for just about everything now something goes wrong
That's not really an environment you control and usually that's part of the value proposition, right?
It's a quote-unquote serverless or at least hey, it's amazon servers. They're just running your app for you
But sometimes you might need a little more information, but you can't set up an ssh server
Well now you can because ton shell is a statically linked pre-compiled single binary that all you need to do is just download it
Run it and boom now you've got ssh access
I love that don't have ssh access. Well, we can fix that
That's pretty neat i'm glad we finally got to this one
Um, we have others that are in the winds. Is that the right? They're in the in the in the rafters
What are you in the wings in the wings? Is that what what does that mean? What does in the wings mean?
What does that even mean wes? I say I call bs on that saying wes ouch
You know i've decided right here on the show, uh, but that doesn't mean we couldn't use some more suggestions
so head over to linuxonplug.com slash contact if uh,
If you've got a pick for us diddle, uh, you say, you know what uh in the wings means
Uh, yeah, it's a theater term in the wings means uh backstage
Okay, that makes sense waiting to make their debut right? They're backstage about to come out on stage. Okay. No. All right
I retract my statement. I like it actually
I think that's pretty great. Uh, all right. Well, yeah, we'll link to that in the uh show notes ton shell
And it's the remote shell into an environment that uh, it's like a subspace environment, you know, this is how this is how in star trek
They would get into a computer that was inside a subspace envelope as they would use ton shell because it's an ephemeral subspace environment
You know this one for me actually I discovered it too late
Just a few weeks ago. I was trying to debug some problems in an ephemeral environment
And I didn't have a tool like this and it was driving me crazy
So I think this is going to be one of those picks that actually makes it into my toolbox. All right
Well, don't forget about that bugathon on september 8th after unplug show up for the show if you can and then stick around
To help us make fedora 33 even better. We need your help
I think it's a great way to kind of contribute, you know
We use linux and desktop linux
We take advantage of all these great projects and work of open source developers and even if you're not a fedora user
It's not a bad way to just sort of stop by and give back a little bit and participate in the community as well
So that'll be next tuesday as we record this and we encourage you to show up also again. Thank you to our
core contributors you guys
wow, um
Amazing and also just a little interesting stat west
Uh, it seems to me when I looked like it's split 50 50 like 50 people
50 of people are using the bootleg feed and 50 of people are going with the ad free feed
It's it's not like one is particularly more popular over the other
Well when you've got two great options can be mighty hard to juice. Oh my god, wes
Unplugged core.com
Uh, we appreciate your support over there. Also, uh big
Thank you to a cloud guru check out the new cloud guru cloud guru.com and also
A big huge. Thank you to lanode, uh for sponsoring this show and making it possible for us to come back indie
I am thrilled lanode.com slash unplugged go check out poppy on the ubuntu podcast and the new show
Which uh, we'll have links. Hey, yo over there. Yeah. Hey, yo, hey, yo, go check that out over there
It's uh, it's a good time mr. Payne
What else should we mention? Maybe the show has a twitter account
We hardly ever mention that at linux unplugged good way to get show updates anything else
Come hang out with us on our new month matrix server. Sure. We've got to get good about the plugs on that one
I'm at chris less. He's at west pain. The network is at jupiter signal
And drew is at drew of doom. Thanks so much for tuning to this week's episode of the unplug program. Oh
Linux action news is back. Check your feeds. See you next tuesday
So
West pain, I can't believe I forgot to mention linux action news is coming back. So as we record
Monday probably the next monday you're hearing this
There'll be a fresh brand new linux action news in your feeds
I I feel so bad. I should have totally put that in the show. There's so much going on right now
It's a good problem to have but I don't want to overwhelm people with the pluggy plugs either, but that's a big one
I'm, very excited about lan. It's a literally huge news. It is very big and um, you know for me
It's like uh, it's like it's a lifestyle change
It is it's like I went a decade plus doing shows on sundays and then just stopped and now it's coming back
The only the biggest downside for me is it lands during the lup lug
So that'll be tricky, but i'll probably i'll try to maybe pop in early. I'm not sure
I'm not sure what to do because we record at noon on sunday
Which was funny because the lup lug started sort of right as the next sunday
I would have been doing lan became lup lug time
I think this just means you need to drag joe into the lup lug for a bit
You know just dabble hang out for a few and then go get your work started
We all know you like to chat before you work. Anyway could yeah, I could run two instances of mumble
He wouldn't even have to do a thing. Don't give him the choice
Yes, he'll love that surprise