I have to apologize to the podcast audience.
There's going to be some rain noise and maybe some thunder, although I think that's past
about 15 minutes before we went on the air.
I was watching a storm approach and it just got bigger and bigger.
And then about 10 minutes before we went on the air,
I realized it was really impacting my LTE performance.
I sent Wes a message and I'm like, Wes, my LTE coverage is dropping rapidly.
So Wes goes and looks up the weather map for me.
He's like playing meteorologist over there.
You know, when I look at it, I'm like, it's not clearing up anytime soon, is it?
No. So I decide, all right, I got to get the cell booster up,
see if I can't get the LTE signal back up to some sort of usable range.
That way we can do the show because I'm remote.
I'm in Wyoming. I have to have good connectivity.
So there I am in probably one of the top 10,
maybe even top five thunder and lightning storms of my life.
Like an idiot, I'm climbing up the ladder on the back of my RV.
Do do do with a coax cable hanging to the ground in my mouth.
So that way my hands are free. Do do do climbing up the back of the RV.
I wrap my arm around the ladder.
So one arms around the ladder.
The other arm is trying to tighten down a coax cable.
The wind is nuts.
My clothes are getting soaked by this crazy sideways rain.
I'm up on the roof getting this thing all tight and I climb down.
Boop, boop, boop, boop, boop, boop.
I'm just totally soaked head to toe.
By now, I feed the wire, the coax cable into the RV in one of the slides.
I just feed it in there.
I go get it all hooked up, power up the cell booster,
sit down, get ready to do the show.
And I notice my cellular performance has not improved at all.
I go look, random air light.
I'm sitting there dripping water on the floor with a random booster air light.
So I've got no LTE. I got a big storm.
But you know what, Wes? The show goes on.
It sure does. Can't stop it.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 254 for June 19th, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's live from a very stormy Casper, Wyoming.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Mr. Payne.
It is good to be connected with you over the past few days.
Over the power of a somewhat shaky LTE connection,
thanks to the thunder and lightning.
But that doesn't prevent us from having a great show.
We're going to get into some major stories
that are really concerning several large open source projects.
We'll talk about what's going on with Blender and their situation with YouTube.
And then we'll get into a bunch of community news,
including some important news for one of the important members.
Important news for an important member of our community, Techstar.
We have an update on his health situation.
Deepen has a new release.
We're doing an update to on the Librem 5,
what they're working on, where they're at,
some new portable hardware coming, a distro you might not have considered.
And then I'll give you an update on my adventures
at setting up Linux Academy with OBS running on Kubuntu 1804
and migrating their live stream from a Mac to GNU slash Linux.
Then we got a little segment on retro games.
I've just sort of embraced it.
I've decided it's time to be an old man.
I'm going to love the old games.
In a way that only the love games, the old games can love me.
Give you an update on my Texas trip.
Plus Linux desktop's usability seems to reach a peak
and then they want to change everything, whoever they might be.
And it all goes out the window for some new design.
And often with that, a loss of usability.
And a follower of the show has documented this process over and over again,
going back to the original Xerox interface to the latest versions of Gnome 3.
So we'll cover that as well in the show.
Get a good conversation going.
But Wes, before we go any further, you know, we got to bring in that mumble room.
So time appropriate greetings, virtual lug.
Hello. Hello.
Good evening. Hello, everybody.
It's super good to be connected with you.
As I was I was driving yesterday for 10 hours and I literally had the thought,
you know, tomorrow I'm going to be sitting down, just hanging out with my buddies.
Like today's kind of a grindy day.
But tomorrow, tomorrow we get to hang out.
So thank you, everybody, for being here. I really appreciate it.
I've been looking forward to it.
That's what got me through driving nonstop yesterday.
But we'll talk more about that later.
Let's get into some of the news that's going on.
It's impacting the community and one that's got Blender Project upset.
The MIT courseware that's open is been been screwed around with.
And it all is kind of building towards my concerns around Article 13.
So that's a lot of stuff I just laid on you.
Let's start with the bigger picture stuff.
YouTube. It's an ongoing issue.
And the centralization of services.
We've been constantly reminded of the limitations that open source
and free software projects run into when they use centralized services
like Slack, like GitHub and like YouTube.
And several popular YouTuber accounts, including the MIT OpenCourseWare account
and the Blender Foundation's accounts have had all of their videos blocked.
Channels just been screwed with completely by YouTube.
And in a little bit of irony, too, the MIT courseware stuff
has been taken down because it contains content from MIT,
according to the YouTube video. Have you seen this, Wes?
Yeah, it seems. Oh, man, I don't know.
It's very frustrating.
I'm still trying to catch up on all that's happened because a lot has happened
kind of quickly.
But just the fact that there's so many blocked videos,
that the centralization of this platform is once again so highlighted.
I just want to watch local media.
Yeah, I know, right? Yeah.
So the MIT one isn't an isolated incident either.
There's other organizations that have been blocked by their own content.
I once got a copyright flag on my own voice.
You know, when I do the introductions, I do them for Koda Radio.
I go, this is Koda Radio, episode 283.
Yes. Yes.
They flagged my own voice once on YouTube claiming that it was owned by somebody else
because it's just some scripts, right?
They're listening to the audio waveforms, doing matching.
It's kind of it's not as advanced as we like to think it is.
And that's how Blender is getting screwed.
No, right. Absolutely not.
It has so much data to churn through.
And it's really just a simple, somewhat simple fingerprinting procedure.
So there's very much limits.
And unfortunately, we hit them all the time.
And you can thank Facebook for all of this.
I think also, though, the YouTube like Python scripts to do content ID matching.
Didn't it really start with the Viacom lawsuit against YouTube before Google bought them?
Sure. But no other company has promoted more responsibility of the
platform to monitor uploads than Facebook.
And now there are even actual very concrete proposals waiting to be voted on, especially
in the EU side on actually making it Google, for example, responsible for the content
and to require automated tools to exist so that content can be removed within an hour.
Right. So if they like any any corporation, like they already had content ID because it
was for the music association to get out of their ass.
Now they have another incentive to try to make sure the algorithms are acting as fast
as possible. And as a consequence, we're seeing now open source projects to be mostly
affected because those were the ones that usually had more loose policies.
I think it's just a natural consequence of the political environment at the moment.
Yes, I think you've nailed it there.
And Blender is taking matters into their own hands.
They've launched a video Blender dot org, which is peer to it's just a test at this
point. But it's peer to which is a peer to peer video distribution platform.
I tried it doesn't work as well for me.
Blender thinks that this is something to do with the monetization strategies at YouTube
because they've never since 2008 tried to monetize their YouTube channel.
But it keeps getting turned on for them and they keep going and turning it off.
Who knows? But I think what what you say, Dar, is the bigger point here is people are
really upset about if we cauterize all this with with legal ease and we essentially take
the YouTube problem, which I just mentioned, and we apply it to the entire Internet where
you're supposed to for every GitHub documentation submission that has a screenshot.
You need to have somebody review that there.
It gets it just gets completely unscalable.
And several different projects are raising a red flag about Article 13.
And UbiPorts is one of them.
They say, Dear UbiPorts supporters, the freedom to develop software collaboratively
online is at serious risk by an article included on the current proposal for copyright
reform in the European Union.
The specific proposal known as Article 13, which just a side note, sounds like something
out of 1984, imposes mandatory upload filters on online platforms that share, quote,
large amounts of user generated content.
Large amounts is not clearly defined. So that's red flag number one.
And it could be as many as 500 pieces of arts, 500 songs, 500 programs, 500 units of any
work that could be legally protected by copyright.
This is extremely concerning, and it's not just UbiPorts is raising this red flag.
The Free Software Foundation over on their website says free software is under attack
within the European Union.
The proposed European Copyright Directive poses a great risk for free software and its
development. The Legal Affairs Committee of the European Parliament will be voting June
20th and 21st on whether or not to continue to allow us, as in the free software
community, to build software online together.
So one of the situations I say is don't, like for, especially for open source projects
listening, don't flunk out of the platforms just yet, because then they will say, see,
you have an alternative.
Use your voice to actually make your argument against the Article 13.
There is a, the EU is actually doing a public consultation and you can, I will provide the
link if you guys want.
Yes, please. I'll drop in the show notes.
That you can participate and basically just answer, say your piece and it's going to
matter. Even if you're not the local business, even if you're not in the EU, it will
matter.
Yeah, I will definitely put that in the show notes.
It's also more than just the 13th Article, the three in Lebanon are also terrible.
Yeah, and I don't understand them as much, but it sounds like it could actually impact
people that are just sharing news articles and whatnot.
What's your understanding?
It doesn't have any correlation to fair use.
So there's, so even if you do something legally in the fair use concept, the European
change, copyright reform would ignore all of that and still say that you're violating
it. And there's other cases where if someone provides a service that you display that
service or let's say, for example, you take a Twitter, like a tweet from Twitter and you
use the embed thing where you display it directly from the Twitter embed code and then
you load it on your website, you're violating the copyright reform of Article 11 at that
point.
Right. And they're trying to essentially protect the journalists and say, you have to
go to the source to get the information.
So therefore they'll stay alive.
They'll stay in business because everybody forced to go to the source.
What are your thoughts, Dar?
No, no, they explicitly put a tax on it, too.
Actually, it's not just forcing you to go to the source.
They the ancillary link that that's what they call it, essentially.
It says that if you include a snippet, it's not so much the link, but if the link brings
a snippet over, that snippet requires a license before you can actually present it.
So platforms that like Google News would essentially have to pay a tax.
What about my show notes where I link to a story and I include like a preview of the
article in there? Like maybe I even embed like a quote.
If you embed that quote, then again, if this place that you're gathering this information
from is a news outlet, because this is very specific to news outlets, it doesn't go and
say, hey, your blog or something.
It goes like into a news agency.
So that is actually the bigger problem, because it's also making distinction between
copyright of some individuals versus other individuals, which is actually probably illegal.
But curiously enough, because you're then you're discriminating against citizens,
different types of citizens. But essentially, the end result is still news organizations
would be able to get these licensing benefits.
At least that's what their their intent is.
And when it comes to the other measure that they want to pass through, which is what we
already talked to Article 13, like fair use right now is not standard across the EU, which
is one of the reasons to bring these actually copyright reform overall.
We're losing out in some countries and in some countries, people are actually gaining.
So even though it feels very negative, when we look at from technical point of view, it
is easy to see why there's actually still some support for these reform.
Some countries don't even allow you to take a picture of a building.
And also the parliament in the UK don't allow you to use any content that's not
to use any content that's for satire.
Like there's all kinds of different things that are violating fair use, the idea of fair
fair use. But there's this that one individual thing is there's so many things wrong
with this, this reform that not there's so many things that break the idea of any kind
of fair use in trade that it makes it where most of these services are just trying to
make as much money as possible.
And so they like, for example, the not being able to have to pay a tax or a license to
display content on your website.
It's so these news organizations that can't somehow figure out how to stay relevant, they
can force people to if they use their content that they have to go that they have to pay
them to use it or don't use it.
So that is really, I think, devastatingly awful to those of us in the states.
But Dar brings up a good point that outside the states, there are some countries where
aspects of this are an improvement.
So I want to move forward in this conversation, keeping that in mind.
But talking specifically about Article 13, this this seems to be the where it really
goes off the rails because you reports other aspects, Article three and those aspects,
maybe maybe there is some merit to that to that argument.
But Article 13 of this whole copyright reform seems really to be where the damning bit that
the Internet's freaking out about is you report says that it's going to totally screw over
Launchpad and GitHub for them and that all user generated content on those platforms
will have to be reviewed at the time of submission and will have to be if it isn't found in
violation or potentially in violation removed instantly.
Yes, that doesn't seem possible.
Like the bigger companies could could maybe you could argue that big companies could sustain
that. But smaller like open source project would be impossible to review any code like
that.
I completely agree.
And not only that, if you actually zoom out a little bit and see what a lot of you
countries are attempting to try to do, they like France and Spain, even a couple of a
couple of countries basically did it.
They've set up what they call A.I. incentive programs for companies to open their A.I.
incentives. To be honest, this is no brainer.
You open an A.I.
center in tax incentive for companies to bring their development to your country.
Then you make it so that it's actually required to use A.I.
services like upload filters.
And there you go.
The economy booms there, not elsewhere.
Yeah, this is no brainer what these countries are actually the countries that are pushing
more for this vision are the countries that did investments to make tax benefits and tax
cuts for setting A.I.
research centers in their country.
Now, from my very U.S.
centric point of view, admittedly, it feels like the EU keeps screwing up my Internet.
So first of all, can I just say I still am angry about all of those notices about cookies.
I don't care if I care about cookies.
I'm taking care of it via other means.
I am so sick and tired of clearing those messages.
This just this week, I finally started actually clearing them out instead of just leaving
them up in protest, wrecking the website.
And then we have GDPR, which is as a business owner has made my life a little bit more
complicated. And now Article 13 is coming down, which gives me once again the heebie
jeebies. Am I am I wrong here, Wes?
But don't you feel like that we're starting to really run up against the edges of traditional
laws and borders and having them applied to the Internet?
It feels like the only reason why this stuff has any chance of being successful is because
of the size of the EU.
If this was some small, tiny little nation, if North Korea was doing all of this, nobody
would give any craps.
Hang on.
Hang on just a minute.
Because it feels like it feels like you guys are wrecking my Internet, to be honest with
you. You're wrecking my net.
So when the US go round hoovering up people for DMCA, DMCA violations outside their
borders, that's fine and dandy.
But when we try to implement laws that protect users, that's bad.
Right. No, I mean, you know, yeah, right.
Exactly. Like there is a place for the GDPR data protections and especially just giving
users control over how their data is stored, that kind of things.
If it's stored, I'm kind of actually for that.
Not actually against it. But the cookie stuff really getting old.
It's like, it's like what it feels like is old people that don't know how the Internet
are working or making laws about the Internet that affects everyone.
Right. And that's not to give them control.
It's to show them what people are collecting about them.
And to make this aware is a good step, in my opinion.
Except it doesn't go too far in which way they proved by when they when they within the
first week of the GDPR becoming in effect, there is like thirty five thousand requests
for removal from Google and various search engines from government officials in the EU.
Oh, my God. Thirty five thousand.
Yeah. There was a variety of countries of all levels of their governments.
Like it was it was the most blatant, obvious usage of it was coming down immediately.
It does seem like it's a problem of scale in many ways there, right?
Like where a lot of these laws, there are intent.
And in the like what you were saying to the to the nature of the Internet, but the you
know, the economic and political impacts of the Internet have grown a lot and maybe the
ways we interact with it haven't.
And so a lot of the intent here maybe makes sense because there are these very large
corporations that do have nation level impact, but it just they are not well crafted enough
to scale down to the individual contributors that make up the parts of the Internet.
We value a lot.
That's true. Nation scale impact.
That's a good way to put it. I do have an extremely positive side note on all of these
debate. So one of the situations that has been complained about is ability to link and
basically to deal with content online.
These changes made it so that it is actually harder to have people like Snowden whistle
blowers. And because of these high criticism generated in parliament about the inability
to have whistle blowers, actually, there is now a whistle blowers protection legislation
coming through because of these debates.
So there has been reticence all over because different countries have different policies
of what it should entitle you to be a whistle blower and making an EU makes it applicable
to the 27 remaining member states.
And when you look at that, you actually see a greater point that they are aware of the
limitations being placed.
So now we just have to say that they will not be elected and we'll try our best to put
it down so that they don't pass it because they are aware if they weren't aware, they
wouldn't debate the need of having now better whistleblower protections because it would
be harder to expose things.
Right. Because when you release a piece of information that is private to an organization,
it will be filtered out by an upload filter.
Right. So ultimately, making yourself becoming a whistleblower is kind of impossible then.
Oh, that is really, really creepy.
Popey, did you want to jump in?
Because I know we kind of just went off on a couple of rabbit holes here.
Did you want to follow up on my whole you guys are recommending it or I've calmed down.
It's fine.
And just to be clear, I don't think anybody here would be happy to defend the DMCA.
No, no. And I wasn't defending GDPR either.
I'm not. I'm not defending it.
I agree with Chris that it was a law implemented by old people who don't understand the Internet.
Right. I get I get that.
But you can't use it as an excuse for why we're all terrible people when other people
around the world do exactly the same kind of thing and they get off scot-free.
Yeah, fair enough. And I got to remember, too, to be nice to old people, because not
only am I quickly becoming one, but I met a ninety three year old listener, I believe
it was at Texas Linux Fest.
That's incredible. Yeah.
Yeah. So I got to remember to be nice.
But now you can get paid for your data because that's a positive thing with GDPR.
You know, I'll take it.
You know, maybe I could just start selling my you know, that could be a good way to make
revenue.
And there's actually definitely a couple of new advantages.
So, for example, right now, if you let's say a speed ticket, you can't actually use the
camera footage to prove that you had, for example, an alibi.
But because the data is yours, you actually have a right to that data.
To request it and to have it, and therefore you can use it, for example, to prove that
you are in a different place in case of a false accusation.
This is just an example of what actually GDPR does for you.
It goes even further. Like you're talking about, for example, how your credit score
gets evaluated because GDPR doesn't cover just your data, but data related about you.
Ultimately, you have to make the question of, all right, if you go to your bank and
say, hey, give me all the data that you have on me, they will have to give you all the
data that you have on me. They will have to basically show you how they are using your
data to evaluate your actual credit score.
And as a consequence, it disambiguates lots of services that are around data.
I think that's a positive thing, because oftentimes algorithms nowadays make decisions
that affect your life.
You kind of want to know how that happens.
In a way, you could also think about this is this could be like a good thing to as far
as it is stops people from forcing like asking for data they don't need because they're
too afraid to like to just store it.
They don't they don't have it. So they'll disable things like the New York Times or
some other news organizations would disable JavaScript entirely so they didn't have to
deal with it anymore.
I've really enjoyed the reduction in spam email that's come my way over the last few
weeks. That's been quite nice.
But also, don't forget that the US have just as many ways to screw up the Internet as the
EU do. You've got SOPA.
You've got net neutrality.
You've got SOPA didn't pass.
PIPA didn't pass.
No, but they could have done.
That's the point.
Net neutrality was good and it's been removed.
And that's true. That is that is that is going to be a problem.
Yeah, that's a fair point.
Yeah, it's you're right.
The US has their everybody really that has any major influence.
It's what you do when you have the influence.
Right. Yeah. Yeah.
So another influence in our community has been Techstar.
He is the guy that made PC Linux OS.
I've been following PC Linux OS since I was a Mandrake user way back in the day.
It's been a long, long journey.
And I have some bad news.
I just wanted to make you guys aware of it and maybe you can send well wishes or do
whatever you do.
It looks like Techstar is facing the end of a battle with cancer.
And he posted on their forum that he doesn't think he's going to be around much longer.
And that is super sad to see because Techstar was one of these individuals who was an early
pioneer in creating a really user friendly Linux desktop operating system.
And he's had he's held strong opinions.
He's been a really unique individual in the community.
And he's somebody Texas, somebody I've followed for a long time.
And when I saw this announcement, I wasn't I know I just wasn't prepared for it.
I was in Texas at the time, too.
So I know. Yes.
Serious is, by the way, she says she says she doesn't understand.
I just want you guys to know that Siri just let me know that she doesn't understand why
Techstar is is losing his battle with cancer.
And I don't like to cover down or stories like this, but it is.
And it's something I think people need to be made aware of.
And we can get into a bus factor and small distribution debates in the future.
But for now, the show's best wishes to Techstar, his family and the PC Linux OS community.
I'll have a link in the show notes.
If you guys want to see that, or if maybe you want to go in and jump in if you've been
a member of the community and leave your comments.
I think there's probably not much to add, but our thoughts are with them.
And it's super sad.
And, man, cancer sucks.
Cancer just like talk about something that has taken some great people.
Absolutely.
Yeah, so that'll be links in the show notes.
If you guys want to read his words and maybe leave a message in the form.
Let's talk about Deepin for a moment, something that we don't get a chance to talk about very
much on the show.
Deepin 15.6 was released.
It's got a new app launcher.
And if you don't remember, one of the things that is sort of unique about Deepin is their
own custom desktop and well, quote unquote, custom, their own unique desktop environment
with a new efficient launcher that's all based on Qt.
It's a little more modeled off of Windows 7, I would say, the launcher.
If I were to give it a description, if it's like a start menu, you click it, you get your
most favorite apps on there.
Left side, then you get computer, document, videos, music, pictures, downloads and the
clock on the right side.
It's a more traditional style launcher and it's a nice update.
There's a new welcome app as well, sort of reminiscent of Monte welcome.
Does anybody in the in the Mumble room that knows better than I remember what distribution
deepens based off of or or what the desktop environment is based off?
Yes, Debbie and they used to be a bunch of them.
They're Debbie and and they're their devs environment is their own.
The deep and desktop environment. What are our thoughts on this?
Um, doesn't seem like it gets much attention because I think it's the largest audience
is outside the US, but they say their claim is sort of expect the simplicity of Gnome
Shell and maybe Budgie and but Qt, you know, like Qt underneath that does sound appealing
to, but I think a lot of what you've talked about previously on the show.
I am downloading it now because it seems like they have caught on to the concept of
it seems like they have caught on to the zeitgeist.
I can't speak to it because I haven't really tried this release, but I will.
They're very friendly every time you talk with the devs and they generally fix the stuff
you complain about.
I had that experience, but also weirdly enough, every time I go to IRC to talk with them,
I get a huge influx, an increase of influx of spam from China.
That may be just a coincidence.
Um, the also the other thing is I guess maybe why people are reluctant to actually use it
as a daily driver, even though there's, you know, technically it's being open source
and we can check it is that the power that Chinese government has on Chinese companies
or whatever organization runs on China.
That generally I think would be their biggest bottleneck, right?
The elephant in the room always.
They did announce that they did have contracts with in some ways with the government.
That makes it even worse.
Like I guess it will work well for their market because all right, people already are using
the system, right?
And are already bound to the same legislation.
So I guess it makes sense.
Like if you're using it's like we understand, you know, Google is going to be a friend of
NSA and so Microsoft, we understand that and we're generally okay because we have that
same regulatory environment in every other company that operates in our territory.
So for them might be okay, but for us it feels like, okay, this is a party we don't really
go with.
Good points.
Dar, you're on fire today.
I wasn't going to say it for some reason, but I agree that is that was the elephant
in the room.
I don't know why I just felt like it was inappropriate to bring it up.
So I'm glad that you said something.
What do you think, Michael?
It is interesting and it definitely has to be said because it's just it just is what
it is, but there's no there's no evidence that there's they're doing anything wrong
as far as tracking information or anything.
There's been multiple attempts to show like to test to see if there's any like spyware
or anything.
And while there are some things that are somewhat sketchy, none of it's technically any kind
of spyware.
So as far as me, the reason why I don't use it is because it doesn't have plasma.
And that was an easy choice.
Boom, right there.
And funny enough, we probably have higher scrutiny for Deepin because just sort of where
they are based and we actually check more than stuff done in our own region.
But, you know, people are biased and isn't that funny?
You're so right.
We should be we should be much more critical of stuff coming out of the US really than
we are.
So all fair points around.
I want to talk to Wimpy in a moment about his his new NUC.
But before we go there, how about just a super brief update on the progress of the Librem
five?
It's something we've been tracking fairly steadily on Linux Action News, but we've kind
of had a few smaller developments that don't quite rank moving up to Linux Action News.
So I thought I'd just bust them out here for you.
First of all, in case you didn't know or forgot, it is a Wayland stack on the Librem five and
they're continuing to work on that.
They've been testing the vibrators in that thing, chargers and the usability improvements
to their posh phone shell.
Posh is the name and they say it's running on top of Wayland now.
They've had some lock screen improvements, arrow widgets were added to the library for
swiping, et cetera, so you can get a little overlay.
They're continuing to work on their back end GTK three calling application that their
dialer application that they call calls.
Clever.
And on the hardware front, they continue evaluating components like the Wi-Fi module.
Still an evaluation right now.
Vibration motors and battery charges.
You got to test some of that stuff, make sure it's the right stuff, especially battery
chargers, I would imagine.
And they're also exploring camera options still for the Librem five.
And I think like all of the previous outreaches, it's really top notch.
Purism has a great blog where they're really keeping everybody up to date and all this
kind of stuff.
They're working hard, I would imagine.
Having been inside companies, they're trying to expose the great work that's happening
to the blog.
It can be a long process and I really commend them for doing that because I love watching
how they're building this thing.
Looking at the prototype stuff that they're doing and the fact that you can get a prototype
sent to you and stuff like that, it's just so cool that there's people now doing videos
of them testing stuff, showing the plasma mobile working on the prototype builds and
stuff like that.
It's very cool to see.
I was under the impression that the plasma mobile folks hadn't got Librem five test
hardware yet.
Although they don't have it.
The Librem Purism is doing it.
The plasma mobile people are getting prototypes.
But the fact that they're showing that plasma mobile is working on their current prototypes
that Purism themselves are doing it to show that it is functional.
That's very cool.
Yeah.
So I think a couple other folks are still waiting to get their test hardware yet.
But maybe they're not there yet.
And it also sounds like Michael Larabell over at Ferronix has noted that they're using
a secondary processor.
So one processor is not good enough, Wes.
They're going to have two processors and it really comes down to the binary blobs.
Did you catch this?
Yeah.
It's interesting.
Well, Chris, your freedom is important, right?
And if that's kind of the whole point of what you're trying to do, it's interesting to see
them taking this rather maybe serious approach and just not have to deal with that.
Not have to embed them on that first processor.
Have a secondary unit that they can talk to you and try to get that information with.
And still, quote unquote, respecting your freedom.
Yeah.
That's a neat trick.
So you get the Free Software Foundation's AOK because it's a secondary processor.
So they need a binary blob for this phone to do the DDR4 memory training.
Of course you do.
That's just we're still there.
We're still in that world.
Oh, wow, though.
Like that's what we're up against is binary blobs that train the DDR4 RAM how to behave
timing wise on boot every single boot.
Like that's the level that we are trying to get down to here.
OK, talk me out of this because right now I'm feeling like this is like an impossible
never ending war that we are going to be constantly behind, never able to catch up on.
So talk me out of this, Dar.
No, I'm not going to talk you out of it.
I'm going to make it worse.
There is just in U.S., for example, there is a law Communications Assistance for Law
Enforcement Act or CALEA for short.
This legislation actually has been used and there's money that government even gives
to companies to make sure that their hardware and software is updated to allow actually
into lawful interception.
So I am curious to see how they're going to do because one of the reasons modems in
phones have direct access is not only for performance when it comes down to, you know,
reaching out to your microphone and your speaker.
And they also have a real time capability.
They connect to the tower.
They have generally overriding capabilities on top of their actual phone OS.
That's also because it helps with complying with CALEA law when you want to sell in the
United States market.
I actually am curious to see how they're going to do this.
Also, on top of this, if you have a VoIP service or even if you just make, let's say, an IP
based only phone, right?
You just you use data.
Well, CALEA law also says that if you are doing VoIP services, you're then classified
as a carrier, the VoIP provider, and therefore you have to support CALEA as well.
There's that part that is interesting too.
So what about this idea of breaking it out into a secondary co-processor or second processor
that you could almost change out per region or situation?
Like, is that a good idea?
That could, I could see that actually working, but it seems like it would add complexity.
It's an excellent idea.
It adds complexity.
Of course, it will drain your battery slightly more.
Hopefully Linux, you know, in Plasma will just be more battery efficient.
We hope for that.
And, you know, at least we're trying, which has been usually the biggest bottleneck is
nobody actually tries because the know-how is, the requirement is just too big, right?
To do it as a single man.
And now there's a team working on it.
Maybe we'll start to find, but I am skeptical.
And I think that in the end of the day, the fight will still end up in the same place.
It's going to be a fight to live in the same place.
It's going to be a fight to legislative reform and not necessarily on the technical means
because the law is there and you have to comply with it, especially because you're selling
a product.
So now my last bit is a bit of a miss for the Purism folks is it looks like potentially
they may have an issue with their iMX8 ARM processor that's going to be in the Librem5.
It just missed the 4.18 kernel window and that's a bit of an issue for them because
the next window for 4.19 will be the last release of 2018.
And so if this iMX8 ARM processor bits, especially the bits around the system on the chip, because
part of it is already actually in the kernel, like the SATA support and some DRM bits are
already upstream in the Linux kernel.
So close.
Yeah, I know.
It's just the rest of the bits of the system on the chip, like the drivers and all that
kind of stuff that haven't made it in the kernel yet.
And if they don't get squared away by 4.19, then there's really not going to be a kernel
for the Librem5 that has upstreamed all of the driver support.
Right.
They can build it in the meanwhile, deal with the situation of the SATA back and be then
the ones providing a kernel that supports the things that they need until they sync
back up and then you're just getting normal releases.
I don't see that as a huge issue.
It's manageable, probably.
I feel like that phrase is said a lot and, you know, it's manageable, probably.
Sometimes that works out, sometimes not.
We will see that.
But yes, it probably is right.
Like if they can just build it with those almost upstream sources and manage their transition,
if they already have a resilient sort of, you know, updating system in place where they
can fall back if it fails, then there's less risk.
If they don't, aren't smart about that, then maybe it's riskier.
It's a phone, it better update well.
It better update well, right?
Yeah, exactly.
It's a phone, it better update well, right?
So it's a good thing, actually.
Let them try it before you buy it.
It's certainly interesting work that Purism are doing with the Librem 5.
You know, there's a lot of technical challenges here and there's a lot of innovation that
needs to happen in order to create a device like this.
But I think the people that are following this project and particularly those people
that are backing the project probably need to reset their expectations as to when they
need to reset their expectations as to when this phone is going to ship as an actual device.
Because I've backed a number of mobile phone type crowdfunding devices in the last 18 months
or so.
And at the moment, they're posting lots of interesting information about the hardware
enablement that they're doing, and the applications that they're writing and their display stack
and all the rest of it.
Their goal is to launch in January, February next year.
On the crowdfunders for similar mobile devices, six months from delivery dates, they were
making prototype devices and manufacturing runs to test the manufacturing processes to
square away quality assurance, you know, niggles and what have you so that they could start
to plan for production runs.
And on both these crowdfunders I'm referring to, one was the Jelly Pro phone and the other
was the Gemini PDA, even though they were doing this four and six months before their
release deadlines for the devices, both missed their release targets by four and seven months,
even though they were, you know, that far along in their, you know, production planning,
actually making the devices.
So for all of the interesting things that are going in in the software, whilst the wireless
chipset is not agreed and whilst the camera module is not agreed, that means that the
casing dimensions and what have you is also not agreed yet.
So they can't be in a place where they're producing casing samples and starting production
runs.
So I think, you know, these devices are going to ship into the back end of 2019.
Hmm, not January?
It will be a Herculean effort if Purism pull it off and they deserve, you know, a round
of applause and all the champagne corks popping in celebration if they do it.
But I can't see how they're going to be able to do that because from what I understand,
they don't have engineering samples of the devices and they don't even have dev boards,
you know, available to all of the people that are working on this stuff yet.
So, you know, hardware enablement needs to happen in various projects and those developers
will need devices in order to do that.
So it's a very interesting project and it's great to see all of the updates.
But, you know, in terms of actually producing a device, a phone that you can hold and use,
I think there's some considerable way out yet.
Yeah, I can't really argue with you on that.
That all kind of adds up.
So let's talk about your NUC for a moment because I have been thinking about making
this RV studio setup permanent.
The part that is not permanent right now is I'm just using my XPS laptop, which is not
quite the right machine for the job.
And I also would like to have that machine available while I'm doing the show for like
browsing the web and whatnot.
And I've been thinking about installing a NUC in a cupboard.
So above where I'm sitting, I have a cabinet and in that cabinet, I have a DBX 286.
I have a PreSonos sound interface and then I have a USB-C hub where I have all of that
stuff connected in and then one USB-C cord down to my XPS.
And I can get all of that with one cord and it's fantastic.
I love it.
Beautiful.
It's great.
I could make it a little bit better, though, if the machine was permanent.
If it wasn't my personal laptop that I just play around with and I use to play video games,
even though it's not got a great video card.
A podcasting station right there in the RV.
Wes, you might call it a podcasting workstation.
Oh, I like it.
So the NUC was really what came to mind because I could just slot it right on top of all this
equipment in the cupboard and it has USB-C on it.
But the last time I talked to Wimpy about it, he said,
there's some stuff missing from the kernel so it doesn't work so good.
He didn't quite say it in that high pitched voice.
But I don't know, a little birdie tells me that perhaps Wimpy has reached some level of success
and now I can't help myself.
I'm beginning to dream, Wimpy.
How are things going with your Linux experiment on the new, what is it, the Hades Canyon NUC?
Yeah, it's the Hades Canyon.
I have a fully hardware accelerated Hades Canyon NUC now.
So I thought the big problem was that the video drivers weren't in the kernel yet from Intel,
like they hadn't actually submitted them upstream or they hadn't.
No, so well, it's actually from AMD because this is a Vega M GPU.
So it's actually the work of AMD.
So what's happened in the last week is this.
Linux kernel 4.18 release candidate one has been released and the necessary kernel drivers
exist in the 4.18 kernel.
So you need the 4.18 kernel.
You need the microcode for the RX Vega M GPU, which is not in the upstream Linux firmware
Git repository yet, but it is available from AMD's staging Git repository.
And the other thing you need is Mesa 18.1.1 or newer.
Are you writing this down, Chris?
The weekend, an interesting thing happened.
So you can install Ubuntu 18.04, any of the flavors will do.
And the Ubuntu mainline kernel PPA now has 4.18 RC1 in it.
So you can go and grab that kernel and Timo Altonen, who's the maintainer for the graphics
stack in Ubuntu, he's been updating Mesa in 18.04, but has also started to prep what will
be the new enablement stack and Mesa 18.1.1 is in the X updates PPA.
So just by turning on a couple of PPAs and installing a different kernel and updating,
you know, just doing an update to pull in those Mesa updates and then adding the microcode
into lib firmware, lib firmware AMD GPU, I now have the whole thing going, which is great.
And it's performing quite well.
Now, the thing is, is that for this to really fly, it needs Mesa 18.2, which is currently
in development. So if you and what I haven't done yet is test this configuration with Mesa
18.2. So that's a project for this weekend. And I expect some modest performance games
by doing that. But right now, as a workstation, all the bits and bobs are now working.
And work casting pod station is what FreqLab calls it in the IRC. And I think that's not
bad.
Just a pod station.
It's a pod station. It sounds like it's a bit of work, but not insurmountable.
It's really, really quite straightforward. Yeah. Once you know, once you know what needs
doing, doing it is really quite straightforward.
Yeah. So how likely would any of this be to land and say like a hardware enablement of
1804?
So by Ubuntu 1804.2, all of the necessary bits and pieces should be landed in order
for this to function.
Oh, I mean, you know, I mean, that sounds really nice.
Yeah. But what I'm talking to some people about at work is also so 18.2 will be out
just after 18.10. So the other thing we're talking about is trying to make sure that
everything we need is landed in 18.10. Because it turns out resellers of these NUCs have
approached Ubuntu and asked about, you know, getting the enablement going for these devices
because it turns out lots of Linux users have been buying them.
Yeah. Good. Good. Voting with the wallet does actually work, it sounds like.
Yeah. And the other thing to add, I think I may have mentioned this before, but the
LVFS project with all of the firmware updating and what have you, this device, all of its
bits and bobs are supported in LVFS. So I was able to do the firmware and BIOS upgrades
all through FWUPD.
Oh, that's fantastic.
Just pretty, pretty nice. Yeah.
That's like a, that is a sleek system now.
That is. Oh, okay. So I think that will be the pod station, but I may be just lazy enough
to wait till 18.02 just simply because, 18.04.2, because after this road trip, and I'm not
going to get the NUC on this road trip, I'm back in studio for a while. So I won't really
need it. So I don't think, I don't know. I don't think, although I say that and then
something comes up and I'm back on the road.
It's just going to happen.
Are you making me want to do it? And the eGPU stuff's all working too Wimpy? The device
is your main driver at this point?
So literally this, this has been, I've got this working within the last 36 hours. So
it's on the desk behind me and I need to like move over all of my data and configurations
and what have you know, I haven't done any of that yet. I've been running benchmarks
and things on it and playing games on it and what have you, but I've not set it up for
real work yet, but it will be over the course of this weekend, it will be transitioning
to my dedicated workstation. And whilst it does work with external GPUs because it has
two Thunderbolt 3 enabled USB-C sockets on it. So you can really go to town with your
Thunderbolt on this device. I want to run it with just the integrated GPU, which in
terms of performance right now with Mesa 18.1.1 is operating around the performance of like
a GTX 1050, something like that. So it's good enough that for 1080p gaming with, you know,
medium to high settings, it's absolutely fine. As soon as you start cranking things
up to, you know, 1440p and you really sort of turn on all of the features, then it starts
to run about, you know, 30 frames a second for the games. But if you go at 1080p, it's
more than capable.
Yeah, fair enough. Yeah. And I, you know, for what I'd be using it for, that would be
totally great. Well, that's a good update. I'm glad to hear all that.
If you've got any GPU, then you just plug in another device. And on that front, I've
also got a Razer Core X now as well.
Oh, what? And how do you like this? And no, so the Razer Core X, isn't that, that's like
the, it was released what, three months ago or something? It's like a fairly new external
GPU unit.
No, the Razer Core X was released a couple of weeks ago. So some time ago. Oh, yeah,
this is brand new. So some time ago I got the Razer Core and then I got the revised
model which was the Razer Core V2. And now I have the Razer Core X. So this is, these
are eGPU enclosures. The difference between the Razer Core X and the earlier models is
it's a much bigger device. So it can take triple width cards. So if you've got a graphics
card with one of these super spanky cooling solutions on it, you know, that makes it super
fat, then it can accommodate those. It's got a higher rated power supply. So it can take
the RX Vega 64, for example, which the other models can't quite cope with. And this one's
cheaper. This is half the price of the other. So this is $250 instead of $500. And those
cost savings come from the fact that it doesn't have any RGB and it doesn't expose any additional
USB ports or ethernet ports on the, on the back of the device, like the, the Razer Core
V1 and V2.
Ah, it's not quite like a hub.
No, it's not like a hub. It is just an enclosure for a PCI card basically.
Yeah, but I do like that additional power.
Yeah, yeah, exactly. So I've put my RX Vega 56 in that now and I'll be selling the Razer
Core V1 so I should keep the V2 and keep the X. I'm all about the eGPUs. I'm an eGPU hipster.
Yeah, you are. Well, I want to talk a little bit about games here in a moment. In fact,
one that you were playing on your live stream in a bit. So actually, let's pick that thread
back up. But let's, let's take a moment and mention a quick app pick and then we'll do
our sponsor block. I first want to mention, though, this is one that came in from James
via the contact form at linuxunplug.com slash contact. And it is a early days, self-hosted
Google Photos clone. Frickin' finally. That's all I have to say about that. It's self-hosted.
It is a front and a back end. Django back end and a React front end. It's in heavy development
right now. Some features are currently implemented. You can label faces, you know, so that way
you can find all your Westpain pictures.
That's right. You want those.
You do, of course. I've got a Westpain search. Westpain all the time. All the time. It's
Docker ready too, Wes. So this is, I think, actually you might have found this. I don't
think I found this. I think you... No, no, it was sent in by James. I just said that.
I don't know if you had a chance to look at it, Wes, but it looks like it could be the
beginning.
Actually, yes, I'm playing with the demo right now. It's not bad. I mean, for the basic browsing
around, looking around, it seemed just fine. There's several galleries on the demo site
of seemingly random faces grouped together, so I don't know what that says about the actual
application performance. But otherwise, it was a fine UI. It seemed to work well.
Yes, you can check it out. If you go to the link we'll have in the show notes, linuxownplug.com
slash 254, and the login is demo. Demo and then demo1234. And the guy says right here
in the Jithub, as Noah calls it, that it's early days. But it's called OwnPhotos. No
relation to OwnCloud or like OwnNotes or anything. It's just a name. It's a semi-name
collision. That happens all the time. And it's got back end. It's got like a back end
and a front end. So the theory could be that if this were to take off, one day you could
have like, say, Shotwell that is using the back end of this thing and Shotwell is a front
end or something. So it could have some potential. Could have some potential. And probably with
a little bit of help from the open source community, it might get there. So we'll have
a link to that in the show notes. Otherwise, like Noah says, it's up on the Jithub.
Now let's talk about our sponsors this week. We're doing this new in the show and I'm actually
sort of actively soliciting feedback on it. We're trying to block all the sponsors together.
It's what's sort of become the new standard in the podcast industry. If you subscribe
to more newer podcasts, you'll notice that about this percentage into the show, it's
kind of like percentage based on the content. They have a real formula for it. It's pretty
adorable. And they put the ads here. They put them right here and they say, we'll put
them all back to back and you listen to this bit and then it doesn't interrupt the flow
of the content earlier or later in the show. I like the idea and I want to see what you
guys think because it also gives me an opportunity to sort of collect all of the cool things
that our sponsors are doing and link them all up in one spot and collate all of that
and kind of get the word out there about the things that our different sponsors are actively
doing because you may have heard of them before. You may know that Linux Academy sponsors us
or that Digital Ocean or Ting sponsored the show. You may know that by now. But you might
not know the new stuff that they're doing. So that's the other thing I kind of like about
this opportunity. So I am actively looking for your feedback. Tweet me at Chris Ellis
or send it into the contact page at Linux Unplugged dot com slash content. So let's
start with Linux Academy because that's why I am on the road. I'm on my way back from
Linux Academy. I'll tell you about that here in just a couple of minutes. Wrapped up their
OBS system, got it all built for them. And while I was there, I started to get the inside
scoop. People are working just like heads down like maniacs on this new content launch
they're doing in July. Now in April, I told you about 70 plus new challenges and courseware
and updates and all the stuff that they'd rolled out. And I was like, that's their biggest
content push ever. Well, in July, they're basically bringing Christmas to July with
150 new courses, challenges and learning activities. They're going to be launching in July. And
this reason I was down there was for their ability to live stream and sort of try to
message what is in all of this update. Because when you get to 150, it starts to get lost
a little bit in the details. And so that's one of the reasons they want to start doing
more live streams. So they can kind of break it down, do giveaways, tell people about what's
in there, that kind of stuff. But this isn't official yet. But I got the scuttlebutt. Like
I was talking to some of the course authors. I got an idea of what's coming down the pipe.
So if you're a Linux Academy subscriber already, if you went to Linux Academy dot com slash
unplugged, you're going to get all of this stuff. Or if you want to go subscribe, you
can get it soon. And this is just one or two of many things. But it looks like they're
going to be slipping in in this 150 plus bundle. Saltstack certification training, Red Hat's
certification for expertise and virtualization, also Red Hat's expertise cert and ansible,
and a Red Hat certified architect full support, which is a big one, I guess, in the industry.
The Red Hat certified architect full support. Also a couple other ones that sounded kind
of interesting. A Lambda deep dive. They're going to have a course where they're going
to be slipping in that 150 bundle. And an AWS security specialty certification. In fact,
I didn't really get the details on this, but it looked like they're going to be doing a
lot of stuff with security. Like that's going to be a big area Linux Academy is going to
go into.
Please.
And it looks like, yeah. And I think they're even doing hiring around that, too, to try
to staff up. That's going to be awesome. So if you're not familiar with Linux Academy,
you can subscribe for seven days for free when you go to Linux Academy dot com slash
unplugged and try out their hands-on labs, their courseware, their schedule planner,
hang out in the community that's stacked full of Jupyter Broadcasting members. They've got
courseware on AWS, Azure, and anything around Linux. Or if it runs Linux or Linux runs on
top of that. And if you're ready to sort of like upgrade your skills on OpenStack or if
you ever need help, they have instructors that are there to help you. It's a great service.
And they're launching Christmas in July with 150 new ways to train and learn, as well as
some Azure courseware that's going to be in there, although I didn't get the details on
what, because the Azure courseware is like, it's hard for my brain to remember, because
it's like, it's like Azure 70-535. And I'm like, what does that even mean? Whereas with
like Red Hat, it's Red Hat certification of expertise and virtualization. I kind of get
what that means. So that I grok. But they're just doing it's a whole bunch of stuff. And
they have some blog posts that are teasing some of it out. So you can check that out.
So thanks to Linux Academy. And thanks to everybody who goes to linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged to sign up, support the show, and get a free seven day trial. And speaking of
good deals, a big thank you to Ting for supporting the Unplugged program for a long, long time
now. The storm has cleared. I don't know if you can hear it, but the storm has cleared
in the background. And my Ting connection is strong. Ting is smarter than unlimited.
If you use less, you pay less. The average Ting bill is just $23 per month. It's $6 for
your phone, $6 for the line. And then it's just your minutes, your messages, and your
megabytes on top of that. Nationwide coverage, you can rest assured that Ting's got your
coverage from coast to coast. They got coverage. And they got CDMA and GSM. So you can pick
whatever works better in your area. Today, I'm on CDMA. I think last time we did the
show, I might have been on GSM. I can't remember, because I just have both now. It's $6 a month
for the line. That's a pretty easy expense to cover. And I use it like a couple of times
a year. I love that, because Ting has a control panel where I can go in and I could actually
turn the service off if I wanted to. I could transfer it. When Rekai decided to go do Twitch
full-time, we transferred his line out of my Ting account to him. So he could just keep
that phone number, keep that phone, all that stuff. It's really nice. And in that particular
case too, their customer service was fantastic, because they need my permission to do a thing.
And then he's got to call up and activate a thing and give payment info. And they were
totally cool about just sort of coordinating all of that. And it's just a super nice aspect
of Ting that doesn't get enough attention. But on top of paying for what you use and
that control panel, they have a great set of devices that you can go grab. Or because
they support CDMA or GSM, you can bring your own. Just check their BYOD page. And for a
little bit, I want to tell you about their giveaway. They're doing something new here.
It's the hashtag Ting Summer. Hashtag pound sign. Pound sign. Ting Summer. And if you
do that, when you like to submit a photo to Twitter or Instagram, and it's a good, you
know, it probably doesn't have to be that good. Let's be honest. They're going to be
nice. They're Ting after all. But try to take a good one. And then do a hashtag on their
Ting Summer on the Facebook, on the Twitter, on the Instagram. And you will get entered
for a bi-weekly giveaway of the Moto Z2 Play. They're also going to give away the True Zoom
Moto Mod snap-on that gives it like an actual DSLR lens on the Moto. If you ever see a picture
of this thing, Wes, it's like a full-fledged lens on the back of a camera, or on the back
of a phone. It's ridiculous. It's awesome though. And they're giving it away for like,
you know, using a hashtag. So I just encourage you to... Ting is awesome, dude. They're just
insane. There's a few rules and the whatnot, so just go over to their blog. But do me a
favor. Start by going to linux.ting.com. That'll take $25 off a device, or if you bring one,
it'll give you $25 in service credit. But on top of that, it lets them know you heard
it here, linux.ting.com, and then click over to that blog post and read about the giveaway.
Because I think you can get on that. I think you could probably get in on that. You know,
sometimes Wes is snapping a few pictures there in that Seattle area. You had that hashtag,
Wes, you might get yourself... I'm on there liking that stuff. I see it. I'm like, oh
yeah, that's good. I'm liking that. You know that? I want you to know I'm liking your stuff
sometimes. It's important you know that. Hashtag Ting Summer. All right. Now, before we go
any further, I got one more thing to give out here, because we all love and know Digital
Ocean, and you can get in on the goodness, do.co.plugged. Get a $100 credit. Yeah, 100s.
100s applied to your account for 60 days when you sign up with a new account. 100s in Digital
Ocean credit is... It's way more than you need. It's an excessive amount of credit.
I think you should go sign up, because I don't know why they haven't turned this off yet,
to be honest with you. If I was Digital Ocean, I would cut this crap off right now. Because
I don't know what you're doing with that 100 bucks. Because here's the thing. Our previous
promo was 10 bucks. That was enough. 10 bucks was enough, Wes. Just like 640k of RAM was
enough. Yeah, right. It's crazy. It was. It was plenty. And now $100. You know, back in
my day, back in my day, we got $10 in credit. And then even further back in my day, we had
to rack our own gear. Okay? So now you're gonna... I can't even with you guys. But if
you go over there to do.co.plugged until Crazy Digital Ocean quits it, you can sign up. And
with a new account, you'll get that 100 credit. And you can try to deploy a system in seconds.
I mean, it just only takes you seconds to get a system up and going. You want to go
try out GitLab and say, screw you to Microsoft, which I don't necessarily agree with. But
I don't judge you either. Well, you can do it with that 100 credit and then just see
how perfectly useful it is and then just keep paying. That's probably what I would do. But
you know what? I can't really say what you're gonna do. You may just want to seed your favorite
distribution for a bit. But they do have some really cool options. Like you can mix and
match droplet resources now, which is kind of a new feature for Digital Ocean. So say
you want like a lot of CPU for all that Monero. Well, then you can just throw like a ton of
CPU, which I also do not recommend. But you could. And let's just say you want a lot of
disk because you're like Crazy Chris and you're backing up all the photos from your road trip
using Nextcloud to your cloud, which is your own cloud up on the Digital Ocean. I want
all the disk, Wes. That's what I do. So I attach 250 gigs of block storage. That's how
I do. And let's just say that I had this really long video message I wanted to send Wes. You
know how I would do that? Digital Ocean spaces generate an URL. You know what somebody ought
to do is they ought to take and this is a serious thing. They ought to take that Digital
Ocean API, which is really well documented, easy to understand, and I think their crazy
great dashboard might be a client of because it's feature complete. I tell you what. Just
make me one app for iOS and you can make it for those Androids if you want to put it in
the share sheet. So I hit a share button. It comes up and then I hit a button on my
share sheet and it creates a Digital Ocean space using the API with my account and then
it generates a link and then I could send that file to Wes because you see that would
be awesome because the Digital Ocean API is so slick that there's already tons of great
open source software that's been created for it. So this is just one more thing that Chris
is asking for. Somebody out there go take advantage of it. Also, because Digital Ocean
is not satisfied with just giving you $100 in credit, they're also going to enable you
to donate your time for writing tutorials to open source projects and charities. You
can write for donations. I'll have a link in the show notes. And if you want to write
up some, say you're an expert on WireGuard, which is probably not super common yet, or
maybe something else that is more common that people are interested in, you could go write
that up, submit it to Digital Ocean, and if they like it, what they were going to pay
you because they do sometimes pay their course authors or whoever is writing up like the
tutorials and stuff. Instead of giving it to you, they'll give it to the charity of
your choice. Isn't that pretty cool? Up to $400 too. I have information in the show notes
if you want to check that out. dio.co slash unplugged and a big thank you to Digital Ocean
for sponsoring the unplugged program. So I got some retro gaming nostalgia on during
Linux Fest Texas and it feels sort of good. Like at first I was like I shouldn't do this.
I shouldn't succumb to nostalgia. I shouldn't allow myself to revert. And you know, I don't
want to be like my folks who like are still listening to the stuff from high school when
they were in high school. They listen to that music. I don't. I try to keep my music taste
current even though all new music is horrible. I want to stay fresh. I want to stay current.
I don't want to let myself become an old man. However, the classics are the classics, man.
And and you can't ever beat Mario. Mario's solid. And there's some other things like
in that category. Like I will. I still love to sit down and play a great game of Doom.
Can't help it. I love it. And another game in that category for me where it may not look
the best. It may not be peak first person shooter. But damn, I love original quake and
and if if this didn't land at just the right time for my soul, there is now a snap to install
quake shareware snap install quick dash shareware and you can play the classic quake first person
shooter back when it games is making quake. And you get the shareware one boom right there
and it's done. It's good to go. Isn't that awesome? This couldn't possibly be easier.
I don't think Melissa came reinstalled. But that's really just that's not that's crazy
sauce. So yes, I know what I'm doing after the show. I also because I'm kind of snap
stupid. So maybe somebody could educate me on this. But I have a snap installed that
I cannot link you to and I don't understand how this works. Because it's in the snap store.
So I thought I could go to snap craft.io and link you to it. But I installed something
I think I can't remember the exact syntax, but something like snap install, go g dash
galaxy dash wine space dash dash edge, I think. And then I get the go g galaxy client for
Windows in a snap container. And I just use that to log into my go g account and started
installing software. And it was great. And I wanted to link you all to it. So you could
try it out. But I don't understand maybe because it's an edge release. I can't link you to
it. Is that what it is? So by default, the web version of the store only shows you stable
channel snaps. And it hides everything in the other channels. But we're looking to change
that. So you will be able to see and link to snaps that are in other channels. But it's
just the default at the moment is stable only. Okay, so that is out there if you want to
install it, I don't really know what the utility of it is other than it just made it really
easy to get the galaxy client going. And then I installed a couple of games. I also I recently
installed the battle net manager so I could get Diablo two and Starcraft three installed.
Yeah, this is it's been happening over here was it's been happening. The guy who made
that go g galaxy snap is actually in the IRC is still down. And he's going to give you
the what you need to do to to to run it. Oh, thank you, sir. Very nice.
So the other thing that I noticed was created as a snap. It's not exactly a retro game,
although it did come out in 2008. So I guess that was like a decade ago, is Trackmania
nations forever, which I got to watch you and wimpy play on wimpy's live stream the
other night. This is now a snap that you can just install somehow. I don't understand how
this works. Maybe somebody can explain explain this to me. You can snap install the Trackmania
snap and it comes down. It pulls down like a Windows installer, which then launches and
loads additional software. Am I getting this right?
Yeah, yeah. So Trackmania nations forever is a free to play Windows game, but it's proprietary
and you can't redistribute it. So the snap is called TM nations forever. And the snap
contains a wine runtime and some scripts to bootstrap that environment. So when you install
the TM nations forever snap and run it for the first time, it interrogates the isolated
wine prefix, sees that the game isn't there, reaches out to the internet, downloads the
installer from the internet, and then installs the game into the contained wine environment
that that snap created. And then you have you that you now have this Windows game running
in wine inside the snap. And now it's just a game that you can use. And also, you're
saying it's retro. But for me, I've been using Linux on a full time basis for 13 years by
the time this game came out. So when I actually discovered it for the first time, this was
a new game, as far as I was concerned, irrespective of what the release date was. And I think
it stands up. I mean, it's it's quite, it's pretty, it runs very fast. It works really
well on integrated graphics and discrete graphics. And it's it's at and the most important thing
is, it's really, really good fun. It's easy to play, but very, very difficult to put down.
Yes. Yeah, I really just enjoyed watching you to play it the other night on your live
stream. And I thought to myself, like, when I when I saw the year was 2008, I thought
to myself, how did I miss that? When I was watching them play that the other night, I
would have thought it was a game for maybe just two years ago. It did look really sharp.
So the 2008 thing isn't a put down. The other thing is when we were doing that live stream,
we were both live streaming. So the papi was live streaming to his channel, and I was streaming
to mine. But we were obviously using the snap of the game. We were using a snap of Firefox
to drive twitch. We were using a snap of discord to communicate with each other. We were using
a snap of OBS to do the live streaming, and then a snap of telegram to orchestrate our
listeners. And we were joined by several of the Ubuntu podcast listeners who installed
the snap and came in and joined us in game.
Incredible.
That's the part I like. Yeah, it just makes it super easy for people watching to also
play snap install and you're good to go. Which is, that's a really great feature.
Yeah, and this was extensive QA because we just published that snap into the stable channel.
So being the dedicated people that we are, papi and I were doing QA on Twitch from half
past nine until half past one in the morning just to make absolutely sure it all worked
fine.
Bless you.
I love my job.
That is the kind of dedication that you just can't pay for. You know, that is true dedication,
gentlemen.
Yeah. Write a letter to Canonical and stall them.
Right.
Mark at Ubuntu.com.
Yeah, yeah. Well, it does seem to work quite well. And so we'll have links to that in the
show notes as well. Mr. West, you and I were debating on the pre-show, like how to cover
this next story. It's from a listener of the show, Pro Bono, and he's also involved with
AppImage. And it does influence his write up a bit over on Medium, but he makes some
solid points about Linux desktop usability. And he writes, why do desktop environments
increasingly degrade the desktop UX that once used to be straightforward and common sense?
Now stick with us here. This isn't like the common rebaked argument we hear all the time.
And don't mistake Pro Bono for anti Linux. He's a fan of the Linux desktop and the projects
we're going to talk about here. But he says there seems to be a tendency specifically
for desktop environments and applications to mess around with the proven concept of
menus. Menus specifically seem to be what have him upset. And Bill Atkinson, the inventor
of menus, well describes them. He says in a quote, I'm proud of the pull down menus.
I thought that pull down menu was a very good solution to providing visibility, spatial
memory of where the commands were as well. And that's a you can find that quote in the
Computer History Museum as well. He says, Pro Bono, he says, he goes on, why is there
an unsettling tendency to kill the beloved file, edit, etc. menus that also date back
to the Lisa interface that has been engraved in our brain muscles for 40 years? This goes
way back. But yet, we seem to keep wanting to reinvent it. Going back to Bill Atkinson,
another quote, he says, the nice thing about this menu was because the titles of the menus
were always much narrower than the items. It basically tripled your effective screen.
You could scan along the top and see all available commands without doing any of them. You could
harmlessly see what is available. And discoverability seems to be a big point of Pro Bono's case
here. He mentions like the new GTK three pop over menus, which they were super, super proud
of have taken out all of the keyboard shortcut commands in order to make the menu shorter.
So there's like no control C for copy, no control P for paste, no control S by the save.
Discoverability is gone. But to make matters worse is then the browsers really started
this offense is it's all compounded by the hamburger menu. Like we gave Microsoft a hard
time for the ribbon. But the hamburger menu is the biggest offender of all of them because
it's just this lazy cram everything in this three dot menu. Just put it all in there,
cram it all in there. And that's really like a huge step back. In fact, and I love this,
Pro Bono goes to point out in his post that when you go way, way, way back to 1981, the
Xerox Star, the original thing that Apple ripped off the idea from and iterated on,
the Xerox Star had a hamburger menu in 1981, had a fricking hamburger menu in 1981. And
then Pro Bono shows the design notes for the Lisa interface where they try out a global
menu, application menus, and they also try out a hamburger menu. Like they try out all
the different stuff in the 1980s, early 1980s, and they have solid notes on why those designs
did or did not work. And so when we go back to the hamburger menu, when we drop global
menus, his point, Pro Bono's point is we're actually going back to design mistakes of
the early 1980s that designers worked and iterated to get us out of for years. And now
some of the most popular open source desktops like GNOME 3 are making the mistake that we
made 40 years ago. And Wes, this is a pretty strong argument that he makes with lots of
pull quotes, screenshots, early UI concept design. And it leaves me just going like damn,
dude really has a point here. What did you think?
Well, we are lucky to live in a pretty rich ecosystem of different paradigms that you
would like to use. And he makes reference to a really large number of them, especially
in projects like Monte where there's even more customization of different layout styles.
I think some of his points are spot on about there are some simple features that could
help discoverability that like, maybe if they're not enabled, is an option of the installer.
Maybe there's some degrees between not having them at all or options to have them there.
I'm wondering what do you think in now that you've spent some time with Plasma? Do you
think any of this is less relevant?
I tell you one of the things that I like about having in Plasma is I've gone in, I've turned
on all of the menus for like in Dolphin. By default, they're off. But now when I launched
Dolphin, I have like my alt, you know, if you hold down alt to get those menus, I have
them now. And the reason why is what he points out where he makes a strong case here is discoverability.
When I'm learning a new UI, I like to have that style, I like to get the little hint
of what the Ctrl C would do for copy or what the Ctrl S would do for save. Like, if I didn't
know that, how do I learn that unless it's put in some menu somewhere? And he makes a
strong case for global menus, which I am not so sold on. Because the basic idea for global
menus comes down to, well, look, you can jam your mouse up to the top of the screen faster
than you can finesse it to the top of an application. That I'm not so sold on. I don't know, does
anybody in the Mumba room have thoughts as has the desktop made steps?
So I actually did a good portion of a master's thesis on the Linux desktop usability. And
I tested Cinnamon, Mate, KDE. It was all the stuff that was on Antegros back in the day
that was all the defaults that were there. I didn't install anything special. And the
most quote unquote usable desktop was Cinnamon. And if you look in the Hacker News comments
for this article, there's actually quite a few people who say, oh, have you tried Cinnamon
in some kind of magical way? And I think there's a lot of stuff that different desktop environments
do well.
And one of the things that's mentioned in the article is on the Mac, for example, they
have the search in menus for help. I can't tell you how many times that's actually saved
my bacon when I've been looking for something quickly. And I think there's a lot of small
things that Linux could learn from Mac and Mac could learn from Windows. And it's a cycle.
But the other thing that's happened in the last 10 years is that obviously mobile interfaces
have come along, and they've kind of shaken up how most people interact with devices.
And you look at things like the hamburger menu, and they are as a direct consequence,
I believe, because of mobile stuff.
Yeah, yeah, I agree.
I don't necessarily need to have the about stuff available, taking up valuable screen
real estate all the time. But I do probably want my history to be available, for example,
easily in a web browser.
Yeah, I definitely see there's a compromise too, when you're trying to save like development
resources and you want to create mobile applications, you want to create desktop applications, you
want to create web applications, there's going to be compromises that are made. I think it's
a tight line between compromises and repeating old mistakes.
And there's also I mean, who are you targeting? You have to think like some of those desktops
you can be very productive in once you've learned everything and discoverability is
perhaps less of a priority for you. Obviously, that's not the best for reaching a wide audience
or a number of things. But for power users, sometimes that's all you care about.
Yeah, and I definitely agree once you kind of know a system. That's a good point. Alex,
you had to drop a link in the IRC to that write up you did. Now, I want to kind of get
out of here with just kind of an update on how things went at Linux Academy and with
the work I did there and just spend the last couple of minutes on that. But just a quick
mention, I think it's FreeBSD's birthday today. I think they just turned 25. So congratulations
to the FreeBSD project. Just want to mention that too in the show. So today, we're doing
the show from Casper, Wyoming. We were just in the middle of a storm, but now actually
blue skies are starting to clear. Since we did the last Linux Unplugged, I've driven
1070 miles.
Whoa!
19 hours and 25 minutes.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Impressive, sir.
Thank you. I left Linux Academy last Friday. And for some crazy reason, Hadia flew back
to Seattle Friday a.m. really early, picked up all three of our kids and brought them
back to Dallas. And now they've been with us for the drive home. So that's been fun.
And it was a good way to spend Father's Day for sure.
That sounds great.
Yeah, it's been, yeah, it has been great. It has been great. It's been challenging like
to do work, but it's also been really nice to have this opportunity. And we split our
time up between playing hard, getting sunburns, which we've now gotten out of our system,
and driving like crazy and doing a bit of work here and there. We had 95 plus days though,
you know, for like weeks. We were just ready to get out of there. So we pushed hard yesterday,
drove a lot. Kids are off at the movies right now as I do the show. They're actually on
their way back right now. And then we're going to continue. We're going to keep on pushing
home, probably do like a couple of more stops, like some swimming holes and things like that.
And then make it home probably this weekend if all things go well. Yeah, so the next Unplugged
I should be back in the studio, I think.
That's wild.
And so I got, I got Dell, I got Dell, I got a Dell XPS desktop set up at Linux Academy
with Kubuntu 18.04 minimal install and the latest version of OBS. Now they got a couple
of PCI expansion. I can't remember. Oh, Sonnet, I think. I can't remember. Somebody makes,
but they're just standard PCI USB cards. But each port has its own dedicated controller
and they got like six ports or something like that on the back of each PCI card. So each
one has a controller with full USB bandwidth going into the PCI bus. Yeah, it's nice. And
then they got Elgato capture cards that hang off of those. And they have different sources
coming in like a Chromebook or like a guest machine or like a desktop. And we also got
them set up with a bit of a mixer setup so they could do a little mix minus action and
a 4K Canon camera coming into that thing, which is the first time I'd ever worked with
4K and OBS, which was fun. And yeah, it's a pretty straightforward setup. They're going
to be using in July when they do their new big content launch. And I got them set up
with the same switcher, the same shuttle pro switcher that I have in the JV one studio.
They had, so now they have one of those, which is sort of fun. Oh, nice. Took a little funky
work to get that going under Linux these days because it's not really well supported anymore,
but it's still my favorite switcher. Yeah, yeah, but it went pretty well. I kind of want
to go back down there in July, which is crazy because I've just gotten home. But that's
when they're doing their live stream stuff for this big content release. And I kind of
want to be there for the first stream because I don't really want to make sure it goes well.
I don't want the first stream on Linux to go badly. Your reputation's on the line. Linux
is reputation too, right? So because otherwise it's right back to Wirecast and the Mac. And
I got to give credit. I met Jacob, their production guy they just hired recently, and he's never
used OBS. He's never used Linux, but he's totally on board with learning because he's
working at Linux Academy now. That's awesome. Yeah. Yeah. And so he was there. I was showing
him how it works. Meanwhile, he was dealing with some exciting family stuff at home. And
so that was like, we were balancing all of that and everybody was super dedicated and
really invested in making it all work. So I just want to be there if I can when it happens.
I don't know. I'll probably fly down if it's possible. Just to make sure that first live
stream on Linux where everybody's watching goes smooth. And then after that, I'll feel
much better. We did a test stream on Friday. So I know it works, but it's a little bit
different when it's actually like the time where it's go time, you know, we'll see. We'll
see how that goes. But yeah, it was a good trip. Now I'm on the way home. And by the
next time we see and hear you here and see me, I'll be in the studio. I'm a little sad,
but I'm also kind of looking forward to getting back to Seattle. I'm looking forward to it.
It'll be nice. I miss the studio. So let's wrap it up with just a little bit of deets.
If you want to support what we're doing here at the network, you go to patreon.com slash
Jupiter signal. If you'd like to go get more of producer Michael, check him out tux digital
or destination Linux. Also, you can check out our friends wimpy and poppy on the Ubuntu
podcast. Go check out Ubuntu podcast. It's always a great show and their adventures continue
here. A lot of things we talked about get picked up or continued on their show. So go
get that at Ubuntu podcast. And if you want more Wes and myself, then tech snaps your
show tech snap dot system will boom. How about that for all the plugs? He's like I got through
them all the little block of plugs ease. Also, why not join us live on a Tuesday? I'm gonna
just throw this out there. Come get yourself a nice healthy Linux sandwich. It's way more
fun, way more fun. You see, we start out around 130 on our live stream Pacific time, we get
going with the unplugged show, we chat, we say things we shouldn't say, then we do the
show. That's the part you just heard. And then we kind of hang out a little bit more
say a few more things we shouldn't say. And then that crazy cat Noah takes over and he
starts answering your questions live, all right here and you just sit back and absorb
via the process similar to osmosis, but nothing like osmosis. Thanks so much for tuning this
week's episode of the unplugged program. We'll be back here next week, back in the Seattle
studio. I'm looking forward to it actually. See you next Tuesday.
All right, now we got to pick a title. Those kids are out from the movie. They're in the
Uber. They're on their way back to the RV. So the countdown has started. It's go time.
So the EU broke the internet is currently on top one. It was a play on words. It was
supposed to be you broke the internet. But anyway, nevermind. Oh, I love it. Who's gonna
read it like that? Who's gonna read it like that? Well me, but then I'm weird. Yeah, yeah.
Article 13. Unlucky for some nation scale. That hasn't been passed really yet. Okay,
let's not get ourselves. Fair enough. Copyright is broken and stop killing the internet. Wow.
Super positive show guys, but they would actually reintroduce 20 years in a way because if you
really think about it, currently it's eight years plus after the author's death and these
new provisions would make it 20 years only. I can't though. All these are super depressing.
We can't name the show that. We can't name the show EU broke the internet or stop killing
the internet. Ionic. Come on now. Ironic. Okay. How about this one? How about everything
is great? How about just everything is great? Let's just do that. Let's just do everything
is great. We love you. Everything is great. Everything should feel fine. Nothing's wrong
here. Nothing to be concerned about. Linux unplugged 254. The longest title ever. Bury
your head in the sand. Yeah. Nothing to see here. How are you?