I tell you what it's one of them. It's one of them things that a girl goes through although although just to add insult to
Injury, I can't seem to actually build. Oh geez now. I just disappeared. I can't seem to actually build a right-click it so
And now I clicked on a menu
that
Existed for a plasma what I deleted and now the whole interface is locked up well shit
I had so many nice things to say and now my whole UI is locked up
But I got like a bajillion tabs open. I don't want to reset all those up, and I'm oh
man
And then I watch the icon little die. What what what just happened? What just happened?
I think plasma desktop is just going crazy on me my screen just went blank
Too many features something damn man that sucks
You know every time I get to a point where I'm like this is it and then then something happens to me in production
I'm like shit. I can't use this. This is no good. This is no good
And you know it's really what really sucks is now. I think I'm getting the point where I'm gonna have to restart X
Hmm, which could screw up HDMI capture which could mess up the stream is gonna close all my tabs which Chrome will likely reopen
But I had things played and paused in certain positions
I had certain pages zoomed in like I took about 15 minutes saying all that up
So I'm gonna lose about 15 minutes of work, and I may lose HDMI capture
Slow down before you do that. I tell you why to restart only plasma 5 there is oh yeah
Well if if it could take input, but well, maybe I could try also to get all tough to and it will always work
Ah, and I just gotta get you the command can give it to me. I'll tell you what this is no good
This is no good. No good because it always happens to me when I'm messing around with plasmoids. That's always when it happens
It's just you like that word though. I don't even know if I'm saying I'm right. There's plasma widgets
All right, so there is a command to restart plasma 5 yes. Yes. I'm just grabbing it
Don't go whoa whoa whoa look at that. There's Chrome so apparently the well
I'm using a totally different task switcher all of a sudden look at that. It's the one on the side
Wow, so there's all my tabs. You can see I'm gonna lose
Nicely set up, and I'm sorry you didn't lose these that's the good thing. Yes, I am just opening up
Okay, I have a shell script. That's why it seems like is there like if I just type restart
Restart the computer nope
That's not the one wow this guy indexes like a son-of-a-bitch man
It's pulling out it's pulling out notes for I'd have from clients from like years back in my text. Yeah, okay. I'm ready
I'm gonna put it in IRC. Okay, okay, okay?
Don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go don't go
All right, so let's see let's wait for it to come up in IRC
Okay, so I got it. I got a kill to come I gotta run two commands
Okay, no all right so P. So P kill f plasma shell, but that sounds dirty doesn't it all right so here
I'll pull it up on screen so you guys can see what happens
So I'm gonna put that in there P a P kill dash f plasma shell okay ran that and
Then now I got it now so nothing happened, but it's probably fault of two
Okay, alt-f two, and then I have to do what case start
Okay, so
Plasma shell dash dash shut up. Yeah, I know that that's stupid. I love that just means don't spit out all kinds of debug
I love it. I love it. Tell me shut up
Okay, so now I have I
Think I have my desk now look at isn't this weird these plasmas showed up on here that I wasn't using before
hmm, and they're blank
That's weird. Yeah, it is
But I have my dry have my dropbox icon down in the system tray. Hey yeah, there you go, so thank you, sir
No, no problem
I have that in a shell and use your local bin and
Every once in a while plasma will just freak right out so now all those widgets just disappeared when I opened up the drawer
Isn't that weird that's very strong. I'm glad you guys are seeing this. It's not just me
We would never believe you but the CPU monitors back which I thought was gone last time
I logged in I'm gonna stop playing with the plasma isn't dropbox icon. We're hanging out. Yeah, well
Thank you for helping me fix that. It's nice to not have to lose work. I
Like I like being able to recover on the fly. It feels very like Hollywood
Yeah, right, you know like reroute the primary operating system guys
Yeah
You know like I remember I was watching 24 one time and Jack Bauer asked Chloe to rewrite to reroute the primary operating system
There's something like that. I was like, I don't know what that means, but that sounds cool
I don't think they think that is anything
You know the thing I used to love from 24 was when he'd say send it to my screen
Yeah, and they're just like grab hold of a window and throw it across the room. Yeah
Yeah, I want that. I'm still waiting on that
Well, actually there was a package
we used to take the piss out of a friend of mine because he was the Debian maintainer for a package called xmove and
Xmove is a program that can do that and has been around for years and years and years, but I think it's broken now
But yeah, you could do that. You could send up an X program from one screen to another. This is Linux Unplugged episode
137 for March 22nd
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's celebrating William Shatner's birthday
And has a few surprises up its sleeve like a huge box. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Do you like that one?
Oh, yeah, I was getting into that one. I was riding the jankies on that one
So coming up on this week's episode huge show big show unbelievable show get out of here. We're gonna have to charge you
It's so big Nvidia claims. They have Wayland working on their current driver, but that might be a little bit presumptuous
We'll tell you why later on in the show major major plans including a big Linux build coming up for Jupiter
Broadcasting right around Linux Fest Northwest. We're gonna tell you about a couple of secret projects that are in the works and big plans
around Linux Fest Northwest and
I'm gonna get psyched up about Noah's switching campaign then later on in the show
Happy birthday, Katie. Well, is it their birthday? What do you call it when they have a release because they do it more frequently than
Every nine months. Yeah, that's true. Happy release a day
That doesn't jazz it up for me enough half
Well, we'll come up with something later on the show because we're talking about plasma desktop 5.6
Been running it for a few days it released today
Gonna do a little bit of follow-up
Some people ask some questions since we talked about a Linux action show
We're gonna do some follow-up on those questions Wes. You've been running right here on this rig
Yeah, you're gonna share your thoughts on it. So we'll discuss that also get the mumble rooms take on
We've got a few Katie users in there and then towards the end of the show
We're gonna do a live throwdown of two open source Google Hangouts killers
They look like they're better quality more control and use WebRTC and our private and safe and peer-to-peer in the background
So pretty cool show and obviously work on Linux
I guess that's kind of a given too and that's just like
The stuff we're gonna do after all of the updates we have to get into from all the projects we follow and stuff
That's broken since the Linux action show
Huge show Wes and get started. I was worried that we were gonna have a bad show today
I I got on the air before you got here. I was like we are screwed and
And I why are you telling everyone our secrets Chris? So I you know, so those of you don't know
There's a Wes had been bringing in great brewskis for us to try during the show and I thought well today won't be the day
He's got to go get a burger Rekai to talk to him into getting a burger for him
And I was like, so he's not gonna have time. I mean really good to the network, right?
Well, there's a burger currency within the network and you can buy favors with people by buying them burgers
So you say you've essentially put a burger in your bank
So that's not a bad move overall strategically for you down the road. I agree, but I was worried. We wouldn't have any beers and
No beers would be a bad show
It's not because we need the alcohols because it's like, you know how certain athletes have certain routines. They have to follow
You know wear the same underwear that kind of thing
Well, of course we're doing that too
but on top of that we like to have one beard or you know with the show and this week Wes brought him something really kind
of eclectic and
It's ecliptic. It's ecliptic brewing and I got the orbiter IPA and you got
Phobos single hop red ale. Damn. Damn
So those would be the brewskis
We're drinking on today's show if you want to drink along with us and maybe just maybe some folks in a mobile room will be
time appropriate greetings mumble room
That's on fire, I love it you guys are fired up ready to go. Okay, so you probably heard the news
It broke on the 21st NVIDIA has published patches for its driver to work with Wayland's Weston, you know
essentially the the reference compositor and
They've made a few tweaks in there and they're pretty happy. They say that this this set of patches
Will allow the Wayland Weston composite run with NVIDIA's new 364 Linux driver series
It's a big deal big deal Wayland support. Ladies and gentlemen, here we are
March 22nd 2016 NVIDIA ships Wayland support
This gets real
Yeah, it felt like a moment for me. However
Not to be a buzzkill but Martin the KWIN maintainer posted on
Google+, that one does not simply run Wayland on Wayland compositor with NVIDIA's new driver. It turns out that
NVIDIA is using EGL streams instead of GBM streams. Okay, what's that mean?
It means that there is code that still is pending in Wayland
To make Wayland work better with EGL
And so really it's coming to Wayland to support EGL and the things that it needs for NVIDIA's driver changes
But NVIDIA's patches essentially accommodate for a Wayland that's just a little bit down the road
Not actually fully shipping just yet from what I'm grokking from this Google plus thread
So while yes NVIDIA gets the headline of shipping Wayland support today. They're shipping support really for Wayland of tomorrow
I suppose that's better than being behind
Totally totally is better than being behind and I think I don't know much but I suspect that's probably a better arrangement from for mobile
Too I suspect there you go. And I mere support might have been in there too. I don't know
I didn't see people got Plymouth working a lot better now. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right. So in between shows
a
Bit of a controversy and if anybody in the mumbo room has anything they want to say what we're talking about this story
Feel free to speak up. Just tag me in the chat room with mum and say what you want
I'll keep an eye out but I why don't I stop covering these these hardware these hardware server updates from the
From the guys over at valve because you know, you don't really ever know how how reliable it is
you don't really know like what triggers it and
You can't really compare it to without knowing all of the details
But that doesn't stop the press from running stories that Linux gaming is shrinking since the launch of we hate games so much
Yeah, Linux users hate spending money Linux users hate playing video games and Linux gaming is doomed
That was the end of last week this week
However, thanks to Liam over at Linux gaming the article has been reversed over a PC world
In fact, the author of the Linux is dying
Chris Hoffman has now written a piece saying the Linux gaming is actually much healthier than Steam's hardware survey implies
There's actually more Linux gamers than ever before. That's great. That is great
Now here's the kind of the basic things you have to understand when people are talking about that steam hardware survey and the the percentage
of Linux users
Well, first of all, do you know do you know what triggers that hardware survey? I do not I'm not completely clear either
But I do understand that a hardware change does and an OS change can sometimes and I guess from my understanding is it seems to happen
A lot more under Windows than it does under Linux like maybe driver changes or video card changes. I
Have only gotten the steam hardware survey once under Linux. Yeah, I have gotten under Windows a couple of times
And what's crazy about that is I've probably ran Windows three times four times, you know, at least in a steam capacity
In as many years, so the fact that I have actually got a Linux every day
Yeah, and that yeah, and I on some of my machine steam auto starts
So it's weird that I haven't gotten the hardware survey under Linux, but I have gotten under Windows
We don't know anything about the sampling rates or any. Yeah
So here's the obvious caveat though. That's really the elephant in the room
Steam's user base is constantly growing
So while the Linux usage on the steam hardware survey has declined from about 2% in March of 2013
to
0.9 1% in February 2015
That's because it's just a small percentage from a larger overall user base and October 2013
Valve announced there were over 65 million steam users around the world in February of 2015. So that was October 2013
65 million in February 2015 valve announced there were over 125 million active users worldwide
Whoa, they doubled in less than a year. So that's it. Yeah, so it took it
Look, it looks you look at you're looking at percentages here in October 2013. You had
0.98 percent of Linux users. That's about six hundred thirty seven thousand Linux users in February 2015
0.9 1% would be 1.2 million Linux gamers. So we've gone up to 1.2 million Linux gamers
Here's the other things kind of crazy
Valve's steam hardware survey doesn't include steam OS what and doesn't include machines in big picture mode. Oh
So if you've built your own steam OS box and use big picture mode
Or if you like that UI better and you use that under Linux or you're using steam OS
You're not getting counted towards Linux
So that's another reason why the numbers are a little low which is a little funky and valve doesn't really publish much. Go ahead. I
guess people just
That were using Linux
To play steam now use team OS a lot of people did the experiment in like and kids in you want to point something out
Too that actually is kind of common for Linux gamers
yeah, one of the things that I find that I have to do to play the games that I want I have to run it and
Wine and I don't know if steam has a way of counting
Users that are running in wine and saying hey, this is not actually a Windows user. This is a
Linux user running it at wine and
That's a very important detail. Yeah wine users get counted as Windows users
Val mentioned that before and the Linux
Gaming on Linux community has mentioned that this are the hardware survey seems to pop up more under wine because to steam it looks like
Your OS our hardware is changing sometimes. So yeah, that can be a thing
Any other thoughts on the steam OS stuff?
I mean
I guess I wanted to just my point in bringing this up on the show today
Was to sort of put a little anti spin on the whole Linux gaming is dying. It's actually grown from
700,000 to 1.2 million in the last year. That's a pretty big deal
It's like one of those things kind of like with political polls where yeah a lot of the reporting spins
How you think about it? Go ahead run. Yeah, I only ever use Linux for gaming anyway, and I've never seen
I've never seen a single hardware survey on Linux for my for my usage in six years. Yeah, I've seen it once I think
So yeah, yeah, you're right. It's just different stats and stuff like that
Okay, so this is the story that people brought up right before we started the show
He said you got to talk about this today. You got to talk about
Ubuntu BSD
Unix for human beings
today with they write we have the great pleasure in their opinion of introducing you to a new project that saw the light of
The internet for the first time this past week on March 12 2016 meet Ubuntu BSD
Ubuntu BSD promises to bring the power of FreeBSD kernel to Ubuntu Linux
It is based on FreeBSD 10.1 and Ubuntu 15.10 right now
And of course it's one of its a highlight Cadillac features is it's using the FreeBSD kernel ergo
you get the famous ZFS combined with of course things like
the port system and I
would imagine
Ubuntu's user land
Ubuntu BSD is currently hosted on SourceForge, and it's got an ISO you could download we have linked in the show notes and
the code name for this release is
Escape from systemd but systemd is misspelled you're right it is I mean you wouldn't expect the BSD crowd to know that
It's a little bit of a Linux nuance. I agree
Yeah
You think if you're actually so that as the register points out one of the genesis of this distribution
Was to break away from to be a savior from FreeBSD
I'm sorry from systemd the systemd argument was you know remember how hot that was remember how what a big deal that was yeah
That was one of the reasons they created this was to save the world from systemd
So you think if they're creating a project to save the world from systemd?
You'd likely look into it a little probably know how to write it. It's in that is an interesting observation
But they did it deliberately. Yeah, they clearly don't like this a bit right in the face
That's why they create with a big D. Yeah, they did do it with a big D
2016 do you host a project on SourceForge? That was why I did specifically mention that just to see if anybody would catch that
I probably I'm dying to know what you think of Ubuntu BSD
Is there gonna be a trademark issue here? Do you think?
Sorry, I saw that on the the thread was on the WMBSD mailing list where it was first discussed and that's where it first
came to
my knowledge
And I think I've read all the mails in the thread and some of the the guy
John Bowden who created it was asked when there'd be a trademark issue
And I think definitely avoided that question or didn't see it or whatever for the benefit of the doubt
Um, I don't know. It's a community project
So much like Ubuntu Marte
It probably should be called something like Ubuntu BSD remix or something like that, which would you know fulfill the the naming conventions?
We use now but
No, I don't see there's gonna be a massive deal about it. I uh, I wonder what your thoughts are just on the concept a little bit
I
Think is interesting and I think it actually is a good thing because it highlights how people can take
what we've done in the Ubuntu project and remix it and change it and
Make it to what they want
You know if someone wants if there's a demand for this if there are a bunch of users out there who feel
that there is a need that's serviced by this to have Ubuntu user land and all those the lovely big package repository that we've got
Plus the BSD kernel then knock yourselves out go for it
I personally speaking I think is a great idea and I think it's it's very positive thing
I think what initially turned me off about it was the
Sort of overreaction to system D and I'm not in the trenches
So I don't really know if it's been I have heard from some admins that say yeah
our life is a little more hell now because of system D and I've heard other guys say that
My life is a lot easier now because of system D. So I'm really I don't have a clear picture of it, but it seems like
It seems like a lot of the naysaying the gloom and doom
Really hasn't
Occurred. I mean things really have just kind of gone along as they always have now
I mean, I think we'll still see, you know, this it'll be a big deployment for system D machines. Yeah that space
But yeah, yeah, that's true. That is true
So yeah, go ahead. They're using XFC for this, right? Yes
Why not just use free BSD with XFC using like package ng?
Yeah, you could my question you could yeah why even bother with it
I wonder if this would help with the curve of the like Linux emulations like this would be a better way for some of the stuff
I doubt it was trying to do because you're still using the BSD kernel
So you'd have to be able to compiling things for the first toolchain anyway
So it's not even like it's the same toolchain or something. Yeah, well there is it
There is one reason you do it. It has the word Ubuntu in it
There you go. That's true. Yeah. Hmm. There you go. Hey everybody. It's got a moon doing it. So it must be good
interesting project and I kind of will I think would be interested in checking in on it and say I
Don't know six months and see where they're at. Maybe see if they base it on 1604
It depends on to you like it's always weird when there's something like it's just like a source forge release and some mailing list stuff
It doesn't feel as much like a project that I will want to check up on it
It doesn't have like a actual infrastructure or a page where you get like real communication from the creator
It basically you you project snob
There are lots of little projects out there that use whatever hosting they can use
just because it doesn't have a
You know a fantastic Twitter page and you know
Discourse and it does have a Twitter page actually things, right? Yeah, but I mean like a wonderfully beautiful one. Yeah
I'm not gonna use it in my infrastructure until I know there's more than one package, you know
Of course, you're not gonna yeah in your infrastructure. Yeah, I would agree
I think if it grew a bit and got a community around it'd be worth checking out
I don't think you have to wait till it's like PCB SD size. No
Which is kind of interesting because PCB SD is grown quite a bit
So Ubuntu BSD at Ubuntu BSD and it's followed by poppy. So look at that. Whoa. Yeah. Yeah
I was following it when I only had 11 followers. Wow. Look at you now now I'm following it when it has
338 followers, so yeah, I like it. So I say now yeah
Kitson I wanted to give you the final word on it before we move on
Yeah, they said I believe was William that said oh, it's Ubuntu and that's why they're doing it
And that's why somebody would use it
I also think that the familiarity with the base OS would also be a big push as well because it is Ubuntu
Not necessarily the name but a lot of people know how to admin Ubuntu
That would like to use some of those lower level features in BSD. Yeah, and that's just a good way of you know
Getting it out there. It's not going to be because you don't have system D
Which Ubuntu and you definitely don't have upstart which Ubuntu would have had in the past
Yeah, and and fast instead of a traditional file system on Linux. Yeah, you're not gonna there's a lot of things
You don't get there's a lot of things. You're not gonna get you're not gonna get Docker or containers. You'll get jails, which is fine
It does feel like a kind of hybrid bastard child of two projects or like three or four projects really doesn't it?
Yeah, and I I'm I wonder too what happens when when FreeBSD finally gets around to developing their system D
You know, it's gonna happen and then where are all those guys gonna go where everybody needs a refuge from that
Where are they gonna go? Where are they gonna go? Gentoo? Slackware? Lumos?
No, this is just the dev one version of BSD
Yeah, you're right. You're right. I know I know I just tease a little bit. Yeah, I tease
Interesting discussion though and a project probably worth some of you keeping your eyes on
So if you end up trying out Ubuntu BSD
I welcome you to let us know let us let us know comment in the in the reddit thread or even better
You could join us
In the mobile room in a future edition of the unplugged show. Hmm
Ubuntu BSD, you know West
My problem is I got a lot going on these next few weeks Linux fest Northwest is getting crazy
Angela and I have like a little lie, you know meeting to this morning right after a tech talk and we were just going down
The list constantly. Okay, we gotta think about this. We got to take care of this. We gotta work on this
We got to make sure this is ready
it is nuts and part of it is because like we have very few opportunities where so many of the crew are in one spot right and
Because we all are fairly technically savvy. You can really pull off some cool projects
so like there's not only is there like the the Linux fest stuff and the
organization of getting everybody in here and getting this place ready to like bring a bunch of people in and
then figuring out like a whole bunch of accommodations for Linux fest Northwest and the booth and the technology to make that all happen and
The scheduling and coordinating needs to happen with the Linux fest people
But on top of all of that
We're gonna pull off a really cool project something that will change JB and bring way more Linux into this area right here
You're looking at over there where there's that wire cast machine. It's gross. I just don't look at it West super excited
I might be biting off more than I can chew and I I pain to tell you how many Bitcoin it has cost me
But first before we get into this new project the new secret project. I want to tell you about ting
Yes, ting ting is my mobile service provider and it's mobile that makes sense minutes messages megabytes and six dollars a month for the line
That's all you pay. No secret crazy plans. No dumb rollover gimmicks
It's just you pay for what you use for minutes messages and megabytes and a flat six dollars for the line
They have fanatical customer service. They have GSM and CDMA networks
So you can get probably at least a high probability that your device will be compatible with ting
Which means you'll get a $25 service credit average ting monthly line is $24
So your first month will be more than paid for if you're in a contract right now. They have early termination reliefs. Oh
Guess what? No contracts and no early termination. Hey, that's right phones are unlocked
You own them outright West you own that phone outright and they have the best control panel in the business
As we get ready to go pick up ham radio for Linux fest Northwest. I'll be bringing my ting hotspot
I just turn it off when I'm not on the road
Doesn't cost me a dollar. It's great turn it on and I just for that road trip. I use that hotspot
Okay, so what's it gonna cost me?
Cuz you know just be paying from I'm paying for my usage
So I go from not paying anything to like 35 45 bucks for one month
Average is out pretty nicely. Yeah, it does. Yeah, I mean, you know
I do that every couple of months it works so smooth and their control panel lets me turn it on and off
I invite you to go check it out. They also have a great blog, but first go to Linux dot ting comm
They have our app picks up on their blog
They have great great 4k online hints if you have a if you have a 4k television
I want to do online streaming your cord cutter and want to watch 4k. They got a great blog post on that
They have information on fiber internet. I mean, it's a great company backed by two cows who've been around for a long time
Linux dot ting comm go there support this show visiting that visiting that page letting them know you heard about it here
Supports the show try out their savings calculator. See if it's worth your money read their blog get to know more about the company
See why I like them so much Linux dot ting comm and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program
We love you guys. You think I'm chatty. I
Think so. Yeah, Jonathan riddle said I was chatty. That's not necessarily a bad thing though. No, no, I suppose not but I mean you are
A Linux I do talk personality. Yeah, kind of have to be I guess that's a lot quieter
You sure you're not trying to make me feel better cuz chatty feels like a bad description
Maybe I don't get well
I mean if you're like the noisy person in the office bothering everyone while they're trying to get work done
But this is your office. Yeah, you know, yeah wimpy. Do you think I'm chatty wimpy?
He's not answer he's left but he authorized me to say oh, do you think I'm chatty? Yeah. Okay, so it define chatty for me
I
Doesn't like there being dead air. Oh true. It's probably a fair. Yeah
Approximation. Yeah, if there's ever dead air
It's intentional dead air because that feels like a left feels like an American broadcasting golden rule though. You don't ever let there be dead air
Informal and lively. Yeah, that sounds nice. Yeah. Yeah, would you look it up? Well naturally you did
Yeah, I I guess I'll take that accusation, you know
every now and then though I go for the opposite effect and I let I let there be a pregnant pause just for
Effect so sometimes it's worth it. All right. Yeah, fine. Thank you. All right. I will so let's chat. Let's be chatty
Let's chat about Linux fest Northwest. So you guys know about I've talked about it a bunch and I won't I won't bore you
With the details. It's April 23rd and 24th. So it's next month. It's in Bellingham, which is a gorgeous
How long was the last time you went to Bellingham?
Mmm, probably like six months ago. Oh, that's actually pretty recently for how far it is from you
It really is beautiful though. Good
Super gorgeous super gorgeous hippie town
You got a while there might be some clouds of weed smoke. You gotta watch out for that
And I walk through one on your way to a restaurant. Yeah, that's true. So
I'm really looking forward to this and one of the things that we kind of did this year
it came out of our visit to system 76 is
Emma and Noah are thrown down and I first I hem and hawt about this and then I decided
Maybe we should really go crazy with this because like we're just switch this
I mean the end goal is to switch people to Linux right? So why not just go all out and have some fun with this? And
I don't have all like it all worked out yet cuz it's no way, you know, he's too busy
Yep, I should have brought him in for the show so I could put him in on the spot
But I feel like it's not calling him on here. Yeah. Oh, yeah
You should start calling him on here. Yeah. Oh, you call him. That'd be so funny
I
Feel like we got to get some of this stuff squared away and I want to go all-in on on making this work
So the goal here is handed to her Emma and Noah Emma from system 76 and Noah are gonna try to convert as many people to
Linux and and get them switched over and happy with Linux now when they both have different approaches
Emma's gonna be giving away swag to people who switch we're gonna bring stickers and swag and Noah's gonna have SSDs. Whoa
Yeah, now here's what I learned and I'm not even joking with you. This is this is legit honest to God
I learned this Emma is doing a frickin dry run in Denver before she comes out. No way
She's doing like a practice run to get herself ready
So that way she's got like all the right moves and stuff Noah's life is basically a practice run though. So that's true
That's a good point, but I'm telling you
You better be prepared. Yeah, and so you and I quick a brainstorm
I'm also I've told him he should contact the local Linux users group up there
And other things like that and I'm hoping that maybe the listener Jed and Angela can maybe work because Jed's from up there
I'm gonna call some like local IT guys people unhappy with their computers bring their clients around. That's really good
That's really good or put that in slack. That's really good. But but you know what put a pin on that we need that one
That's good. Yeah, get the local IT or a USB drive that just wipes their whole computer and puts Linux on that's the other
I want to take it up a notch and we we have we're bringing a whole where here's my thoughts
We're bringing the crew in right? So we're gonna give jobs to the crew during this time. We're gonna go all in
It's gonna be a network-wide effort. We're gonna have people go out in the audience and like grab people
I don't know where we're ever at restaurants library bar at Linux fest
We're gonna have people go out into the crowd and like pre-screen and get likely candidates and and have them funnel them into Noah
So that he can sit there and rapid convert people. So we're gonna have the crew do preliminary work
I don't think she's gonna be doing I probably shouldn't be telecasting too much. I got other plans. He's not listening
Well, she she can't compete with we're gonna bring the army and the weight of the broadcasting network down on this thing
And there is a crew. There is a critical component that we are launching today
To help us with this effort and to help you with this effort
Teespring.com slash. Here's the thing. It is a brand new t-shirt hoodie and long-sleeve shirt
We're hoping to raise some funds for our efforts over at Linux fest and we're doing it now
So that way you'd actually have in time
To wear at Linux fest if you want to meet up with us and become part of our crew or just get it for yourself
Here it is. Look at this beauty West it reads on the front
By popular demand. It has a nice classy last breast logo over the wear that anywhere. Yeah on the front
It's nice and classy and we have multiple colors. We also have the hoodie and
We have the long-sleeve at teespring.com slash. Here's the thing and then on the back
It says here's the thing dot-dot-dot and then our last tux we're holding the Jupiter broadcasting rocket
Here's the thing
Do you have a minute to talk about?
Linux that's great
This is your opening line to get people to convert to Linux right here
And if you if you want to grab it now
We're it's gonna go for 13 more days 5 hours 17 minutes
And it should ship in time for Linux fest Northwest or to have on your own and the funds for this will go towards
Supporting bringing people out here getting I mean just beginning
I mean, this is a massively expensive thing that we're doing but we got we can't run too far into the red
So we got to start something here. Plus this is an awesome shirt
We've had people been asking to have the logo on the front smaller because otherwise it's like this monster
It's as mastered like huge
Advertisement billboard on your belly. And so now we've got a logo over the breast pocket area
There's no breast pocket but in that general area and on the back
Big tux, isn't that awesome? And if you didn't want to show that break wear a jacket
But so teespring.com slash here's the thing three more needed to be ordered for it to ship
13 days total
This is part one. This is phase one
We'll be giving these out and will be probably there may be a special edition at Linux fest, too
If you have one you may be qualified for a special edition. We'll see I've talked to Angie about that teespring.com slash
Here's the thing. So that's phase one, right? That's phase one phase two is we got to change up a little software
We got to make a little front-end back-end change to get ready for this
Last time I went on the road trip. I used something called silver cloud to track my trip
So you could go to broadcast no columns last rover and watch where I'm going Chris creep on me
That was a proprietary piece of hardware and I want to switch over to using something open source
So, you know something run like on a mobile device and Poby I know didn't you play with track car Poby?
No, it wasn't me. I wrote my own. Oh, you did write your own now
Oh because it was running on Ubuntu, huh?
Yeah, it would have run on any phone, but I happen to write a problem, too
And so I'm looking at track car
I don't know. Did now did you look at track car before you wrote your own tracking or did you just say?
Yeah, this is easy enough. I just looked at yours and thought that was cool. I should read
Yeah, and I of course I just went the easy button I wanted a dedicated piece of hardware
But now now I'm thinking okay, I could probably make it work on the phone
So there's two projects and I'd like to the audience if anybody in the audience has tried this track car trac car
It is an open source GPS tracking system for various different types of devices
It could work on hardware or in my case on mobile and then it reports back to your own server
That you could be running anywhere, right? You could be running droplet or whatever
And then it lets you embed like a Google Map of your position
So that's track car and then Wes you found own tracks own
Tracks is a different project that allows you to keep track of your own location
And you can have a you could share it with just certain people or I could publicly I could publicly publish it
it's also open source and uses open protocols and
Looks to be a little more mobile focused
Yeah, and it also is more like social networking focus
Like if you're looking at the app like you can see your friends on the map, right?
So I'm feeling like track car might be the better likes you want to meet up with all your JB friends
Well, that would be cool too, but I don't need to track their location
Yeah, you know they can track mine, but I don't need to track theirs
I kind of want to set up a track server on a digital ocean droplet
I hate asking this but if anybody out there is has experience doing this and wants to save me time and
Then just transfer me the droplet. I would totally love that because I got a lot coming up for Linux fest. So track car
Is I think how I'll do my live rover tracking so I don't have to pay for that proprietary solution
You have like ten phones in your pocket. Yeah. Well, yeah, and I'm trying to get as much Linux and open-source into Lady Jupiter as possible
So every part where I have a proprietary hardware solution or software. I'm trying to put something that's awesome
So track car org if anybody knows how to set that up and wants to set me up one, that'd be awesome
Otherwise, I'll try to get to it before they go pick up ham. So one of the things we're doing is
the weekend before
Linux fest Northwest
Where Noah if all goes as planned should be in town
Arriving Saturday night to do Linux action show Sunday in studio
Then we'll complete Linux action show in studio Sunday. We may do it early
Hit the road in Lady Jupiter head over to Idaho
Meet up with ham. Yeah
Then potentially on the way back
There are rumors afoot that we may meet up with a few other JB audience members and do like a caravan back
From from Idaho. That sounds awesome. Yeah, it really does sound awesome
So the track car would be tracking all of that. So we're getting all of that set up right now
It should be yeah, right. Lady Jupiter is the rover. So like you have
Function the rover and you have the name of current rover, which is Lady Jupiter. Okay
part of our secret
Linux fest Northwest plans
Are contained in this box West. Did you see this box when you walked in? No, I missed it. It's very secretive
You missed this box. It's right over there. I was delivering hamburgers and beers and beer. That's true. All right
I'll give you credit there. Oh, that's true
I uh
I have had a heck of a time with video and sometimes when power goes out we lose episodes because the best days. Mm-hmm
when power goes out, uh, so we
Oh boy
I know what everybody I'm you know what i'm stopping myself because i'm realizing all of the emails i'm going to get
Why don't you use a ups? Why don't you have?
I don't have a ups on our main broadcasting machine because in the past has been introducing buzz to our audio
So I removed a ups from our main broadcasting machine, which means when the power goes out
You lose the recording because the way the video files are written to hard disks
they
They close out the atom file at the end of the video file and if you don't write that atom file properly
The rest of the video is unusable. There are some recovery tools, but they suck and pretty much only work for mp4s not
lossless video
And this has sucked so bad because we we've lost hours of content before and um
Because it can get stormy here in the pacific northwest. That's like a thing and
so what we're going to do
is uh
Build a new solution build a new solution based on linux and obs
obs
and uh
So last week, I think it might have been after linux unplugged. I can't remember
You know, I've I uh, i've always sort of as a hobby followed bitcoin for a while. I did plan b as a podcast and um,
i've always been pretty good at
i've always been pretty good at watching when bitcoin bitcoin rises and when bitcoin falls, what is it right now?
Let's check it out. Yeah, will you check out? What is the bitcoin price right now if I uh,
Too bad you uh, let's see. So we're 19 29 4 16 at coinbase right now. And uh, what'd you see?
Well, this is bitcoin average 4 19 4 19. Yeah, that's pretty good
So the low has been like around 407 today or 4010 or 410. I mean and the high has been 4 17
So it got around I think it was up at 4 22 bitcoin was and I said to rikai
I said because rikai, you know rikai for say is pretty current on on hardware and I said to him
uh
Could you build me a list of a really powerful machine? I gave him all the things I wanted to do
uh and
The one caveat is all these things have to be shipped directly by newegg because if i'm going to pay in bitcoin
And bitcoin is only accepted by newegg when you ship directly from newegg. That's the little catch
Ah
If it's any of their third-party, uh marketer market providers, they don't accept bitcoin
And I wanted to buy this in bitcoin because uh, otherwise i'm i'm poor and uh all your money's in the coin
Well, no, but that's where any learning a bit about your portfolio any money I can spend is in bitcoin. Uh, and uh,
So, uh, I look at as a personal investment in the business a little bit
So what I decided to do was uh, I spent quite a bit of bitcoin actually
Um because I figured 425 was probably going to be the high point for a while. So spend while it's high, right?
maybe i'm wrong, but
Uh, my philosophy with bitcoin is is if you see it going up and down if you get it somewhere in the mid average up
Even if it goes up a little bit you did pretty good
And so, uh, I ordered I don't remember all of the details now
I probably should have pulled this up before the show
But uh a six core processor a new motherboard, uh quite a bit of ram
Uh about 32 gigs worth of ram excellent, um ssd m sata m dot
Or 2.5 drives wherever the ones that go into the motherboard instead of uh, like, you know, the regular 2.5 inch
um
nvidia 960 I think gtx graphics
Lots of goodies
And the other thing I did is I bought two of everything
So what we'll do now is we will build two of these machines. That's great identical builds identical software configs
Both installed ready to be obs broadcast machines
And one will be over there
Doing all of our endpoint broadcasting and recording a real-time backup of the live stream
And then the second build will be sitting under this table the the broadcast the desk here
And if anything ever happens to the main broadcast machine
I just unplug the one under the table here and plug in over there and I can start broadcasting again
I have a I have a one-to-one backup
Uh, and that also means down the road
Like if we want to experiment with new crazy versions of obs or linux
We could switch over to the backup one run off that for a couple of days
Do our upgrades and experimentations on the new machine?
Maybe like a new patch or something like that
And if you ever need to you just fail back to the exactly one you haven't touched
It's going to be so so so so nice and it's going to get rid of so many problems of the mac pro caused
Uh, I am majorly looking forward to it. So that's one of the projects
So all of like all of like the little components showed up today in that box
What's still missing is I haven't picked a case. I'd like to have identical nice cases. Yeah
But I don't want to spend too much on that
and storage because the one thing is is the hardest thing is I don't know if I can really
I don't know if I can buy two sets of storage storage for this thing because the thing needs like two three terabytes
really fast
Maybe even more like five terabytes
Really fast and maybe even more than that if possible and I don't really want to buy two sets of those
So I haven't bought that yet. I haven't gotten a case yet
There's still a lot I have to buy and it's like
I only I only want to spend so much of my personal money
But the network can't really afford to do it right now
but this I think is going to be such a huge upgrade for us because
on the back end
We're going to rework a ton of stuff the way a ton of stuff works the way we broadcast
We should be it should open us up to a bunch of more streams and then down the road
Hopefully take to our capabilities even further
So it's going to be a nice rig with with six physical cores and then hyper-threading on top of that
We should be able to stream to multiple places do multiple encodings
Live backups all that kind of stuff and then on top of all of that
We should be able to record the build of these things and the configuration of these things and get some content out of it, too
So i'm i'm i'm thinking it's going to be a big huge upgrade for us
And it's going to reduce a bunch of dependency on on on wirecast, which i'm really excited about
So yeah, that's a big call so obs can do it
Well, we'll see
I don't know if it'll handle all the camera switching
But it's definitely going to handle all of the streaming all of the master recording and switching of uh live stream to recorded streams
Which even if I just take all of that off of wirecast
That itself will make wirecast more stable and reliable and then we can just because a part of the problem is i'd have to
Buy all new capture cards, too
Possibly we will go we what we what I plan to do is take it as far as we can take it
We may try taking the capture cards out of that machine and putting them in the new machine and seeing how far we can
Take it and if we can go all the way
We would go all the way but there's a lot of little things like green screening and compositing that
Uh, we would need to be able to do like dynamic stuff that
Possible but yeah. Yeah
Really excited about that and so for for us linux fest isn't just about the fest
And this emma noah competition
But there's also some really cool projects
We're going to be working on that are going to have big long-term improvements for the network down some network technical debt here
So i'm pretty excited so it all is so at least not all of it
I think but a huge chunk of it
It's funny because it's so much money that I spend and then I see it in one box like that
I'm, like I was expecting more boxes makes you feel just poor
but then again like amazon ships boxes within boxes within boxes, so I I guess I
I guess I can't complain too much and I don't know. I don't know. We'll see where it goes
Noah's already scheming about the setup. So I think it should be really fun. I know obs can do green screening, uh, but uh,
I'm particular
Yeah, oh that's super exciting. Thanks. Yeah, I I'm I it's been it's been a long time since i've had a really new
Uh computer to build right except for with the exception of these lebrons and the apollo
Which has been boom all of a sudden hit at the same time
But uh, you know, my main machine upstairs is like a original first generation i7. Oh wow
Uh, that is a that that broadcast machine. There's a 2012 model, right? So that's an old rig
So all these machines are getting several generations old so to get two of the identical current generation
Machines and build them and the nice thing is when that machine's over under the table acting is just like a backup
I'll use it as like all my visuals
It'll have a nice video card so I can I can show off some nice new steam games
And do you know like 60 frames per second gaming stuff like that, which will be really nice
Get captured you won't have any hardware excuses when your program that you're testing out on air brakes live. Yeah, I am
Uh, I it is it is it's funny, you know, because it's it's one point. It's a little crazy
It's a little scary because i'm I we're we're building up a whole bunch of stuff and i've just spent a whole bunch of money
on it
Uh at the south at the other time though
I can't wait to have it all sort of done and just have that stage that i've been waiting on for so many years done
It feels like i'll be checking off a box that has been years in the making i'm really excited about that
Uh, and just rekindle today we're talking about some of the crazy things we're going to be able to do now
Um, they're going to make other things that will make some of like the live stream experience smoother
we won't have to like bring the stream down between shows and
Um, but it'll also make it so that way we don't lose content for the released versions, too
So it's like it's going to improve the live streams and the recorded shows and it's going to be used and it's going to be
done using linux
That is awesome. Mm-hmm
I am really pretty super excited really coming along the way. Yeah, well, we'll see
We'll see now the next but the thing is to focus on right now
We got to get as many people switched to linux as possible. We got to come up with a game plan
So if you are in the bellingham area
Which has got to be just a few of you
And you could help us come up with a solid winning game plan where we could take noah and our crew
And interrupt people and not get them upset and convince them to try linux
And the other thing that was thinking is if you're going to linux fest northwest bring a friend who hasn't yet switched
Yeah, because they're going to get an ssd they're going to get swag and they're going to get switched to linux
So that's pretty cool and you can help our effort teespring.com slash. Here's the thing. That's a pretty cool shirt, too
I I want the long sleeve one myself. We're selling the t-shirt pretty much at cost
Uh with a slight markup just a real small one to hopefully raise a little bit of funds
Uh, I mean someone's got to buy those ssds shipping april 4th, hopefully or uh, not shipping april 4th
the uh, teespring campaign ends april 4th and probably printing several days after that to make it in time for
The end of april. So that's at teespring.com slash. Here's the thing
I'm, pretty excited
Yeah, it looks like we meet the threshold to uh ship so yeah awesome. Thanks guys
I think uh, I think this could be a thing that we do at other fests too
like if we could get the formula right we could do like a little sub event where we
You know because a lot of so uh lugs in washington
I would imagine everywhere but lugs everywhere will have um
Uh install fest days. Have you seen this? Absolutely
We have people, you know right there on site
You can ask questions as you're trying to get things set up
We could we could put together that kind of thing and like if this works like we could put together
A meetup and we could get audience members that would help out with the initiative and you know
Because really what you just need is like a production line people bring their laptops in or their desktops
And you know it'd be cool
Like if we really seriously got into this is if we could have like monitors and keyboards and mice there
So they if they want to get their desktop switch, they just bring their tower
They don't bring all their stuff and of course if they're bringing a laptop
It's super easy and get a little networking in there
So that way they could get we could send them home patched
And all that kind of stuff 100 up to date just ask it. Hey what oh my gosh
What are your favorite applications get their icons all set up for them?
Like we could really do this and we could do it like itself. We could do it at scale
We could do it at linux fest northwest
That could be like a really cool thing we do when we go out there and it would always make for great like a little
Like two minute update in the show, too
So anyways, oh, sorry wimpy says he's not i'm sorry wimpy
So anyways really excited about linux fest northwest
You'll probably be hearing obnoxiously more about it
And if you're uh, if you're ham radio
You're really gonna hear more about it because we're gonna be coming your direction ham prepare your body
Put pants on when they get there. We're coming for you
and uh
I got like a few things I got to fix in lady jupiter because you know
What i've realized is living in an rv is like living in a boat and there it is a constantly decaying
Object see in a house you you tell yourself that you could live in this thing for 30 years
And you'll just have to fix up a few things here and there but about five ten years into it
You realize there's like tens of thousands of dollars worth of work to do but with an rv
Every month there's something to do now. It's not always as big but there's always something so right now
Uh, I can't use my uh microwave when i'm on generator power. Why would you want to?
I can't go pick up ham without a functioning microwave. So I gotta fix that i'm gonna try to fix that tonight after the show
And so i'm beginning to repair it to get it ready for the road like each each major voyage you go on
There's like a little something you got to do afterwards
So that's mine is uh fix the uh fix the generator
So that way the microwave and more importantly the electric fireplace work while we're on the road
I mean ham has expectations about the mood in
In late jupiter, all right, uh, very good. Very good. So i'm looking forward to that and and uh, you'll probably uh,
Probably see some sort of video update soon with the ham smile and face on it
And more from linux fast northwest and then of course if you can't make it
We will be streaming it live and we'll have a meetup page hopefully launched
Soon. All right. So i'm itching to tell you about something that uh, i'm surprised i'm this happy about
Are you still are you in kd 5.6 right there? Uh, I switched back
But i've been using it. Oh, you are no longer. Yeah, and now i'm trying it out in a virtual machine
Oh, look at you. Look at you. Look at you. Well, okay, so it came out today
So we got to talk about i've been running it for a few days here
And uh, it's easier than ever now to try it
There's like many options and I know we have a few different people trying a few different ways
In the mummer room plus i'll tell you about how i'm trying it and we'll find out how west is trying it too
And how you can try but first
Let's talk about digital ocean
Love digital ocean, uh speaking of some of our plans for linux fest northwest
Yeah, some of them involve spinning up droplets when we go on location
You know if you want to stream to multiple destinations
You could do that from your connection
But if you really want to have high resolution streams
You could consider also streaming from a digital ocean droplet. OBS is very easy to send from one spot to the other in fact
Uh tax syndicate just recently did a video on this
We were kind of concocting this solution for our new setup digital ocean droplets are just our go-to infrastructure
You need a linux rig with a super fast connection a blazing fast cpu
That's crazy easy to manage and a beautiful ui to set up
That's digital ocean starts at just five dollars a month. You get 512 megabytes of ram
All ssds the five dollar one gives you a 20 gigabyte ssd with a terabyte
Of transfer and of course their pricing structure just works really simply and it goes up from there
If you just need it for a few hours easy peasy their interface is so simple. You can be a server master
Working on servers since servers were a thing or you could be a total noob and you will still find digital ocean's interface appealing
Isn't that like an amazing? It's awesome. That's like a line they have struck that is very rare, especially
Let's just be honest in a web app
Like it almost never happens in a web app and I mean if anyone's going to complain about it
It's going to be you so the fact that you like it. It's very I don't yeah, you're right about that
Also, they have a great api which meant love that api you can use that api
You can tap that api all you want or you can take advantage of the open source code
That's already done that and then you can just and it's like it's like one curl be like, yeah
Bam lazy web. You got it. Boom. Uh, check them out digital ocean.com use our promo code do unplug
That's how you support this show do unplugged all one word lowercase gives you a ten dollar dollar credit over digital ocean
You can spin up an ubuntu rig a debian rig a fedora free bsd
uh
I do generally ubuntu lds, but I don't judge if you do free bsd. I won't judge and the
Bsd now guys have talked about a few cool ways. You can use that html5 console on digital ocean
To actually install other bsds as well
Or arch or whatever you want. Yeah, i'll just the power of kvm. We're just gonna put that out there
Yeah, because they're using kvm as the virtualizer. Uh, it's a really great infrastructure
It's a great infrastructure based on linux
A great way to run linux rigs and a great way to support the show digital ocean.com. Just use that promo code
Do unplugged all one word lowercase and a big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the linux unplugged program
And i'll just give a quick shout out too. Um, we haven't talked a lot about this features, uh, since it first came out
Floating ips are a brilliant way to make you to make a 10 operation look like a 50 million dollar operation
And team accounts if you're an open source project or in a business are also
Rocking so check them out digital ocean.com use the promo code do unplugged. They're really great data centers all over the world
Thank you digital ocean
Okay, so anybody in the mumble room running like a uh, um
Um leap or uh or tumbleweed with that with a current version of plasma desktop installed on their machine in the mumble room
I am
Oh, can you can you describe your setup a little bit to me?
Uh, yes, it's uh, just uh, the most current version of plasma on tumbleweed. It's very basic
Do you know is that five six already?
I believe it's five point five point six or something like that
Well, sir, that is no longer the latest because today plasma 5.6, which i'm sure you'll get very soon
Has been released and uh, it is interesting and also
It comes with a video. How about this? I don't think i've ever seen plasma
Kde desktop do this and it's it's kind of interesting. We could watch a few seconds of it
So it is the time to release plasma 5.6, which brings many improvements and features to your desktop
The default plasma theme breeze now follows the application color scheme allowing for a more personalized experience
K runner gained cleaner look and support for drag and drop
The much improved task manager in plasma 5.6 now displays proper
5.6 now displays progress of tasks such as downloading or copying files. This is actually kind of a neat feature
So, uh in dolphin when you're moving files around in the task manager
There's a little loading bar that goes across the dolphin entry to indicate the progress of the file copy
Isn't that kind of a nice little touch? It's a nice touch
Playback a music or video player shows beautiful album art and media controls
This actually hasn't worked for me yet. But the idea is like when you hover over a task bar, uh, um entry
For your task manager normally you'd get like a plasma window that pops up with a preview of the window
Well with like vlc or sandstorm or um, not sandstorm what app I don't know what application that is, uh or spotify
You you get not only a preview of the window, but you actually get little player control bars at the bottom of that little
Comp is like a pop-up preview. I don't know what you call that. So you never have to leave the application
You're currently working with
Users that place a folder applet in their panel can now choose between list and icon view
Additionally tooltip animations have become more subtle
I
Like this next one desktop widgets all windows get minimized and the widget explorer becomes semi transparent during drag
Isn't that cool? Yeah, that's nice
Activity manager backend was revamped so creating and switching between activities should be noticeably faster
This release brings back the weather and media frame widget I actually like that
If you enjoy using plasma, please consider donating to kde
So we can continue to work together and make the best free software possible. I guess I shouldn't cut her off
Uh, so there you go. She just sort of covered some of the features of 5.6
So here it was my takeaway and then I want to get your takeaway and then we'll go to the mumble room
um, and then we'll wrap it up, but uh
Something really weird happened to me this week and i'm really uncomfortable with it because i've never been in this position before
Never yeah, and i'm glad wimpy's not here anymore wimpy you left, right?
Good, oh good because I would feel bad even saying this if he was listening because I would just feel awful
I found myself. Uh, so this here is the libram that i'm running a 5.6 on
And I have the apollo still running abutu mattei 1510, which is now i'm just using as my portable and I have this one here
I know here's the thing
I found myself every time I wasn't using this desktop missing plasma 5.6. Wow little things. Um, like, uh,
I uh, I was at home and my mi-fi dropped out actually didn't drop out. I restarted it
And uh when I restarted it
I could never get abutu mattei to refresh my available wireless networks and connect to it again and right here on kd plasma 5.6
There's just a little refresh button
You just click and it just refreshes all the wireless networks. Now. I'm not saying that's what i'm saying. There's there's about a million
Of these little things now in 5.6
That have been refined and come together to actually make a really tremendous desktop
Um, it's really performant. It's really fast. I I don't I I mean mate is fast as well
But it's definitely faster than gnome 3 as somebody who drives gnome 3 all the time. It's definitely faster than gnome 3
uh, and there are things in it like the new krunner looks a lot better
You can do alt space to launch the new krunner and it's cleaner. It looks better
It searches like a son of a gun man. Yeah, it does
It is a one of the best test top searches krunner itself is really powerful
And there's a whole bunch of other functionalities. You know what too and I this is always something i've always known
And one of the reasons I always kind of have been sort of attracted to a kde desktop or a plasma desktop
Console is one of the best things to do. It's a lot of fun
Kde desktop or plasma desktop console is one of the best terminal emulators out there
Have you ever had like three or four tabs open to your servers?
Did you know you can send and the other terminal applications do this as well, but this is the default guys
Did you know you can send your input to all of your tabs at once?
So like if you want to do app dash get update across all your machines
You can be ssh'd in tab tab tab and just say execute this command right in console across all my tabs
And you could update all your you know, it's just it's a great console application. Kate is a great text editor dolphin
Is a great file manager like really good and the problem has always been
The problem has always been for me since they went to version 5 has been plasma shell itself now
It did actually crash on me in the pre-show and hopefully that'll be in the after show if you guys want to see that
Uh, but we're able to recover like I didn't have to restart
back up and running
Here's where i'm at with this and this is why i'm genuinely excited about this
Every single stinking release of kde
Since about 5.3 has been for me personally
Remarkably better and now 5.6 is the accumulation of much needed improvements to the breeze theme the breeze theme is
Much more consistent now. They have the icons much more flushed out. It adopts whatever color choices you've chosen
The default layouts at least on this kubuntu with neon, uh packages installed are much more
uh clean and sensible there's i'm not overloaded with choice and um
I kind of feel like it feels more modern than
Gnome 3 in some ways, uh, like, uh
The way the way okay. Here's just an example. So it's just been really nice
All of my icons down there are just working and I know that's not the case
My icons down there are just working and I know I don't know exactly why
But like I I have my chrome icon. I have my hangouts icon. I have my dropbox icon down there in my system tray
And you know what wes?
They don't have ugly white boxes around. They don't like they're not oddly sized
They're not mismatched in size like they used to be on the plasma desktop. They're all consistent
They all look good and I have the power to hide them if I want to
um
Yeah, I just for me I I i'm actually seriously considering putting
Plasma 5 6 on everything and just going all in for a little while and see how I feel wow
I've never uh, oh so I before I go too much further actually before I I will follow up
I i'll write it down so I don't forget because i've got a lot of questions after our our our
Our friday or sunday show so I will write down the questions
I wanted to hear your thoughts because i've been talking for a little bit. What would you try it out on the spot nick?
What did you think?
No, I was also similarly impressed. I feel like for a little while
Plasma 5 had felt kind of like the early days of gnome 3 where I really liked what they were doing
I liked all the changes. I liked seeing the updates
But it the same kind of thing where it just wasn't quite
Stable enough where I'd had enough problems or enough things had changed. I wasn't sure how they were going to work out
But I really enjoyed it. It worked really well. Um, I was using kubuntu on here. It's been working very nicely
I want to try maybe something like open seuss with it as well
I think that would be entertaining and that might be something that I would consider putting on like friends computers
Uh, but it has been it still might personally kde is always still feels like a lot of you know
It's a huge it's a huge desktop environment and it does what it does really well, but it takes over everything
So I don't know if i'll be using it every day. But for systems where that's what I want. That's an interesting
It works really well
That's an interesting comment and an interesting way to put it in kits
And I kind of wanted to let you jump off from uh from wes's point there because you say you like the way it feels
Yeah, I like the way it feels. Um, and i'm actually a traditional gnome user believe it or not
And I think that the reason that it works so well
And and I think the reason that you like it too is because it feels like how a computer should work
It doesn't feel like a touch interface
shoehorned onto a desktop
Wow, that is a good point. Yeah, that is a good point, you know the other thing that uh,
Because and because I haven't been using it for a while
So there's still novelties to me that uh are are fun. Like when you take a screenshot
They just have like one of the best screenshot applications and it like you have you can
With a little bit of work you can send like your screenshots to third-party services right from the screenshot application like imager
Or stuff like that. They have great online account integration
I'm going to stick with it for a bit and I might try loading on the apollo, too
Anybody else in the mobile room want to jump in on their thoughts on kde?
And i'd like to know if you've what distros you've been trying it on
I've used uh 5.5.6 on multiple different distros. I haven't used 5.6 yet, obviously, but uh
I mean everything that a lot of the stuff that they mentioned in this is actually already in 5.5.6
Like the media player, uh plasmoid is really cool because you can create custom shortcuts
So that when no matter what media player is playing you can actually automatically like pause something or move move songs
Regardless of what actual player you use so you can always have the same global shortcut and that's really awesome. Oh, that is nice
Mm-hmm. That is nice. So rotten sounds like you've been sticking with it for a while
What is it that's been sticky for you about plasma desktop? What's kept you there?
Uh, well, I switched uh a year ago actually about a little bit over a year ago
And i've i've gone back and forth with different ds, but i've always gone back to kde now
And it's because uh plasma has a infinite amount of control like if you want to have
Like for example, uh kissanay said that he liked it because it was a traditional desktop and it wasn't like a touch thing
But if you want a touch looking desktop you can do that
I actually have like if you've seen my setup it kind of looks similar to gnome
Because I can change it to the way I want it to look
But that that's one of the that's the power of plasma
But the the huge the biggest reason to use kde plasma is actually kwin
Because you can do that's fair pretty much anything you want to do with kwin anything that any other window manager can do
Kwin can do it and there's tons of things that only kwin can do. I am continually impressed with kwin
Yeah, and I think it's a big part of the why the 5.6 desktop feels so responsive to the based compared to the gtk
Desktops and i'm talking about like resizing windows or when the way they draw it just feels
It feels like a little bit like how good how good compass feels to me compass and kwin
I can perceive a difference in the way that mutter renders things or whatever gnome is using uh, so yeah
I mean just even on my virtual machine when you like drag drag the window around it
It's fast. It's yeah the transparency works like in a vm. Yeah
There's a really cool default feature a hold alt and then use your right click
The right click mouse on any corner and you can resize the window super fast
Oh, so you don't have to get like all accurate with where you grab it that is nice, right?
There's also the one of the things that I like this is actually the reason why
I was having a conversation with here on mumble and someone said uh, that
Like we have a conversation about games and full screen and stuff
And you know, sometimes window mode games are better. Yeah, then are better performers than right screen, right?
If in in kde with kwin you can use uh, there's the no borders rule
So you can actually just put a game in window mode and then right click the title bar
And go and go through the process of more options and click no borders. It removes the border full screen that window
And it looks like it's a full screen, even though it's not. Yeah, the thing that I love about windows is
It's a full screen even though it's not. Yeah, the things you can tweak are pretty impressive. That is really cool
Uh, so that yeah that I could see that making it sticky for you, uh
Wizard you've tried it on debian. I don't think we've gotten a debian take yet. What what's your impressions?
Uh, so i've had ups and downs with it all the way through I stuck around
I went through the kde 4 to kde 5 transition inside of debian and it was terrifying but uh,
It's uh, it was it ended up working out really well, uh, you know, there's there's been ups and downs
I've had i've been through the points where the desktop has crashed continually. That's actually why
That's I had that script sticking around somewhere
because my desktop crashed a lot at the beginning, but it's
It's been getting better every and like I it's getting to the point where I have to use that restart plasma
Uh the script I use maybe once every couple months
You know, it's it's really good now. Yeah, in fairness. I have a restart cinnamon script. So yeah. Yeah, isn't that built into cinnamon?
Yeah, but well, there were some other features. So, you know what really sucks super super bad, uh, uh, and it's
It's just what it is right now, but the discover or muon or whatever. It's called software center. Um,
Are you seeing this?
I mean, I know they're trying and I don't want to be mean but look how awkward this is
So let's go into oh, I don't know. Let's go into system settings, right? So that's a category system and settings and look at this wes
it's just
Blank like there's just there's just appear to be anything there. There's nothing there and like the icons are all strange
You know what's right here are widgets like the weather widget awesome widgets
uh compared to the software boutique or
Um app grid. Yep on for yeah, i'm just talking for ubuntu systems
The software boutique is what uh is what wimpy's been working on which is just awesome
This is I installed vlc, but I mean this is just this is a huge disappointment
I like that it's cross distro that is a nice like gnome software in that sense
I do I respect that I understand it's a big challenge, but I am not like
I need to deliver more what I want from the boutique and what I want from ubuntu software center
And what I want from muon discover, whatever you want to call it
I want to find a new app that it delights me and I want to install it on my desktop and I
I want to I want to then share it with linux action show audience
I want to discover new software via this I you know
I didn't necessarily do that with the software boutique, but you know, I installed a whole bunch of apps in about five minutes
That was really I mean for people they're going to get ubuntu mattei 1604 and they're going to they're going to launch that welcome center
They're going to in in five minutes
They're going to have their entire software stack and and what would they learn about what a ppa is?
You won't have to deal with anything
It just takes care of all of that for you and it gives you the best software on linux in minutes
This doesn't do that. This does speculate. Uh, this does speculate this does spotlight
Uh digicam vlc carita, you know some really solid qt applications
But just doesn't do just and marvel but just doesn't do justice to all the desktop applications available for linux
And I find it to be a major disappointment
That one actually used to be better but they started recently as in five point five point three update
They started porting it more because it used to just not be on framework five
Then they started porting it and they changed a lot of stuff that I don't really like
Like the update system is actually it used to be much better than it is now
So check this out, uh, just to kind of give you an example west now
I don't have anything loaded uh in this vlc media player. So it's not as cool
All the lower third is probably going to block this but as I hover over vlc and my task manager
You can kind of see it there west you see I have play and previous and next
And I can also it's so it's integrated now into the freaking task manager our playback controls
And the reason why this is a big deal for me is I play a lot of media through vlc
I'm usually using live streamer
Or i'm grabbing the rtsp stream of something and i'm tossing or i'm throwing an mp3 and i'm listening to a podcast
And so to be able to just play and pause right there is neat
It's it's neat because it's a different way to do it and it accommodates for multiple media applications at once
So whereas a media applet will just do whatever application is controlling the volume
This I can manage spotify vlc and the other just for me because i'm sometimes running several apps. Yeah, exactly really nice
This is just a really tight desktop really well performing and uh, one of the other things true to their word the kde neon project
Already has a developer version now. Remember this is really just for testing and developing
It's not for daily use. They already have an iso out with 5.6. I'll have it linked in the show notes
You can download this and try it out right now
The uh, the kde neon project
Has their files hosted at files.kde.org
Kde.org
They're all in with the kde project. Uh, so anyways if you want to try it out if you want to try out 5.6
We do have
Uh a link in the show notes you can cook. I i'm i'm i'm
This is kind of a big deal for me and I don't want to
For me this feels huge because not only am I thinking about switching to kde, but i'm thinking about switching
To neon specifically wow in anticipation of 1604. Yeah
And to be switching not only from gnome, but to also be switching from arch
That's a big change. It feels like a mistake almost but uh, because arch will have 5.6
Yeah, and I already have it but the neon project
Itself is such an interesting experiment and 16 of 1604. It looks like such a promising release
I know and even if I don't stay with 1604
It's like I feel like I have to install it and use it for a while just to like be in the zeitgeist of what?
It releases. Yeah. Yeah, so but it's funny because you know
My 1604 review is coming up and it's like I need to immerse myself in unity and yet here I am
I'm extremely attracted to 5.6. Yeah
So, uh, yeah, I don't see I know I know I know I know it gets in
You can go ahead and mention it on the air
You don't have to just type it you want to give a plug for tumbleweed. We should mention tumbleweed. Go ahead
Yeah, I actually think that you should uh, give tumbleweed a try. I think you'd have great luck with it
I have I really haven't ran into any problems or surprises updating anything and i've been running it for almost a month now
Sonic's 7-1-1 in the chat room says i'm chasing the dragon. I should be careful
You know, you might be right and here's what I was thinking is I would like to really try to give it a go
And so you want some of you listening might be wondering
Well, what about your sound problems chris?
And this was like the number one question that got sent into the linux action show now
Uh, yeah by all in on phonon. Am I am I super excited about phonon? No, but in recent uh, kde releases
I think I might have been in 5.5. Uh, they have they have
Well, who who who?
So 5.5 started it. Yes, and then 5.6 is the more full
Implementation. Yeah. Yeah, I kind of suspected those guys. Thank you for the clarification. Uh, so
I can do a process of elimination now
That essentially prevents problems it requires I manage it more but it allows me at the same time I can manage it
So it's actually not bad. So if you're looking at my screen right now on the video version here of linux unplugged
You see i'm in the audio volume settings
And you can just get there by right clicking on the volume volume applet and going to um audio settings
All the tabs are super important input devices output devices, but you see something here west
You see how I only have one device listed in output devices. Yes, I do
And you see how I only have one device listed in input devices now
Uh, there are some instances where I have a machine that literally has three sound cards in it
The hdmi port a usb sound card and the onboard
Well what you can do now in starting like rotten said in 5.5 and continued in 5.6 and there's other things as well
But uh, but one of the nice things is is I can simply just turn those other sound cards off
And then the plasma desktop isn't even aware they're available and it can't cock it up
It's literally it's you just choose what you actually want to use
Yeah
By a process of elimination by eliminating all the other sound cards as an available options to the system and only making the one sound
Card I want available everything defaults to it
Solve my problem. And so I am now able to use the plasma desktop and
And drive the sound effects from this machine
And not have it randomly change sound cards on me
Or what was happening to me in plasma before is some desktop application would use one sound card
And other ones would use another sound that's the worst he's awful
So that was the number one question that came in after last is but what about the sound because i've gone on and on about that
Problem. I don't think it's particularly solved but because I can disable devices that I don't want to use it solves the problem for me
So there you go
Problem solved if you don't have two three sound cards in a machine
It's not as big of a deal. But most of us these days do have hdmi out
And if that supports sound which it does then probably have your nice usb dag. I mean, yeah now, you know, I haven't
Hmm
I haven't tried it on the deck upstairs where I had a problem. It would reset the volume to maximum. Ooh, that would be phase two
That's phase two. Yeah, it is because the speakers up there are my editing speakers and they are loud dude
It literally I think I think it gave me a heart palpitation when the first time
Because it was like a kd like error message like a bring air and it was so loud
My ears rang afterwards and rikai. I I think came out of him says everything. Okay, like like it was
ridiculous, uh, yeah, so
Kitson has that happened to you?
Where it just resets the volume to maximum for like an application like what happened if I recall was
Is for some reason an application volume got set low
But the system volume would be set to 100 and so a system message would come up at 100
System messages. Have you gotten that kitson?
I've had that happen a couple times. Uh, not recently the one big thing that happens to me is
Uh, my mic will get unplugged because I got an old mic and the connection's kind of janky
And then i'll go to plug it back in and it'll be muted and I have to switch everything back over
It doesn't default correctly. Yeah. Yeah, I you know, i'll see if I run into those kind
I think the only way I can really find out is if I
Try to jump in. Yep. Holy smokes. This is slick desktop
Oh, oh also should mention speaking of martin and kwin and how great kwin is, uh five dot six
Real solid like this one will run on wayland release. This is the will run on wayland release. That might be fun to try
Yeah, big deal now not ready for production not 100 but so much work has gone into making this freaking work on wayland
And a lot of that work is showing up in five six
um
Pretty cool pretty damn cool and you could probably just go try it out using the neon
Uh iso in the show notes
And you know all the you know, what's funny what's ironic what's ironic about this and the story of my life as a linux user
Super I don't distro hop anymore. I desktop well actually i'm about to distro hop too. You are right god old habits die hard, don't they?
Uh, what's what's really frustrating is all this freaking choice because also gnome 320 is about to come out and
Gnome 320 is looking really good
Yeah, so go figure i'm getting all excited about plasma desktop right as the new gnome is about to come out
I just I uh, these are good problems to have though. Yeah. Yeah, we're first world problems for sure
But yeah, I tell you what and you know what I I just uh, i'll just revel in it
I'll just revel in it. I guess at least I have a place to talk about my problems
You guys are like my therapy session. That's right
Okay, uh mumble room any uh closing thoughts before we move on from plasma desktop 5 6
Yeah, I thought with that video that uh, kde was totally going the gnome direction with release announcements
but I think that they
Really messed it up. The music was awful. The voiceover was boring. You still need a good mic
Yeah, and there was a little bit too much echo the music was kind of robotic
Yeah, the uh, the music could be a little more excited like you could do something like a you know
Plasma 5.6 is a brand new release from the kd, you know or something you could you could you could spice it up
Just talk to chris. He'll do it. Yeah, totally I would too. Uh, but I actually at the same time
I'm really glad because uh, one of the things that I have complained about
Is how bad linux journalism is and when the projects are releasing videos themselves?
Like you've been watching the mycroft project has done this brilliantly. Uh is
You don't fumble the message
You don't have a chance for there to be a misinterpretation because the journalist
Well, not only will they get to write about what you're what you're doing
But they'll just also embed your video
It gives you an opportunity to speak to the public directly about what's great and new and not having it lost in translation
Um, and now it's just a matter of refinement make it a little peppier make it a little more excited
This is a big deal. A lot of awesome stuff just happened and you are excited about it
I mean, I am more excited about it than the person that video was not to be too critical
But let's be real and also yeah, the music did suck. But you know what at least they had music
Yeah, the old cloud project didn't even have music right? So we're seeing we helped him out though
This is legitimately a new interesting trend. We are seeing an open source
We are going from the community that barely even has screenshots of our shit to the community that is creating video
Videos. Yeah about our shit like that is a huge transition for us and one I completely support
because if nothing else
It gives people an opportunity to share something. I know that sounds stupid
But you know a two minute youtube video is an easy share
And you can spread the word and people can watch it. It's a lot easier
Yeah, it's so much easier to be like hey check out this cool desktop. I'm using rather than
Github readme with just text and like q5 says to point out is to help some control their image in the message
Uh, and so that way, you know, it doesn't get fumbled by the quote-unquote journalists out there
I I actually think it's a good trend but the problem is doing a doing a video
And doing a good video
Are hard that was that was that was a good attempt and I really I respect them for trying it
They could they could spice it up a little bit
Um, and it's just it just takes a little bit of time of trial and error
I mean look at my look at my people who know how to do it and my early stuff is embarrassing as hell
Like my current stuff is embarrassing as hell and i've been doing it for 10 years. So I can't give them that much crap
You know what? I can talk about that and I do love this linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged go support the unplugged program and learn more actually go support yourself
This is a great opportunity to learn more about any of the technologies built around linux the linux stack
Or any of the really good stuff that people make money off of on linux
And what I love about the linux academy is it isn't just a feature
For their training website gotta have that linux and open source stuff on there. It's really what they're all about
They got in this as a way to be advocates for linux programmers developers linux enthusiasts system administrators
They got together and they built the linux academy platform. They now have
2339 video self-paced courses downloadable comprehensive study guides seven plus distributions
you get to choose from life server spun up on the demand with an ssh connection and
Not only have they recently expanded into new offices launched an app for mobile
But they've brought in a whole bunch of staff to get new content on board even faster and make sure older content stays relevant
Because you know what turns out linux changes a bunch
Like all the time and they get that, you know, it's not they're not going to just create something and let it rot
They really have some interesting technology too like scenario based labs, which are right in the middle of a common everyday environment task
So you really have hands-on experience and confidence
Instructor mentoring is available, which is great
Especially for stuff like this experts who like know what they're doing. Have you ever have you ever done like work training?
Have you ever done like a work training program?
I worked for a few places that would actually give me like a little bit like a like I was like like 1200 bucks a year
Something like this. Have you ever had anything like that? No
Yeah, I worked for a place or like well, we'll give you courses, uh, which is all on banking
Uh, or you can get a 1200 budget
And so I just kind of worked that in moving too when I went into contracting and I worked for somebody as a contractor for
A while. I still I had like a 1200 educational budget
um, but that was because I was going to community colleges and I was going to like professional court training courses for citrix and
And uh vmware and nothing nothing like linux academy existed for me now today something like linux academy would have changed my game
It would I could have taken on new clients and had the confidence to expand into different technologies fast
I know I could have stayed current and part of that game was staying certified
Even if it was for a review so that way I get a raise or if it was for getting a client
It was just to make myself feel better and challenge myself
Having a resource like linux academy would have blown my face off linux academy dot com slash unplugged go there to support the show
And blow your own face off. They got courseware on amazon web services
They got the red hat certifications python ruby android development
If you want to get into that biz php if you know what's good for you
Don't tell michael dominic and of course the entire linux stack nginx apache ruby on rails
All of it's over at linux academy dot com
And they have a community that's stacked full of jupiter broadcasting members because i've been talking about them for a while
In-depth resources are great. Listen to it in the shower or while you're on the go
Mix it in with your podcast playlist and advance your skill set linux academy dot com
Slash unplugged and a big thank you to linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Check out their live stream archives, too. So
Google hangouts
pretty damn good
hard to beat
But not a ton of people no not open and uh, maybe a little creepy
And so a couple of things have been submitted into the show recently one from producer rotten corpse and one from our very own
wes
and
They both in their own corners are powerful open source google hangout and skype killers
And there's been a lot of hoopla around skype recently on linux
So let's start with the new contender the one that most of us haven't heard about before
Hubble dot in you think i'm saying that right hubble dot in
I think that's how you're saying it and I want to start up and I want it
Let's do a let's do a meeting right now with our live chat room. So i'm going to go uh lup
Well, i'm just going to do slash lup. So it's uh, h u b l
H u b l dot i n slash lup i'm going to start up a video conference right now
And we'll see it and then we'll compare this to the other contender the other open source contender, which has recently gotten a whole
Bunch of real live science right here on linux. All right, so i'm going to set my name and look at this
I like this right off the bat. So you set your name here?
This is one thing that struck me
But then look at this west choose your video quality low rate medium rate or awesome right up front. I'm gonna go awesome rate
That feels good. Right? Okay, so now next. Okay. So now i've started it's going to ask for uh permission to use my webcam
I'll say yes go ahead use my webcam
And I could send email invites out to people
Uh if I wanted to look at that, we already got we already got somebody in there. That's great. Yeah
So there's poppy down there. That's awesome. That's really good
Uh, that's cool. Hey guys, how's it going? Hello. Hi. Hi
Hi, look at that
Popey, oh, yeah, you're in the moment room. So you have your mic muted. That's cool
And so you see it has uh, the little uh thumbnails down here
Oh, we just had another another person join. So it's really easy for everybody get in there and uh, fatty fatso just got in there
It's fatty fatso. He's in as the linux talks
He doesn't have to use video if he doesn't want
You can turn off your microphone or your webcam if you want to be private for a moment
Which is a kind of a cool feature. I mean really a needed one for any like enterprise scale use
Here's what I like though. I gave out I gave out uh one url hubble.in
Slash lup and now we've got one two three four five six people who've joined
Now some of them have like that some of them are we're getting a little playback. So
Uh, but that is it is nice. You have the ability to start a chat
Uh now two more people just joined look at that. Hello ptd. Hello patrick
So there we go. A couple more people just came in. Hi guys. Good to see you
uh
I love my microphones in the shot. Um, that is really nice slick easy to do way way quicker than hangouts. And here's a nice thing
Look at this
It is using peer-to-peer web technology. It's not going through their servers. They're not recording it
It's all happening peer-to-peer. All right, i'm gonna hang up on you guys, but thank you. That was a good experiment
So okay, that's contender number one
hubble
Contender number two
A well-established name someone we know with a varied history kind of trust
Used to use it on the desktop, but now they want you to use it on the web. Yes friends. It's jitzy
And rotten corpse. You're the one that submitted jitzy for a contender this week
Do you want to mention what it was about the new jitzy updates that uh, got you all excited and wanted to plug it on
the show
And by the way
Before rotten starts it's meat dot jit dot si slash love
I'll put the hopefully i'll be able to put the full uh url in the show notes. But okay, go ahead rotten
You might be in transit right now. Oh, okay. Okay. Very good. So here we go
So you've joined charham join me. You can see me here. I'm on the uh, have you tried out?
Have you tried out jitzy west? Yeah, i'm on there right now. Are you did you only?
That's me
Hi, chris. Hello west as you can see it's doing the automatic switching. Uh, hello fellow jitzer. So it just calls him fellow jitzer
But I like how it's switching between them and also this one shows you the signal strength of individual people
Which is kind of nice and oh look at this I can
I can make I can make people disappear which is kind of nice. I can mute individual people. I can kick people out
I'm digging this open close the contact list show or hide the film
Oh, we should switch to this on last this just be google hangouts right there one button hide the strips that is really neat
Look at everybody showing up. It's handling this connection just fine. So both of them using webrtc
And we're both using it. Yeah
This is this is a hard call, but I think I want to give the nod to uh, jitzy here for a couple of different reasons
Uh a little bit these notifications when someone else connects too. Yeah, I like the jitzy notification system
Jitzy meet also allows you to share documents with everybody participating share a prezzi session
And it allows you to share your screen
So I think it has hubble beat a little bit. Yeah, this is a new update allowing you to share
Your screen is really cool. So I i'm I would try it
But then I would just share my screen share my screen of sharing you should try sharing your screen west
Do you want to try sharing your screen?
And then I think I can click you to bring you up. So there's west right there. I like this. Oh, wow. Look at that
I can oh
I hover over your uh your signals there. Look at that west
I get your exact bitrate that you're currently sending me right now and the resolution it says a little low resolution
But of course, that's probably just your webcam. Yeah, probably so there's your screen up is the best
Yeah, because here's uh, here's a mr. Uh, uh, let's see. What's it say?
His name is lynn fax or something like that. He's sending me a different resolution than you are and uh,
Uh, whoever this guy is he's sending me. Well, he's sending me the same resolution here. This guy looks like he's uh, hello
Fellow jits are i'm bringing you up on screen. He's sending me no 160 by 90. I'm not sure
I gotta play. I gotta see if I can get a high definition. What about me? What am I sending? What am I sending?
I'm sending 320 by 180. So that would be the one thing is if I could get it up. Let's see settings
Listen, which it is. You can start without audio. That's kind of neat
Hmm, yeah, okay. I think that I think these are both pretty good winners here, but uh sam radio you have 720p on yours
All right, well that's something
Huh? Hey citizen coming in with no video so you can still participate
I like that. This is pretty cool. I think bit I think if you need a google hangouts replacement that you want to be open source
That works in your web browser
I think I think you give it to meet.jit.si. We'll have a link in the show notes
I did have to install a chrome extension to get the uh screen sharing to work
But it installed very quickly. Yeah, it did if you did it on air
Yeah, I mean it was just like one hit add and so are you able to go?
So can you bring your screen back? Oh, you turned your screen off. Oh, okay. No, that's fine. That's fine
Oh, we have somebody else. This is really cool. Oh, there's poppy. So what's poppy coming in now?
Poppy's coming in at 640 by 380 for some reason and he's yeah, I don't know why he's not higher resolution video
I don't know why it's not higher resolution video
That seems to be the thing
Got to play with that. Yeah, but this is a more controlled trial be interesting
You can lock the room down too so people can stop joining you can invite others to join
That is great
So there you go to open source google plus. Oh, are you back rotten?
No, it's not rotten it's me
um, but I just saying just saying that uh, the another advantage that gt has over all of the other competitors
Is that it has the video bridge with the gt from the desktop?
So if someone is on the regular gt can talk, oh, so you could still use the desktop. That is damn cool, dude
That is really nice. I really like that the options something that
That's something that they've been working on
Uh to to make it work, you know
Um, we could use this so when poppy talks poppy could be on video
Yeah
That so poppy try talking in the mumble room while you're on gitsy video. See if you can pull that off
That could be kind of yeah, I can do that. Oh, look at that. That is so cool
And it's almost synced up too. Look at that
This could be a cool way to get the actual faces of the bumble room on the stream if we want to take it up
And I mean we have the video stream anyway. Yeah. Yeah, that is really neat
I could I could route my microphone through this as well
You could but but I don't know I think it's more because we're because the nice thing is you could have some people on here
I guess i'd have to know when to switch it
I guess this could be used in place of mumble too, but I like the mumble room better for this kind of thing
Yeah. All right. Well, very cool. So, uh, we'll have links to both of those open source google hangout and skype replacement
So if you've been bellyaching about microsoft killing support for skype
Uh, this might be a go-to replacement for family members chats with friends
Yeah kits and you had something you wanted to jump in before we move on. Yeah, um, actually it's uh,
Something that I found it's a different topic
Did you see this thing about a uh rust written microkernel? I did and they were throwing some shade on linux if I recall, right?
Yeah, this is really cool
Redox. Yeah. Yeah, and they were they were slamming linux a bit in their announcement. But yeah redox
A rust written microkernel open source os. Yeah
Yeah
Yeah, I have heard of it. I just don't it's impressive. They've gotten a pretty good way
They've got a gooey up and yeah, they say the whole thing weighs in at just 26 megabytes for that. So
26 megabytes, maybe i'll give that a spin this week. You should dude. Can you report back? Yeah, that'd be pretty cool. That'd be pretty good
Uh, all right. So, uh, that's probably the end. I love this. I uh wave. Goodbye poppy wave. Goodbye poppy
Oh that beautiful beautiful poppy. Bye. Bye. Bye now
Bye guys, thanks for testing the different uh, uh html webrtc powered solutions. I'm hanging up on your face
It is nice to know that it's you know, we're all just connecting as peers. Thanks for using jitsi meat
Yeah, you're right
And you know what that's going to mean is hopefully I better connection speeds right and better latency and whatnot because you're not routing through
A server and the nice thing is of course since you're not running through a server if nobody's recording your session
You could record your session, but nobody else we recorded that session. We did we did that's an example of that
All right. So there's a lot coming up on future episodes of linux unplugged, especially as linux fest northwest gets closer
But also as some major distros release
There's going to be a lot of stuff and a lot of opportunity for you to get your thoughts in on the show
So please do join us live go over to jblive.tv. We do the show on tuesdays
You can go to jupyterbroadcasting.com
Slash calendar to get that s converted to your local time zone and then you join our virtual log via mumble
Which is an open source communications program and you can get the server in our chat room the information by doing bang mumble
It's kind of like our little like that's like that's like the hardest part
That's the test to prove you're worthy
You got to join the chat room
You got to do bang mumble and you got to install mumble and then that's it
You just got to have a working nice to blaster
That's probably a good idea
Uh, and it's our virtual log
You can hang out with us and share your thoughts and as some big stuff is coming up
It's a great opportunity for you to get in there and take part of it
So we'd love to have you go to jupyterbroadcasting.com
Slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone and a big thank you to our virtual log for making it this week
Thanks to west for once again saving the show by supplying the beer
It's a close call to what I can the beer and the burger you want above and beyond this week, man
That's pretty impressive. That means rika. I'll get this show out, you know
Split greasely greased up with uh five guys grease that is gross
Follow the network at jupiter signal for uh show announcements and live streams at chris
Isles for my stuff about linux fest northwest linuxactionshow.reddit.com for feedback
On this week's episode and topic suggestions. Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of linux unplugged
And we'll see you right back here next tuesday
So
Why don't we why don't we kill a few minutes and talk about something I
I started to bring this up in tech talk and I shut the conversation down because I actually wanted to talk about it here
In linux unplugged saved it. I know it so android n has been out for certain devices
I don't think you've tried it yet though. I haven't no, but you could right on your nexus 5. Yeah, maybe I should
Yeah, uh, well, I don't know if you'll be able to try this on the nexus 5, but one of the hidden features in android n
is
Multi-windowed mode so not just like side-by-side windows
But like full-on broken up multi-windowing desktop environment with a bar down at the bottom a system tray quick launch icons
awkward black around chrome desktop icons on the desktop android n is
Potentially i'm looking at this thinking
This could be a chrome os. This could be a chrome os killer
Easily. Yeah, it looks like it
Wow, could it also be
an ubuntu desktop killer
Because you get a linux based os and the x86 project is even more
So you get a linux based os you get mainstream corporate applications like microsoft office
Uh adobe lightroom you get an official telegram evernote you get google chrome netflix hulu, uh, all of that stuff
on a desktop environment
That could run on arm or intel
I mean, maybe if you're like, you know, so I was looking at the stack exchange
Did you see the stack exchange survey that came out recently? Yes, I did
And like the number one thing everybody's working on is web dev, right? That's like the well you could do web dev on this thing
Potentially, you know, I suppose so take this thing like take this thing down to like like ang said in tech talk
Take this down to like android q. So this has been around for a few years
I'm not saying with n this happens
But android q you have a really well flushed out multi-windowing system that you could download an iso for and set up on a laptop
Or buy a chromebook that actually runs this
Yeah, okay, I can see it yeah, I can see installing it on people's machines
I mean I might if it was flushed out. I might rather install this on my like a friend's machine than say windows
What do you think about uh, like uh wimpy? What do you think about like like, uh, more hardcore work cases that like production?
Development do you think something do you think it's ever going to be possible on something like this?
Um, my question to you is if this is an ubuntu desktop killer. Can you produce a show on it?
You know, I don't know about today
But uh, there are becoming some decent media production tools for android like uh, there are um ice cast
And um live video streaming rtmp and and twitch you could do from android devices on ios
There's full-fledged video editors. I have not looked on android
Maybe I don't think I don't think today
But maybe one day
hmm
Yeah, what about what about you wimpy? Could you do your?
Could you do most of your daily driving on an android device if it was multi-windowed on a powerful considerably powerful hardware?
So say you could pick your x86 box of choice
I don't need much power to do what I do
Um, but yes, um, I have used android successfully to do the things I would need to do of a day
I could definitely see this on a tablet
Like if you had a nice bluetooth keyboard and a good you know
Like ssh program to get some work done and you have chrome up on one half of the screen terminal on the other
That'd probably work for a lot of remote stuff