Well, the reason why I was asking if producer rotten corpse was here is because he had a
write up that was pretty cool over at make use of dot com about the easy way to watch
Netflix on Linux spoiler alert.
Really the easy way.
Do you know what it is, Wes?
Install Chrome.
How could he?
How could it be easier?
Mm hmm.
Yeah.
But he walks through that and he also walks through a couple other options you have, like
breaking it off into its own desktop application and the issue where it is with where it's out
on Firefox and things like that.
So that's really cool.
But we actually had an email into Linux Unplugged just this week that was asking how to get
Netflix running again.
So I thought, boy, what a great chance to mention that.
And then kind of great timing.
Also Joey on OMG Ubuntu has a how to watch Hulu on Ubuntu 14.04, which includes installing
HAL, I guess, because flash DRM doesn't work on Ubuntu without that.
So it goes through how to get that going on Ubuntu 14.04 or later.
So Hulu on Linux and Netflix use Hulu, you know, only occasionally.
So I'd be glad to have a guy like this.
Have you read that article carefully?
You've spotted anything familiar at all in that article?
Let me see.
I actually just pulled it up right here.
I'm noticing.
Let's see.
I can add an Ubuntu PPA here.
It's very nice.
I can stall.
What am I missing as I peruse through it?
Is there PPA?
Is it whose PPA?
Well, I noticed that that's actually what jumped out at me to tell you the truth.
But I don't know.
I mean, is that how do you say a flexi on dot org flexi on flexi?
Tell us about that, Wimpy.
Tell us about that.
That's me.
Yeah.
Are you is this an issue that you've been working on for Ubuntu Mate edition or what
is what's going on here?
What's
Yeah.
It's built into Ubuntu Mate.
Oh, that's beautiful.
Gosh, I love that.
I love that.
I say it's built.
I say it's built in.
So actually, I found the upstream project some months ago.
Oh, here's the credit to you right here.
Very nice.
Very good.
Good for Joey for pointing that out.
I like that.
Yeah.
Well deserved.
So the upstream project has done all the hard work.
All I did was add some packaging for Debian and Ubuntu and chuck it in a PPA.
And in Ubuntu Mate welcome, when you install Adobe Flash, it automatically pulls in that
Hal Flash plugin as well, so that you get all the good stuff baked in.
And what I'm currently working on is getting that into the Debian archives.
So then it appears in Ubuntu official archives, and everyone's got access to it.
Jeez, you are really making that a great out-of-the-box experience for regular users.
That is super cool, Wimpy.
But now everybody else can take advantage of it too.
The secret is unleashed.
Mwa ha ha ha.
For all of you who want to watch it.
That is no secret.
I've been rather poorly doing the job of trying to publicize this.
And Stuart Langridge has been poking fun at me every time he's found the alternative methods
in the online press.
So I was very pleased that Joey actually did the job that was somewhere down my list of
things to do.
Very good.
Which is actually write this up.
Yeah.
So yeah, he's done me a favor there.
Very nice.
And now others can take advantage of it.
Maybe we'll try it out later.
Yeah.
All right, this is Linux Unplugged episode 110 for September 15th, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's just about to hit the road.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hey there, Wes.
So I am all stoked to talk about today's episode.
It's funny because our pre-show, we were kind of talking about online streaming, but really
in today's episode, we're going to have an emphasis on offline life like you're online.
I like that.
It's all the things we're used to in the modern era, but without a connection.
Exactly.
That's my world right now.
And so we're going to cover a couple of really great, well, actually more than a couple of
really great open source projects that help you live completely offline, but enjoy some
of the perks of being online.
Of course, we're also going to get into a block level backup system that is a little
bit cooler than LVM snapshots.
It gives you copy on write essentially to any file system.
It even works with ButterFS if you want to use it with ButterFS and it looks like it
just runs in the background transparently.
We're going to tell you a little bit about that coming up in the show.
And then also we've been talking about Munich and their big Linux switch and all of the
news that's been coming out of that on the Linux action show for about three weeks now.
And we're going to give the final word to our virtual lug as we say goodbye to the Munich
story with how they contribute upstream to open source.
We'll cover that in today's episode, plus a little update on the impending road show
and some really, really great feedback.
So we have a whole bunch of stuff to get into.
So before we go any further, we should probably totally bring in that mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings in virtual lug.
Hey, Pep.
Hello.
There they are.
Hello, everybody.
So guess what?
Guess what?
We got to get right into it today because we have lots of stuff to cover.
So I want to start with the emails that have been coming to Linux Unplugged.
Dow wrote in with a name for the road show.
Here's my contribution.
Love all the shows.
Good luck with the endeavor.
He says we should call it the Finding Linux Roadshow.
So in Linux action show, we named the mobile studio the JB Rover, Rover for short.
Now we have to name this tour.
Each road show will have its own name.
Each tour will have its own name.
So we can refer to it as that.
So Dow suggests we're going to name it.
We're going to decide today on Linux Unplugged what it is.
So yeah, we're going to vote and decide.
So Dow says we should name it the Finding Linux Roadshow.
And that's a good idea because I do plan everywhere I go to try to find if they use Linux.
Everywhere I go.
So that's not bad.
The Finding Linux Roadshow.
That's not bad.
Not bad.
But we have more.
Hold on.
Hold your thoughts.
Because Terry writes in with a few names for the road show.
Now get ready for these ones, Wes.
The Very Open Roadshow, or VORCE for short.
The Wide Open Roadshow, or VORCE for short, the Linux Open Roadshow, or Linux on the Move.
So those are a couple of submissions there.
And what I'm going to suggest is while we talk about this a little more, I'm going to
submit, this will be in the show notes as well, I'm going to submit this to the chat
room for voting.
Put them all in there.
You guys go vote.
I got to say, so J.B.
Rover was the mobile studio name, but Jupiter 2 was a very common popular suggestion.
So I have a poll up right now for naming the road show.
This will go on while we do the rest of the show.
And chat room and Mumba room, if you could vote away, I just put the link in the show
notes, strawpoll.me, slash 5496571.
And we get to vote.
See if we got any votes yet.
Finding Linux is the Finding Linux Roadshow, and Last Cribs Roadshow is also up there for
voting.
Because remember, I'm going to Noah's house.
I'm going to do a Last Cribs episode.
So there you go.
And then one more email kind of in this, and we'll let the votes continue.
Alex wrote in asking the following.
He says, for the road show, I heard you might be passing by Colorado.
In case that is so, it would be great if you'd like to come by for a beer at a microboo.
Oh, cool.
All right.
Well, hold on to that thought there, Alex.
But here's the second thing.
He says, this week, I was at a student's meeting of Linux users at the university.
And it was great to see so many people that were interested in Linux.
They helped installing Mint or whoever liked to try Linux out.
Some of them were even running Arch.
There were around 10 to 15 people.
Perhaps you'd like to meet them.
They're a new generation of Linux users.
So maybe I could meet them when I come back.
That might be a fun thing to do.
Yeah.
So Alex asked about meeting up in Colorado.
And Alex, so right now, we may actually end up going through Colorado on the return trip.
But that's all a little tentative at the moment.
So if you go to meetup.com slash jupyterbroadcasting, we have Odyssey West right here in the Mumble
Room.
He's going to be setting up some Mumble, or I'm sorry, some meetups as we go along.
And you'll be able to see where we're at, because we're going to have a Jupiter Broadcast.
We already have jupyterbroadcasting.com slash rover set up.
It's a live tracker of the journey of where the rover is at.
So you'll be able to see what town it's at.
And you'll be able to tweet me or email rover at jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Rover at Jupiter Broadcasting.
Very own email.
I love it.
Yep.
Rover at Jupiter Broadcasting is great for trailer tips.
A lot of people are emailing in with suggestions and tips for the trailer.
If you want to meet up on the road, we'll be checking that inbox.
And all that kind of stuff can go to rover at jupyterbroadcasting.com.
It's also on the contact page.
And if you go to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash rover, you can see where the rover is in real
time.
Odyssey Westridge is going to have access to that, too.
And he'll be able to set up some meetups and things like that.
So meetup.com slash jupyterbroadcasting if you want to meet up along the way.
Because, Alex, I think that'd be really cool.
I'd like that.
So let's try to get that set up.
So let's check in with the votes one more time.
Ooh.
Last Cribs Roadshow is up to the top.
Look at that.
With 47% of the votes so far, Finding Linux is number two.
And the Linux Open Roadshow is number three.
No votes.
The wide open roadshow and the very open roadshow are getting no votes.
Might be good to keep Finding Linux in your back pocket here.
This one is a Cribs trip.
Yeah.
Right.
Finding Linux.
That's true.
When you're out of ideas and you want to hit the open road, you can just go hunt down
Linux.
That's true.
That's good.
Finding Linux could apply to a future road trip.
Not that we should be influencing the votes, Wes.
Certainly not.
Please.
Just disregard everything.
That's just standing order.
Yeah.
So there you go.
Let's see what happens.
And then by the end of this episode, maybe we'll have a name.
We'll see what.
We'll see.
If the votes are really super clear about it, we'll see if we have a name.
So this is the last Linux Unplugged recording in studio.
You'll be in studio.
Yeah.
But I will not be in studio starting next week.
I'll be on the road.
And there's definitely a few things still to work out.
I don't actually have all of the studio itself assembled in the RV yet.
And I have disgusting tank issues that need to be worked out.
Extra baggage.
Yeah.
There are a few things that are just really kind of still up in the air.
So it's a little crazy.
And I still have, you know, before I leave on Saturday, I still have unfiltered two tech
snaps and a Linux action show to record and see if I can fit in a tech talk.
So it's going to be nuts.
It's going to be good.
It's going to be nuts.
That's all I'm saying.
And you know, speaking of the road trip, and then we'll start.
Let's talk about Munich.
I am really excited to say that right before we started the show, my first I'm going to
get I'm going to have two Ting MiFi devices and they just sent me one of the CDMA devices.
But I'm going to use on the road.
So I'll have Ting sponsored connectivity while I'm on the go, thankfully, which is going
to solve a huge part of the problem.
That's amazing.
Yeah, it's really great.
And you know, right now Ting is doing a $50 promo for the month of September.
If you go to Linux.ting.com, that'll support this show and give you $50 off Ting service
for you.
Ting is pay for what you use mobile.
It's $6 a line and then just your usage on top of that.
That's how Ting works.
They have a really great dashboard and they have no hold customer service.
And that's the core recipe of Ting.
And they really make they make this super, super valuable.
Like it is unbelievable with three lines and paying like $40 a month for three smartphones.
It's amazing.
And the nice thing is if you need like a MiFi device, you just need data from time to time,
Ting could be a great, great solution for you because it's just $6 for the line.
You can even suspend the line when you're not using it.
Go to Linux.ting.com and click on that how much you would save and put your deets in
there and check them out because they've got a CDMA and GSM network.
They have a lot of coverage you can choose from and that also means there's a lot of
devices you can use.
In fact, very likely you might have already a Ting compatible device, in which case you'll
get a $50 service credit.
And they have some devices that are just absolutely unbelievable.
Like right now the Galaxy S6 is on sale.
The Blue Studio 6LTE is on sale and look at the Kyocero Duro XT.
I think that thing could survive like an alien attack.
It's so cool.
Forty seven dollars for a feature phone and the battery just lasts forever.
And Noah was saying that the speaker on that thing is so loud, too, that that's a really
nice feature because it's designed for construction sites.
So a lot of good phones, everything from the feature phones up to the latest and greatest
devices.
And you know the Karma Go is new and I've been looking at that Karma Go.
That might be what they sent me.
I don't know.
They either sent me that or the neck ear unit.
I'm not quite sure which one I got.
To show them off on some future updates.
Totally, totally.
Yeah, there's a great range of devices to pick from including all the iPhone devices,
the latest Android devices and you can get that $50 credit by going to linux.ting.com.
Check them out.
Take a read at their blog.
Try their savings calculator.
I think you're going to be impressed on how different a mobile company can be.
It's a really cool setup and Ting's a unique company backed by a great company, Two Cows.
You're probably familiar with them.
You can go to linux.ting.com to support the show and get our discount and a big thanks
to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Okay, so we've covered the Munich switch now for well, for years in Linux Action Show technically.
But in the last couple of weeks, there's been a lot of hoopla around, do the users want
to switch away?
Is it a core group of people?
Or maybe it's just these one group of department department users that want to switch away
and some Microsoft spokespersons.
And in all of this coverage, I think one of the things that came up was holy crap, the
Munich IT department is modifying the Linux that they're using.
I mean, they have Limux and the LibreOffice they're using quite a bit, something like
40 patches to LibreOffice.
Huge patch load to carry.
Yeah.
And a lot of people thought this was a big mistake.
Now one thing we did mention in the show, but I think it kind of got missed is the patches
that they're doing, they are sending upstream.
That's awesome.
That's the way to do it.
So they are, they consider themselves a major contributor to free and open source projects,
sending bug fixes to upstream developers, making available software solutions and sharing
best practices and technical information.
Now this is true.
I know that there are IT folks when they, when some of the things they've discovered
employing large sets of Linux machines they've been sharing.
One of the things they say is the development cycle is long.
And one of the members of the city's Linux client development team was saying that one
of the reasons the wide range of computer hardware is supported.
So this is one of the challenges they have is because the development cycle of Limux
and the applications they use is long, hardware changes fairly quickly.
So they say whatever computer hardware was built in the last 20 years, Munich is running
and it's a central IT department, it's central that the IT department has to support it.
So they have 18,000 PCs, so you can imagine how much hardware breaks per day.
And that's why we always stock half a year's worth of hardware.
And of course sometimes they have to do custom patches to support some of this hardware.
And some of these include patches for like scanners to do certain kinds of document scanning.
They have a web based solution to administer accounts for groups, servers and workstations
with an LDAP distributed directory with information services.
They have fully automated installation services that make software available updates to people,
to all the workstations, over 50 offices across the city.
And they're on the fifth version of Limux, which isn't deployed for everybody but it's
based on Kubuntu.
Now you were just recently playing with automated deployments.
When you hear numbers like this, you know, you look at impressive organizations.
Yeah, that's 18,000 PCs, 50 offices.
When you think of automating something like that, does it boggle the mind a little bit?
It definitely does.
Yeah, I can't even, I mean, you'd have to though.
You would have to.
I mean, and I can understand how they have some legacy needs that perhaps smaller, more
nimble organizations are not buckled down with.
Yeah.
I wanted to kind of mention to you guys though, do you guys have any takeaways from our recent
Munich coverage?
Anything, any gaps that you wanted to fill in on the Munich coverage?
Anybody?
Because I know it's been a popular topic in our subreddit, so I wanted to open it up for
discussion here in the show.
Really?
I've got to figure somebody has an opinion on it.
The only thing that's occurred to me, I mean, I know it's been a long time since they started
this effort, but this day and age, do they need their own distribution?
Could they not find a commercially supported distribution and repurpose that?
Just tweak the applications that are installed and use Ubuntu or OpenSUSE or?
It does sound like they're doing a lot of work to keep up with everything.
It's a lot to keep in house.
They're starting with Ubuntu, yeah.
Yeah, but it's quite old, isn't it?
It is, yeah.
Yeah.
The design of, the only thing that I think is silly is the design that they have of like
a six year cycle between different versions.
So there's at least one year they're guaranteed not to get support and they did that on purpose.
Well if you were going to do it today, wouldn't you almost do it somewhat similar sort of
as your own spin off of the distro?
Like it would be PPAs that you lay down on top of it and things like that.
Isn't that kind of how you would do it if you were going to do it today?
But it would be as close to mainline Ubuntu as possible?
Yeah.
And I would update every two years.
Borky makes a good point.
They're running KDE, so why don't they base this on OpenSUSE?
Yeah, there's like with the studio to spin your own and then the build service to build
the applications.
And maybe you could have different versions for different sets of hardware if you needed
it.
Truly SUSE could really, the SUSE studio and the SUSE builds or open build service could
provide a ton of infrastructure for them.
Yeah.
Well isn't this the risk when you adopt too early?
Did they?
Okay, Wimpy.
But very frankly, did they adopt Linux too early?
No, I wouldn't want to say that because somebody has to sort of take the first step and Munich
have been sort of the shining light for everyone else to follow.
And there have been examples of other organizations and municipalities following their lead.
So I think that's all good.
And I think that what's changed is that the Linux landscape has changed a little bit since
they first set out on this endeavor.
Yeah.
Somebody had to do it.
Somebody at a large scale had to do it.
And it's great to see them contributing some of what they've learned about trying to – hopefully
the next city that adopts it will do a leaner job.
What about my concern though that because they're kind of – I mean I really respect
the work they're doing here and I think it's great that they've taken this on.
But isn't it also not the best example for us?
Because it is sort of an old style of doing an implementation, it feels like every time
the press goes to it every year to look at how it's doing and the story that comes
out is well, they're struggling a little bit but they're still chugging along.
That feels like not a great use case.
It doesn't get you excited about it.
Yeah.
It doesn't make me want to switch my company over if I'm some CTO, right?
Right.
That I worry about a little bit is I'd love to see some of the companies that are out
there that are huge that have switched over to Ubuntu on the desktop that just have massive
deployments and they don't talk about it.
That I would really like to see.
Because I think if more people talked about it, it's like it becomes like part of people's
secret sauce.
It's like it's part of their, what keeps them different.
I don't know what it is, exactly why companies aren't talking about it, but if they would,
I feel like it would feel like it was more commonplace.
But Munich's what we get.
What's that?
I'd like to know where Munich falls on the spectrum of organizations that have really
customized their installation.
Are there entities out there with 18,000 desktops that just take Ubuntu or Red Hat out of the
box?
Well, we know there's gubuntu, so we know Ubuntu's, or I mean we know Google is modifying
Ubuntu.
I feel like we also miss out on some of the maybe enterprise that have some Linux deployment
on the desktop.
You know, like maybe developers and some of the IT staff, maybe not the accountants.
Yeah, for sure.
I'm sure that happens quite a bit.
And if you watch Mr. Robot, apparently everybody runs Linux.
You ever watch Mr. Robot, that show?
Only the first episode.
Oh, really?
Yeah, I have to catch up.
Well, it's a pretty interesting show, but the one thing that does seem to keep me coming
back every single week is every single week they have gratuitous shots of the Linux desktop.
That's beautiful.
Yeah, it actually is.
A Linux desktop.
Yeah.
I mean...
Not what they say it is.
Oh, I see you're running GNOME.
It's not GNOME.
Well, sometimes they have run, they've shown GNOME, but it's mostly, it looks like KDE
a lot of times.
Like I was watching episode eight of season one last night and it looked like console
came up and he was seeding the slash opt slash something or other.
Do they have like a Linux advisor like big studios have science advisors for their films?
It seems to have, yeah.
They do actually.
That's beautiful.
Yeah.
They have, it's impressive that they actually run commands and the stuff that it displays
is really what it actually does.
You guys...
That's mind blowing.
You guys heard us play this clip in last, a couple of weeks ago, but I'm going to play
it again anyways, because it's like, when I heard this, when I heard this clip, I was
like, okay, well now I have to watch that show.
And I'd heard about the show and I was like, Christian Slater, okay, that's fine.
I don't have anything really against him, but not totally drawing me in.
And then when I saw this clip, I was like, okay, yeah, I'm going to watch this show.
So I see a running gnome, you know, I'm actually on KDE myself.
I know this desktop environment is supposed to be better, but you know what they say,
old habits, they die hard.
An executive running Linux, but I know what you're thinking.
I'm an executive.
I mean, why am I even running Linux?
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
That's great though.
Thanks Leo.
That's such a great clip.
When I saw that, I thought, wow, okay, I got to watch that show.
So I don't know how we got on that topic, but if you're a Linux, well, you probably
listen to this show.
You're probably a Linux user and you want a television show to watch, Mr. Robot's a
good one.
I'm stocking up on a couple of episodes for the road trip, which I'm going to talk about
a little bit on how I'm going to do some of my things offline while I'm on the road.
I think it'll be an interesting challenge.
Yeah, Xavier, you're welcome.
Thanks for the new habit.
Is anybody in the mumble room watching Mr. Robot?
I watched a few of them, but I haven't kept up to date with it.
I keep watching them in batches and every time I watch it, I'm glad I do, but I don't,
I seem to let it go for a few weeks.
How I do with them.
It's good and it has like a little bit of things that kind of put you off for like a
little bit, but then it pulls you back in with some of the tech stuff and you're like.
It does.
Yeah.
It actually really does.
Like I really, they say some of the people that are consulting with them are actually
completely anonymous.
Like they're, they're people they talk to over like Tor chat or something.
Yeah.
So there you go.
All right.
So I want to get into the topic of how I hope to enjoy some of the benefits of being online
while offline in the trailer, because the realities of the trailer are I'm going to
be really limited on connectivity because a I'm either going to be on, on cellular,
which will probably be at best limited connectivity on I-90.
And there's not, it's not exactly free.
I mean, yes, Ting's giving to me for free, but I, you know, I don't want to abuse it.
And then, and then if I don't have a Ting connection, then, then I'm really going to
need to be self-sufficient.
And so I'm trying to come up with a couple of different open source projects that I can
install.
I'm envisioning, so if you're familiar with how RV trailers work, usually there's a spot
where you eat and there's a table and there's two bench seats and those bench seats open
up and underneath there, there's a perfect spot to set up like a NUC server and maybe
like an external mirrored hard drive or something like that and put it underneath the, the seat,
the bench and build a server there and then install some really nice, and I'm not doing
this this trip, but I'm going to do some of these on a laptop just to sort of test it
on the drive since I have the laptop.
Version 1.0.
Yeah.
Version 1.0 is going to be on a laptop, like a beta.
And I'm thinking what couple, what different open source projects could I glue together
to essentially give me an online like experience while on the road?
And there's a few major ones and that's also going to be a continuing topic in this week's
episode of the Linux action show.
We're going to double down and really, really focus on one really important one and show
you how to set it up.
But first, before we get to that, I want to mention DigitalOcean, which I'm considering
how DigitalOcean could be sort of like an offsite cache for me.
Maybe I have cron jobs on DigitalOcean that go retrieve things and in one spot I pull
it down, maybe I'm on a Wi-Fi connection, something like that.
So DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way for you to spin up your own cloud server.
So if you want to get a Linux server set up, this could be a really great way for you to
spin up something really fast and try it out for two months absolutely for free.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED and you get a $10 credit over DigitalOcean.
You can get started in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans start at only $5 a month.
And for $5 a month you get 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU and a terabyte
of transfer.
And DigitalOcean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam,
London and Germany.
But what I really like about DigitalOcean, well what I really like about DigitalOcean
is that it's all running on Linux, it's all using KVM for the virtualization and they
use SSDs for all of their disk I.O.
So that I really like about it.
And they have tier one data connections.
That's stuff I really like about DigitalOcean but the thing that really makes it all sing
is the interface they set on top of it.
It is a glorious interface that is really intuitive to easy and maybe simple.
But I don't want to make it sound like it's not powerful because it is very powerful.
You can do just about anything you'd want in there.
And the nice thing is if you want to get really pro level, they've got a straightforward API.
So go use that promo code DOUNPLUG, try out a five dollar droplet, two months for absolutely
free.
See what I'm talking about, DigitalOcean is cray and I have a feeling they're going to
play a key role in my offline online world.
Because the DigitalOcean droplet can always be online, while the trailer cannot.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUG and try them out.
Trust me, you can find something, once you just try it for a little bit, it's obvious
what you want.
You will be hooked.
You will be.
That's right.
DigitalOcean.com and a big thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show and
thanks to you guys for using promo code DOUNPLUGED.
All right, so I want to talk about a couple of different projects that Wes and I were
brainstorming that would help somebody live sort of an online life while offline.
Because this is going to be a key thing for me and I thought this is probably a good mental
exercise to go through anyways.
And one of the things I really want to do while on the road is read.
I want to be able to get my reading and catch up on articles and things like this.
Word and Instapaper are kind of like the go-to for this and that's great if you can connect
to your Instapaper queue or your Pocket queue and download them to your device.
But nothing guarantees that when I decide to fire up the device, the app, on my phone
for the first time in two days, nothing guarantees I'm actually going to have a connection.
So I would really like something that would be sort of storing the articles for me in
the trailer, getting them ready to read whenever I want to, when I'm on the local trailer network.
And so that's where Wallabag comes in.
Wallabag is essentially an open source Pocket competitor.
The application is going to suck down the web page for you and store it offline for
reading anytime you want.
We're going to get to other ways you could do this, but this is a very Instapaper Pocket
kind of way.
And Wes, are you familiar with Wallabag?
I've tried it out a little bit on one of their older versions.
It seemed like a great idea.
I don't know how the implementation has improved.
Are you using Pocket right now?
I have been using Pocket.
So you get the idea.
I sure do.
And the same thing here, you can have a JavaScript bookmarklet that will send it to your queue.
They have apps for Android where you can share to Wallabag, and it saves it to your local
server.
It's very handy.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
So that's Wallabag.
I don't know if anybody in the Mumba Room has an experience with it.
You feel free to jump in.
But this is on my try-to-do list.
We've talked about it once before, but it's pretty cool.
And then something else that I've got to really come to terms with is right now I'm a really
big LastPass user.
But if I'm offline for an extended period of time, it might be worth looking into KeePass
and maybe specifically KeePass X, because you were saying maybe I might prefer this
over standard KeePass.
I like it a little more for native Linux implementation.
If you track their Git, they have I think Beta 2 now.
They're using the new KeePass 2.0 format that has a little better, you know, if you have
multiple versions, you can intermingle them.
They won't conflict anymore.
So it's definitely worth a try.
Yeah.
I found it to be extremely stable.
So no mono required seems really nice.
Yes.
And you see, it's in there.
You are.
Yep.
So it's easy for me to get up and going.
You can download the stable release, which works very well.
I've had no problems with.
And then the version 2 Beta, which is cool.
Do you have any idea what the process is to move from LastPass to KeePass?
I do not.
I've actually never used LastPass.
Oh, OK.
KeePass has been meeting all of my needs.
If your issue is to have access when you're not online, LastPass actually has a thing
called Yosemite or something where you download your entire vault and it's locked down on your
stuff so you can use it offline and you can use it like a portable app or you can use
it.
Oh, it's Open Sesame.
So that's what it is.
Open Sesame.
OK.
All right.
I got it.
Yosemite.
I got to look into that.
OK.
Open Sesame for KeePass.
All right.
Now, that seems like that.
So that might be a good solution for this trip.
That's a good one.
Yeah.
I thought there was a way, too.
Imacon in the chat room says, pretty sure you can export your LastPass vault to a format.
KeePass can read.
Oh, that's beautiful.
Oh, and look at that.
Odyssey says, here is your LastPass vault user manual for exporting.
Cool.
Thank you, guys.
So that might be something I'll look into.
Maybe not for this trip, but maybe for a future one.
So Wes, you were trying to convince me.
The other big thing that I want to be able to do, and I can't think of another way to
do this, and I bet Wimpy is going to back you up on this, you know, right now I'm relying
on Dropbox a lot for file sync.
Yes.
And I want to be able to continue to work across all of my machines, which is really
going to be three computers in the trailer, maybe four.
And I want to be able to update files in them and have them all be able to share the files
so that way I can do show prep on the road, and then when I get a connection, have it
sync back up.
And I think you probably can't get around the fact that, I mean, to do that, I've got
to use SyncThing.
You've got to use SyncThing.
I mean, there are some alternatives, but I think SyncThing works really well.
It runs great just on a LAN, or if you have your occasional connectivity to your droplet,
you can mirror things up there as you can.
Yeah.
I don't know, Wimpy.
What do you think?
Do you think this is the time to switch to SyncThing, or can Dropbox do the job?
I think Dropbox can do the job.
Without the cloud piece?
Of course.
Well, you only need one instance of Dropbox, don't you?
You don't need all of your machines running Dropbox.
You could have all of your machines running Dropbox and use LAN syncing, or you just export
your Dropbox folder from one machine over NFS and mount that Dropbox instance on the
other machines.
That's true.
That would be one way to do it, would be to have a...
Because I do want to have access to all of the files on all the machines, because it
could be notes sometimes and things like that, but if I had them all over NFS and then just
had Dropbox running on the NFS server, that could be a way to do it.
As long as you stay in the trailer.
I don't know if you'll be...
Oh, that's true.
You know, if you go work in a coffee shop or you're eating Noah's, you can sync yourself.
I often will be Wi-Fi hunting.
That's a really big component of it.
But if the Dropbox, you know, the local LAN sync works fine, then you'll...
LAN sync seems to only work when it actually has connectivity to the cloud server to get
the master index with Dropbox.
No, it needs LAN sync to do the first initial upload, and then once the first initial upload
of the files is done, the rest goes over the LAN.
This is a challenging one.
I'm not sure what to do here, because it's too big of a transition to make before Saturday.
But the more I think about it, if I want four computers to be able to all work off the same
files and be able to take one of those four to a coffee shop and still have all that work
updated, that's got to probably be syncing.
With maybe...
What's the VPN client?
Oh, Tink?
Yeah, with Tink.
So that way, when I'm at the coffee shop, I'm connected back to the...
Well...
And you can have the droplet with it, too?
That would be how to do it.
Yeah, the droplet, yeah.
Yeah, the droplet could be in the Tink network, too.
Oh, yeah.
No problem.
Oh, man.
You don't...
The Tink bit is optional, though.
Yeah, it's totally optional.
You don't need Tink.
Yeah.
I was thinking...
Keep it simple, Chris.
No, well, here, let me...
I've listened to a couple of your, you know, ideas, and I fear that you're overcomplicating
your connectivity requirements.
That's true.
I'll tell you what I was thinking.
What I was thinking was it'd be nice if the trailer had Wi-Fi connectivity to have it
be able to also be getting the files.
Like, say, I'm working back here at the studio, and the trailer has Wi-Fi connectivity.
It'd be nice if the changes here were already back at the trailer when I got there, if it
has a persistent connection.
And the only way I can really think to do that is to have the...
To either have, like, the trailer, every time it connects, have, like, dynamic DNS, updated
DNS record, or use Tink to just make sure it's always on the same network.
I don't know.
That's not...
Again, that's not all, like...
That's not all right in this first trip, anyways.
That's all...
And there's a lot of permutations that could work there.
I just think it's gonna be...
I think it's going on the project list, though.
I think solving this...
I don't know how I'm gonna solve it, but this particular problem is going on the...
Is on that list.
All right.
GB Infrastructure Initiative.
Right.
The mobile studio needs a good Linux infrastructure.
And then last but not least, this one is probably the one all of you were guessing in the chat
room.
I think I might just archive some websites with wget.
And it turns out, like, the command...
If we have the command in the show notes, it's crazy easy.
There's an option in wget for website archive.
So like, we were thinking maybe we'd use ARIA 2, or, you know, there's a lot of different
methods to pull this particular problem off.
I mean, you could even just send a Lava to Wallabag.
But the nice thing about wget is it can just archive the single website.
So we have the command there.
And if you want to try it out, you can.
I think I will beg you for some reading, like, just grab a few sites, pull it down, and then
read them later.
Yeah.
You've got all your CSS images, everything.
I could VPN to the trailer from Starbucks, Xavier.
That's exactly what I was thinking.
So Mamba Room, did you guys have any other...
So any other suggestions of open source projects that kind of help replicate the online experience
when you're offline with no connectivity?
Chris has got a real bad internet addiction, and he needs help.
This is exactly it.
I need the slight sensation of being on the internet, even if it's just like a Nicorette
gum.
I need...
I need something.
Keep him going on his long journey.
Because when I turn off the MiFi, right now...
So here's what happens right now is I have a couple of different hotspot devices to
connect to, depending on what signal is the strongest that morning.
And then when I turn them on, all of a sudden I get a LAN, and all the devices connect,
and all of a sudden they can all talk to each other and self-discover, and it's amazing.
And then when I want to save bandwidth, I turn off the MiFi device, and my LAN collapses,
and none of the devices have any IP addresses, and nothing can talk to itself.
The Dark Ages.
It's like they're all just individual monsters, just in the dark, bumping into each other.
And then I decide, okay, I want to do something online.
So I turn the MiFi device back on, and the LAN comes back online.
And it feels so quiet.
And it's been cool for about a week and a half or so, or whatever it's been, but today
and last night I'm kind of like, okay, I would really like to have some solid connectivity.
So I'm just curious what other projects you guys might suggest that I could use to kind
of get that experience.
If you wanted an offline search type thing, you could do local search with Yacy.
That's true.
Oh, yeah.
That's a good one.
That's not bad, actually.
When I want to look something up but don't have connectivity...
Now, will Yacy do archiving, because I'll have to be able to read the results offline.
Yeah, it can.
By default, it doesn't.
It just indexes, but you can make it archive, too.
Grab a TP link and get a USB mobile dongle.
So Inagogo, you need to tell me more about that.
If you would email Rover at JupiterBroadcasting.com, because I'm trying to figure out how the NUC...
So the NUC is also going to be my firewall, I assume, and I need to know how that NUC
is going to jump between different cellular connections for the LAN.
Winby, do you have any input on Wi-Fi and things like that in an RV?
Yeah.
So I've got what we would call over here an SUV, which I think is more or less the same
kind of thing.
Okay.
And I've got wireless and Ethernet in mine.
And I used one of these travel routers, you know, so it's battery packed router and wireless
end, and it's got a USB port on it that I plug a 3G, 4G USB dongle into.
So that device, that router uses the 3G, 4G to get an internet connection and provides
the LAN and it has one Ethernet port.
So I can have one hardwired device, not that I ever use it.
So I could plug that into the NUC, for example.
For example.
Yeah.
And that way, when you don't want internet connectivity, but you do want the LAN, you
simply unplug the USB dongle and you retain your LAN, but you've physically removed yourself
from the internet.
Yeah.
That's exactly what I want.
And that's got that, you know, that's got caching DNS and all of that stuff on it and
DHCP.
Ooh.
Okay.
All right.
Do you have a link to that one?
I'll look it up and post it in the IRC in a second.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Ever resourceful mumble room.
You suggested MPD.
That would be one option.
And I was thinking, what was the, anybody remember the alternative to subsonic?
What was that?
Remember how there's a sub rage or something like that?
There was a, there's an alternative subsonic that's come out recently that would also possibly
it's kind of like replaced.
That would basically be replacing Spotify.
Yes.
But other than that, that was kind of where I was starting to kind of, I mean, I have
a couple ideas that I'm saving for last that are huge, but other than that, that's kind
of what I've come up with.
So if you go to linuxactionshow.reddit.com in the subreddit and look for episode one
10 and give me your ideas for open source projects that give you that online experience
while you're offline.
And the thing I love about this is it's not, it's mad Sonic.
Yeah.
That's what it was.
Thank you guys.
Mad Sonic.
I think I love about this idea.
It's not just for those of us that are living on a metered cellular connections, but it's
also great for just that whole bringing things offline again, moving things out of the cloud
and bringing it back on your own land or your own droplet or what or whatever.
Oh, Winby, did you find it?
Very good.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Zoomtel.com.
Oh yeah, that's nice.
I have the 4506AG.
Okay.
I'll put a link to that in the show notes for people that are looking for something
similar out there.
So that is perfect.
So it runs off, I don't know if you have them in the US, but we have what used to be called
cigarette lighters, but they're now just used to power stuff.
Yeah.
That's what I use in the trailer.
Nice.
Yeah.
And it also has a battery pack in it.
That's perfect.
So when it comes off the power, it's charged and it runs for a few hours off its own battery.
So it's the travel one that you have?
Yeah.
I have the 4506AG, the travel router wireless end.
You sold me with the DC power connector, to be honest with you, because I need everything
to run off of DC.
I don't even know if you can make a NUC run off of DC power, but if you can, I need it
to.
So, Staple sells them, perfect.
But what you will need is a USB, a compatible USB dongle, and they've got a detailed list
of what the compatible options are.
And they have the, I bought mine on Amazon and it had the option to buy the car kit.
The car kit.
Yeah.
I'm looking at it right now on Amazon.
Very good.
Yeah.
Let me see what I need.
Jesus.
What?
How can it only be $30?
Yeah.
It's as cheap as.
Holy crap.
That's great.
Yeah.
I think I'm going to put this on the list for something to look into after this trip.
Now you don't have the ability to hook up to like an ethernet connection on the WAN
side, do you?
You can use WAN on the ethernet side.
You can either use it as LAN or WAN.
It's a selectable thing in the UOS.
So when I have the trailer parked here at the studio, I could run ethernet out to the
trailer network?
Yeah.
Oh my gosh.
That is so exciting.
I'm putting that on the list right now.
Man, thank you.
Perfect.
That's exactly what I.
You can plug right into Noah's network.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And then I'll have the NUC sitting behind that.
So that way the LAN's IP address and DNS always stays the same or something.
I mean, I don't know.
That could be.
Yeah.
It does port address translation and UPnP and all that stuff.
So yeah, there you go.
So do you say you have the 4506A or what I'm looking?
Yeah.
4506AG.
AG.
Yeah.
OK.
AG.
Well, geez.
That's great, Wimpy.
Good pick.
So I'll have to make sure I put the right one on my list.
All right.
Anybody else have any other suggestions for replicating online experience?
NUC does need DC input.
So it might be possible to get the NUC to do that.
Very cool.
All right.
Do you have any suggestions when you're listening?
Oh, look at that.
Well, look what Rekai just found.
You can use any.
Oh, that is so awesome.
You do not need a DC to DC converter.
Oh, my gosh.
It's perfect.
So it looks like other people have already had this same thought process.
That's why it's the next unit of computing.
That's right.
Yes.
Yes, yes, yes.
That is so cool.
That is so awesome.
12 volts, 36 watts.
That's amazing.
That means I could run the NUC off of total battery power that's charged by solar panel.
The homeland on the trailer would be run off of the solar panel.
Okay, I'm just going to absorb that for a moment.
I'm going to sit with that for a second.
Now I think I'm going to tell you.
Oh, go ahead, Wimpy.
You had another one?
The 4506?
That's the list of compatible USB adapter.
That's probably good to have, too.
I will also add the link to that in the show notes so that way we all have that because
I'll probably come back to this episode to look for it myself when I'm ready to make
the purchase.
So that's cool.
All right.
So now I have been looking at different ways to do backup for some of our production machines.
And it's not just because I love rolling releases that I want to find a really good
backup.
That might be part of what's niggling at the back of my mind.
So I have been looking at a kind of a slick way to do a real easy snapshot and restore
system that doesn't take a whole bunch of storage space, doesn't require like a blank
dedicated volume, and doesn't require a specialized file system that I'm not completely comfortable
using yet.
And so I'm going to tell you about that.
But first I want to tell you about our friends over at Linux Academy because you can check
them out and maybe take your skill sets up to the next level.
They're sponsors of the Linux Unplugged program.
I want you to go to LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged gets you our special 33% discount.
Now what does Linux Academy have?
Well it's a training ground full of stuff based around Linux and open source.
Self-paced courses, over 1,800 videos, they have scenario based labs so you get real hands
on training with it.
I think it was probably early 2004, 2005, I decided to go into community college to
get training.
Not nearly as efficient as this.
Now like the concept of going in a few nights a week, how do people have time to do that?
I don't know.
I don't know how they do that to be honest with you.
See Linux Academy, not only is it all self-paced and so you can just go at it with your own
time availability, but if you really want to get specific about it, they have time availability
selectors.
So you can go in there and say okay on Monday I have this much time, Tuesday, Wednesday,
Thursday, Friday I have this much time, Saturday I'm taking a break, Sunday I'm taking a break,
right?
Or whatever you want to do.
Or maybe you want to do it only on the weekends.
You tell Linux Academy how much time you have and they automatically generate courseware
that matches your availability including reminders for exams, things like that.
They have seven plus Linux distributions you get to choose from.
They automatically adjust the course where they have them cool nuggets and they've just
recently updated the nuggets too and I'm going to be honest with you guys, these might be
some nuggets that are worth your time.
So these nuggets are like two to 60 minutes, just a deep dive into a specific course.
Aliases and escapes in Bash.
You know you could be saving time with better aliases.
The comma is your friend in Bash.
Command history shortcuts in Bash.
Those are all extremely useful nuggets.
You just go in there right there and get it.
Alternative command line for the email, privacy, web browsing with privacy badger, manipulating
logs with sed, dig for DNS, user key loggers, Linux signals, a short tutorial, that's a
great one.
Check them out.
You can go to linuxacademy.com slash nuggets but start by going to linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged and also if you're interested in doing some training or writing some practice
exams or maybe you want to do some backend work for Linux Academy, they're hiring.
You can email them career at linuxacademy.com.
So go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and if you want to get a gig, career at linuxacademy.com.
Big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Okay.
So Wes, it's called, I think, I'm going to say Datto block driver, D-A-T-T-O Datto.
It's a Datto block driver.
Now here's how they set it up.
Now they recognize, and I like this, they build the case that Linux has some basic tools
for creating snapshots of file systems.
Most use copy on write schemes to allow point in time consistent snapshots.
Currently, both LVM and device mapper on which LVM is built support copy and write snapshotting.
Unfortunately, both have limitations that render them unusable for supporting live server
snapshotting across desperate Linux environments.
For example, LVM snapshotting requires an unused volume in order to track your copy
on write data.
So enter the Datto block driver, Datto BD.
It solves the above problems.
It is an open source Linux kernel module for a point in time live snapshotting.
Datto BD can be loaded onto a running Linux machine without reboot and used to create
an image file representing any block device at the instant the snapshot was taken.
After the first snapshot, Datto B tracks incremental changes to the block device and can therefore
efficiently update existing backups by copying only the blocks that have changed.
With a single command, Datto DB can almost instantly create a point in time snapshot
device representing the snapshot state.
Between snapshots, disk writes are tracked so incremental changes can be quickly and
efficiently applied to an existing image file.
Datto DB is designed to run on any Linux device from small test virtual machines to live production
servers with minimal impact on IO or CPU performance.
Since the driver works at the block layer, it supports the most common file systems including
extended XFS and even ZFS and Butterfess.
Although file systems with their own block device management such as ZFS and Butterfess
cannot be supported.
So Butterfess is not supported.
Kind of a bummer but I guess not necessary since Butterfess has copy on write support
in itself.
All copy on write data is tracked in a file on the source block device itself eliminating
the need to have a spare volume in order to store that snapshot.
So in summary, Datto DB brings functionality of similar to like volume shadow copy on Windows
to a broad range of Linux installs, file systems and kernels.
Are you impressed at all Wes?
I'm very curious.
You know they say efficiently.
I'm interested in what the overhead might be.
It'd be very fun to try this on some running systems and see what happens.
All right so let's put it to the mumble room.
Is anybody in the mumble room?
Now remember Chris is going to be on the road next week and it would be great if we all
met back here for 1.11 with a real good like story.
Is anybody in the mumble room willing to try this out?
You can do it on a virtual machine or an actual machine this week and report back next week
on how it went.
Anybody?
Yeah, I'll give it a go.
Oh I love it.
That was easy.
Yeah.
So I'll have it linked in the show notes.
I'm just really curious you know if it really can easily I don't know like maybe the test
would be update a system and see if it's easy to go back or recover date exactly how it
works.
Could be kind of neat.
Yeah but I've got a machine here that I'm using as my main workstation which I'm about
to upgrade so I don't really mind if it goes horribly wrong so I think what I'll do is
do some backups, do some updates and do some backups and roll back and then I'll do a full
distribution upgrade and try and roll back and see what happens.
Oh I can't wait.
I'm really excited.
This is exciting, yeah.
So Datto block driver, D-A-T-T-O, Datto, oh very neat.
They got me when they said that it makes it super fast to do incremental updates because
that made me think that you know once you get the first one done then it's not really
that much of a tax to fire off a quick homo free to an update or something like that.
And I love the idea that you could just plug it you know add this to a running system.
Yes.
I didn't use a copy on write file system but I'd really love to be able to you know especially
if you're running a rolling release.
And especially if you know you don't really you know you have a system where extended
four is just fine for you, something like that and speaking of extended four did you
guys see that the next kernel update is going to drop extended three support or at least
the explicit driver?
Okay.
Oh is that what it is?
Not the support for it.
Okay.
So it'll still be there if somebody has extended three.
Well it'll load it.
Like a module type.
Yeah exactly.
Extended four now will be the extended three support.
Right.
Yeah because it can read it too.
That's interesting.
So it's not really a big deal at all.
Not really at all.
It's an interesting discussion though.
Even if you didn't have it like who cares?
It is an interesting discussion and if you look at the mailing list yeah and how they
kind of go through and decide like you know the thought process behind it, what's it going
to break, do we really want to run this risk and okay well if we have the backwards compatibility
here and we can module it.
So Corky says that Linus blocked it.
He did.
It looked like at least on the mailing list that then there was further discussion in
the file system development that they are willing to say that the ext4 does not enforce
new features so that you could if you had an ext3 then you use the ext4 driver and wanted
to go back to a kernel just using the ext3 driver it would still work and they were willing
to support that.
That's my understanding.
And I think I read that today or yesterday so it's pretty recent Corky if you maybe missed
it.
But it doesn't really affect anybody that's running ext3.
The other thing that was interesting is that it points out that they're keeping or probably
keeping ext2 just because it's a really good example file system so maybe anyone interested
in Linux kernel development or file system development that's a good one to go study.
It's simple but effective?
Yeah.
Huh.
That is interesting.
And if you wanted to implement a new file system there's a skeleton you can use.
Start with something I suppose.
Yeah.
I mean it has it's pretty it's pretty road proven as I say because I'm thinking about
road trips you know.
It's very important.
Yeah.
So that brings us well at least towards the end of this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
I'm really I'm really actually pretty happy.
We had a really good turnout for what is sort of universally known in like the news business
as the slowest weeks of like this starting you know a couple of weeks ago till now is
like in the US like our Congress goes on vacation like the news people go on vacation Anderson
Cooper goes on vacation.
Yes even Anderson Cooper goes on vacation.
Oh my gosh it's Anderson Cooper everybody.
Megyn Kelly goes on vacation but not the mumble room.
The mumble room still showed up and I was a troopers.
You guys really are.
I hope you will show up next week.
I have no idea what my connection is going to be like but it'll be fun guys.
Yeah I'll also be remote.
I'll be remote with you but if all goes as planned my audio is going to be recorded locally
ham radio will be slapping it all together delivering to Rekai for video production and
hopefully it'll still sound pretty good even though I'm on the road.
That's the goal.
The live show you'll hear me on the remote connection but in the downloaded version I
should sound pretty good.
That is the intention at least.
We'll see how that goes.
You'll find out episode 100 and 11.
Join us on Sunday's episode of the Linux action show.
I'm going to take this topic of enjoying online life while you're offline and I'm going to
zoom into an open source project that needs way more attention.
Wes turned me on to it a few weeks ago and I think a lot of people are going to be talking
about it after we talk about it.
I think there's already some people in the IRC I've seen using it.
Don't spoil it dude but I'm really excited and Noah and I have been using it for a little
bit so that way we can give you our impressions on it after a couple of weeks of marinating.
So it fits in so perfect with our topic today.
So if this at all it was an interest to you and you want to deep dive into something check
out Sunday's episode.
Actually I keep saying Sunday but I think we're recording on Friday that way we can
record while I'm still in town.
So we'll be live on Friday for the Linux action show for release on Sunday for download.
All right well that right there will bring us to the end of this week's episode of Linux
Unplugged.
We should be live next week at our regular time.
Go over to jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone.
If you want to suggest an offline open source project linuxactionshow.reddit.com look for
the 110 feedback thread or you can email us at jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact.
I got a magical drop down right there.
It's incredible.
It's great.
Also don't forget jupitabroadcasting.com slash rover to follow the road trip as it's live
and rover at jupitabroadcasting.com to email anything about the road trip.
All right Wes well I will talk to you from afar next week.
Oh this will be fun.
All right everybody.
Well thanks for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged and we'll see you right
back here next week.
Well look at that.
Wimpy says he knows one of the guys that works at Datto.
Really Wimpy?
That's interesting.
Tell me more about that.
Well I didn't realize until I started looking through the github.
His name's Dan Fury and he did some work in Arch a little while ago and I took on some
packages that he'd been maintaining in the AUR.
He'd been doing some work on Compiz and I just thought hang on a minute that username
looks familiar.
That's great.
He's the guy pushing the source and in the same github account they've got a PDF which
goes into some detail about how this all works.
Very cool.
Nice spot.
It's the basis of a commercial product, dattobackup.com.
Interesting.
So although the code has only landed in github about a month ago this appears to be battle
tested.
It's proven in production.
I heard about it.
I was emailed in.
Somebody said I've been using this for a little bit and I thought okay well that's interesting.
Let's take a look at it.
Datto.com is products built around this solution.
Fascinating.
Look at that.
So yeah that's nice that it has a commercial back and it's battle tested.
JBtitles.com also last chance to vote on the roadshow name.
Right now Last Cribs Roadshow is currently winning with 42% of the votes.
Finding Linux coming up number two.
On titles we have Linux Unhitched and Last Cribs Trip.
I don't know.
Keeping Linux online.
Going offline.
No place like slash home.
Classic.
That's true.
That's not bad.
Feel like we could do something more around the going offline thing.
Yes.
So what do you think?
JBtitles.com.
Last chance to vote.
Anything grabbing you there Wes?
Do you like any of those in particular?
Well let me take a look.
Yeah take a look.
So that's...
Is that Datto?
That was a big NAS they had there?
That's interesting.
I wonder if they sell it to NAS creators.
Yeah.
They've got some cloud to cloud solutions as well.
No place like Tilda.
Keeping Linux online.
I don't know I feel like something offline.
How to download the internet.
That's almost there.
Going offline almost sounds like the show's ending.
I don't know if I like that idea.
Yeah that's weird.
Linux Unhitched is close.
Yeah it's close but not quite it.
Linux Hits the Road is not quite it because that feels like that could be next week's
episode.
Linux Unplugged disconnects.
That could be next week's episode title too though.
Yeah.
Ah this is close.
How about live offline like you're online.
Is that too long?
Is that dumb?
Linux Unplugged unplugs the internet.
Linux Unplugged gets away.
This should not be this hard.
Alright so hold on real quick.
Let's just focus in here.
We can do this.
We can do this you guys.
I have faith.
And the value of this is negative.
Alright well there's no place like slash homes not bad but that could break the internet
too.
Ah let's see.
Offline Online Solutions Offline Action Show.
Offline Online Solutions kind of funny.
I kind of feel like Linux 11 oh that's a little weird never mind.
I kind of feel like maybe there's no place like slash homes the way to go.
Is that awful?
Oh my gosh we've got to find something.
We've got to find something.
What about no place like 127.0.0.1?
Yeah that's not bad either.
Offline Online Solutions Offline Action Show Linux hits the road why is this so hard?
I think that we should all make those businesses fail.
Dang it RMS you're just distracting me.
I'm bringing down the economy.
Icarus says off the grid that's pretty good.
Linux off the grid what is it?
What is it?
He said off the grid in the RV but I just tweaked that and make it something like I
don't know.
Linux living offline.
Return of the local host I like that Shadow 7.
Return of the local host isn't bad.
Off great Linux.
So I think Linux living offline or what was the other one?
Most recent one?
Yeah the one you just said.
Return of the local host.
So I think that's the return of a local host or living Linux offline.
Which one do you guys like better?
Wouldn't it be better if return of the local host was used when you returned and were a
local host?
Okay if we can remember.
Living Linux offline.
Is that good?
What do you think of that?
You don't like it?
It's okay.
Okay.
I'm not vetoing.
Yeah but you're not jazzed up.
Goes off the grid.
Huh?
Linux goes off the grid.
Old man voice there.
Huh?
What'd you say?
What was it?
Come on.
Come again.
Uh gosh dang it you guys.
Gosh dang it.
This is too tough.
All right here we go.
This is it.
This is it right here.
No take backs.
Okay.
I kind of think return of the local host just because we probably won't remember to use
it when I get back.
Well probably.
We are the worst so.
There's a thing I could just say.
I think I could remember.
I don't know.
I feel like I feel like if we if we hold on to it I think no I feel like we should use
it.
Google calendar.
No it's not.
It's not that much worth it.
I think we are so we need a good title right now.
I say we can come up with another.
I have faith.
Faith of the heart.
I've got faith that we can make it up again.
Surviving offline is a real goof.
Is real good.
Oh.
That was real good.
Okay.
Amazing.
The one little difference that makes.
Thanks the anime.
All right.
Thanks you guys.
We're done here.