This is BSD Unplugged, episode 34, for April 1st, 2014.
Welcome to BSD Unplugged, your weekly BSD talk show that's too busy getting actual
work done to care about what your silly display server.
My name is Alan.
Get it out of here.
What?
How did that guy get in there?
No, that's not what we're doing this week.
We're just having a little fun.
Hello, everybody.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged.
Hey there, Matt.
Hey, how's it going?
Oh, good.
You know, it is April Fools, and so this week we're going to stick it to a little bit of
an April Fool.
We're not talking about BSD, but we had to let those guys give us a little bit of a poke,
right?
How great was Alan's intro, too?
Check it out.
Welcome to BSD Unplugged, your weekly BSD talk show that's too busy getting actual work
done to care about what your silly display server.
My name is Alan.
I like his enunciation on actual work.
Yeah, you can feel a little bit of BSD superiority in it.
Well so this week, we're going to talk about somebody that I have actually quite a bit
of respect for.
Not only did I watch him when I was a youngster on ZDTV and then later TechTV, but also I
really respect him for what he's done for the podcast industry, quote, unquote.
But this last week, this Saturday, Mr. Leo Laporte went on his national radio show and
trashed Linux kind of in a bad way, and he kind of trashed it for things that actually
aren't strengths.
So I want to play those clips, and we'll use that as an opportunity to kind of do a little
FUD debunking here on Linux Unplugged and discuss maybe what he got wrong and maybe
what he could have said instead, because not everything he said was incorrect.
So we're going to discuss that, and then if we have a little bit of time left over, I
want to discuss Ubuntu dropping the Amazon lenses from the default search.
So not in 14.04 necessarily, but starting in Unity 8, whenever that lands on whatever
device you run it on, when you search in the dash, it won't by default query Amazon for
shopping results anymore.
Now technically, I don't think it's going to really query any scope particularly, but
it's kind of a reversal on a position that Canonical's had for a while.
So if we have time, we're going to discuss that as well.
But first, Matt, a little bit of business we have to take care of.
We generated a ton of feedback last week when we were talking about the whole mirror Wayland
situation again, and I got a lot of heat.
People really stuck it to me.
I guess they didn't like it when I went on to rant.
So I want to cover a couple of those things because we got a couple of different, I mean,
seriously, it was probably 55, 60, you know, individual emails that address this topic,
and I'm not going to put all of them in the show.
Wow.
Yeah.
Oh my.
We would need a feedback show for our feedback show if I covered all that feedback.
So what we're going to do is, I couldn't even read all of them, although I will try to make
sure to get to all of them before the next Linux action show, but what I want to start
with is the few that I did put aside that I thought represented maybe a larger majority
of the opinions.
And our first one came in from Merlin and he says, uh, dear Chris, sorry, Matt, but
this one's for Chris.
Your breathless rage against me really blew me away, but not in a good sense.
I share your views on a lot of the topics, but not on this one.
Even if I would share your views, I would never express them so bluntly.
I am very grateful that Popey was able to react so civil and polite to your rage.
I admire that you try to show both sides of the story, but this time you failed.
Again, thanks to Popey for showing the other side of this subject.
You're very passionate about making the Linux desktop breakthrough to the masses.
You see, we're very close to that point and you are very afraid that something will go
wrong.
You direct that fear to Ubuntu, while Ubuntu is the one, is one of the reasons we've even
gotten this far.
Why don't you have more faith in Ubuntu?
How long until you see that all the dumb choices Ubuntu makes are the kind of choices Linux
needs?
I support Ubuntu completely.
I am part of the community and Ubuntu did not alienate me at all.
In fact, the opposite is true.
Ubuntu is the reason I am excited about Linux.
Ubuntu is the reason I'll stick with Linux.
The direction Ubuntu is taking is the direction I want Linux to go.
With kind regards, Merlin.
That's definitely...
So to recap, I think what I'm mainly concerned about is Mirror and Wayland creating such
technical differences at the core level of Linux that you'll have application inconsistencies
across desktops and distros.
Even if it was maybe Gnome on an Ubuntu machine after you installed Wayland or something like
that.
It could still be an Ubuntu base.
Maybe it's Mint and they go with Wayland and they have Cinnamon running on top of Wayland.
Well, so when you're on Mint with Cinnamon and Wayland, maybe Thunderbird doesn't pop
up a new mail notification.
And when you're on Unity on Ubuntu, you get the new mail notification or vice versa.
That kind of inconsistency, I argued, is once again Linux not bringing its A game to now
a fight that is being dominated by Google and Apple who not only bring their A game
but bring it to a level we have never seen it before in the technology industry.
Now Merlin feels that perhaps, you know, I think what I'm kind of extracting from Merlin's
email is the other distributions, the community as a whole, is never going to have a chance
to succeed entirely on its own.
And you need a standout player to rise above the noise, choose the best, build where there
isn't something that does the job, and maybe perhaps at the cost of the others, but at
least one true Linux will stand alone and have users.
The problem is, if you have a long perspective on Linux, and Matt I know you totally are
in this camp with me, when you have the long tail perspective on Linux, you know that things
come and go in Linux.
There are some things that have been around for a while, but no distro is necessarily
forever, even if it's maybe still around, it's not maybe as popular as it once was.
So to bet everything on one particular commercial entity is sort of negating the benefits of
having this open community where things are being developed freely amongst multiple stakeholders,
yes I said stakeholders, that is actually, even though it's this weird organic evolutionary
growth that doesn't have awesome ass keynotes where we just are blowing everybody away with
a great demo, it means that there is this general purpose computing platform that is
being worked on by thousands of people with thousands of different reasons to work on
it, and together in harmony they're moving something incredible forward that's like nothing
else.
And when you silo all of that up into one distribution, you're kind of negating some
of those benefits.
I mean that distribution is able to build on top of the shoulders of those giants, but
it's also sending a ton of risk to one particular silo.
What do you think of that?
I think that's absolutely correct, especially when you consider the fact that the biggest
strength that Linux on the desktop has is the fact that there's so many different options
out there.
Historically there have been very popular Ubuntu-like distributions that honestly a
few people thought were really it, and things change, priorities go a different direction.
Anything could happen, you never know, and to put all your chips in that one basket is
incredibly short-sighted, so I agree with you there.
Now coming back to his original point, I would stand with him in the idea that I'm going
to wait and see.
I don't necessarily think it's going to completely go to hell until I actually see it do that.
I think that we're maybe jumping the gun just a little bit.
I have faith in Ubuntu to at least give them enough – I'm going to give them a chance
before I completely just write them off as screwing everything up, but at the same time
I would agree with you in that putting all your balls in that basket, into one distribution's
basket, is incredibly short-sighted, very, very short-sighted.
I think Colby is going to kind of fall in line here.
He says, hey there Chris and Matt.
I just finished listening to episode 33 and I just thought I'd share my perspective on
this issue.
I agree completely with your assertion that the amateur hour handling of small details
on Linux desktop is a problem for future adoption.
However, while you admonish Ubuntu for making the situation worse, I actually praise them
for getting things done.
I envision the following scenario happening, and I like this Matt, so put on your theater
of the mind cap.
Okay.
He says, imagine a table full of Linux celebrities sitting around arguing about the future of
the Linux desktop.
You've got Gnome and KDE guys, they're going back and forth as they've been for
a decade now, and you've got the GPL 2 and the GPL 3 guys, they're bantering back
and forth.
Of course the video driver binary blob camp versus the open kernel driver camp and the
dev versus RPM advocates are there.
The rolling versus non-rolling release crew and the system D versus upstart folks are
also there, all sitting around yelling at each other about how someone is killing the
desktop Linux.
At some point, Canonical pushes back their chair, stands up and says, look, you guys
can sit here and argue about almost literally everything in the Linux ecosystem if you want.
Have that at Haas.
While you do that, we're going to go over here and start building software in a platform
that actual people use.
All of you guys do good work.
But it's a shame that instead of actually accomplishing something tangible, you spend
all this time and energy spinning your wheels in all of these academic discussions.
If you need us, we'll be over there, in the corner, making and selling actual products.
Later, AC goes on to say, I too have given up on the greater Linux community and have
adopted a more practical philosophy.
The first group that actually releases something that works and is widely supported is the
so-called winner.
I'll let others have all the academic discussions about the future of Linux desktop because
quite honestly, the only practical Linux desktop that has any chance of doing anything in the
marketplace is to build an ecosystem and build an ecosystem is Ubuntu.
The broad Linux ecosystem is far too fragmented to ever have a chance.
It's always been that way and it doesn't look to change anytime soon.
Keep up the good work.
At this point, Jupiter Broadcasting has a monopoly on my media consumption.
Thanks, Colby.
Nice.
You know, and it kind of makes me think back to what Alan was saying there during the intro.
It really kind of brings it home.
You know, it's an interesting point because I think that the unification is going to have
to happen at some level.
That's not to say other distributions can't perhaps come to a group think mentality to
maybe where we get two or three that are able to come on board, maybe picking up with what
Ubuntu is doing.
Who knows?
But you know, I've come to the realization that I think Ubuntu, like anybody, is going
to make – as a group, they're going to make mistakes.
But historically, again, looking long term, they have been pretty darn good about rectifying
them.
I don't know for my taste, but they do rectify those mistakes.
Yeah.
And I think, too, that there's a valid point in actually going off and making something,
but I think you have to underscore that the foundation in which they will be making that
something under is QT, the Linux kernel, GNU Utils, the GPL itself, the community that
Linux itself brings, the advocacy that that group brings.
It is not something created out of whole cloth.
It is something that is created because all of these groups that he said are arguing with
themselves all the time actually do produce things.
But the thing is, it is certainly seeing the entire – the trees amongst the whole forest
where when you are standing in the forest, all you just see is a whole bunch of trees
right in front of you having fights.
You know, stick fights.
You know, right?
Tree stick fights.
Well, and also, not only that, but I think like QT and all these sort of things, they're
fighting.
You see these groups fighting amongst themselves, and a lot of times, the things they're fighting
over may not make sense to the casual user.
It's lots of low-level stuff that most people are rolling their eyes thinking, God, who
cares?
In reality, we should care.
We've established this.
But again, visually, it doesn't seem that appealing.
It doesn't actually execute the solution right now.
I think people see Ubuntu as coming along and saying, look, we're going to take a
step back.
We'll do our thing.
We'll watch them do theirs, and at the end of the day, we'll probably use what's
best for us.
I think the point I was trying to make last week is that I think that's absolutely reasonable
and a rational position to take.
The flip side is I wanted to argue, and I hope I successfully argue, that there are
some components within the Linux user land that our resources are so scarce, and the
expertise required to work those things is so high that it can literally be maybe a handful
of people, five, six, a dozen people in the entire industry that know how to do this work.
When you split our focus at that level, that split reaches from the beginning of that expertise
to create a display server and reaches all the way up to developers making desktop applications.
What it essentially creates is Ubuntu, or let's just call it, it essentially creates
a mirror versus Wayland.
The competition for Ubuntu becomes the other Linux distributions in some sense.
Not completely, not outright, because there's still an all rising tide boats thing happening.
But there is a sense where developers will have to make the choice.
What is the primary platform I want to target?
That kind of competition internally is not something that I am fully convinced Linux
can sustain.
However, and we're going to have an email that makes a point about this, I think in
the long run it's not going to be as bad as it sounds right now, but honestly the only
way to make it not as bad as we're all fearing it's going to be is to hammer these things
out and figure them out and talk about them and figure out what the actual problems are
in these scenarios.
So that's part of this process in the open source community too is it's a little bit
of airing our dirty laundry, but at the same time it's also coming to a group consensus
on this stuff.
Well, I would have one closing thought on it and I would put it this way.
Whatever side of the argument someone may fall onto, the one thing that drives me nuts
is when they take the argument to a low level point.
If it's like, let's say you're pro QT, okay, that's fine.
Show me why not using it breaks blank.
Show me, identify exactly where it messes with my life and I think the arguments become
much stronger.
The problem I see within the Linux community is that the arguments are so low level, so
bottom of the barrel complicated that the average folks don't care because they can't
identify.
You say, look, you go GTK and this is what's going to break like you brought up with the
alerts and things like that as far as not being able to unify that when APIs and whatnot,
all this other stuff, I think you start nailing those individual actionable things to where
you can point to and say, that's going to break because of this, that's going to break
because of that.
Then people like me start to care.
Right.
Then you bring it home a little bit.
And you know what?
It's the truth for anything that's extremely complicated and abstract.
You could make the same argument about NSA spying and anything that's really complex
like that.
That's why no one's complaining about it.
That's why no one complains about it because it's still low level.
It may be complicated arguments, absolutely, but at the end of the day, if you don't, it's
not dumbing it down.
You got to identify how it affects things in your life you care about.
That's so important.
You just have to connect it to something that people care about.
Right.
And I'll tell you about something I care about and that is our first sponsor this week.
That is Ting.
Go over to linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com is where you want to get started.
And let me tell you, Ting is a mobile service that has zero BS, no contracts, no early termination
fee and you only pay for what you use.
Have you ever been on your phone and you've gotten a text message from your carrier and
it's like, hey dog, you're about to go over your data limit, I just wanted to let you
know.
What?
Data limit?
How about you just let me pay for what I actually want to use?
Oh, guess what?
That's exactly how Ting works and it's never been a better time to be a Ting customer because
guess what?
Today, April 1st, Ting has announced the new Ting Android skin.
That's right.
Nice.
Yeah, you see, you can go get yourself a custom Ting carrier skin.
Now by the way, a little bit of a heads up, if your Ting device isn't running Ice Cream
Sandwich, don't worry, the installer will automatically migrate your device running
Jelly Bean or Kit Kat over to ICS so you can get that nice downgrade, super smooth.
And if your phone can't run Ice Cream Sandwich, you've got 30 days to buy a new phone if you
want support from Ting, real nice.
And another, they have some developers testing stuff for Jelly Bean, so they might have a
Jelly Bean version out in Q1 2015, so you can check that out.
Here's what you get.
You get the Ting splash screen, you get the Ting music store, you get the Ting app store,
you get the Ting wallpaper store so you can buy wallpapers, you get the Ting ring tone
store and of course the Ting remote and the Ting splash screen.
Now Ting music, you get the latest hits from artists of yesterday because Ting, as Ting
grows in popularity, they'll be able to sign up more artists, but right now, nobody's using
it so it's all cover bands.
You can download hundreds of songs with it and they're just $2 per song, Ting apps, who
needs Google Play?
Ting has gotten rid of the Google Play.
I've listened to you guys.
The Ting app store offers a huge selection of almost 1,000 apps.
You can choose from favorites like MySpace or AOL Instant Messenger, ICQ, MSN Live, Bing
and a few hundred other ones, yeah.
And guess what?
I can get MySpace right on.
You don't have to worry about a credit card map.
They're just going to build this stuff directly to your Ting bill.
Yeah.
Oh, nice.
Yeah, and if you want to get a Ting retinal wallpaper, they're called Ting retinals, you
can get stunning high-resolution wallpapers to completely customize your home screen.
And by the way, more than 20% of songs available in the Ting music store, so that's almost
a dozen, are also available as a ringtone.
So you got to pay like 50%.
I want to get Bieber on that, bad boy.
This is one of the best April Fools ever.
And you know what?
The reason why I love this, because it shows you, Ting knows how much all this crap is
just crap.
They totally see it.
So I thought this is, and apparently a few people in the comments thought this was serious,
and so Ting actually had to make a disclaimer.
Ting is so awesome.
Wow, wow.
So here, listen, this is why I've been a Ting customer, because not only is the Sprint Network
rolling out LTE like crazy these days, they have the Sprint Vision plan, which is awesome.
They've got tri-band LTE, LTE now in 400 markets.
If you haven't checked out the service coverage lately, go over to linux.ting.com and check
out their coverage map.
If you haven't tried out their savings calculator, plug that in there.
Go put your minutes, go put your megabytes and your messages in your bill total and see
how much you'll save over two years with Ting.
And every device you buy from Ting, you own it outright.
That's your device, and Ting's only going to charge you for what you use.
I love it.
So go to linux.ting.com, see what I've been talking about, and a big thank you to Ting
for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Happy April Fools, Ting.
That's pretty good.
That was great.
So John wrote in, he's got a different angle on this display server thing, so this is one
of two last emails we're going to read here.
He says, hey Chris and Matt, I want to keep this short.
The display server problem is proof that Ubuntu is changing from a Linux distro or a Linux
variant to a completely standalone OS.
That's really what Canonical wants, wouldn't you think?
Ubuntu will become closer to what Android is, an OS created from whole cloth.
They have a competitive advantage over basically every other Linux distro, and though it might
be cheap, Mirror is one way of ensuring that people don't switch to something else.
So in my opinion, your frustrations are completely valid.
I think the free software world is justified in feeling taken advantage of.
They piggybacked on all of the goodies that Linux provides, and they took a huge chunk
of the user base, and now they're creating something completely different.
This isn't going to cause problems.
Oh, he says this is going to cause problems.
But because of Ubuntu's market share, I think there will come a time that other Linux issues
will be forced to work with Canonical just to stay competitive.
Then again, maybe they crash and burn and Mirror sucks, so they will switch back to Wayland.
Cheers, John.
Cheers.
That's a nice ending, just kind of, eh, whatever.
You know, or it could be completely opposite of what I'm talking about.
Always nice to, you know, you learn from my monkey suit debacle, you know, always keep
your butt covered.
Yeah.
The monkey suit lesson, it lives on in our audience.
All right, our last email on this topic, it comes in from Netlore, aka James.
He says, hey Chris and Matt, I completely failed to get on mumble for the last Linux
unplug.
You know, we do loop in our virtual lug, and if you join us live on Tuesdays at 2pm Pacific,
you can take part in that.
He says, because there's a point I wanted to bring up.
If there are things which have no, okay, so this is a point he would have made if he's
going to be on the mumble server.
If there are, and this is the point I wanted to kind of hold on to make so he could make
it, because I think this is a great point.
If there are things which have no abstraction, which the applications have to hit the display
server directly to solve, those things need to be abstracted.
This in itself will make Linux more mature and quote-unquote better, and it will solve
the issues with all of the machines still running X11, including BSD and Solaris, etc.
For a long time, as we all are going to be solving these mainland mirror issues now.
Not to mention the possibility down the road of X12.
Also, what happens if we go through this again?
Really?
I mean, Linux has always been into playing the long game, and Wayland will be old and
obsolete at some point, or maybe just need to be updated, so making sure we abstract
all of those functions benefits us now and benefits the maintenance of all display servers
over time and makes it easier to migrate to something new in the future when things change
again.
Finally, it's my understanding that part of the reason MIR was created was a failure
of the Wayland developers to work with Canonical to help them use Wayland.
Surely, if the project alienates one of its largest potential users by refusing to work
with them, then surely complaining when they decide that they need to do their own thing
is somewhat disingenuous.
Overall, I agree that having this fragmentation will hurt Linux a little in the short term,
but it's already happened.
It's not going to go away, and if we embrace it, we can make Linux stronger, so why not
do that?
I think that's really the best option.
And I know that for the people that actually have to do that work, aka the developers out
there who are raising heck right now, to them they're like, well yeah, screw you guys, of
course you say that.
But in reality, that's kind of what has to happen.
Well, that's kind of what has always happened, I think, at some level.
I don't know.
I mean, I think history will end up dictating how all this works out, but I think right
now we just need to focus on the positive, let go of the negative, and let's just see
where it all falls down.
Boombayah, Matt.
Let's see.
Let's make Linux stronger where we can, and we'll keep following it.
You know, as things develop and we start to get a sense of what direction things are going,
we'll talk about it.
You know, and we'll just keep an open dialogue as we go.
There you go.
Oh my goodness.
Uh oh.
We have a little breaking news right here on April 1st, 2014, Matt.
I don't know if you caught the headline.
It's taking the internet by storm, but Jupiter Broadcasting announces they have bought Linux
Gamecast weekly.
The new media tycoon, Chris Fisher, owner of Jupiter Broadcasting and Hairstyle Extraordinaire,
has reportedly bought Linux Gamecast for approximately $14.4 billion.
Holy cow.
You've been holding out.
Or two Bitcoins.
Yeah.
Yeah, I bought it in Bitcoins.
So, oh, rootgamer.com had a little fun today, poking a little fun at us.
I thought that was a great one, those Linux Gamecast guys.
They just got done reviewing the goat simulator.
Have you seen that?
Oh, I was playing it all day today.
As a matter of fact, I tagged then.
Dude, it's like if you've ever wanted to take Barnyard Action and bundle it with Postal,
that's this game.
Now, is this the game where the goat gets a jet pack?
Does he get a jet pack?
Oh, dude, it's like, it's literally, the goal of the game is, I mean, obviously to level
up and stuff, but basically, I just run around running people over, bowling them over.
It's literally like Postal minus the shovel.
And you're a goat the whole time, right?
Yeah.
That's crazy.
It's fun.
Oh, my God.
Did you get this on Steam?
No, no, no, no.
I found the executable.
Oh, okay.
I got you.
I got your gist, Matt.
I got your gist.
Yeah, my gist.
But yeah, anyway, yeah.
You can do it on Steam, though.
The same principle applies.
You're still going to have to do it with Wine, though.
I want to get to our topic du jour today, but first I want to thank DigitalOcean for
sponsoring this episode of Linux Unplugged.
What is DigitalOcean?
Man, you need to find out.
First of all, we're going to get you two months for free if you use the promo code UnpluggedApril.
Let me tell you why you want to try out DigitalOcean.
It's simple cloud hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive way and easy way to spin
up a cloud server.
Users can create a server in 55 seconds.
I think our audience record right now is 47 seconds.
If you beat 47 seconds, let me know.
And pricing plans, or maybe it was 44, and pricing plans start at only $5 per month,
and this is key.
For $5 a month, think about, think about what that, $5, that's less than, that was less
than the KFC I got today on my way back from the studio, okay?
$5 a month gets you 512 megabytes of RAM, 20 gigabytes of SSD, a CPU, and a terabyte
of transfer.
That's a quantifiable cost.
You know, it's a fixed cost every single month for a tier one cloud server that you have
root access over running on Linux on top of KVM and with any distribution you want with
a full-fledged snapshotting and droplet system that lets you deploy applications with one
click, make a backup before you make any big changes, and DigitalOcean has data center
locations in New York, San Francisco, Amsterdam, and Singapore.
Their interface is simple.
Their control panel is intuitive, and power users can replicate that control panel with
their straightforward API.
So you want to do a little automation, boom, they got a great API for it, it's beautiful,
and listeners of Linux Unplugged can get that $10 credit by using the new promo code, brand
new Unplugged April.
Brand new promo code for this month, Unplugged April gets you a $10 credit, lets you kick
the tires.
Let me tell you, I have every single thing I have set up on my DigitalOcean machine,
my droplet, has made that $5 worth it.
And right now, my latest favorite is, we got Rekai working for us now, he's like, Chris,
I know you like the Quasl client, I'm like, yeah, I like Smuxy a little bit more, he's
like, well, did you know that Quasl has a server component, I'm like, yeah, I've heard
of that.
He's like, but have you used it?
No, I've never tried it.
IRC is amazing, IRC is the legit social network, so now on my DigitalOcean droplet, I have
a Quasl connector server that keeps me logged in to several IRC servers and several rooms
related to Jupyter broadcasting at all times.
I now can connect from a tablet, from my Nexus 5, from my desktop, from my laptop, from multiple
desktops, they all connect back to this one connector, they all share the same login session,
all the same nick, I can see all of my messages, I can see anything that transpires since I
connected last time.
It has made communicating with our team so much more efficient, I would gladly pay more
than $5 a month for this right now.
And it's one of the many things I have running on my $5 a month DigitalOcean droplet.
Not only that, but DigitalOcean is built on top of those SSDs with tier one bandwidth,
backed by Linux's KVM technology, it completely rocks.
So go over to DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code UnpluggedApril to go get yourself
your own cloud server powered by SSD drives, UnpluggedApril.
And a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring Linux Unplugged, DigitalOcean.com UnpluggedApril.
Such a great deal, so powerful, I mean, because you can pretty much do anything you want on
it, it's awesome.
It is, it is, it is so much better than so many other ways you could go, like having
to port forward to a virtual machine, screw that.
Just go get an actual cloud server, and man, DigitalOcean is blowing up these days.
They're hiring right now, they just got a great round of investments, they've refined
their control panel to a whole new level, it's awesome.
And you know, I heard about them from Michael Dominick from our corner radio program because
they're awesome for developers too.
And some of the largest sites on the web are running on DigitalOcean, so it's pretty cool.
All right, so I want to get into an area that's difficult, because I have a lot of respect
for Leo Laporte and the TWiT network, and I respect what he's done to legitimize the
podcasting medium, and I enjoyed watching the screensavers back before it was, you know,
really mainstream.
Like I had a satellite dish, and I was watching ZDTV before they would call it TechTV.
In fact, I even saw him a little bit on MSNBC when he was playing, I think it was called
Dash or something, like he was a virtual character, I've been following him for years.
And one of the things that we played on Sunday's live stream was his old interview with Linus
Torvalds, right?
So he's given Linux a lot of mentions in the past, and in fact, even on his nationally
syndicated radio show that was airing this last Saturday, he did have some sort of fate
praise to give Linux.
Most of the web runs on servers powered by Linux.
That's how reliable it is.
Android phones are based on Linux.
All Android phones run Linux.
That's the operating system.
You're probably using Linux all the time, maybe you don't even know it.
So you can get a free version of Linux, there are many as I mentioned, Ubuntu is a good
one, ubuntu.com.
You can download it and install it on your XP machine, you wipe, in fact, I would wipe
out all of XP and just install it.
There doesn't run Windows software very well, it does in fact run it, but not very well.
But that's okay because it has an entire office suite available for it for free, LibreOffice.
It has all the software, you know, Photoshop clone called the GIMP.
There's all the software you'd want is free and available on the Linux platform.
So I wanted to play that because you can see he's giving some praise to Linux there.
So the question was, and this is something that's been coming up on his radio show a
lot is, look at XP, it goes kaput this week.
What should I do, Leo?
I'm thinking I don't have the money to buy a new machine.
Should I keep XP?
Should I try this Linux thing?
That was the caller's question.
And this is where things went off the rails.
There's all the software you'd want is free and available on the Linux platform.
All of that's well and good.
Here's the downside, and this is why I asked Sy, do you know about computers and he does.
Linux has never really been for real average people.
It's really designed by and used by computer enthusiasts.
And so you'll use Linux for a while and then you'll run up against something that's just
weird.
And unlike Windows, there's so few people that use it as a desktop operating system.
It's sometimes hard to figure out how to get around these roadblocks.
Things don't work right.
I'll give you an example.
Now, before he goes on, I mean, I'm kind of like, okay, I can kind of see where he's going.
I don't necessarily 100% agree at this point, but you know, to be absolutely fair, it is
challenging for most average users.
Okay.
So this point I'm giving the benefit of the doubt.
All right.
I was running a version of Ubuntu and I decided to use the open source version of Google's
Chrome browsers called Chromium on it.
And then I updated Ubuntu, got the newest version and Chromium stopped working.
Just wouldn't, it wouldn't run.
Now I was able to figure out what was wrong and it was a library.
This is the kind of thing that happens with Linux.
So I actually watched this happen and if folks who watch a lot of our live shows might remember
I talked about this.
I watched Leo got the Dell XPS Sputnik developer laptop.
You remember this thing?
I remember this.
Yes.
Yeah.
Very clearly.
So I watched Leo on the live stream on like a Saturday or Sunday.
I can't remember.
He was, I think it was after a Linux action show actually.
He was unboxing it.
He pulls the Sputnik out and he boots it up and he's reading his chat room.
And before he's even logged into the computer for the first time, and Dell has this little
first time setup wizard, the chat room says, Leo, you've got to remove Unity.
Uninstall Unity, app get removed, purge Ubuntu desktop, app get installed, Zubuntu desktop.
And Leo just kind of blindly did it.
And he created a lot of problems for himself when he did that immediately.
He never even gave Unity a shot, he just immediately uninstalled it.
And then, and then the chat room said, Leo, Leo, that is Ubuntu 12.04 on there.
You should upgrade to Ubuntu 13.10, Leo.
Do app dash get dist upgrade.
And then he did an app dash get dist upgrade, and this is where he started running into
problems.
Now he never mentions that.
And again, this is a use, that kind of use case scenario would never happen to an average
user.
There was a library that Chromium needed.
Remember I was talking about those DLLs, Linux has them too.
There was a library that Chromium needed that the people who make Ubuntu decided didn't
really need to be included in the new version.
So they took it off.
So I had to find the library, download a copy of it, put it on my operating system, and
then Chromium worked.
It's not the kind of thing you want to do, and it's certainly not the kind of thing people
who are used to running Windows XP want to do.
So my general recommendation is that Ubuntu is a good choice if you're an enthusiast and
you like messing around with them, tinkering around with computers, you enjoy that.
It's great for kids.
It's a great way for kids to learn how Linux and Unix based operating systems work.
These are the fundamental workhorse operating systems of the whole internet.
So that's a great thing to learn.
But for the average person who just wants to surf a little bit, open the email once
in a while, might not be the best choice.
And of course that's patently false because that's exactly who should be using Ubuntu
or any kind of Linux is somebody who wants to browse the web a little bit, read email
a little bit, do social networking.
And his recommendation is stick with XP, stick with XP.
And the problem is, is what he is parroting right there is, think of it this way.
Think of a Mac user or maybe a Windows switcher that goes out and buys a MacBook Pro, okay?
And I'm trying to put this in parlance that Leo would understand because he's a Mac user.
And he goes out there and he buys a MacBook Pro, he brings it back home, and he immediately
formats the drive and puts Windows 8 on it.
And then he notices, hey, you know what?
This is great.
I've got good performance, but my fans are running crazy.
Like the thermal cooling on this thing really sucks.
MacBooks don't have good thermal cooling at all.
It keeps overheating and shutting down.
MacBooks are awful.
Apple makes bad products.
When in reality, he's using the product differently than how it was intended because Apple doesn't
make drivers available for Windows for the thermal management system.
So it's down to emergency cooling.
And if you look at that, if you look at what he's done here, he took a product, the Dell
Sputnik, he immediately uninstalls with a purge command the Unity desktop, installs
Zubuntu, then installs Chromium and does a desktop grading, complains about a library
problem.
Now he never says that on air, but then he takes that experience and he says, can't use
it.
Not good for regular users if you just want to browse the web, if you just want to go
out there and do a little Amazon shopping.
In fact, he goes on even further.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
And you know who you are.
If you're somebody who doesn't want to mess with computers.
I just want to surf the...
I just want to buy something on Amazon, send an email to my kids, look at some websites.
If that's you, you don't want to mess with it, probably not a good choice.
I think the Chromebooks are a good choice.
I think a new version of Windows would be fine, Windows 8, if you can afford it.
A Macintosh, if you've got even more money, that's a good choice.
It's only for the enthusiasts that I'd recommend Ubuntu.
And the thing that is, and I was going to let this go because we played the clip on
the last live stream and I was like, all right, bygones be bygones, water under the bridge.
Sure it was on a national radio show, sure maybe potentially a million people just heard
you kind of crap on Linux for your own mistake.
What really bugged me, and maybe this is just a little too inside baseball, what really
bugged me is then Twit took the clip of Leo Laporte dumping on Linux and made it the highlighted
clip for that show.
So every super long show that Twit does, they release what's called a Twit bit, where they
put a couple of minutes from that show on their YouTube channel for Twit, and it's sort
of like, here's the best moment of that show.
And this is what we want you to watch to get you hooked to watch the whole two hour long
show.
And this is the moment, this moment where Leo has taken a big stinky dump on Linux is
the moment that they chose to highlight from his three hour radio show, because this was
so important.
And this is the part that made me angry, because the absolute arrogance and irresponsibility
of somebody who has a national radio show, who didn't properly do the work, who screwed
it up themselves but is still too arrogant to admit that, then dumps on the platform
as a whole because they screwed it up on their own, applying a use case scenario that no
average user would ever do, and then tarnishing the platform as a whole.
That is irresponsible.
And I, that's what upsets me about it.
You know, it's kind of funny too, because those people who he mentioned are, who only
browse the web occasionally and shop on Amazon, are the people who are going to be getting
the viruses and needed protection when he provides, so.
Right.
That's the, that's the thing is that's what has me kind of irked about it is he's actually
in a sense like he's completely got it wrong.
Like maybe if that caller was a PC gamer enthusiast or a video editor, like that would be the
person to give that speech to.
But somebody who literally wants to read email and shop on Amazon, guess what?
Go get Ubuntu.
It's got Amazon built in.
You know what I'm saying?
Like that's the perfect operating system for somebody who wants to shop on Amazon.
It is, it is false on its face and this kind of old school FUD still, I think, is the predominant
narrative that Linux has to combat this.
This is not what he says is not true.
Am I, am I wrong?
I mean, I think what he's trying to say is that it's not good for the average user.
If you're stupid enough to blindly just delete things that you have no idea what they do,
but you can say that about any operating system to have like exactly anything.
Like why is it that easy to break the library dependency?
Like it's in the frequency package manager, you won't, it'll be like, you can't delete
that.
It's required by this.
They have an integration package for the Unity desktop for Chromium.
Of course, if you uninstall all of Unity, which Chromium has this nice little integration
feature involved, kind of like Gnome has the extensions in the browser.
It's kind of nice and integrated there.
Of course, it's going to kind of blow something up or at least kind of cause us unusual problem.
But it seems like there's an undeclared dependency there that should have resolved it.
The issue is that he's there.
He removed the integration features taking random commands from people in a chat room
or whatever and running them on his machine.
Right.
But if like, for example, he was, he removed something that Ubuntu created and then he
tried to install something that Ubuntu made like from the Ubuntu repo that dependent on
the thing he removed.
So why did the repo just do it?
He did a purge.
He purged it.
I don't know what that means.
That means force it.
Regardless.
Like just rip it out of there.
Get it.
I don't care if there's errors.
If you want to kick back a warning to me, screw you.
Pull it out anyways.
Right.
Wait, wait, wait.
Sorry.
Purge means something completely different.
All right.
Hold on.
Okay.
Let's break down.
So Ik, I wanted to get this before we go too far.
I know purge means fully remove.
I know.
So Ik, you and I both have experimented with moving our parents over to Linux.
What has your experience been with their sort of that average user scenario?
Has this been a problem?
Well, the biggest thing about that clip that I wanted to mention is that my parents heard
the clip and immediately they said he was full of crap and my parents are not techy.
That's nice.
And wait.
Now, as far as the use case scenario for somebody who just uses Linux to browse the web and
do email and write stuff, I would say that that use case would be my wife.
My wife would be the exact use case that Leah was describing.
She has no problem.
Of course, I'm there to help her if something goes weird but at the same time, it's not
that huge of a deal to just say app.get install Chromium and everything is all better.
My parents, my dad especially, was just like, that is completely false.
He's making assumptions based on stuff he didn't even do any research on.
And he picked up on that right away.
I think this is true.
Now, let's discuss Alan's point.
Alan's point is, you know, maybe the system should be smarter than that.
If you give it the force flag, then that's your fault.
Well, he didn't give it a force.
He gave it a purge flag.
But what if the chat room had said rm-rf/.
He could still be blaming Linux for that.
I think at the end of the day, he essentially engaged in a scenario in which no user who
got a machine pre-loaded with Ubuntu would ever go through.
Unless they knew what they wanted ahead of time.
Well, do you know what he actually hit?
It was a dependency in which the Ubuntu package did not declare.
If the Ubuntu package did declare, it would have been resolved.
And it does now.
That has also been fixed.
It was a bug.
You're right.
It didn't declare dependency.
Poppy?
Damn it.
Poppy ruined everything.
Yeah.
And like Matt pointed out, I mean, hell, even Kim Commando, though, has been better spoken
in this area on this topic.
And I wonder if Leo is just maybe falling subject to just a pervasive narrative that
has just kind of bubbled up through the tech industry for years.
Because I don't think this is even a justified issue.
Yes, there was a bug in declaring that dependency.
But again, this isn't something somebody would have gone through normally.
So what can we do to sort of, and I have a theory, but...
The big question is how often does doing the regular updates that you should be doing actually
break something?
Very rarely.
Yeah, very rarely.
Very, very rarely.
Especially lately.
I guess it depends on someone's definition of very rarely.
It depends on if you rip out your desktop before you try to do an upgrade.
Yeah.
I also run SID.
Running SID even is fine.
And I've been running SID for a long time.
It's a little dangerous, but that's even, it's almost not exactly experimental.
But if it's going to be a problem, it's going to be a problem in SID.
And SID is pretty good.
I love it.
I have a question.
All right.
Well, hold on.
I want to give Daredevil, one second, Daredevil, go ahead before we get too far.
Go ahead and make your point.
I would actually just give a suggestion to distributions, if anyone is listening, install
at least bugs by default and you will solve the most problems you have because the users
see, oh, there's a bug.
I'm not going to update right now.
And that's it.
In FreeBSD, we have something like that called the updating file that explains the problems
you will run into while trying to do an upgrade.
And go ahead, Crash.
I think part, like this is, this is a problem that the community has though, is that like
this guy's made this thing and what the actual issue was, whether it was an Ubuntu issue
or a Chromium issue, whatever, is sort of missing the point slightly.
Because the real issue here is that hundreds of thousands of millions of people watch his
show and get the wrong impression.
And that's, and that's the thing.
It reminds me of the, Chris, you probably remember that guy many years ago who did that
thing about, is Linux good for servers?
And he installed CentOS and then tried to install Attitude on it and it's exactly the
same as that, where the guy has, and then he makes this blog post and everybody reads
the blog post and they assume because he's speaking, you know, he's a trusted person
that they trust his opinion, they assume that he's correct.
And this is, this is the real thing that we need to be fighting whether or not the actual
issue was with Ubuntu or Attitude or whatever, that's, I mean, those are the little paper
cuts that we need to fix as well.
But the real issue is that there's a perception, like he says, that it's not for average users
when Ubuntu is perfect for average users who probably wouldn't even try to install Chromium,
they would just use Firefox because it's there.
Right.
And I, go ahead Riley.
It's kind of funny too, because I remember watching a while back he did a show that was
only like repurposing old hardware to use Linux and they did Puppy Linux on it.
Oh, cool.
And they just got the flash drive and they put the ISO on it and they use the unit boot
and they put Puppy Linux on there.
First, you're fine when you need them.
Yeah, I mean, he's given good lip service to Linux in the past, but I feel like he's
never given it a good, I don't know.
That actually might be why.
He should know better though, he should know better is the thing.
That might be why, because if you look at Puppy, Puppy is awesome, it is great for what
it's designed for to get as much as you can out of the hardware, but it is not designed
to be completely user-friendly, it is not for average users.
People using XD should not be using Ubuntu because their hardware is that old, but Unity
is not.
Well, no, the latest versions of Unity are much more light.
Go ahead, let's give Daredevil a chance to go.
To be fair, most users don't even uninstall things.
If you actually do any maintenance, they don't even uninstall, they just keep installing.
So as long as it works.
Right.
Yeah.
And so, Puppy, I wanted to give, because Puppy, did you try to pop up with something that
we haven't?
Well, so I can see his point.
He made a bunch of points that are fairly valid, that it has been for geeks in the past.
And it's still for a lot, i3, and you could argue, KDE, very much for geeks, right?
I think GNOME is a geek.
I think, and I embrace that too at the same time, like I'm glad there's an OS for me.
But the flip side is, I wouldn't say KDE is only for geeks, no, not only for geeks,
indeed.
No, no, no, I mean.
Windows to make the switch easier.
Oh, I don't mean to make, I don't make KDE to sound like it's only for geeks.
I mean to say, like, it's an operating, it is a desktop environment that appeals to geeks
for a lot of reasons.
Oh, yeah.
The two things that struck me as problems here is one, we shouldn't let users break
their desktop in quite that bad a way by typing a couple of commands, by removing, yeah, but
then you're making the Mac, then you're, then it's a Mac.
No, no, there's certain situations that we should not let happen.
Like, you know, removing Ubuntu desktop, we try and that we try not to let you do that.
But unfortunately, people do that.
And for years, people have removed Ubuntu desktop for whatever reason, maybe they wanted
to rip out Unity or rip out some bits and they remove Ubuntu desktop and the upgrade
tool that they when they come to do an upgrade later on from one release to another, the
upgrade tool depends on that being there.
And what happens is you end up upgrading and not not installing packages that should be
there and would be there if you had Ubuntu desktop there in the first place.
The number of systems that I've seen broken that have been fixed by simply reinstalling
that package and pulling in all its dependencies and then magically everything's fixed.
So the problem that he had was following instructions from clueless numpties on IRC who felt that
they were experts in this realm when in fact, they've typed that once and then probably
bitched six months later when their own upgrade failed, which was their own fault and nobody
else's.
Right.
And unfortunately, that IRC room is always full of fresh fools who are trying it for
the first time.
Riley, you wanted to make a disclaimer?
Um, yeah.
Like, Poppy, here's the thought on that, like, why don't y'all put this like whenever you
want to add that upgrade, why don't y'all put a disclaimer in it like warning this can
break your system or something like that?
We do.
But we don't, we don't recommend this upgrade as a way to go from one release to another.
We've got a graphical upgrade tool that tries to do a whole bunch of sanity checks.
It's called Update Manager, and it's got a button that you press to upgrade from one
release to the next.
And it's got a whole lot of sanity checks.
It does things like disable PPAs and check for the existence of certain packages and
it tries to figure out that kind of stuff.
If you work around it, we've got to let you work around it.
Otherwise, we're giving you a walled garden like an iPad and one big button in the middle.
Yeah, I think people like even like Dave right now, he's I think you guys are missing like
Ubuntu desktop isn't unity.
It's like and maybe this is what people get wrong.
It's like a lot of the bits that make it Ubuntu.
And so that's why when you pull that and that's what he did.
I mean, and I go back to there's no I just I again, it's not a real scenario use case
scenario.
Maybe you should have an Ubuntu should have a feature where when you try to remove it
it says Leo, is that you?
What do you think should match it Ubuntu or distros like it?
Maybe make it a lot harder for the user to break it like that.
Well, that's what the first two things that come to mind on this one, these are the two
important things to keep in mind on this is first and foremost, anybody that's been in
technology as long as Leo is concerned, taking advice from an IRC chat room should be slapped
at that level.
If it's a new operating system, you're not that experienced with don't take advice from
a chat room.
Just don't.
If you want to take advice from the chat room, that's fine, but then verify it.
Make sure it actually matches the second piece of information is as far as the warnings are
concerned.
Ubuntu warnings are excellent, but I think that they're a little soft.
You're talking about people as a whole, especially as a community, tend to be pretty boneheaded
and unless you make it in big blinking red text, they're going to ignore it.
So maybe spice it up a little bit because it is really soft.
I've seen the warnings.
They're not really that compelling.
We talked about this on TechSnap.
There was a study, a university data, about the language used in the warnings and saying
this file could be dangerous isn't helpful because it doesn't tell you why it could be
dangerous and so on.
So saying this upgrade could break your computer and they're like, well, yeah, okay, whatever,
whereas it says doing this may cause Chromium not to work.
Maybe something more clear like this is how it actually affects you.
It was like two or three months ago in TechSnap.
There's an actual paper from a university about updating these warnings specifically
they were talking about the ones your browser gives so that people clicking through the
warnings and then getting spyware and then being like, why did I get spyware?
Because you said I accept responsibility and will take this file that my computer tried
to warn me but it did it in such a way that I ignored it.
In general, this is a little bit overblown.
This is a little bit over-exaggerated.
Yes, it did cause a big problem but this is a package problem that could have been like
it was a tiny problem.
It would never usually come up under normal circumstances.
Well, Sarah Devlin, wouldn't you argue that maybe the package manager has a role and perhaps
we get good information before we install, but what about information before we uninstall?
Yes, because I mean, if you were uninstalling the desktop environment, you should say like,
all right, you're not going to be able to then have a graphical interface and maybe
a little link or description of what actually that means.
So when you're removing Unity, you know what that means and what that will impact.
But at the same time, this is also the problem with not having properly curated documentation,
right?
Yeah.
He's taking advice from the chat room because in general with Linux, the chat room is the
best place to get advice.
But if the chat room is an official chat room and not some random Twitch chat room, there
are other people there who... if he'd gone into Hashibantu, there is no way anyone would
have told him to sudo apt-get remove Unity and force him to...
I'm going to sit in that channel and tell that to everyone now.
You got to understand though that like Leo, that's his IRC room.
He trusts those guys.
You know, he's got regulars in there that he looks at, you know, just like me.
I like my chat room.
I got people I take advice from and things like that.
So I think what it is is he went into that situation not knowing what to do and people
that he knows who's given him good advice before told him what to do and he did it.
And then he based his judgment on what happened as a result of that.
But maybe moving away from Leo, because like we said, it's a bigger problem overall.
I wonder if this isn't exactly why what's happening with Ubuntu and Convergence has
to happen because we have to almost just come at this from a whole new fresh perspective
where we say, yeah, you want to use this because then you can have the operating system on
one device.
And yeah, it's Linux, but it's this Ubuntu version where they've kind of made this whole
new interface and it works on all your systems.
Like I wonder if we need a reboot of it all together and that's perhaps why Google doesn't
even say it's not a Linux Chromebook, right?
It's Chrome OS.
It's a Chrome OS Chromebook.
And I think it's that same exact philosophy there.
Interesting point.
I think at the end of the day, a full screen that pops up says you have to you actually
have to type out the word.
I am an idiot if you install this thing, because literally you're not only acknowledging the
fact you are, in fact, an idiot, but you're also acknowledging the fact that you are going
to be doing something potentially stupid.
I say that solves all the problems.
That's just me.
Think about all these controversies around.
Think about all the controversy around Mir and how different that makes Ubuntu and how
I think, I don't know.
Who knows?
But I would be, if I was a betting man, I would bet in the next year or two, the conversation
around Ubuntu and the desktop is going to switch from all this heat about SystemD and
all that and Mir to, God, all these apps feel like big blown up mobile apps on my desktop
and we're going to go through a period where those get refined for both types of environments
and I didn't get tons of crap for that for a while.
But I think all of these controversies will build toward this overall narrative that Ubuntu
is different than Linux and so if you've ever had a problem with Linux, well, there's this
Ubuntu one where they went off and they polished off some of these rough edges and they have
this convergent system where you can get a phone and a desktop and a TV thing and it's
kind of neat and if you've ever had a problem with Linux where you have this weird software
problem, well, Ubuntu takes care of all that because they have a software app store just
like the iOS does and only it works on your desktop too.
It's really cool because you just buy the app once.
Like I could see this, almost all of these controversies are almost contributing to an
end result narrative that almost helps establish the differentiating brand that Ubuntu needs
to sort of break away from all this noise and these old assumptions that old guys like
Leo are making and I'm not saying it's necessarily a good thing, but I almost wonder if at the
end of all of this, all the stuff we're talking about today eventually adds to this perception
that sort of gives Linux a push and gives Ubuntu a push.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, I think so.
I think so.
I, you know, there's aspects of it that have me concerned, but I think the latter point
of, you know, the old way of thinking, the old way of doing things, old, you know, legacy
way of doing things isn't always better.
Just because we've been doing it all along doesn't make it right.
So I think I'm down with that facet of it.
And this also goes back a little bit to that old horse that I love to kick about more responsible
journalism in the sense.
I think, you know, Leo perhaps owes it to his national audience to actually get a Linux
machine for a little while and try it as the vendor intends.
Like I would love, for example, for Leo to get contacted by System76 and give him a whole
inclusive like here's a laptop, well actually, you know, something like that.
I don't know if maybe if he could just try it over with Adele, he already has the machine,
but if it was some sort of here's the whole product, use the product as it's supposed
to be like, here Leo, like somebody sit down with him.
Like if there was somebody who could go to Twit and sit down with Leo and be like, this
is this, this is that, and not, not, you know, because the problem is I don't want to repeat
the same scenario that just happened again and have it reaffirmed.
There's only one rule you need to ask him to follow and it's not a vast list of commands
and tutorials.
Just don't copy and paste dumb commands pasted by idiots on the internet.
It's really simple.
I know, but I see, here's what I want is I want, I want, I don't, this is now something
he'll just continue to perpetuate and I think a lot of people do it and I just, I'm trying
to figure out a way we as a community could maybe evangelize like there are, maybe there's
people in our audience that are Twit fans and Linux unplugged fans that could go to
the Twit studios at some point because they have an open studio and maybe they could take
their laptop there and they could show it to Leo how it's supposed to work.
Like maybe one of the ways we could address, like seriously address some of these problems
is by just getting a little boots on the ground here and using the spread of our audience
to say, Hey, if you ever, ever have an opportunity to give somebody a guided tour, do it.
And it like, I don't know, I think this, this is the problem that he had.
Yeah.
Okay.
We can talk about why it happened and the bugs and the stupid commands people ran, but
it's a symptom of his mentality that, you know, gung-ho going in and trying this thing
out.
I don't think that fixing that one guy, despite his large listenership and viewership, I don't
think that fixing that is going to necessarily undo what he's already said.
It'd have to be a lot of people.
I know he's just, he's just an example of a problem that affects, it's a much larger
problem.
I think he's well aware of how the system should work, you know, he knows exactly what
should happen.
It's a problem is he has a, he has an immediate perceptive bias of the system when he sees
it.
It's this immediate assumption he has going in, whereas this, I think he just, I think
he just had a very valid point that the point he was making and he was, he was using a rather
contrived example, but the point he was trying to make was sometimes you get weird error
messages or odd situations that are difficult to fix.
And that is true.
It's probably more true for Linux because people don't know it that way.
I go back to bias.
The entire, the entire reason Leo Laporte, and I'm not even BSing here, the entire reason
Leo Laporte has a national radio show is because Windows users constantly have problems and
he can stack a phone bank of Windows users having issues.
So it is a problem that affects every single operating system.
So it is, it is a bias to say it only applies to Linux.
If you, if you, if you F around with your registry on Windows, if you go download C
cleaner and wipe that registry one too many times, you're going to have all kinds of weird
software problems and all kinds of DLLs that won't start.
This is, it's not you in a ripping out Ubuntu desktop is equivalent to taking a hatchet
to the Windows registry.
And it is, it, you, you cannot say that it's something that is unique to Linux or something
is unique to Windows.
And so that's why I say there is a little bit of a bias at play here.
That's not even a little bit.
But the nice thing about Linux is those, the issues that he had, if he just stopped, they
could have been fixed and very easily fixed with a couple of app get commands.
Probably we could have like got him back on track, whereas taking a hatchet to the registry
is actually quite a hard thing to, to, you know, back out of, but, but all of these,
all of these systems, Windows, Linux, and Mac, they all require experts on hand to help
you when you get into a tricky situation.
I don't, I don't think Linux requires more experts or it just requires experts with different
knowledge.
That's all.
Yeah, exactly.
And, and I don't know, and I wonder if why maybe if we, if there is some sort of new
magical product category, maybe the perceptions and the, and the biases would be put aside
and they would start a new, they would, you know, maybe he wouldn't feel like he should
just gung ho and go in like a cowboy.
Maybe he'd feel like this is something new that I need to understand and spend a little
time with.
And that's a road trip to Petaluma.
Yeah, I know.
We should, you know, we should do as a live Linux action show from twit, like while they're
doing twit and like, that would be funny.
Well, so here's the thing with Leo that most people don't understand.
And I only know of, because I know people that used to work with him.
So let me, let me put this to your point blank at the end of the day, Leo doesn't like to
be wrong.
And so when something goes wrong, you know, I, you know, that's my, that's my impression.
I know.
Nobody does.
So I am going to get so much hate mail from our audience for saying anything bad about
Leo.
And I was a nice guy.
I don't want to make this approach.
And the reason, the reason, the reason why we are doing this is a quite literally it's
available in audio B it was on a national radio show in the United States that also
streamed on the internet and listened by thousands of people and then downloaded by about another,
you know, a hundred thousand people.
And see, it was made to it spotlight special and I, that, that just pulled my irk chain.
This isn't necessarily about Leo.
Leo is representing a common bias that is out there that many people that may be a lot
of people even in our audience have.
So I am not trying, I'm not trying to flame Leo, but he, exactly.
He knows better.
And what he really owes, if you're going to, if you're in the position, if you're in the
position of acting as a radio personality on a nationally syndicated radio show, giving
technology advice, I would argue it is perhaps your responsibility to actually have experience
with some of these things before you give such a definitive answer on the topic.
The issue is probably like is, is kind of, uh, goes back to a, every tech person has
the same kind of opinion where they don't want to, if someone asks me a question, they
just don't want to say, I don't know.
They could just, they could say, I don't know, and someone move on and get help.
But we want to say, we want to be helpful even if what we say is not helpful.
Right.
You got to have an answer, especially when you're on the radio.
Yeah.
Just, it's the difference is when I'm wrong, it's a friend of mine having, having a problem
that I have to figure out how to fix it versus millions of people he is never going to talk
to.
However, I would just like to say, I mean, the only, I know Popey made a good point,
you know, like changing Leo's mind in the big picture really is just a drop in the ocean,
but I actually think it's a drop we could make happen.
So if somebody is in the California area and wants to go up there with a, like a, like
a ultra pro or something like that, or if somebody has a, a nice, uh, you know, a ThinkPad
running a Ubuntu or Linux like that, go show it to him.
Like, uh, go up there Sunday, uh, go after the tech guy show.
So show up about 2 PM and you'll have an hour between 2 PM and 3 PM where he's just screwing
off sitting at the twit table and you can sit down and you can talk to him and you can
show him how to actually use it and maybe you can change his mind.
And maybe next time he's at, well, there you go.
And the next time, and the next time he's, the next time he's on a nationally syndicated
radio show asked, what should I do when I replace XP?
Maybe he'll have a slightly different answer.
And maybe if you're even comfortable explaining to him what the problem was and, and kind
of where he went wrong, that might help and make it equivalent to, you know, taking a
hack to the registry, make you, he'll understand that.
And I think if we can at least change one voice on the radio, especially at a time like
this, when literally I guarantee it next weekend, it's the weekend after XP support ends, he's
going to get calls asked what I should, what should I do with my old XP machine?
This is a change we could actually make, but I would say a more productive approach is
to just reach out to Kim commando quite honestly, because I think they're about as equal.
They're equally relevant in my mind personally.
They're both nice people.
I have no problem with them personally, but I, I, I there's things that there's, there's
so much stuff behind the scenes that makes me livid.
It's like, Oh, Leo, this Leo, that Leo's a nice guy, but he's not, he's not the second
coming.
He makes mistakes just like any one of us might and you know, yeah, he's human, but
at the end of the day, let's, you know, I don't, I think it's cool to show him and stuff,
but I think honestly going out and to someone that's actually going to be more receptive,
I don't think he's going to be as receptive as people think he's going to be.
I really don't.
Yeah.
Maybe not.
Maybe instead of sending someone there, like if someone goes there to teach him how to
use it or show him how we could take it to somebody would do that, but bring their parents
with them and say, here's an actual average user.
See what happens.
There you go.
Yeah.
That would be interesting.
All right.
Okay.
Well, so the final thing, or there is one thing that we have to worry about is that
Leo's been lulled into a false sense of security by Steve Gibson because he said he was okay
to run for certain power users who apparently quote unquote know what they're doing.
This is also something I do take a bit of an issue with essentially they're saying XP
is fine.
In fact, you don't even have to have the latest service pack of XP or even the last update
since that latest service pack, all you have to do is don't run as a user.
Well, I can tell you as somebody who has had hundreds and hundreds, literally hundreds
and hundreds of users that I was support for and almost the vast majority, at least the
vast majority of them, I would say almost 90% of them were all running as regular users
on XP had incredible amounts of problems.
Yes, it's running as a regular user is still a good idea.
You know, it helps you.
It keeps like that drive by malware problem.
Like it helps like IE stuff tamps that down, but everyone clean nailed it.
Leo needs a co-host.
That would be awesome.
I say Stallman problem solved.
The problem is recommending XP, like literally recommending XP over Linux is a little, I
think, I think it's a little almost dangerous.
Oh, it's beyond dangerous.
Yeah.
So anyway, that's why I'm so angry about it just because it's like, it's so irresponsible.
It's one thing if you don't know better, but come on.
But what Gibson said doesn't make sense either because if the power users, even if they're
a windows power user, they're, they are fully aware that they should not be running XP.
Yeah, exactly.
I mean, yeah, this is, see, this is, but okay, but okay, let's put this in perspective here.
This is the level of bias that we're up against that the option is actually for them in their
minds it is a better option to continue using XP for somebody who wants to use Amazon and
check email.
It is a better option for them to use XP than use Linux.
That is the amount of bias that is out there and that to me seems like a Berlin wall level
of bias.
True.
You know, XP could be secure if you remove all drives, all USB ports and totally disconnected
from the internet.
I mean, it's the most secure operating system in the world.
There you go.
Just run it from Ram.
Never restart.
Exactly.
See.
Yeah.
All right.
All right, guys, I got to go see the electricians at the studio and I, gosh, I hope this didn't
come across necessarily as bashing one person.
Well, and direct your bashing to me because I'm the one bashing and he's the one sticking
up for me.
So throw it my way because I'll defend it.
So I think we'll have to bump it to the big show.
I think we'll, we can take more, we'll take more on the topic in the post show, but the
topic we'll have to bump to the big show is Ubuntu makes the Amazon product results opt
in.
Love to know your thoughts on this one, guys.
So leave us some feedback either in our main subreddit thread where we always post these
shows or you can go over to jupiterbroadcasting.com clicking that contact link and choose Linux
unplugged from the dropdown.
What do you think about the changes coming to the Ubuntu scopes?
Do you care?
Are you glad?
Is it about time?
Is it a huge reversal?
It is outrageous.
I'd love to know your thoughts.
Just send them in to us.
Don't forget you can join us live on Tuesdays, 2 p.m. Pacific over to jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar and line us on Thursday, 7 p.m. on jblive.tv.
Go to the calendar to get that in your local time.
Matt, I'll see you on Sunday.
Download Sabi and load it on your machine and get an opinion, okay?
Okay.
All right, everyone.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Join us on Sunday for the big show.
We'll be reviewing Sabi and Linux and then if everything works out as planned next Tuesday
on Linux Unplugged.
All right, everyone.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.