how's it feeling being home you got right back to work yeah you got some photos of me doing some
drywall projects with my brother he's uh he does some renovation-y kind of work and uh you know
it's nice having a clone around to help you every now and then so i certainly yeah i got back into
it i gotta say though you know how there are some activities that you may be really good at
and yet you don't necessarily enjoy that much yeah it turns out i'm pretty darn good at like
drywall finishing but after about three days of doing it i'm like yeah it seems really tedious
work can only listen to so many podcasts or so much music you know yeah and it's repetitive
yeah that's it repetitive is the word so it was good it was a good project though we spent maybe
six days doing it and it's all done it looks amazing now it was kind of one of these i don't
know if you could tell from that photo i sent you but it was one of these like attics converted into
living space so most of the ceiling is like all vaulted i guess you call it and exposed sort of
collar ties and stuff so it's really really cool space in the end and there's a chimney going right
through it you know with some masonry work and stuff so it looked pretty cool i bet but you're
gonna regret admitting that on air because you know alex is gonna want you to do that to his space
now it's true he uh he did have a little bit of that kind of work he wanted to build a new wall
in his office and uh it took me a few days but i convinced him to do a little maybe maybe hesitate
for now and think about doing it later i'm just saying he's got that great attic space it just
needs a little bit of finish work on it could be a great recording studio that's true it's so nice
up there there's a little structural work to do there too so maybe i can convince him that way
not to do it but yeah it is a nice space now what he needs to do instead is do a recording shed in
the backyard he's got that beautiful backyard put a little recording shed out there well that's nice
for him he's got a bunch of options i think i think if he did that it would feel like your little
dream of having a little studio tucked in the woods because he's got all that those trees and
stuff in that backyard it's really nice i could see it one day you know myself having a little
piece of the land on there you know i take dupes up there i parker and maybe i maybe i get like one
of them shipping containers or something you know and i deck it out with sound insulation and
proofings and maybe a split ac unit and a bunch of silent computers i just go crazy just go crazy
some solar panels on top generates its own power sounds like good content i think we should get to
it i'm thinking right like we could say the jb studio is powered by the sun that'd be pretty rad
hey we know some people that are experts in the uh the solars you know you know the other advantage
yeah the panels would kind of act as like shade you've been thinking about this for a while i'm
just saying it's an advantage that's not often talked about with solar is that it's it shades
your sort of attic space a little bit and that makes a big difference in the end get a little
airflow up there to help cool it down you get a little shade so and then plus you had a split ac
unit i think that would i think that would work just fine if you had enough solar power and
battery i'm thinking a solar shed right so on this piece of property i have a solar shed
it is basically a big shed with some panels on the roof pointed towards the you know the
the sun as much as i can and then inside is essentially a battery bank and a large inverter
so i can pull dupes up and plug her in and then as things got you know more built out maybe if i
had a well and a septic over time i'd add a washer and dryer in there so we could park dupes somewhere
and have a big large residential washer and dryer so we could just do a bunch of chores and clean and
do laundry and have the battery power to recharge our batteries plus dupes would have her own solar
so i mean it'd be great chris where do the racks of pies go you can have them i mean they'd probably
be in the recording uh crate i don't know what we'd call it but yeah the recording crate which
i'm already taking to uh you know because i think i'd do reaper on a pie right then i'd have like
the remote host pie i don't have a mumble pie really do you think they can handle it i mean
maybe maybe in a year or two they'll be like super pies but i don't know doesn't jeff geerling have a
uh system for racking up pies and putting them in like a regular direct probably yeah probably
yeah you could see it i mean you've you know you may be like the cm4 the cm5 you could just have a
wall panel of oh man imagine just a wall panel with with modules mounted and and they're just
doing different studio tasks on on one wall mount minimum clean wires running into it because you
just need usb interfaces oh all netbooting so they're all running off centralized storage
which would be solid state woo all running off ethernet poe if i could maybe get little hats
or whatever you know carrier boards that do poe i'm just saying imagine if the only connection
they had was the ethernet so we were doing audio over ethernet as well and and poe so you got you
got a cluster ish they'd all be separate machines but basically a cluster of compute modules that
have carrier boards that support poe and that's all that's going to them and it's all dc oh my
goodness i'm just telling you man can dream i'll tell you what that's great i'll start thinking
about it now so that way after i spend loads of money trying to get jupes fixed up i can
i can interrupt there one day and plop around that piece of property and then begin building
my base around her podcast compound it's office hours with chris hello everyone welcome into my
office at least twice a month i open the door and say i come on in other than that it's closed all
the time but it's open right now we're live noon pacific 3 p.m eastern on a tuesday over jblive.tv
chattin with our mumble room and our matrix room brent and i were just trading different
stories back and forth hello brent lee how are you doing you're back home now hello i'm good yeah
i'm back home and the stories we tell each other chris there are many we should like do a podcast
with them or something like that oh that's a good idea we gotta figure out how to do that you know
where we always get great stories brent meetups on the way to the meetups i think that's really
what you mean that was my like hey brent you could plug the fact that we're gonna have a
meeting segment like real smooth clearly yeah you're good you're good it turns out that alex
has been scheming a little bit to uh have a meetup in london now this is not london ontario for all
you people in my neck of the woods this is like london london the real one uh he's gonna be headed
there august 6th and he has a meetup and uh you know i i checked out the page earlier this morning
and there are already 40 people who say they're going to be attending i did see a wimpy's name
on there i didn't get to browse everybody but um i really want to go now i know and i i just not
long ago said yes to something in the first week of august here at home and i don't know if i could
go anyways but now i like to think that's what i get for committing ahead of time to something
you know like i'm like oh dang it yeah you know how i have a whole thing about that you know you
gotta choose wisely are you gonna try it turns out alex also booked me ahead of time and uh he would
like me to uh dog sit for him during that time so i think he's made it so i can't go so i don't know
what's going on are you really yeah are you are you telling me are you telling me are you are you
gonna fly to north carolina to raleigh north carolina to dog sit i think also they're hoping
to see me in that time but um yeah it turns out archie is uh pretty amazing but they're gonna be
leaving yeah but he's got the drum the fancy drum kit and he's got all the machines and stuff i could
play with and break so uh 3d printing maybe it's true it's true we'll see we'll see i just remember
you're gonna be on camera you know how that goes checking in on you i know i got duct tape it's fine
i hope this happens meetup.com stupid broadcasting if you're in the london area and uh maybe you
could go i mean 40 people it's probably gonna happen now i don't think there's any going back
so yeah i don't know if they have any pubs big enough for 40 people uh that might be a problem
so we'll see what happens we got big website updates today big website energy before we get
there just a couple of podcast news items i wanted to cover here in the office just keeping an eye on
things i thought this was pretty funny because dynamically inserted ads are a hot topic in
podcasting right now this is one of the biggest trends sweeping podcasting that we are not
participating in but just about everybody else is especially the pod the spotify platform and
they had a bit of a technical faux pas this week they started putting booze ads on all different
kinds of podcasts as banner ads and whatnot in fact some you could even click to buy the booze
i think it was wild turkey but the automated system ended up putting ads on podcasts about
sobriety and alcoholism even ones where you could click and buy immediately there were also
a bunch of fake sex worker podcasts submitted to the podcast index that spotify just auto accepted
and started placing booze ads on oh my goodness just like i don't know like and of course spotify
a spokesperson said on saturday they made a technical error that caused the ads featuring
wild turkey brand incorrectly be placed on a number of podcasts sure spotify you know they
fix it right but the damage is done imagine imagine you were listening to a podcast about
something for something for alcoholics that are trying not to drink right and it's about that
topic and you see an ad for wild turkey on there that's like the worst of the worst don't you think
most people would blame the podcaster they wouldn't think it was spotify that placed it there
they think the podcaster no no of course of course i wonder if that's how they they learned
of it you know they got some feedback into the podcast the podcast was like wait a second
and i think that's really what happens when you start taking humans away from this whole process
right um you start getting just things that humans would never do to each other which is unfortunate
which is a rampant problem on the youtube platform and there is a just a really kind of gross thing
happening where a couple of the biggest tracking or sponsor uh number coalition collating uh
businesses i don't have a better term for them they're middlemen that basically track podcast
downloads and then sell ads to advertisers at scale pod track is one of them libson is in this
business as well several others are and they're always kind of putting information out there
that's harmful to podcasts i never quite get it usually they're like it's like information to
lower the podcast ad rates or or now it's essentially a research paper they've posted that
says that uh podcasters who post their podcast to youtube see a much better engagement and the pod
track white paper says that they did an analysis of audio and video podcasts that post to youtube
and discover they have much higher engagement why is this this seems like a kind of a good
thing like we're on youtube right now right this is maybe maybe this is a good thing i'll tell you
what's going on and this is becoming alarming and i i try not to focus on the negative so i'll just
touch on this briefly there is a ginormous shift in the podcast marketing spending towards youtube
google gives them the ability to kind of slice and dice the demographics in a way that podcasts
just don't expose that data and they have also a much higher click rate in general supposedly
because of the link down in the description stuff that's such a prominent thing on youtube
and so you're already seeing a ginormous shift in podcast advertising spend from podcast to youtube
and so when you have groups like pod track coming out and saying this stuff they're really only kind
of undermining the actual podcast market but here's the reality of it is there is some truth
there there is reasons to be on youtube the ad platform is automatic it scales automatically
there is a lot of data that advertisers can request they love that kind of stuff there is
pretty good engagement you know you got the comment section there you do have the description box
and there's generally depending on you know your channel a pretty good community over there
sometimes not but it's a different audience right and all different audiences are valuable and the
podcaster audience is generally somebody who's you know commuting or maybe they're doing chores
or they're going for a walk or a bike ride or they're drywalling you know they're an addict
that their brother's working on right like it's people that are generally doing something maybe
people that are decision makers at their work like it's a different category of audience
and they're all good audiences but instead of doing research on that and getting those answers
which i can tell you from 15 years of doing this i've tried all the different platforms
and i clearly think that the podcast audience is the best audience out there and there's i have
solid pretty core reasons for that for that belief and there's things they could go do to verify
that anybody who's passionate about this industry would know what some of those things are and we
could could if they had the time and money and resources to make white papers they could go write
those white papers and bolster the podcast industry but instead you have pod track which is a
very common we've used them we do use them for some of our links to track downloads and then that
lets advertisers know that there's a third party arbitrating the data that says yep this is
verifiable even though we keep our own numbers and they're accurate we need them to be in fact
they're better than pod tracks numbers pod track is just there because we can use them as a third
party to verify those numbers that we have a lot of people use it for that and they're not really
helping the podcast industry with this kind of stuff but maybe it's just more of the trend that
way it's sort of shifting anyways brent you know what i mean like i feel like it's a different
i feel like with the boosts and the really positive response to the value for value model
and kind of just the parabolic adoption we're seeing in other areas of the podcast i don't
know i feel like the maybe maybe this stuff just doesn't matter because more and more podcasters
and more and more audience members are kind of getting it all figured out i mean that's sort of
the silver lining here podcasting is kind of maturing quite a bit in the even in the last
what two or three years feels like it was kind of on a steady trend but then like you said there's
this exponential innovation maybe is what we can call it especially you know we're seeing with the
podcast 2.0 stuff even just the technical features that are we're seeing coming down the pipe is
super super super super super fun so i think it's good for us if we're concentrating in the areas
that we think work right yeah and i think you're seeing a consolidation in other areas so you're
you're seeing the decentralized podcast industry i think you're seeing to get stronger i think
that's what you're just touching on there and i think on the other side you're seeing sort of a
commercialization and consolidation of solidification of some elements that have
always been really commercial elements of the podcast industry so this morning for example or
maybe it was last night as we record serious xm announced that they have acquired the podcast
producer team for team coco they produce conan o'brien needs a friend which is a very popular
podcast and they've entered into a five-year talent agreement with the company according
to the wall street journal the reported value of the deal is at 150 million dollars so they cut
conan a check for 150 million dollars and now serious xm is running the podcast they did that
not too long ago with megan kelly as well so they're trying to acquire some of the bigger
names with some of the larger distribution so you are seeing a consolidation there and of course
those are very traditional sounds a bit like a joe rogan thing doesn't it it very much does huh
like that's just like we're just seeing more of that and the companies have the money to spend
like serious like funny right because their business is supposed to be satellite radio
but i i wonder i i wonder if the podcast stuff isn't a way larger audience for them i would
imagine it is certainly i mean i can't remember last time i listened to satellite radio in like
a rental car or something it's always podcasts that i have bring with me so i would imagine
podcasting is squatting their main business and they got to diversify all right well a little
bit of jb stuff including uh some uh website stuff that we've been working on but really just
briefly i wanted to mention with the decentralized podcast stuff and the value for value for a few
weeks i'm experimenting with 15 of all of the boosts that come into office hours and linux
unplugged are being sent to open sats we've included open sats in our split so when you
contribute to this show via a boost 15 of it will be split to open sats they're supporting
contributors on bitcoin and other free open source projects this is something i wanted to try
is can we give a little bit of a cut to different open source projects and i like open sats because
they're donating 100 of what they receive to open source projects they are a full charity in the u.s
here they are what a 5013c or whatever it is probably getting that wrong but that's you can
find it out on their website at opensats.org and they pass through 100 and we're sending it to
their general fund all of that will be given to open source free software developers i love this
idea and so i wanted to help support them because i'm i'm at least hoping it encourages other free
software projects to turn on a lightning address and then we could start including them in splits
we could kind of share the love around a little bit the concept of giving a little bit to projects
has always been something we've wanted to do i know for me personally but um i've run up to
the challenge as you know of it just being difficult to give to a bunch of different
projects at the same time so i'm hoping this solves a little bit of that if only the implementation
details can be you know smooth enough to make it fairly easy for projects to sign up and also for
people like us to be on the other side and to make those donations possible in an easy kind of
fashion so that brings me to i guess asking you about some of the implementation details that i'm
always so curious about like i know you have your little node at the studio and i wondered how easy
it was for you to get connected to the opensats in a way to do splits you i don't think you touched
on that yet and i'm curious you know i've seen you open channels to like the podcast index and such
but how was it this time around this is why i'm it's a good question because this is kind of one
of the reasons i'm excited about this so uh we just enter them in as a split in our rss feed
there's a value namespace tag that podcasting 2.0 has created and you can just add multiple
value tags and you just put a percentage of the split so i'm giving them a 15 split i don't even
have to open a channel i don't even have to say anything to them i just go get their public
lightning address i put it in my split and now they just get 15 of all the boosts that's pretty
awesome it's so easy what i love about that is that makes it really easy for me in a few weeks
to put a different open source project in there and then put a different open source project in
there right it's real low effort super straightforward and i'm very excited about
that because you know i mean imagine like um we have on say a developer who's working on an open
source project that we like uh we just include them in the splits that week or stefan who we're
about to chat with is working on our website if he had a lightning address i could put him in as a
split this week so he gets some sats for helping us out you know and that i think could help just
build community and help encourage people to contribute to free software projects and i think
it's pretty great no the recipients don't actually know so we're getting asked by cuba if the
recipients know who it comes from they could there's there's on chain analytics that open
sats could probably look into but no chris you mentioned implementing this as a like a rss feed
level split i was curious if there's an episode level split or if that's something that uh they're
looking into yes so you can do that we would need to be generating our own rss feeds to do that
there's um a lot of ways you can solve this problem i'm just putting the split in at the
podcast index level but if we managed our own feed you could have default show splits and then we
could have per episode splits that we put into the feed entry for that episode that's very cool
yeah that's gonna be fire so i'm very i'm very much like excited about that so i wanted to kick
a little over to open sats to a help some open source projects they have my absolute favorite
bitcoin wallet as one of the there's a bunch of good projects on there but one of the recipients
is the sparrow project which makes i think the wallet i feel the most comfortable recommending
to the audience it's technical but it's it's a really good product and there's a few other
things they support on there that i really like too and a bunch of other projects so
uh now before we get to stephen one more thing i want to talk about a question that we've got
in on various platforms we also received it in our github thread where we're talking about our
new website and like reese here he says what about using something like castapod for the new jupyter
broadcasting it's a podcast host that supports podcasting 2.0 and it can be self-hosted and has
a paid offering i think it bundles a home page for multiple podcasts as well but i'm not sure
this is a really good question so castapod is an awesome open source project and yeah you can also
self-host it it's really something that i should be talking more about and if you wanted to start
a podcast today and you wanted to self-host it and you wanted a platform to help you do that
i really really think castapod would be worth looking at castapod.org it's like a fireside in
a box and uh you know a whole podcasting hosting platform but with support for all the great 2.0
features right there from the beginning like things like clips trailers transcripts and of
of course value value for value support like boosts i really love this project i wish it was
a solution for us because you know we could deploy this in an afternoon and we're good to go
um but castapod would be probably perfect for us if we had linux unplugged and linux action
news maybe we just did those two shows or something like that right but what we are
looking for is something that accommodates a whole network of shows and allows us to push
forward in areas when we want to push forward instead of having to wait for the vendor platform
to push forward and i say that from a lot of years of just trying one platform after another
initially we started on a single server using wordpress and then we used wordpress plugins
to accomplish a lot of this then we moved to the scale engine system and we we came up with
uh a scale engine approach to wordpress and kind of expanded on the original idea and built in cdns
and all that kind of stuff and then ultimately we moved a lot of the hosting work over to fireside
which is a pretty great platform and you've seen a lot of my friends in the linux podcasting space
move over to it as well to host their podcasts and that has worked pretty well for us but as
new things develop in the podcasting space we have to wait on fireside to deliver them or there's
some features we've been waiting on fireside to deliver like network support for like three and
a half years and they just haven't delivered on it so we don't have like one cohesive fireside
powered website we still have to maintain a separate jupiter broadcasting.com website which
is wordpress that's not ideal but also we want to be able to control our own rss feeds like we just
talked about for reasons that are pretty obvious to anybody listening at this point and we want to
be able to have you know power over that sort of stuff and we ultimately find that while these
platforms work for us for a few years we always eventually outgrow them so the thinking has been
what if we stuck with using open source tools and free software and all that stuff but we went down
a layer so instead of using these end result products like castapod or fireside we use the
tools that they could be using to build those things so we do things like we create an ingestion
system that maybe is based around github actions that then could do things like generate a website
for us once a static website once a show has been posted and maybe there's tooling we could use in
there like hugo to help accomplish some of that but it's just part of one of the solutions right
because when you think about what we do from a publishing house standpoint we record a file here
we record multiple tracks here in the studio we deliver that to our editors who are wonderful
individuals and what's mostly true right drew and drew and marius now drew is our lead editor now
he does his job of like making a sound better and making it sound more intelligent and
then he publishes that as a flak up to an encoding system that we've built called casta blasta
and that generates audio files like mp3 it generates a youtube video visualizer it creates
a wordpress post it it creates rss feed entries it uploads the mp3 to fireside it does a lot of
back-end things and what we want to do is sort of streamline that process and make it a little bit
simpler with a more consistent source of truth based around a github workflow where we check
things in people can do pull requests against them to fix them that's all logged and tracked there
kicks off github actions that goes out and builds things like the post it does the uploads and and
and that's where we're getting to and instead of relying on one built-in cms that has all these
features when we want to add something new to the rss feed well we're just adding a new line to the
xml file we're generating and so instead of using the end result of the tooling we're going to use
the tooling that creates that stuff is basically where we're going with this and so while castapod
would be a great solution if we were looking for the end result we're now deciding we're going to
get to the point where none of these platforms have ever really fit us so we're going to use
some of the same primitives to build the tooling we need without going crazy and so that's why
we've been really kind of hung up on how do we want to get all this like workflow stuff figured
out because the website is important but it's an implementation detail and thankfully stefan has
come along and he's provided what is essentially an mvp of a statically generated website that i'm
looking at and thinking there's a lot here already like this has been really impressive so stefan
welcome into the office thanks for being here how you doing thanks for having me uh i'm doing fine
i hope you uh well too good evening to you i know it's late where you're at so i appreciate you
coming on here you created this hugo powered mvp of a jupiter broadcasting website can you just
tell us a little bit about what it is and how it's being built and all that stuff give us an
overview here so it basically is like a hugo static site um and um it has also the capabilities to
um yeah deploy multiple pages from the same source so meaning you have the jupiter broadcast
overview site and then you can for example build the coda radio sub site from that source as well
and that's then just has the coda radio episodes and so on not all shows and um yeah then i went
from there it's able to generate xml feeds it has a video player um an audio player with like chapter
support uh yeah markdown support for the show notes um the hosts are linked from a from a central
location so only one one file per person exists and that is linked to the episode same goes for
like guests and sponsors and so on and i i just started like for fun and then i i got really far
in like four or five hours and then yeah i got a bit crazy from there and yeah so i've worked
for a week on that it's all deployed and built using github actions and i think it checks like
a lot of boxes you had as a requirement for what you want to do and yeah i just wanted to prove
that it's possible and viable to do so i'm really glad you did because i had suspected hugo could be
a route to go for us we hadn't really picked on it you know i landed on a technology yet but i
know in the back of my mind i was thinking maybe it's going to be hugo and so what you've done here
is basically shown us that with a markdown file you can generate a lot of the website kicked off
from github which is sort of the exact model we're thinking about we still have internally
questions around how we want to generate rss feeds and how we want to host those rss feeds and all
of that but i think what you've created here is a good starting point for us to tweak the design a
little bit but basically the bones of this thing we could we could make the website it's it's like
not but not that far it's like probably 70 of the way there if not more i know you also kind of
added a cms element to this which i thought was interesting and i didn't realize that even was
a thing with hugo so yeah that was maybe uh due to my not being a native english speaker but lost
in translation so um i built something so i have the problem now that i have to generate like a lot
of markdown files for all the shows i probably have to do this over and over because i tweaked
i tweaked the front matter in hugo where the episode information lives and so on and i wanted
a way to have like um a single point of truth where i can query data in a structured manner
be it from fireside sites or from jupiter hub and so on and so i've installed a headless cms
which is basically a cms without a front end and just a rest api and then i built a
uh python scraper a content scraper that goes over jupiter hub and fire sites and then creates
hosts posts shows and so on from there and then i can just like generate with also python script
the markdown files for hugo for all the shows and all the archive and so on so that's basically
yeah to get the legacy content in that is so amazing yeah i could see us down the road when
we get to this fabled source of truth where we're we're essentially checking a yaml file into github
which this yaml file will contain all the details about the episode i could see that being what
generates the website when we get to that point yeah right so everything is generated from
markdown files in in hugo and from the github repository but i just want to make it easier
to generate those markdown files for the archive this is so cool uh what i want to do is try to
get a few of us on a call with wes on here and alex and brent and myself and talk more about this
you know at another time when we're not when we're not recording and just sort of start working out
the details because i think this is the direction to go i think wes probably has a few questions
and i know you probably there's more you want to tell us and show us yeah sorry um yeah no no no
don't be sorry at all thank you so much for doing this this is so great what i really appreciate
about it is it it lets us focus on the workflow stuff which is really where wes and i have been
spending the most time thinking because that's the stuff we hit up against every single day
and it's the stuff that we have the most eyes on right whereas this is something
that we really can get help with and so i really appreciate stefan you stepping up
and doing that and also for sticking around this evening and coming on and telling about it live
yeah super happy super happy to do so well thank you sir thank you and keep up the great work we'll
stay in touch you and i are chatting on matrix so we'll uh we'll keep talking see you soon bye
thank you sir thank you wow and there he goes there look at him what a handsome
bastard that guy is too really appreciate him thank you sir
just browsing through the discussions that were happening on github um where we i think it was
office hours three we we sort of kicked that off um man the discussions have been amazing they're
exchanging ideas and different technologies and just like asking important questions it's a really
great read actually i would highly suggest you just diving in there if you're at all interested
in the the back end of all of this it's been pretty amazing yeah and we've been kicking around
some of the links hey what do you think of this idea like even though we haven't always like i've
been driving and traveling so much but you've still been jumping in there and then we'll see
like a link show up on our slack and so we'll be like what do you think of this idea so it's been
great it's been really it's been really really nice and i think it's helped us really get some
good ideas that maybe wouldn't have even considered in the first place yeah i think a huge thank you
to everyone who uh who really shared ideas and is are really active in there uh to everybody you
yeah thanks a lot it's been been amazing what do you say we do some boost boost that first one eric
pardee wrote in three days ago with uh 15 000 sats thank you thank you sir and he had a note in here
about fountain showing show notes versus other apps he says thanks guys speaking of fountain
i'm not sure why but fountain seems to be cutting off the links when you compare it to say pocket
casts you can see that there is a lot more notes and he included some screenshots for us which is
nice in a boost probably not the super easiest thing to do either uh and you can see it and i've
noticed this too i'm not sure what's up i'm probably gonna have to try to talk to oscar
in fountain you get like the episode description and and that's kind of it but in pocket cast you
get all of the links and all the stuff that we spent a lot of time curating you know and
the sponsored by which is also pretty important we work super hard on that stuff yeah yeah we do
so it's like i can't believe neither of us have noticed that considering how much time we spend
with them yeah i know i know it's it shows you like well for our stuff like i go in there to
clip our stuff i don't go in there to look at the links because yeah i know i know we do yeah but i
do i do appreciate it we know what the links are all right we got one from the golden dragon he says
thanks for another great office hour session what i'm the most excited about in the 2.0 spec for
podcasting is that i can support this network shows without breaking the bank strike and fountain fm
was a super easy setup to get up and running boostagrams are fun and of course i like the
value for value aspect a lot as well hopefully the splits work out because the ideas in this
episode were fantastic i'm glad to hear uh that you like the splits golden dragon because you're
a frequent booster and i i'd love to hear your thoughts on us including open sats for a little
bit as our first trial and experimentation i mean we're going to do brent too as well but he's got
to get a lightning note up and running that stays up and running that's got to be a thing somewhere
in the world anyways you know alex alex crushed my last one so we'll see i might have come across
an application that would let me run multiple node addresses and so i could run like a bank account
for you on my note or something like that oh i see you're gonna charge me fees though aren't you
yeah there's a great idea that's a great idea i have seen at like um norcal dad was saying uh that
he doesn't see the ability to boost office hours in fountain i think there's like two feed entries
in there and i'm not sure what's going on so i have a couple of i have a couple of things i
got to talk to the fountain fm developers about thankfully they've been really awesome and super
responsive so i don't think it'll be a problem but yeah that is definitely gonna be on my list
of to-dos this week b-o-o-s-t tv titan boosted in seven days ago with 3,333 sats thanks for office
hours i've been enjoying them would you guys consider leaving the video version on youtube
after the stream uh i prefer to catch the show on my tv yeah i know what you mean i actually when i
go home in the evenings i you know this brent i watch a fair amount of youtube on the tv i think
it's a really nice way to kind of feel even more connected when you're watching a podcast or
something like that you know so well you know pod track says oh well it's true all the way around
i've been noodling this in my head a bit because we're practicing with video in office hours and
for self-hosted as well and the only problem is is we we screw around a lot on the pre-show and
we cut some of that out in the mp3 or most of that out in the mp3 that we release quite a bit
and drew cleans up mistakes and makes it sound better so it's much better in the car or in your
headphones but i could see leaving the video version up on youtube and maybe we just don't
publish the audio version to youtube i could see doing that i've also been considering
if i could find a community member that would work with me and wanted to be the admin of a jb
peer tube instance i think i'd like to start publishing our stuff to peer tube maybe using
that for live streaming and putting the videos up there it's basically camera capture of the
recording session if we expand that out to lup and those shows we'd probably start posting that
on peer tube as well so if anybody out there is listening and is a peer tube enthusiast like you
know peer tube and would like to help run it you can run it on my infrastructure i have a linode
ready to go but i don't want to be in charge of it beyond having an admin account because i if you
go to jupiter.tube right now i have a hugo page up there speaking of hugo where i identify all the
issues that i ran into with running peer tube at scale and i reread that this morning and i think
some of those things still are valid but if somebody was willing to generate the you know
the back end stuff and or the time and dedicate the time to it for the back end and for managing
it then we could probably make it work we could start posting stuff over there but i don't know
what do you think should we leave this up on youtube the booster wants it who is it tv titan he
wants it up on youtube i mean he's sending a boost i mean appropriate name isn't it yeah it is you're
right i get your hesitation and i i'm feeling the same way as you for some of the other shows we
have that sort of uncut total live feed for members as a nice perk and and i think that's
really attractive because this sort of really clean polished you know all the work that that
our editors do to make us sound far more intelligent um is sort of the public facing
part of the podcast which i think is like a good demonstration of the quality we're always chasing
and the raw stuff is really just you know once once you're cozy with that and you know that
that's the quality that we have then you kind of want a little bit of dirt in there from time to
time just to get some uh some some tasty bits of i don't know the stuff that happens before and
after the show so but you want your first impression to be like the best cut of you
exactly maybe maybe this could be an office hours perk perhaps that we think about but i would
hesitate to throw it out as a raw i think the question you're raising there is who is the
youtube audience are they like new discoveries or are they people who follow the network already
i think that's one question and i think the other question is because youtube is a video medium
does the rawness sort of not matter because it's superseded by the video aspect which is what the
platform is built around because you see like the views on the waveform videos are very low as you
would expect them to be on youtube right i don't know we're not getting a lot of engagement with
the audio waveform already i'm not sure we could experiment with it would probably be my my preferred
way to do would be to have our own peer tube instance and then people because that is people
specifically seeking us out intentionally going somewhere they're already kind of they already
know about it because they heard about it from us so they're getting the raw thing but they're
getting the raw thing because they've chosen to and then the public facing thing should go on
youtube i would think but i'd be willing to experiment we could try it with this episode
i'd have to let wes know we have to make a little tweak to the publishing system so it doesn't
publish the other one but you follow what i'm saying there like peer tube might be the better
place for like the more uncut stuff because it sort of self-selects a little bit for people
who already know that the kind of the kind of stuff we typically do you know the real way to
do it would be to do what bitcoin did podcast does which is a super clean video thing but
i remember now it's been a few years you decided to stop doing all of that so that's another tricky
thing right it's like how much do you push that envelope and then you get into the same territory
that uh that we were in previously so that's another question oh yeah i kind of like what
we're doing now is we're doing a live stream you know we've got we've got cameras going
we've got a couple of camera angles but it's not really relevant to the show doesn't really change
the aspect what it doesn't change any of the content and nobody's editing it it's just it
goes out as it is it's like a separate thing and i think that's how i prefer to have it i could
see it i think if i ever want to get into like actual video shows i'd want to shoot it for video
you know and yeah you'd want to do it well you know we'd set up more than just my
crap webcam here and stuff like that we know how to do it better funny enough your crap setup
there kind of betrays the fact that when you're when you're actually working and you're on
location setting up a camera shot you put an enormous amount of effort you're kind of like
a MacGyver of lighting too you're very clever i'm uncomfortable with my situation right now so
i don't know if that shows oh man all right well we got just a couple of thank you boosts into so
thank you to pitar who sent us an f yeah for boosts and tokyo trucker who was streaming sats while he
listened thanks to both of you if you'd like to send us a boost to try out any of the new podcasting
channel stuff you can go to newpodcastapps.com i will link in the show notes to office hours on
podverse podverse is interesting it does support value it supports clips it supports podcasting
2.0 what i'm kind of digging about podverse is it has a full featured web podcast player
and then it has an android app and an ios app i think it has like a membership system though
i haven't got into that only that but i've been checking it out so i'll link to office
hours on podverse if you want to try it out otherwise the app that i use on the daily is
fountain i i have you can follow me on fountain i'm at chris las i have a profile there and i'm
cranking out clips from time to time of our shows and the various shows that i listen to so that's
kind of one of the nice things that the fountain has going for it if you're into the clips which
initially i wasn't and then i end up sticking around for the clips and now i'm all about the
clips yeah the clips are pretty tasty yeah and they let you share web versions and they'll
generate video versions it's slick it's a nice implementation isn't it and we talked about
discovering new podcasts that way too because you get a little bit of a preview too and so i think
it's great here's the thing bren here's the thing this is the this is the lord's truth about
podcasting really nobody wants to take the chance on like an hour-long podcast or long or 45 minute
or two hour podcast just randomly if you're maybe super into something and you're looking that up
you'll do it right but generally especially like a show like this show or some show that's kind of
more general you're gonna need somebody to recommend it to you're gonna need word of mouth
that is the number one version of marketing right it's word of mouth oh yeah i think it's
probably always going to be by a strong lead the number one form of marketing for podcasts
but i could see a world where a distant number two is clips because i've probably started listening
to two or three different podcasts now because i found a clip of them first that somebody in our
community shared with me and i get it i get it because sometimes there's a little nugget in one
of those podcasts and you're like oh i like that maybe i'll go listen to the rest of them and i
end up tapping and following their whole their whole show i am excited about clips i don't
expect it to be huge they're a little tedious sometimes but i could see it being a nice way
to share the show so if you want to make a clip and share it have at it you know what i'm saying
all right brian i think that's everything yeah i think we're done sounds good yeah i don't have
anything on my list left so i think we're in good shape all right office hours dot hair slash five
for links of what we talked about today you can find our rss feed over there too we got a lot of
projects i wanted to talk more about the summer road trip if you're in the west coast area listen
up we got big plans for the summer and there's going to be something really special at the end
of the road trip it's only going to be available to a limited amount of people you'll understand
why it's not a price thing anything like that it's just because the facility is only so large
but we'll we'll tell you we got so many more details on all of that coming up soon so be sure
you're subscribed lots of adventures over the summer lots of projects new website stuff all of
it office hours dot hair slash subscribe you can send a boost into the show as well to give us
feedback and give us ideas we'll cover them on the next episode anyway it's time to get out of here
office is closed close yeah don't let the door hit you on the way out
thanks for being here